♪ ♪
Shawn: Hi, I am Shawn.
I am an engineer
on the Internet Technologies team.
Today, we are going to talk about
reducing network delays in your app
with L4S.
L4S stands for Low Latency,
Low Loss, and Scalable throughput.
It is an incredible technology
that dramatically improves
the performance of apps
where network latency can impact
the user experience.
To name just a few benefits,
it can help your app
reduce content load time,
improve video quality,
and bring more responsive collaboration
between users.
Today, we'll first explore how L4S works
and how it reduces network delays.
Then, we will go over
how to prepare your app for L4S
and how to turn on L4S on your server.
Finally, we will talk about
the steps you can take
to configure an L4S network
and test your app.
First, let's explore the benefits of L4S
and how it works.
A busy network can be
especially challenging
for apps that depend on features
like real-time audio and video.
When the network is used
by many devices at once,
it can often cause
high latency and packet loss
in these types of apps.
For example,
you might have experienced delays
or video stalls during a video call
when someone else using the same network
is watching a movie
or downloading a video game.
To show you how much L4S can help
in such a difficult situation,
we have made a sample app
that makes video calls
between two devices.
I will show you two video calls
with my sample app
made at different times,
one without L4S
and the other with L4S turned on.
For both these calls,
I used the same constrained network
with low bandwidth.
In addition,
there are also multiple other devices
actively using the same network
at the same time.
Let's see this in action.
You will notice a remarkable difference
in video quality between the two calls.
The legacy one shows
occasional video stalls and delays,
especially during motion.
However, with L4S,
the video is smooth and responsive,
without any significant delays.
Now let's analyze the video calls
we have just witnessed
to understand what was happening.
In this demo,
L4S allowed our app to achieve
significant improvements
across all key networking metrics.
First, let's look at the distribution
of round trip time of packets
during these video calls.
A shorter round trip time
indicates a lower
and better latency on the network.
For an interactive app like this,
the tail latency is extremely important,
as it shows the worst case
that a user experiences.
Our test network has
a minimum round trip time
of 20 milliseconds.
However, without L4S,
packets experienced a round trip time
of up to 45 milliseconds.
But with L4S turned on,
even the worst-case latency
was cut by 50%
and reduced to less than 25 milliseconds.
Next, let's look at packet loss.
A lower packet loss represents
a more reliable connection
between devices.
With the legacy one,
packet loss rate reached over 40%.
But with L4S, packet loss
in our video call was nearly eliminated.
That means much fewer frame drops
or stalls due to loss of data.
The improved latency
and packet loss rate translated directly
into better rendering metrics
of our video call.
First, let's look
at the video stall percentage.
A lower stall percentage means
fewer freezes during a video call.
Without L4S, we experienced video stalls
in our app from time to time.
But with L4S, video stalls were
almost completely eliminated.
Next, let's look
at received video frame rate.
A higher and more consistent
received video frame rate
means a richer and smoother video call.
With L4S, received video frame rate
was above 25 frames per second
for most of the time.
However, the legacy one sometimes dropped
to as low as 0 frame per second,
which means a complete video stall.
Altogether, these improvements give
a much better user experience
even in a constrained network.
You can bring
these same improvements to your app
by adopting L4S.
Now, let's take a look at how L4S works.
We see such remarkable improvements,
because L4S reduces queueing
and packet loss.
Let's first take a look
at how a queue builds up in a network.
When a packet is sent from your app,
it is routed
through different network hops
before reaching your server.
This set of hops your packet traverses
is called a network path.
On a path through a network,
you can only deliver data end-to-end
at the rate that is supported
by the slowest hop,
which is called the bottleneck.
For many people, this is their
internet service provider connection,
and the highest rate it can handle packets
determines the maximum throughput
supported on the path.
If the sender exceeds
the maximum throughput,
a queue will form at the bottleneck,
causing delays for subsequent packets.
Without L4S,
the queue will continue to grow
until the queue cannot accommodate
any more packets.
When that happens, packets are dropped,
harming both latency and throughput.
L4S solves this problem
through a collaboration
between the client, the server,
and the bottleneck.
With L4S,
a client or server sending packets
needs to signal that they will cooperate
to manage network congestion.
To do this, an L4S-capable sender
will use a technology
called Explicit Congestion Notification,
also known as ECN.
When transmitting a packet,
the sender indicates support for L4S
by using the ECN bits
in the packet's IP header.
When an L4S hop receives these packets,
it will apply
L4S queue management to them.
When a queue starts to build up
at the bottleneck,
L4S queue management will indicate
that there is congestion
by setting a different ECN label
on the packets.
This label indicates that the network has
experienced congestion
before forwarding them to the next hop.
Upon receiving these packets,
the receiver counts the number of packets
marked with the congestion label
and reports the number
back to the sender.
When the sender receives this number,
it uses this feedback to understand
the congestion on the network.
The sender then adjusts its sending rate
according to the level of congestion
at the bottleneck,
so that it does not exceed
the maximum throughput.
With an adjusted sending rate,
the sender can avoid
building a large queue of packets
at the bottleneck.
This allows L4S to maximize its throughput
and achieve low end-to-end latency
at the same time.
Now, let's explore what you need to do
to enable this collaboration
to deliver these benefits to your users.
First, let's discuss
how you can prepare your app for L4S.
Using networking APIs in URLSession
and Network framework
is the best way to adopt L4S in your app.
If your app uses HTTP/3
or QUIC within these frameworks,
L4S support is automatically built in.
You don't have to make
any code changes to your app.
Alternatively,
if your app uses HTTP/2 or TCP,
iOS 17 and macOS Sonoma have
built-in L4S support
for downloads on these protocols.
These are the best ways
to add L4S support to your app
because they do not require
any code changes.
However, if your app uses
a custom protocol,
there are a few things
you'll need to implement
in order to support L4S in your app.
RFC 9330 is a good starting point
to learn about L4S requirements.
You will need to implement
a few new behaviors.
For example,
your protocol needs to understand
L4S congestion feedback from the network
and adjust its sending rate accordingly.
To do that, you need to implement
a scalable congestion control algorithm.
Then, you need to make sure
your app sends L4S traffic
only when the network lets
ECN bits pass through.
To do that,
implement an ECN validation mechanism
that checks for any network issues
that may be interfering with ECN,
such as ECN bleaching.
When acting as a receiver,
your protocol also needs to have
a relay mechanism to echo back
the network's ECN feedback to the sender.
If your implementation is
based on Network framework,
you can use the ECN property
on your packet metadata
to send and receive ECN flags
for your custom protocol.
If you are using sockets,
you can use the set socket option
or send and receive message system calls
to send and receive ECN flags.
Now we have covered
how to prepare your app for L4S,
let's explore how to set up your server.
If your app uses QUIC,
your server's implementation of QUIC
also needs to support L4S
and ECN markings.
There are numerous QUIC implementations
available on the server side.
Ask your server provider
about how to enable ECN and L4S.
If they do not support
sending L4S traffic yet,
you can still enable ECN
to receive L4S traffic on your server.
Now is a great time to encourage them
to fully support L4S.
If your app is using TCP,
you will need to add L4S support
to your server's TCP implementation.
For Linux based server,
follow instructions on this GitHub page
to add support to your server.
You can also find more details
from the article
in the related items for this video.
For all other server platforms,
please consult your server provider,
as there may be additional configurations
or changes required
in order to support L4S.
Now that we have covered how your app
and server can be set up for L4S,
let's explore how to set up
an L4S network to test your app.
First, let's review
what makes a network L4S-capable.
The network must not block ECN markings.
ECN markings are used
to communicate information
about the network between the sender,
the bottleneck, and the receiver.
If your network interferes
with ECN markings, L4S will not work.
The documentation has steps
you can follow,
along with additional tools,
that you can use to verify
if your network is ECN compatible.
Next, the network bottleneck must support
L4S queue management.
This is essential to being able
to see the benefits of L4S.
Once you have verified
that your network is ECN compatible,
you just need to add L4S queue management
to the bottleneck.
To set up a test network
that supports L4S queue management,
the best way is to use Internet Sharing.
In macOS Sonoma, Internet Sharing supports
L4S queue management.
When a device joins the network
created by a Mac with Internet Sharing,
the Mac itself becomes
an additional network hop
between the device and the server.
If you configure the Mac to be
the bottleneck on the network,
it will apply L4S queue management
to traffic going through it,
allowing you to build
a complete L4S network.
To enable Internet Sharing in macOS,
navigate to the Internet Sharing pane
in System Settings.
Click the disclosure button
to choose the interface to share
and the interface
to which your test device will connect.
To make the Mac act
as a bottleneck on this network,
you need to throttle its bandwidth.
Use this ifconfig command in Terminal
with the interface you are sharing,
as well as the interface
your device will connect to.
Replace the interface name in this command
with the name of the interfaces
you are using,
for example, en1.
Then, join the network on your test device
and test your app
to see the benefits of L4S.
To reverse
the bandwidth throttling on the Mac,
you can either reboot
or run the same ifconfig command
but change the bandwidth to 0
instead of 10 megabits per second.
In iOS 17 and macOS Sonoma,
L4S will be progressively rolled out
to a random set of users.
To ensure your test device
has L4S turned on,
navigate to Developer Settings
and turn on L4S.
In macOS, you can enable L4S
by running this defaults write command
before testing.
If your network or server
does not support L4S,
TCP and QUIC will continue to work
in the legacy mode.
However, you should turn L4S on
and test your application
to identify any issues.
Provide feedback
using the Feedback Assistant
if any issues arise.
The documentation also provides
helpful information
about debugging and testing L4S
in your app.
I am so excited that apps and networks
are now able to support
reduced latency
and reduced packet loss with L4S.
Test your app in iOS 17
and macOS Sonoma today
on networks that support L4S
as well as on networks that do not.
Work with your server or CDN provider
to enable support for L4S
on your app's servers,
if they haven't already done so.
Use the Feedback Assistant to report
any issues you encounter
with L4S turned on in your app.
Thanks for watching.
I am looking forward to building
even better apps with you using L4S.
♪ ♪