♪ ♪
Nick: Hi, I'm Nick,
an engineer on the SwiftUI team.
Inspector is
an exciting new element in SwiftUI.
I'll go over what an inspector is
and how to use the API.
After that, I'll review modifiers
for presentation customizations.
Inspector is the name for views that show
further detail of selected content.
You have probably interacted
with one before.
Keynote uses an inspector
to show formatting details
for a selection, in this case,
the shape formatter.
Here the inspector presents
as a trailing sidebar.
Another common use case for inspectors
is showing content
that supplements an app's main content.
Shortcuts uses inspector for this purpose.
The main interface is the shortcut
that the user is editing,
and the inspector supplements that with
the library of available apps and actions.
I will be using this sample app
to explore the inspector API.
I've been getting to know the animals
in and around Apple Park.
This app saves the animals I've met,
tracks their name,
tracks their favorite fruits,
and there's this column
that I'll get to later
labeled "Suspicion Level."
And now, meet, SwiftUI's inspector!
The inspector shows a read-write view
of details about the selected animal.
Here I'm adjusting
Fabrizio Fish's suspicion level
up to "Extremely suspicious."
Actually I'll keep him at fishy.
Inspector is available to
SwiftUI Developers on macOS
and iPadOS and iOS too!
The inspector API includes
programmatic control over column width,
allowing you to tune the width
of the trailing column.
The API includes programmatic control
over presented state,
allowing hiding and showing
of the inspector as needed.
Inspector is a higher level abstraction
than just a trailing sidebar.
In compact size classes,
it adapts to a resizable sheet
and inspector will automatically overlay
in split screen on larger iPads.
SwiftUI already has an existing set
of structural APIs.
Inspector fits in alongside these APIs
with characteristics of both
navigation components and presentations.
Similar to NavigationSplitView
and NavigationStack,
inspector is used to build
the scaffolding of your scene.
Similar to Sheet, popover, alert,
and confirmation dialogs,
inspector is a presentation,
dismissing and presenting as needed.
It's time to learn
how to adopt the new inspector API.
Earlier, I showed off the sample app
I made for this session.
You may have noticed I was tracking
each animal's suspicion level.
That's because I am trying to solve
a high-stakes mystery.
Someone is eating
all the fruit at Apple Park!
I added inspector to my app so that I,
Inspector Nick,
can gather the details of each animal.
I'll show you how easy it was
to adopt the inspector API,
and maybe I can solve
this fruity mystery along the way.
Quickly, to Xcode!
The game is a-fruit!
The first step to adding inspector
is using the new modifier, inspector.
Like some other presentations,
this takes a Bool presented binding,
and then the inspector's content
in the trailing view builder.
For the inspector content,
I have a ready made AnimalInspectorForm.
I have some custom methods for passing
in the animal currently being inspected.
And there's my inspector, presenting
as a trailing column here on macOS.
I have planted the seeds of
a wonderful inspector experience.
This AnimalForm
is using the grouped style.
In case you haven't encountered form
styles before, they're applied like this.
But because inspector contexts
use the grouped style by default,
I don't need to style it myself.
I can even interact with the inspector
in the preview's canvas.
Ah, this reminds me,
while inspectors can collapse by default,
they aren't resizable by default.
I can change that
using the inspector column width modifier.
I'll use some sensible defaults.
200 for min, 300 for ideal,
and 400 for max.
This ideal parameter will be
the size of the column at at first launch,
but if the user resizes the inspector,
the system will persist
that size across launches.
Lastly, I'll add a toolbar
item to toggle the presented state.
I'll use a button
that toggles the presented property,
and for its label, a Label,
using the info.circle system image.
The toolbar item will appear
in the section of the toolbar
above the inspector because it's declared
within the inspector's view builder.
When I scroll, the toolbar
behaves exactly like I'd expect,
showing a shadow pocket when enough
of the content is underneath the toolbar.
I used the inspector modifier
on the AnimalTable intentionally,
rather than some other spot
in the view hierarchy.
Like many SwiftUI APIs,
the inspector modifier
has different behaviors depending
on the context of where it is applied.
Specifically,
the placement decides whether
the full height style is used,
where there is no separation
between toolbar and content,
or the under toolbar style is used,
where the inspector
is nested under the toolbar.
Notice the title separator
spans the full width
of the window
in the under toolbar appearance.
Similarly, toolbar content will be placed
in the main content's toolbar...
or in the inspector's toolbar,
depending on where
the toolbar modifier is used.
There are two points to consider
when using the inspector API.
First, is the inspector
going to be placed inside
or outside of a navigation structure like
a NavigationStack or NavigationSplitView?
Second, should the toolbar content
be inside or outside
of the inspector's view builder?
I'll walk through two
of these constructions.
First up, placing inspector
inside a navigation structure,
with toolbar content
outside the inspector.
When an inspector is contained
within a NavigationStack,
the inspector is underneath
the navigation stack's toolbar.
Here, the toolbar content is declared
outside of the inspector
on the main content and is rendered
in the navigation stack's toolbar.
In compact horizontal size classes,
the inspector presents as a sheet
and the toolbar item stays
in the main content's toolbar.
Back to my table of possibilities.
For the second construction,
I'll look at placing the inspector
outside of a navigation structure,
with toolbar content
inside the inspector view builder.
When the inspector modifier is placed
outside of a navigation structure,
the inspector is given the full height
of the trailing column to lay out.
If the inspector has toolbar content,
that content will be placed
in a toolbar section
specifically for the inspector.
These two toolbar items are positioned
with the principal placement
and end up centered in the navigation
toolbar above the inspector.
This time, however,
because the toolbar content
is inside the inspector's view builder,
when the inspector presents as a sheet,
the toolbar content is in the sheet.
These principles extend to macOS,
except inspector does not present
as a sheet on macOS,
and so the table becomes simpler.
The only axis to worry about is inside
or outside a navigation structure.
A final, but important note:
If you are using an inspector
within a NavigationSplitView,
the inspector should be placed
in the detail column's view builder,
or, just like before,
it can also be placed entirely
outside the navigation structure.
Wow, all of this mystery solving
is making me hungry!
[apple crunches]
Oh!
I'm getting a Nibble Bulletin in the app!
The app shows Nibble Bulletins
as resizable sheets
with some information about
where and when the fruit was nibbled.
This is a great time for me to talk about
presentation customizations
SwiftUI released with iOS 16.4.
The fruit nibble bulletin is a sheet,
not an inspector.
Presentation modifiers allow
deep customization of sheets
and other presentations like popovers.
I'll try a few of them out.
The presentation background modifier
is aptly named.
It will set the background
of a presentation.
Unlike the existing background modifier,
the presentation specific modifier
will fill the entire presentation
and allow underlying content
to show through.
So, if I use a thinMaterial,
I'll see a hint of the List
behind the sheet.
I'd like to allow interaction
with content behind the sheet,
in case I want to scroll the list,
and look at suspects
while reading the Nibble Bulletin.
This is as simple as
presentationBackgroundInteraction enabled.
The dimming view is removed
and I can now interact
with the background content.
The PresentationBackgroundInteraction
type
can also have an upThrough parameter
accepting a presentation detent.
As long as the provided argument matches
one of the given presentation's detents,
SwiftUI will only provide
the dimming view at detents
greater than the upThrough argument.
I want dimming at any detent
above a height of 200,
so I will first add a height detent of 200
using the presentationDetents modifier.
I'll adjust the sheet
from its current detent of medium...
down to my custom height of 200.
When I only enable background interaction
up through 200,
the dimming view will return
for the medium and large detents.
There are more customizations
available to you
to get the perfect look and feel
for presentations.
Many of these modifiers have effects
on other presentations too,
not just sheets.
And one more thing
about presentation modifiers.
Those same modifiers compose
with Inspector
when Inspector is presenting as a sheet.
For my inspector from earlier,
to disable background content interaction
at the medium detent,
I can use the same exact code
from before...
declaring a height detent,
and only enabling background interaction
up through the same detent.
Now the inspector dims
at the medium detent and higher.
And that's inspectors in SwiftUI.
In this video, I introduced the inspector
API and the nuances of using it.
I picked some of my favorite sheet
presentation modifiers to demonstrate,
and showed how
they can compose with inspectors.
So what are you waiting for?
Go out and get inspecting.
Place the inspector somewhere in your app.
Keep it going
by customizing your presentations.
And as for the nibbler,
I guess our efforts to solve this mystery
were fruitless.
♪ ♪