♪ ♪
Alex Hoppen: Who likes writing repetitive
boilerplate code?
Nobody does!
And that's why in Swift 5.9
we are introducing Swift macros.
Swift macros allow you to generate
that repetitive code at compile time,
making your app's codebases
more expressive and easier to read.
My name is Alex Hoppen,
and today I am going to show you
how you can write your own macros.
I will start off by giving you
a short overview of how macros work.
Afterwards,
we will jump straight into Xcode
and see how
you can create your first macro.
Having seen our first macro in Xcode,
we will explore more roles
in which you can use macros
and I will show you how I used macros
to simplify the codebase of an app
I am currently working on.
Finally, I will show you how macros
can communicate errors or warnings
back to the compiler if they are not
applicable in a certain context.
So let's get started.
Here we have a list of calculations
that first-year students can use
to practice their arithmetic skills.
We have the result
as an integer on the left
and the calculation as a string literal
on the right side of the tuple.
Notice how this is repetitive,
redundant, and even error prone
because nobody can guarantee that the
result actually matches the calculation.
Luckily, with Swift 5.9 we can define
a stringify macro to simplify this.
This macro also happens to be the one
that is included in Xcode's template.
The stringify macro only takes
the calculation as a single parameter.
At compile time it expands to the tuple
that we saw before,
guaranteeing that the calculation
and the result match.
So how does this work?
Let's take a look at the definition
of the macro itself.
Notice that it looks a lot
like a function.
The stringify macro takes an integer
as the input parameter
and outputs a tuple
containing an the result,
an integer, and the calculation--
a string.
If the arguments of the macro expression
don't match the macro's parameters,
or don't type check by themselves,
the compiler will emit an error
without applying the macro expansion.
For example,
if I pass a string literal to this macro,
the compiler complains
that 'String' is not convertible
to expected argument type 'Int'.
This is different to, for example,
C macros,
which are evaluated at the pre-processor
stage before type-checking.
But it allows us to use all the powers
that you know and love
from Swift functions,
like being able
to make your macro generic.
Also note that this macro is declared with
the freestanding expression macro role.
This means that you can use the macro
wherever you can use an expression,
and that it will be indicated by the hash
character, like we see with #stringify.
Other kinds of macros are attached macros
that can augment declarations.
I will cover those later.
After checking that all the arguments
match the macro's parameters,
the compiler performs the macro expansion.
To see how that works,
let's focus on a single macro expression.
To perform the expansion,
each macro defines its implementation
in a compiler plug-in.
The compiler will send the source code
of the entire macro expression
to that plug-in.
The first thing
that the macro plug-in does,
is to parse the source code of the macro
into a SwiftSyntax tree.
This tree is a source-accurate, structural
representation of the macro,
and it will be the basis
on which the macro operates.
For example, our 'stringify' macro
is represented in the tree
as a macro expansion expression node.
That expression
has the macro name 'stringify'.
And it takes a single argument,
which is the infix operator plus
applied to 2 and 3.
What's really powerful about Swift macros
is that that the macro's implementation
is itself a program written in Swift
and can perform any transformation
to the syntax tree it wants.
In our case,
it generates a tuple like we saw before.
It will then serialize the generated
syntax tree into source code again
and send it to the compiler,
which will replace the macro expression
by the expanded code.
That's really cool,
but now I want to understand how
all of this actually looks like in code.
The new macro template in Xcode
defines the stringify macro
that we have just seen.
Let us walk through that template
and explore the macro's definition,
how the expansion works,
and how the macro can be tested.
To create the template,
I click File, New, Package,
and now I select the Swift Macro template.
Let's call our first macro "WWDC".
So what do we get with the template?
Here we have an invocation
of the #stringify macro,
similar to what we have seen before.
It takes a parameter "a + b"
and returns the result,
as well as the code that produced it.
If I want to know
what the macro expands to,
I can right-click on it
and select Expand Macro.
That's exactly what we saw before.
But how is the macro defined?
Let's jump to its definition.
Here we have
a slightly generalized version
of our previous 'stringify' macro.
Instead of taking an integer,
this macro is generic
and can receive any type T.
The macro is declared
as an external macro.
This tells the compiler
that to perform the expansion,
it needs to look at
the StringifyMacro type
in the WWDCMacros module.
How is that type defined?
Let's take a closer look at it.
Because stringify is declared
as a freestanding expression macro,
the StringifyMacro type needs to conform
to the ExpressionMacro protocol.
This protocol has a single requirement:
The expansion function.
It takes the syntax tree
of the macro expression itself,
as well as a context that can be used
to communicate with the compiler.
The expansion function then returns
the rewritten expression syntax.
What does it do in the implementation?
At first, it retrieves the single argument
to the macro expression.
It knows that this argument exists
because stringify is declared
as taking a single parameter
and all arguments need to type-check
before the macro expansion can be applied.
It then uses string interpolation
to create the syntax tree of a tuple.
The first element is the argument itself
and the second is a string literal
containing the source code
of the argument.
Notice that the function
is not returning a string here.
It is returning an expression syntax.
The macro will automatically invoke
the Swift parser
to transform this literal
into a syntax tree.
And because it is using
the literal interpolation style
for the second argument,
it will make sure that the literal's
contents are properly escaped.
Nobody likes bugs.
But what I like even less
are bugs in code that I don't see
unless I explicitly ask for it
by expanding the macro.
That is why you want to make sure
that your macro is well-tested.
Because macros don't have side effects
and the source code of syntax trees
is easy to compare,
a great way to test them
is to write unit tests.
The macro template already comes with one.
This test case uses
the 'assertMacroExpansion' function
from the SwiftSyntax package
to verify that the 'stringify' macro
expands correctly.
It takes the '#stringify(a + b)'
expression,
that we saw before, as input.
and asserts
that after the macro is expanded,
it produces a tuple containing 'a + b'
and the string literal 'a + b'.
To tell the test case
how to expand the macros,
it passes the 'testMacros' parameter,
which specifies that the macro ‘#stringify'
should be expanded
using the 'StringifyMacro' type.
Let's run the tests in the same way
that you might already run the tests
of your app,
to see if they indeed pass.
The tests pass,
and with that,
we already have our first macro.
In it, we saw its basic building blocks.
The macro declaration
defines the macro's signature.
It also declares the macros roles.
The compiler plug-in
performs the expansion.
It is a program
that is itself written in Swift
and operates on SwiftSyntax trees.
We also saw that macros are very testable
because they are deterministic
transformations of syntax trees
and the source code of syntax trees
is easy to compare.
So you might wonder, "In which other
situations can we use macros?"
We have already seen
a freestanding expression macro.
Just to recap,
this macro is spelled with a hash
and allows you to rewrite
the entire macro expression.
There's also
a freestanding declaration role
that expands to a declaration
instead of an expression.
The other kinds of macros
are attached macros.
These are spelled with an @,
just like attributes,
and allow the macro to augment
the declaration they are attached to.
For example, an attached member macro
adds new members of the type
it is attached to.
To learn more about these other roles,
I highly recommend watching
"Expand on Swift macros"
where Becca goes over them
in great detail.
But I want to focus
on the attached member role
because it helped me
improve the codebase of an app
I am currently working on.
I am also a ski instructor,
and recently I have been working on an app
that allows me to plan the tours
I want to take my students on.
One thing you absolutely want to avoid
as a ski instructor
is to take beginners on slopes
that are too hard for them.
I want to use the Swift type system
to enforce that.
That's why,
in addition to the Slope enum
that contains all the slopes
in my favorite ski resort,
I also have an EasySlope type that only
contains slopes suitable for beginners.
It has an initializer
to convert a slope to an easy slope,
if the slope is indeed easy,
and a computed property to convert
an easy slope back to a general slope.
While this provides great type safety,
it is really repetitive.
If I want to add an easy slope,
I need to add it to Slope...
EasySlope,
the initializer,
and the computed property.
Let's see if we can improve things
using a macro.
What we want to do is to
automatically generate the initializer
and the computed property.
How can we do this?
Both the initializer
and the computed property
are members of the EasySlope type,
so we need to declare
an attached member macro.
Next, we will create the compiler plug-in
that contains the macro's implementation.
To make sure
that our macro behaves as expected,
we want to develop it
in a test-driven way.
Thus,
we will leave its implementation empty
until we write a test case for it.
After we defined the macro's behavior
in a test case,
we will write the implementation
to match that test case.
And finally, we will integrate
the new macro into my app.
If all goes well,
we will be able to remove the initializer
and have the macro generate it for us.
To develop the macro, we work with
the template that we created earlier.
And since I don't really need
the ‘#stringify' macro in my app,
I have already removed it.
I start by declaring
a new attached member macro
by using the '@attached(member)'
attribute.
I call it SlopeSubset because
EasySlope is a subset of Slope.
The macro also defines the names
of the members it introduces.
In this demo, I will just be showing you
how to generate the initializer.
Generating the computed property
is very similar,
because it's also just a switch statement
that switches over all the cases.
With this declaration,
we have defined the macro,
but we have not implemented
the expansion that it actually performs.
For this, our macro references
the SlopeSubsetMacro type
in the WWDCMacros module .
Let us go and create that type
so we can continue
to the really exciting part:
The actual macro implementation.
Since we declared SlopeSubset
as an attached member macro,
the corresponding implementation needs
to conform to the MemberMacro protocol.
This protocol has a single requirement:
The 'expansion' function,
similar to ExpressionMacro.
The 'expansion' function
takes the attribute
with which we apply the macro
to a declaration,
as well as the declaration that the macro
is being applied to.
In our case, this will be
the EasySlope enum declaration.
The macro then returns the list
of all the new members
it wants to add to that declaration.
I know that it's very tempting
to start implementing this transformation
straight away,
but we agreed that we wanted to start
by writing a test case for it.
So for now,
let us just return an empty array,
indicating that no new members
should be added.
Finally, we need to make SlopeSubset
visible to the compiler.
For this, I add it
to the 'providingMacros' property
down here.
Before diving any deeper,
I want to make sure
that what we have so far works.
While I could try
applying the macro in Xcode
and looking at the expanded code,
I much prefer to write a test case for it
that I can rerun
whenever I'm making changes to the macro,
to make sure
I'm not introducing regressions.
Just like in the test case
in the template,
we use the 'assertMacroExpansion' function
to verify our macro's behavior.
What we want to test
is what the macro generates
when applied to the EasySlope type,
so we use that as our test case's input.
And since the macro's
not doing anything yet,
we just expect it to remove the attribute
and not add any new members,
so the expected expanded code
is the same as the input,
just without '@SlopeSubset'.
Finally, we need to let the test case know
that it should expand the macro
SlopeSubset
using the SlopeSubsetMacro implementation.
For that, we need to map the macro name
to its implementing type
in the 'testMacros' dictionary
and pass that dictionary
to the assertion function.
Let's run our tests now
to check that what
we have written so far actually works.
It does.
Great.
But we want really wanted
is to check that our macro
actually generates the initializer,
not just remove the attribute.
So I'll copy the code that I previously
wrote by hand into the test case
because really, that's what we want
the plug-in to generate.
If we run the test again…
...it fails
because our macro doesn't actually
generate the initializer yet.
Let's change that now.
The initializer switches over all the enum
elements declared in the EasySlopes enum.
So the first thing that we need to do
is to retrieve these enum elements
from the declaration.
Since enum elements can only be declared
inside enum declarations,
we start by casting 'declaration'
to an enum declaration.
If the macro is attached to a type
that is not an enum,
we should be emitting an error.
I added a TODO
so that we don’t forget to do it later,
and return an empty array for now.
Next, we need to get all the elements
that the enum declares.
To figure out how to do that,
I want to inspect the syntactic structure
of our enum in the SwiftSyntax tree.
Since the macro's implementation
is just an ordinary Swift program,
I can use all the tools that you know
from Xcode to debug your programs.
For example, I can set a breakpoint inside
the expansion function
and run the test cases
to hit that breakpoint.
We now have the debugger paused
inside the macro’s implementation
and 'enumDecl' is the EasySlopes enum.
We can print it in the debugger
by typing 'po enumDecl'.
Let's inspect the output.
The innermost nodes of the syntax tree
represent the enum elements,
the 'beginnersParadise',
and 'practiceRun' slopes.
To retrieve them,
we need to follow the structure
that is outlined to us in the syntax tree.
Let us walk through that structure
step-by-step
and write the access code as we go.
The enum declaration
has a child called 'memberBlock'.
This member block contains both the braces
and the actual members.
So to access the members,
we start with
'enumDecl.memberBlock.members'.
These members contain
the actual declaration,
as well as an optional semicolon.
We are interested in the declarations,
in particular those declarations
that actually declare enum cases.
I'm using compact map to get a list
of all the member declarations
that are enum cases.
Each case declaration
can declare multiple elements.
This is because instead of declaring
each slope on a new line
after a separate case keyword,
I could have written them on the same line
as 'case beginnersParadise, practiceRun'.
To retrieve all of them,
we can use 'flatMap'.
And now that we have retrieved
all the elements,
we can start constructing the initializer
that we actually want to add to EasySlope.
The initializer declaration
has a single item:
A switch expression.
This switch expression contains a case
for each element in the enum,
as well as a default case
that returns nil.
We need to create syntax nodes
for all of these.
Two great ways of finding
the syntax nodes to create, are
either by printing the syntax tree
like we did before,
or by reading SwiftSyntax's documentation.
We start by constructing
an InitializerDeclSyntax.
This type can be constructed
by building the body
using a result builder
and specifying the header--
that is the 'init' keyword
and all the parameters.
This will allow us to use a for loop
inside the result builder
to iterate over all the elements,
exactly what we need.
I just copy the init header
from our test case.
Inside the body,
we need a switch expression.
This type also has an initializer
that takes a header and a result builder.
Let's use it again.
Now we can use the power
of result builders
by iterating over all elements
that we gathered earlier.
For each element,
we want to create a new case item,
which we can construct
using string interpolation
just like we saw for ‘#stringify'.
We also need to add a default case
that returns nil.
And finally,
we can return the initializer.
Let's run the tests to see if we are
indeed generating the correct initializer.
We are.
So we know that our macro works
and we can start using it in my app.
To add our macro package
to my Xcode project,
I can right-click on it
and select "Add Package Dependencies".
I can now select the local package
that we just created.
To be able to use the macro,
I add the WWDC target
as a dependency of my app.
We can now import the WWDC module
from the package
and apply the SlopeSubset macro
to the EasySlope type.
…
If we build...
...the compiler complains
that the hand-written initializer
is an invalid redeclaration.
And that's because
the macro now generates it for us.
So we can just delete it.
It's always fun to delete code. Right?
So if we want to see
what the macro actually generated,
we can right-click on SlopeSubset
and click Expand Macro.
And if I forgot what the macro does,
I can also Option-click on it
to read its documentation.
The next step would be
to also generate the computed property,
but I'll do that later today.
By using macros, we were able to get
the type safety of EasySlopes
without the need to write repetitive code.
How did we do that?
We started with
the Swift macro package template.
To explore the syntax tree's structure,
we stopped the macro's execution
and printed the syntax node
inside the debugger.
This allowed us to see
which properties we needed to access
to get all the enum elements.
And it was really easy to develop
the macro on its own using a test case.
After we added it to my app,
it worked straight away.
But what happens if your macro is used
in situations that it doesn't support?
Just like you never want to take
a beginner skier onto a difficult slope,
you never want to let you macro
perform unexpected expansions,
or generate code that does not compile.
If your macro is used in ways
that it doesn't support,
always emit error messages that inform
your adopters about what's going wrong,
instead of having them read
the generated code to debug your macro.
In that spirit, let's go and fix
the TODO we left in our codebase.
When SlopeSubset is applied
to a type that is not an enum,
the macro should emit an error,
saying that it is only applicable
to enums.
Just like before,
let's start by adding a test case.
This time, we are applying
the SlopeSubset macro to a struct.
Since there are no enum elements
in the struct,
we don't expect the macro
to generate an initializer.
Instead, it should emit a diagnostic,
that is an error,
informing us that SlopeSubset
can only be applied to an enum.
If we run this test...
...it fails
because we are not outputting
the error message yet.
Let's go to the compiler plug-in
to do so now.
Macro errors can be represented
by any type
that conforms to the Swift Error protocol.
I use an enum with a single case
to describe the error message
if SlopeSubset is applied
to a type that's not an enum.
If we throw the error
from the expansion function,
it will be shown at the attribute
that calls the macro expansion.
If you want to show the error message at
a different location than the attribute,
generate warnings,
or even show Fix-Its in Xcode,
there's an 'addDiagnostic' method
on the context parameter
that allows you
to generate rich diagnostics.
But I think in this case, it's efficient
to just show a simple error message
at the attribute.
Now, let's see if we did everything right
and if our tests pass.
Great, they do.
So how does it look like in Xcode
if I apply SlopeSubset to a struct?
For this,
let me copy the test case into a file.
Xcode shows the custom error message
inline with all other compilation errors.
That makes it easy for adopters of
my macro to see what they are doing wrong.
And you know what?
Now that we have good error handling,
I think this macro might also be useful
for other developers
specifying enum subsets,
not just for slopes.
Let's go and generalize it.
To specify the superset of the enum,
that we have so far hard-coded as Slope,
we add a generic parameter
to the macro declaration.
And since the macro is now
no longer specific to slopes,
let's rename it to EnumSubset
by right clicking on SlopeSubset
and selecting Refactor, Rename.
I can also choose to rename all occurences
inside string literals and comments
by Command-clicking them.
We now need to adjust
our macro implementation
to use the generic parameter,
instead of the hard-coded Slopes type.
If we print the attribute
inside the debugger
and inspect its layout,
just like we did for 'enumDecl',
we can see that we can retrieve
the generic parameter
by accessing the 'argumentType'
of the first argument
in the 'genericArgumentClause'
of the attribute's name.
So now that we've retrieved
the generic parameter,
we can replace
the so-far hardcoded Slope type
by the variable 'supersetType'.
I still need to make
a couple more changes,
like renaming the initializer's parameter,
changing the macro implementation's
type name,
and updating the documentation.
I'll do that later.
Instead, for now, let's make sure
that our tests are still passing.
Since we made EnumSubset generic,
we need to explicitly specify
that EasySlope is a subset of Slope
by passing slope as a generic parameter
to the EnumSubset macro.
Let's see if the tests are now passing.
They are.
I should really consider publishing this
macro to others as a Swift package.
So that's a lot of ground
we covered today.
Let's recap what we went through.
To create a macro, you can start
with the macro package template,
which includes the stringify macro
as a great starting point.
While developing your macro,
we highly encourage you
to write test cases
to make sure that the code
your macro generates is indeed valid.
And if you're doing this, you can inspect
the layout of the syntax tree
by setting a breakpoint
in the expansion function,
running a test, and printing
the syntax tree in the debugger.
And finally, if your macro is not
applicable in certain circumstances,
so that even if things go wrong,
your macro will shine.
Thanks for watching, and I'm thrilled to
see what kind of macros you will create.