♪ ♪
Marina: Hello and welcome to WWDC.
My name is Marina, and later,
I'll be joined by my colleague Matt.
We are
from the localization team at Apple,
and today, we're excited
to show you String Catalogs.
Here at Apple, we strongly believe
in accessibility and inclusivity.
Localizing your app is one way
to ensure your content reaches
more people around the world.
In fact,
today we ship our operating systems
in more than 40 languages
and are continuously expanding this number
so that everyone can use our products
in their native language.
Our team is committed
to providing the tools in Xcode
to make localization as easy as possible,
and today we are excited
to present new improvements and workflows
for managing the localized content
in your project.
Previously,
if you wanted to localize your app,
you had to maintain strings
and stringsdict files.
This required you to manually keep
all strings in sync with your code,
and oftentimes,
you might miss localizing content.
This can result
in unlocalized strings for your users.
Our projects have relied
on this process for many years,
but in Xcode 15,
we're introducing String Catalogs.
Over time, this new format will supersede
both strings
and stringsdict files in Xcode.
String Catalogs make it easy
to manage all of your strings in one place
and be confident that your content
is fully localized before shipping.
Let's see how it works.
Here in code, I'm using SwiftUI controls
to build my views and populate content.
And this is a String Catalog.
All the strings
we just saw in my Swift code
have been
automatically extracted by Xcode.
I didn't have to add them myself.
I want to ensure that my friends in Brazil
will be able to use this app,
so I've translated it into Portuguese.
I have this view
in which I display the recent birds
that have visited this backyard.
Here, I want to make sure
we'll show the actual number of birds
that visited the backyard,
so let me add a variable
to represent this number.
And here it is in the preview.
Now we can see the number of birds.
I'll build the project
and go back to the catalog.
That was easy.
Here's the new string.
And we can see that
my translation progress has gone down.
String Catalogs also come
with powerful editing capabilities
that allow complex operations
to be done easily.
For example,
this string has the word tap,
but this a multi-platform app,
so for Mac devices,
I want to make sure
we use the correct word.
So let me go back
to my English strings,
find the string "tap to learn more."
Here it is.
I'll right click on it.
Choose vary by device.
Choose Mac.
And adapt the text correctly.
And that's it.
Now if I go back to my view
and change my run destination to Mac...
we can use the previews to check my work.
That was easy.
There's so much
you can do with String Catalogs.
Let's take a deeper look
at how everything works.
We'll start with the places
strings can be extracted from,
explore Xcode's native editor
for interacting with String Catalogs
and review
the localization export process.
Then we'll take a look
at how String Catalogs get built
and how you can adopt them
in your existing projects.
To start, I'll hand it over to Matt
to discuss localizable strings
and where they come from.
Matt: Thanks Marina!
A localizable string is simply
some string of text that will be presented
to the user at runtime,
and therefore needs to be translated
into all of the languages
your app supports.
Localizable strings have four components:
The key is a unique identifier
for the string,
often equivalent to the string itself.
This is what will be used at runtime
to look up the appropriate value
to display.
The default value can be
specified explicitly if desired,
but will otherwise fall back
to the key in the default localization.
Xcode 14.3 introduced the ability
to change the default localization
of your project using the Project Editor.
This is useful if the strings
in your source code are not in English.
Next, string comments provide a way
to give the translator context
about where and how the string
is being used in the user interface.
We recommend adding comments
to strings in order
to help resolve ambiguities
for the translator.
Finally, each localizable string
belongs to a string table,
which corresponds to one or more files
in which translations will be stored.
By default, strings from code
are placed in the "Localizable" table,
but that can be customized if you'd like
to organize your strings some other way.
Let's take a closer look at String Tables.
For an existing application
using .strings files,
a single string table actually contains
.strings and possibly .stringsdict files
within each supported language's
lproj directory.
All of the files shown here
make up the "Localizable" string table.
A String Catalog, on the other hand,
contains an entire string table
in a single file.
This includes all translations
and extra metadata
for each localizable string in that table.
If you'd like to organize your strings
into multiple string tables,
you can create multiple String Catalogs.
Each Catalog holds the string keys
belonging to that table,
along with their translations
in every language your app supports.
Although keys are always unique
within their containing table,
there is no requirement
that keys be unique across tables.
For example, the "Welcome to WWDC!" string
is present in both files here,
since it might be displayed
in different contexts within the app.
As Marina previously mentioned,
Xcode 15 will automatically populate
your String Catalogs
and make a best effort to keep them
in sync with localizable strings
found in your project.
But where does Xcode find
these localizable strings?
Well, there are a variety of places
where localizable strings might live.
Xcode can find strings in source code,
interface builder files,
and even Info plists
to include in your String Catalogs.
If you've been localizing your app
for a while now,
many of these should feel familiar.
Let's take a closer look at a few of them.
We'll start with SwiftUI.
SwiftUI makes localization seamless
because anytime you specify
a string literal within a view,
that string is
automatically considered localizable.
All of these strings are considered
localizable and will be extracted
to the String Catalog named
Localizable.xcstrings if it exists.
This works for any parameter
accepting a type of LocalizedStringKey.
SwiftUI strings can use text views
to specify comments,
custom table names,
or bundles for string lookup.
You can also define your own custom views
that accept strings
that should be
considered localizable for clients.
Notice we're using LocalizedStringResource
as the String type here.
When Xcode sees a string literal
being used to instantiate
a LocalizedStringResource
at the call site,
it will know that string is localizable.
LocalizedStringResource
is the recommended type
for representing and passing around
localizable strings.
It not only supports initialization
using a string literal,
but can also be provided with a comment,
table name,
or even a default value
that's different from the string key.
Now let's turn our attention
to Swift code more generally.
Here I have some model code that includes
strings that will be presented later.
I'm using the localized: initializers
on String and AttributedString
to specify strings I know will
be displayed to the user at runtime.
You can also use
LocalizedStringResource directly
anywhere you've imported Foundation.
String Catalogs make use
of powerful technology
in the Swift compiler in order
to extract localizable Swift strings.
For this reason,
be sure to enable the build setting
Use Compiler to Extract Swift Strings.
But String Catalogs can extract strings
from more than just Swift code.
Here's an example of some Objective-C
code using NSLocalizedString.
Any string literal embedded
in an NSLocalizedString macro
is automatically considered localizable,
and you can even define
your own similar macros
that can be detected as well.
The same concepts can also be used
in C code using CFCopyLocalizedString.
To specify any custom localized
string macros in C or Objective-C,
use the Localized String Macro Names
build setting.
Now that we've seen
how this works for source code,
let's explore localizable strings
in Interface Builder.
Strings specified in Interface Builder
are automatically treated as localizable.
Using the inspector,
you can also specify a comment
for these strings
to provide the translator with context
about where it will appear.
When a String Catalog is paired
with a Storyboard or xib,
all localizable strings
from interface builder
will be present in the Catalog.
Just like source code,
Xcode updates the Catalog
every time the project is built.
This process works similarly
for Info plist files.
For this,
simply add an InfoPlist.xcstrings file
to your project,
and add it to the desired target.
Every time you build,
Xcode will add a known set
of localizable info plist keys
to the Catalog,
and more can be added manually if needed.
Finally, Xcode includes
some big improvements this year
to the way App Shortcut phrases
are localized.
To find out more,
be sure to check out this year's talk,
"Spotlight your app with App Shortcuts."
Now that we've taken a tour of the various
places Xcode can find localizable strings,
let's talk a bit more
about how these strings
make their way to String Catalogs.
Every time you build,
Xcode will discover localizable strings
in the current scheme and platform.
Strings from source code act as the source
of truth for localizable strings,
while source strings
in the String Catalog are kept in sync.
When new strings are discovered in code,
Xcode will add them
to your String Catalog.
At this point,
the string is ready to be translated.
As we discussed earlier,
localizable strings might have
a default source value specified in code.
In that case,
the Catalog will be updated
with any new value from code.
Xcode can also discover
when you've removed a string from code.
If the string hasn't yet been translated,
Xcode will remove it for you.
However,
if you've already provided translations
for a string and then remove it,
Xcode will instead leave it alone
and mark it as Stale.
This indicates that the string
could no longer be found in code.
You can delete the string
and its translations
if you can confirm
that it is no longer needed.
Alternatively,
you can use the inspector to tell Xcode
that you'd like
to manually manage that particular string.
Manually-managed strings will
never be updated or removed by Xcode
when syncing localizations after a build.
This can be useful for strings whose keys
are either dynamically constructed in code
or perhaps originate from a database.
Now that we have all of our strings
extracted into a String Catalog,
let's take a closer look
at how the String Catalog Editor
makes it easy to manage translations.
String Catalogs come
with first-class support
for tracking states
and translation progress
as you localize your app.
We've already talked about how
Xcode will show strings as Stale
when they are no longer found in code.
But there are three other localization
states you should be aware of.
"New" indicates that a string
hasn't yet been translated
into the selected language.
You'll see this
after adding a new string in code.
"Needs Review" indicates that the string
requires the localizer's attention
because the value
might need to be changed.
If you'd like to use the current value,
simply choose "Mark as Reviewed"
from the context menu.
You can also use this menu to mark
a string for review by the localizer.
This might be useful if you receive
a bug report about a faulty translation.
Finally, strings that have been
translated in the selected language
will show a green checkmark.
This indicates
that no further action is needed.
As a developer, another common
localization challenge is pluralization.
For example,
here's the string Marina previously added
to Backyard Birds,
displaying a count of recent visitors.
In English,
we would need to change the grammar
of the string depending on whether
the number is one or some other number.
However, in a language such as Ukrainian,
there may be even more cases to consider.
To solve this problem,
we need a way to vary the string
based on the value
of the passed in number.
Previously, solving this problem
for a large number of languages
would have required a stringsdict file.
This plist format can be difficult
to use correctly and introduces
a fairly high barrier to a simple task,
like pluralizing a string.
Now the String Catalog Editor
includes built-in support
for string variation workflows.
By revealing the context menu on a string,
I'm presented
with options to vary the string.
And when I vary the string
in the default localization,
translations will
automatically be varied as well.
Here's a more complex example
of a string that needs
to use plural variation
with two variables.
At runtime, we could end up
with a few different scenarios.
We might have a single bird
in a single backyard,
multiple birds in a single backyard,
multiple birds in multiple backyards,
or a single bird
despite having multiple backyards.
In each case,
the string surrounding the numbers
needs be translated a bit differently
to maintain grammatical agreement.
The String Catalog editor
makes it easy to do this too.
This is where substitutions come in.
Here, we've varied both
of the arguments in the string by plural.
Each substitution,
prefixed with an @ sign,
stores a dictionary
of plural cases and their values.
This example
includes a "birds" substitution
for formatting a count of birds
and a "yards" substitution
for formatting a count of backyards.
At runtime, the top-level string
shown here will be used,
substituting in
the appropriate plural case
from each referenced substitution.
So in this example,
any of these strings could be produced,
effectively creating a permutation
of possible plural cases
for each substitution.
Substitutions usually correspond
to arguments passed into the string,
often using string interpolation.
In the inspector, Xcode shows information
about the position of the argument
to use for the number,
as well as the C-style format specifier
of the type being passed.
The yards substitution shown here
corresponds to argument two
because it is the second
string interpolation
used in source code.
The value of backyards.count
will then be used to determine whether
we end up using the one or other case
within this substitution.
In this way, String Catalogs
provide a simple UI for varying strings,
while still supporting
advanced use cases like this one.
Now back to Marina
to put these techniques in action.
Marina: Thanks, Matt.
Back in the Backyard Birds app,
the String Catalog Editor
makes it easy for me
to find the strings I'm looking for.
I can filter to find all the strings
containing the word "learn"
or sort by state to see
the most important states at the top.
As Matt pointed out,
there might be some strings
that are not in code
but will be displayed in the app.
For example,
I know that my app might display
a special type of bird that comes
from the cloud for app subscribers.
In this case, I can use the plus button
here to define a manual string,
give it a key…
and a comment.
Keep in mind that manually-managed strings
won't be updated or removed by Xcode.
If you'd like Xcode to start
extracting your strings from code,
expand the inspector...
and set the string
to be managed automatically.
Xcode also makes it easy
to track my localization progress.
Beside each string,
you can see a badge
that represents a translation state.
When a string was just added from code,
or manually, like we just did,
you'll see it marked as "NEW,"
meaning that it
hasn't been translated yet.
Anytime the source string changes,
the translations
will be marked for review.
Earlier, I changed this string in English,
so the existing translations
were marked for review.
If this string was okay as is,
I could just right click on the string
and choose "mark as reviewed."
Since I speak Portuguese,
I know that I need
to update this translation.
With this change,
we can see here on the sidebar
that our localization percentage went up.
Once a language is fully localized,
you'll see a green checkmark
here in the sidebar.
This is the first time you can track
your localization progress in Xcode
and be confident
that your app is fully localized
before submitting it to the App Store.
I also want to prepare this app
to be localized in Ukrainian.
I can do this
right from the String Catalog Editor
by hitting the plus button
and choosing a new language
from this list.
And here's my Ukrainian catalog
with no translations yet.
This is the string we added earlier,
and it looks like
it needs to be varied by plural.
For that, let's go back to English.
I'll right click on this string
and choose "vary by plural."
For English,
I know that I need to differentiate
between plural and singular,
so let's fix that.
In Portuguese,
the plural cases are the same as English.
However, if we peek at Ukrainian,
you can see that a different set
of plural cases was added for me.
My Ukrainian translator
will know exactly what to do with this.
Back in my view,
I wanted to add another label
that indicates the number of birds
there are in each of my backyards.
So let me add it...
Build...
And go back to my Catalog.
And here it is in my Catalog.
I also want to vary the string by plural,
but it contains multiple arguments.
This time,
when I right click on the string
and choose vary by plural,
I can choose which argument
I'd like to vary.
Let's vary by both.
Next, I'll set up my substitutions so that
they can get pluralized at runtime.
Let's move out the words
that need to agree with the argument.
So "birds" into the “birds” substitution
and "backyards"
into the "yards" substitution.
For readability,
I'd like to rename my substitutions
so that I know what arguments
the variables correspond to.
That's easier to understand.
Now Matt will show us how we can export
our strings to send them out
for translations in Ukrainian.
Matt: Thanks, Marina.
As you've already seen,
Xcode makes it easy to provide
and edit translations
directly in a String Catalog,
but oftentimes,
you'll need to work with translators
to localize the strings
in your app outside of Xcode.
For this scenario, Xcode offers
the Export Localizations option.
This generates one Localization Catalog
for each language,
which can be sent out for translation.
A Localization Catalog,
first introduced in Xcode 10,
is a package format
that contains all the localizable content
within a project or workspace.
For now, we'll focus
on the inner XLIFF file,
which contains all localizable strings
and their translations.
XLIFF is an industry-standard format
for storing and transporting
localizations.
If you or tools you maintain
work directly with XLIFF files,
you'll want to be aware of some changes
to how varied strings are represented
for projects using String Catalogs.
Here's an example XLIFF representation
of a plural string
originally defined in a .stringsdict file.
The trans unit identifiers
shown here act as paths
into the stringsdict plist format.
When varied strings instead originate
from a String Catalog,
they'll look like this instead.
They contain the string key,
a separator sequence,
and finally,
a dot-separated configuration string.
This configuration string
could be a simple plural specifier,
a device specifier,
a chain of multiple conditions,
or a path to a plural case
inside a substitution.
Not only should it be easy
for automation tooling to read these keys,
but we've also designed them
to be easy for humans
to read and understand at a glance.
Translation tools are also able to vary
a string that wasn't previously varied
by replacing the translation units
in the XLIFF
with the desired variation structure.
For example, here's a string
that is not currently varied at all.
But in Portuguese,
I'd like to provide a shorter string
on Apple Watch specifically.
By replacing that unit
with device.applewatch
and device.other variants in the XLIFF,
we can influence the variation structure
that will be present
for this language on the next import.
To ensure that XLIFF defaults
to using the String Catalog format
when exporting localizations,
be sure to set
Localization Prefers String Catalogs
to Yes.
Once you receive a translated
Localization Catalog from a translator,
you can import that back into the project.
For strings that came
from String Catalogs,
the translations specified
in the imported files will be added
to the appropriate
String Catalog automatically.
Let's try this out in Backyard Birds.
Marina: Since I speak Portuguese,
I already took care
of translating my app into Portuguese,
but I need to send
my Ukrainian localization catalog
for a translator
to provide the localized content.
I'll start by clicking here
in the Product Menu,
choose Export Localizations,
and select the languages I want to export.
In this case, just Ukrainian.
Now I can click Export.
Once they send me the translations back,
I can import them into my app.
[laptop chimes]
Oh, here they are.
Now with the translations ready,
I'll go back to my app,
click the Product menu,
this time, choose Import Localizations,
and choose
my Ukrainian localization catalog.
Okay, let's see how everything looks.
Perfect,
my Ukrainian translations are in place,
and now I have my app
completely localized in both languages.
Let's see how it looks in Portuguese.
I'll click on the scheme selector
and choose Edit Scheme.
Under the options, I can change the app
language from system to Portuguese.
And I'll run the app.
Cool, here are some
of the strings we worked with.
Now that we're done translating,
take it over, Matt.
Matt: Now that our app's content
is fully translated,
let's briefly discuss
what happens during the build.
String Catalogs are designed specifically
for interaction within an Xcode project.
As JSON files under the hood,
they should also be
easily diffable in source control.
Then, at build time, these files compile
to .strings and .stringsdict files.
Because these file formats
have been supported
in our operating systems
for many years now,
I'm happy to say that you can start
using String Catalogs right away
without having to update
your minimum deployment target.
It's also worth noting
that source strings extracted from code
are not included in the final build.
This should save on disk space
without affecting the strings
displayed at runtime.
Now that we've seen
all these benefits in action,
Marina will show you how to get started
with String Catalogs
in your existing projects.
Marina: Xcode makes it easy
for you to migrate your existing projects
to use String Catalogs.
And you can do this at your own pace.
Whenever you're ready,
you can pick which strings files
and targets to migrate.
Here's an existing app
that we localized last year, FoodTruck.
You can see here that it has
a strings and stringsdict file.
String Catalogs can coexist
with the legacy formats,
so I can choose to migrate
the Localizable table whenever I'm ready.
Let's do this now.
I'll right click on the file and choose
"Migrate to String Catalog."
Xcode includes
a built-in Migration Assistant
that lists all the migratable files
in my project.
Here I can see the Localizable table
that is part of the FoodTruck target.
I'm gonna go ahead and migrate this now.
Nice! After migrating,
Xcode will build my project
to extract strings.
Let's see how
the Catalog looks after the build.
Here we can see that all
of the strings from my strings file
and even the plurals
from the stringsdict file were migrated.
All my Arabic translations are in place,
but we can see here
that the translation progress
is not 100% for French.
String Catalogs are already helping me
find unlocalized strings in my project.
FoodTruck also has a swift package,
FoodTruckKit,
that hasn't been localized yet.
Getting started localizing
a new package or project is super easy
with String Catalogs.
I'll start by adding
a default localization
to the package manifest
and ensure
I'm using Swift Tools version 5.9.
Then I'll add a new String Catalog
to the package
with the default table name "Localizable."
After building my project,
I can see all of the strings
from throughout my package.
It's that easy to get started
localizing a new project or package.
String Catalogs are the new
foundation of localization in Xcode
and simplify the process
of managing translations in your project.
We hope you'll get started today
by migrating your existing strings.
And if you've
never localized an app before,
we hope you'll be inspired
by how easy it is to get started.
Obrigada pela companhia hoje.
Thanks for joining us,
and happy birdwatching.
♪ ♪