♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Ryan Taylor: Hello!
My name is Ryan.
Conner Brooks: And I'm Conner.
Ryan: In this session, we are
going to introduce you
to ARKit for spatial computing.
We will discuss
the critical role that it plays
on this new platform
and how you can leverage it
to build the next
generation of apps.
ARKit uses sophisticated
computer vision algorithms
to construct an understanding
of the world around you,
as well as your movements.
We first introduced
this technology in iOS 11
as a way for developers
to create
amazing augmented reality
experiences
that you can use
in the palm of your hand.
On this platform,
ARKit has matured
into a full-blown
system service,
rebuilt from the ground up with
a new real-time foundation.
ARKit is deeply woven
into the fabric
of the entire operating system,
powering everything
from interacting with a window,
to playing an immersive game.
As part of this journey,
we have also given our API
a complete overhaul.
The new design is
a result of everything
that we learned on iOS,
plus the unique needs
of spatial computing,
and we think
you are going to love it.
ARKit provides a variety
of powerful features
that you can combine
to do incredible things,
such as place virtual content
on a table.
You can reach out
and touch the content,
as if it is really there,
and then watch
as the content interacts
with the real world.
It is truly
a magical experience.
Now that you have seen a glimpse
of what can be accomplished
using ARKit
on this new platform,
let me walk you
through our agenda.
We will begin with an overview
of the fundamental concepts
and building blocks
that make up our API.
Next, we will dive
into world tracking,
which is essential
for placing virtual content
relative to the real world.
Then, we will explore our
scene understanding features,
which provide useful information
about your surroundings.
After that, we will introduce
you to our newest feature,
hand tracking, an exciting new
addition that you can leverage
for placing virtual content
relative to your hands
or building other types
of bespoke interactions.
And lastly, we will come
full circle and take a look
at a practical application
of some of these features
by examining code from the video
that we showed you a moment ago.
All right, let's get started!
Our new API has been
meticulously crafted
in two invigorating flavors,
modern Swift and classic C.
All ARKit features are
now provided à la carte.
We wanted developers to have
as much flexibility as possible,
so that you can simply pick
and choose what you need
to build your experience.
Access to ARKit data
has been designed
with a privacy-first approach.
We have put safeguards
into place
to protect people's privacy,
while also maintaining
simplicity for developers.
The API consists of three
fundamental building blocks:
sessions,
data providers,
and anchors.
Let's begin with anchors
and then work our way
back up to sessions.
An anchor represents
a position and orientation
in the real world.
All anchors include
a unique identifier,
as well as a transform.
Some types of anchors
are also trackable.
When a trackable anchor
is not being tracked,
you should hide
any virtual content
that you have anchored with it.
A data provider represents
an individual ARKit feature.
Data providers
allow you to poll for
or observe data updates,
such as anchor changes.
Different types
of data providers
provide different types of data.
A session represents
a combined set of ARKit features
that you would like
to use together
for a particular experience.
You run a session by providing
it with a set of data providers.
Once the session is running,
the data providers
will begin receiving data.
Updates arrive asynchronously
and at different frequencies,
depending on the type of data.
Let's move on now
and talk about privacy
and how your app
gets access to ARKit data.
Privacy is a fundamental
human right.
It is also one
of our core values.
ARKit's architecture and API
have been thoughtfully designed
to protect people's privacy.
In order for ARKit to construct
an understanding
of the world around you,
the device has many cameras
and other types of sensors.
Data from these sensors,
such as camera frames,
is never sent to client space.
Instead, sensor data is sent
to ARKit's daemon
for secure processing
by our algorithms.
The resulting data that is
produced by these algorithms
is then carefully curated
before being forwarded
to any clients that are
requesting the data,
such as your app.
There are a few prerequisites
to accessing ARKit data.
First, your app must enter
a Full Space.
ARKit does not send data to apps
that are in the Shared Space.
Second, some types of ARKit data
require permission to access.
If the person does
not grant permission,
then we will not send
that type of data to your app.
To facilitate this,
ARKit provides
a convenient authorization API
for handling permission.
Using your session,
you can request authorization
for the types of data
that you would like to access.
If you do not do this,
ARKit will automatically prompt
the person for permission
when you run the session,
if necessary.
Here, we are requesting access
to hand tracking data.
You can batch all of
the authorization types
that you need together
in a single request.
Once we have
the authorization results,
we iterate over them
and check the status
for each authorization type.
If the person has
granted permission,
the status will be allowed.
Attempting to run a session
with a data provider
that provides data that
the person has denied access to
will result
in the session failing.
Now, let's take a closer look
at each of the features
that ARKit supports
on this platform,
starting with world tracking.
World tracking allows you
to anchor virtual content
in the real world.
ARKit tracks
the device's movement
in six degrees of freedom
and updates each anchor,
so that they stay
in the same place
relative to your surroundings.
The type of DataProvider
that world tracking uses
is called WorldTrackingProvider,
and it gives you
several important capabilities.
It allows you to add
WorldAnchors,
which ARKit will then update
to remain fixed
relative to people's
surroundings
as the device moves around.
WorldAnchors are
an essential tool
for virtual content placement.
Any WorldAnchors that you add
are automatically persisted
across app launches and reboots.
If this behavior is undesirable
for the experience
that you are building,
you can simply remove
the anchors when
you are done with them,
and they will no longer
be persisted.
It is important to note
that there are some cases
where persistence
will not be available.
You can also use
a WorldTrackingProvider
to get the device's pose
relative to the app origin,
which is necessary if you are
doing your own rendering
using Metal.
Let's begin by taking a closer
look at what a WorldAnchor is
and why you would
want to use one.
A WorldAnchor is
a TrackableAnchor
with an initializer
that takes a transform,
which is the position
and orientation
that you would like
to place the anchor at,
relative to the app's origin.
We have prepared an example
to help visualize the difference
between virtual content
that is not anchored
versus content that is anchored.
Here we have two cubes.
The blue cube on the left is not
being updated by a WorldAnchor,
while the red cube
on the right is being updated
by a WorldAnchor.
Both cubes were placed relative
to the app's origin
when the app was launched.
As the device moves around,
both cubes remain
where they were placed.
You can press and hold the crown
to recenter the app.
When recentering occurs,
the app's origin will be moved
to your current location.
Notice that the blue cube,
which is not anchored,
relocates to maintain
its relative placement
to the app's origin;
while the red cube,
which is anchored,
remains fixed
relative to the real world.
Let's take a look at how
WorldAnchor persistence works.
As the device moves around,
ARKit builds a map
of your surroundings.
When you add WorldAnchors,
we insert them into the map
and automatically
persist them for you.
Only WorldAnchor identifiers
and transforms are persisted.
No other data,
such as your virtual content,
is included.
It is up to you
to maintain a mapping
of WorldAnchor identifiers
to any virtual content
that you associate with them.
Maps are location based,
so when you take your device
to a new location --
for instance,
from home to the office --
the map of your home
will be unloaded,
and then a different map will be
localized for the office.
Any anchors that you add
at this new location
will go into that map.
When you leave the office
at the end of the day
and head home,
the map that ARKit
has been building at the office,
along with any anchors
that you placed there,
will be unloaded.
Once again, though,
we have been
automatically persisting the map
along with your anchors.
Upon returning home,
ARKit will recognize that
the location has changed,
and we will begin
the process of relocalizing
by checking for an existing map
for this location.
If we find one,
we will localize with it,
and all of the anchors that
you previously added at home
will become tracked once again.
Let's move on
to the device pose.
Along with adding
and removing WorldAnchors,
you can also use
a WorldTrackingProvider
to get the pose of the device.
The pose is the position
and orientation of the device
relative to the app's origin.
Querying the pose is required
if you are doing
your own rendering with Metal
and CompositorServices
in a fully immersive experience.
This query
is relatively expensive.
Exercise caution when
querying for the device pose
for other types of app logic,
such as content placement.
Let's quickly walk through
a simplified rendering example
to demonstrate how you can
provide device poses
from ARKit
to CompositorServices.
We have a Renderer struct
that will hold our session,
world tracking provider,
and latest pose.
When initializing the Renderer,
we start by creating a session.
Next, we create
a world tracking provider,
which we will use to query
for the device pose
when we render each frame.
Now, we can go ahead
and run our session
with any data providers
that we need.
In this case, we are only using
a world tracking provider.
We also create a pose
to avoid allocating
in the render function.
Let's jump over
to our render function now,
which we will be calling
at frame rate.
Using the drawable
from CompositorServices,
we fetch the target render time.
Next, we use
the target render time
to query for the pose
of the device.
If successful, we can extract
a transform of the pose
relative to the app's origin.
This is the transform to use
for rendering your content.
Lastly, before we submit
the frame for compositing,
we set the pose on the drawable,
so that the compositor knows
which pose we used
to render content for the frame.
For more information
on doing your own rendering,
see the dedicated session
for using Metal
to create immersive apps.
Additionally,
there is a great session
on spatial computing
performance considerations
that we encourage you
to check out as well.
Next, let's take a look
at scene understanding.
Scene understanding
is a category of features
that inform you about your
surroundings in different ways.
Let's begin
with plane detection.
Plane detection provides
anchors for horizontal
and vertical surfaces that
ARKit detects in the real world.
The type of DataProvider
that plane detection uses
is called
PlaneDetectionProvider.
As planes are detected
in your surroundings,
they are provided to you
in the form of PlaneAnchors.
PlaneAnchors can be used
to facilitate content placement,
such as placing
a virtual object on a table.
Additionally, you can use planes
for physics simulations
where basic, flat geometry,
such as a floor or wall,
is sufficient.
Each PlaneAnchor
includes an alignment,
which is horizontal or vertical;
the geometry of the plane;
and a semantic classification.
Planes can be classified
as a variety
of different types of surfaces,
such as floor or table.
If we are unable to identify
a particular surface,
the provided classification will
be marked as either unknown,
undetermined, or not available,
depending on the circumstances.
Now, let's move on
to scene geometry.
Scene geometry provides anchors
containing a polygonal mesh
that estimates the shape
of the real world.
The type of DataProvider
that scene geometry uses
is called
SceneReconstructionProvider.
As ARKit scans
the world around you,
we reconstruct your surroundings
as a subdivided mesh,
which is then provided to you
in the form of MeshAnchors.
Like PlaneAnchors,
MeshAnchors can be used
to facilitate content placement.
You can also achieve
higher-fidelity
physics simulations
in cases where you need
virtual content to interact
with objects that are not
just simple, flat surfaces.
Each MeshAnchor includes
geometry of the mesh.
This geometry contains
vertices, normals, faces,
and semantic classifications,
which are per face.
Mesh faces can be
classified as a variety
of different types of objects.
If we are unable to identify
a particular object,
the provided classification
will be none.
Lastly, let's take a look
at image tracking.
Image tracking enables you
to detect 2D images
in the real world.
The type of DataProvider
that image tracking uses
is called ImageTrackingProvider.
You configure
ImageTrackingProvider
with a set of ReferenceImages
that you want to detect.
These ReferenceImages can be
created in a few different ways.
One option is to load them
from an AR resource group
in your project's asset catalog.
Alternatively,
you can also initialize
a ReferenceImage yourself
by providing a CVPixelBuffer
or CGImage.
When an image is detected,
ARKit provides you
with an ImageAnchor.
ImageAnchors can be used
to place content
at known,
statically placed images.
For instance, you can display
some information
about a movie
next to a movie poster.
ImageAnchors are
TrackableAnchors
that include an estimated
scale factor,
which indicates how the size
of the detected image
compares to the physical size
that you specified
and the ReferenceImage
that the anchor corresponds to.
Now, to tell you about
our new feature, hand tracking,
and then walk you
through the example,
here is Conner.
Conner: Howdy.
Let's take a look
at hand tracking,
a brand-new addition to ARKit.
Hand tracking provides you
with anchors
containing skeletal data
for each of your hands.
The type of DataProvider
that hand tracking uses
is called HandTrackingProvider.
When your hands are detected,
they are provided to you
in the form of HandAnchors.
A HandAnchor is
a TrackableAnchor.
HandAnchors include a skeleton
and a chirality.
The chirality tells us whether
this is a left or a right hand.
A HandAnchor's transform
is the wrist's transform
relative to the app origin.
The skeleton consists of joints,
which can be queried by name.
A joint contains
its parent joint; its name;
a localTransform, which is
relative to its parent joint;
a rootTransform, which is
relative to the root joint;
and finally, each joint
contains a bool,
which indicates whether or not
this joint is tracked.
Here we enumerate all
of the available joints
in the hand skeleton.
Let's walk through a subset
of the joint's hierarchy.
The wrist is the root joint
for the hand.
For each finger, the first joint
is parented to the wrist;
for example, 1 is parented to 0.
Subsequent finger joints are
parented to the previous joint;
for example, 2 is parented to 1,
and so on.
HandAnchors can be
used to place content
relative to your hands
or detect custom gestures.
There are two options
for receiving HandAnchors --
you can either poll for updates
or receive anchors
asynchronously
when they are available.
We'll take a look
at asynchronous updates
in our Swift example later on,
so let's add hand anchor polling
to our renderer from earlier.
Here's our updated
struct definition.
We've added
a hand tracking provider,
along with a left and right
hand anchor.
In our updated init function,
we create
our new hand tracking provider
and add it to the list
of providers that we run;
we then create
the left and right hand anchors
that we'll need when we poll.
Note, we create these
ahead of time
in order to avoid allocating
in the render loop.
With our struct updated
and initialized,
we can call get_latest_anchors
in our render function.
We pass the provider and
our preallocated hand anchors.
Our anchors will be populated
with the latest available data.
With our latest
anchors populated,
we can now use their data
in our experience.
Very cool.
Now it's time to revisit the
example we showed you earlier.
We used a combination of ARKit
and RealityKit features
to build this experience.
Scene geometry was used
as colliders for physics
and gestures,
while hand tracking was used
to directly interact
with the cube entities.
Let's take a look
at how we built this example.
First, we'll check out
the app struct and view model.
Next, we'll initialize
the ARKit session.
Then we'll add colliders
for our fingertips
and colliders
from scene reconstruction.
Finally, we'll look at how
to add cubes with gestures.
Let's just jump right into it.
Here is our app, TimeForCube.
We have a relatively standard
SwiftUI app and scene setup.
Within our scene,
we declare an ImmersiveSpace.
The IimmersiveSpace is required
as we'll need to move
to a Full Space in order
to get access to ARKit data.
Within the ImmersiveSpace,
we define a RealityView
which will present the content
from our view model.
The view model is where most
of our app's logic will live.
Let's take a quick look.
The view model holds
onto the ARKit session;
the data providers
we'll be using;
our content entity,
which will contain
all other entities
that we create;
and both our scene
and hand collider maps.
Our view model also
provides various functions
that we'll call from the app.
We'll go through each of these
in context from the app.
The first function we'll call
is within our RealityView's
make closure to set up
the contentEntity.
We'll add this entity to
the content of our RealityView,
so that the view model can add
entities to the view's content.
setupContentEntity simply adds
all the finger entities
in our map as children
of the contentEntity
and then returns it.
Nice!
Let's move on
to session initialization.
Our session initialization
runs in one of three tasks.
Our first task calls
the runSession function.
This function simply runs the
session with our two providers.
With the session running,
we can start receiving
anchor updates.
Let's create and update
our fingertip colliders
we'll use to interact
with cubes.
Here is our task
for processing hand updates.
Its function iterates over
the async sequence
of anchor updates
on the provider.
We ensure that the hand anchor
is tracked,
get the index fingertip joint,
and check that the joint itself
is also tracked.
We then compute the transform
of the tip of the index finger
relative to the app origin.
Finally, we look up which
finger entity we should update
and set its transform.
Let's revisit
our finger entity map.
We create an entity per hand
via an extension to ModelEntity,
This extension creates a 5mm
sphere with a collision shape.
We add a kinematic
physics body component
and hide this entity by adding
an opacity component.
Though we'll hide these
for our use case,
it'd be nice to visualize
our fingertip entities
to verify that everything
is working as expected.
Let's temporarily set
our opacity to one
and make sure our entities
are in the right place.
Great!
We can see spheres
right where our fingertips are!
Notice, our hands are partially
covering up the spheres.
This is called hand occlusion,
a system feature that allows
a person to see their hands
on top of virtual content.
This is enabled by default,
but if we'd like to see our
sphere a little more clearly,
we can configure
hand occlusion visibility
by using the upperLimbVisibility
setter on our scene.
If we set limb visibility
to hidden,
we'll see the entire sphere
regardless of where
our hands are.
For our example, we'll leave
the upper limb visibility
as the default value and set
the opacity back to zero.
Neat! Now let's add
scene colliders --
we'll use these for physics
and as gesture targets.
Here's the task that calls
the function on our model.
We iterate over the async
sequence of anchor updates
on the provider,
attempt to generate
a ShapeResource
from the MeshAnchor,
then switch on the anchor
update's event.
If we're adding an anchor,
we create a new entity,
set its transform,
add a collision and
physics body component,
then add an input target
component
so that this collider
can be a target for gestures.
Finally, we add
a new entity to our map
and as a child
of our content entity.
To update an entity,
we retrieve it from the map,
then update its transform
and collision component shape.
For removal, we remove
the corresponding entity
from its parent and the map.
Now that we have
hand and scene colliders,
we can use gestures
to add cubes.
We add a SpatialTapGesture
targeted to any entity,
which will let us know
if someone has tapped
on any entity in
our RealityView's content.
When that tap has ended,
we receive a 3D location
we convert from global
to scene coordinates.
Let's visualize this location.
Here's what we'd see
if we added a sphere
at the location of the tap.
Now, we tell our view model
to add a cube
relative to this location.
To add a cube, we first
calculate a placement location
that's 20 centimeters
above the tap location.
We then create the cube
and set its position
to our calculated
placement location.
We add an InputTargetComponent,
which allows us set
which types of gestures
our entity will respond to.
For our use case, we'll allow
only indirect input types
for these cubes,
as our fingertip colliders
will provide direct interaction.
We add a PhysicsBodyComponent
with custom parameters
to make the physics interactions
a bit nicer.
Last, we add our cube
to the content entity,
which means it is finally
time for cube.
Let's take one last look
at our example, end to end.
Every time we tap on
the scene colliders or a cube,
a new cube is added
above the tap location.
The physics system
causes the cube
to drop onto
the scene colliders,
and our hand colliders allow us
to interact with the cubes.
For more information
about RealityKit,
check out the introductory
session on using RealityKit
for spatial computing.
And, if you already have
an existing ARKit experience
on iOS that you're interested
in bringing over
to this platform,
be sure to watch
the dedicated session on
this topic for further guidance.
Our entire team is incredibly
thrilled for you
to get your hands on
the new version of ARKit.
We cannot wait to see all
of the groundbreaking apps
that you will create
for this exciting new platform.
Ryan: Thanks for watching!
♪