♪ ♪
Philippe: Hi, my name is Philippe.
I am really pleased to present a magical
new feature in Swift:
Observation.
This feature lets you define your models
using standard Swift syntax
and use those types to have UI
respond to changes to that model.
This makes developing with SwiftUI
seamless and intuitive.
Today we will be covering a few topics:
An overview of what Observation is,
a set of handy rules on when to use
the property wrappers from SwiftUI,
then we'll cover a few of
the more advanced usages of observable.
And we'll wrap up with some examples
on how to update code
from using ObservableObject
to the new @Observable macro.
Observation is a new Swift feature
for tracking changes to properties.
It works with normal Swift types
and transforms them with magic of macros.
We often write data model types,
and they have a number of properties
that eventually,
we'll want to use in SwiftUI.
What if I told you adding @Observable
is all you need
to make UI respond to changes
in your data models?
New in Swift 5.9 you can
make models simpler than ever.
This uses the new macro system in Swift.
The "@Observable" tells the Swift compiler
to transform your code
from what you wrote to an expanded form
that makes the type able to be observed.
You can use observable types
to power your SwiftUI views.
And the amazing part is that they don't
need any sort of property wrapper to work.
I have some tasty samples
from our donut food truck app,
so let's dive right in.
Here we have a simple view showing donuts.
SwiftUI knows that the model
accesses specific properties
when executing the body call.
In this case it can detect
that the property 'donuts'
is accessed when executing
the body of the donut menu view.
When body is executed,
SwiftUI tracks all access
to properties used
from 'Observable' types.
It then takes that tracking information
and uses it to determine
when the next change to any of those
properties on those specific instances
will change.
Here, if we change the donuts array
by clicking the add donut button,
it will invalidate the donut menu view
and the UI is updated accordingly.
What's neat, is that if,
say an order is added,
the view won't be invalidated
because that property
isn't part of the tracked properties
it determined
when executing the body of the view.
Let's next cover what happens
when you use a computed property.
Adding in a computed property
follows those same rules as before.
When a property that is used changes,
the UI updates.
In the newly added content,
the model's orderCount is called,
which that accesses the orders property.
So that means, in this example
if the orders change,
that text will be updated
because the orderCount
accesses the order's property.
Using the "@Observable" macro
expands your types
so they can support Observation.
This lets SwiftUI track access
to those properties
and observe when the next property
will change out of that Observation.
Tracking things like that
let your UI only recalculate
the body of views
when those specific properties change,
which we've seen some really fantastic
performance improvements from that.
If you wanna dive deep into macros,
make sure to check out the
"Write Swift macros"
and "Expand on Swift macros" sessions.
With Observable, the property wrappers
for SwiftUI are even easier than ever.
State, environment, and bindable
are the three primary property wrappers
for working with SwiftUI.
We've already covered the case
where you don't need any property wrappers
to interface with observable types
with SwiftUI,
but let's dive into the cases
where you do.
Starting off with @State.
When the view needs to have its own state
stored in a model,
use the @State property.
Here we have the observable model object
Donut being used in a sheet presentation.
When the sheet is presented,
the donutToAdd state variable
is used to bind values
to the editable fields.
The "donutToAdd" property
is managed by the lifetime of the view
it's contained in.
Next up, @Environment.
Environment lets values be propagated
as globally accessible values.
This lets things be shared in many places.
Observable types work fantastically here
since the updates created by them
are based upon access.
When invoking the body of
the food truck menu view,
the property userName
of the account object is accessed.
So when the userName will change,
the menu view updates.
The newest of the family of
property wrappers is '@Bindable'.
The bindable property wrapper
is really lightweight.
All it does is allow bindings
to be created from that type.
Getting binding out of a bindable
wrapped property is really easy.
Just use the $ syntax
to get the binding to that property.
Most often, this will be bindings
to observable types.
For the donut view, we have
the name being displayed with Text.
But in reality, we want to be able
to edit that name.
So instead of a Text,
we can use a TextField.
That TextField takes a binding.
It reads from the binding
to populate the value of the TextField,
but it also writes back to the binding
when the user changes the value.
To make bindings to the donut,
all we need to do is use
the '@Bindable' property wrapper
on the donut property.
The property wrapper annotation allows us
to use the '$donut.name' syntax
and creates a binding when used.
To wrap up the wrappers,
there are only three questions
you need to answer for using
observable models in SwiftUI.
Does this model
need to be state of the view itself?
If so, use '@State'.
Does this model need to be part of
the global environment of the application?
If so, use '@Environment'.
Does this model just need bindings?
If so, use the new '@Bindable'.
And if none of these questions
have the answer as yes,
just use the model
as a property of your view.
So far, we've covered properties
that start off in your model as stored.
Observable can do a lot more.
Because SwiftUI tracks access
to fields per instance,
it means that you can use arrays,
optionals, or for that matter,
any type that contains
your observable models.
The donut list view has
an array of donut models.
Each model itself is '@Observable'.
When any of the names
of those donuts change,
SwiftUI detects the access to that
property on that specific instance
and tracks it to know
when to invalidate the view.
So here, when the donut name
is changed via the randomize button,
the view updates accordingly.
This lets you build your models
how you want.
You can have arrays of models
being observed,
or even model types
that contain other observable model types.
The general rule is for Observable,
if a property that is used changes,
the view will update.
There is a case
where that rule does not fully apply.
If a computed property does not have
any stored property it is comprised with,
then two extra steps need to be taken
to make it work with Observation.
This only needs to be done
when the property that would be observed
is not changed
via some sort of composition
of stored properties
in the observable type.
In this case, all that needs to be done
is tell Observation
when the property is accessed
and when the property changes.
This is how Observation synthesizes
access to properties normally,
except here we've rewritten
those custom access points manually
so that the non-observable location
can be read and store the name.
Most of the time, these type
of manual cases are not needed,
because most of the time,
properties of the models in question
are composed from other stored properties.
But in the rare cases where
you need that advanced capability,
Observation is flexible enough
but easy enough to do on your own.
SwiftUI can identify changes
in composition
since it tracks observable types
by access to those properties.
This means that if a computed property
is composed from other stored properties,
then the Observation will just work.
However, in the few cases
where that's not true,
you can use Observation directly
to manually add those calls
to flag access and mutation.
Previously in the Food Truck app,
we used ObservableObject to achieve some
of the same things
we did with the new @Observable macro.
If you have an app
that uses SwiftUI today,
you might be in a very similar situation.
The Observable macro
can simplify your code
and chances are, you might see
a decent performance boost too.
Before the change,
the FoodTruckModel type
had an ObservableObject conformance,
and it had a number of properties
that were marked
with the @Published property wrapper.
Changing over to
the @Observable macro was pretty easy.
All we needed to do is remove
the conformance to ObservableObject,
remove the '@Published',
and mark it with the '@Observable' macro.
When it comes to the views,
there were a number of '@ObservedObject'
and '@EnvironmentObject'
property wrappers.
In all cases
of the '@ObservedObject' wrappers,
either disappeared
or needed just the bindings
and changed to the new '@Bindable'.
The '@EnvironmentObject' wrappers
got transformed into just '@Environment'.
Changing from ObservableObject
to the new '@Observable' macro
was mostly just deleting annotations.
Or simplifying them down
to the three primary property wrappers;
@State, @Environment, and @Bindable.
Which makes writing new features
easier to reason about
since there are fewer options
that need to be considered.
Observation has
just the right level of magic.
It lets you get started easily
and lets you work
with your data models directly
by using the @Observable macro.
When you need,
it lets you write the manual versions
for advanced use cases.
For new development, using Observable
is the easiest way to get started.
And for existing applications,
using Observable can simplify your models
and improve performance
when adding new features.
I encourage you to try it out
and harness that magic yourself.
♪ ♪