♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Justin Thomas: Hi, everyone!
My name
is Justin Thomas.
I'm an engineer
on the App Store Connect team.
Maciej Kujalowicz: And I am
Maciej Kujalowicz,
an engineer
on the TestFlight team.
Justin: Together, we will show
you how xrOS opens the door
for you to create amazing
spatial experiences.
And with a new App Store
on xrOS,
users can discover and download
your incredible apps.
In this session,
I'll start by walking through
all the different ways you can
make your apps available
on xrOS.
Then, Maciej will show you
everything you need to know
about beta testing on xrOS.
Finally, I'll help you make sure
that your app is ready
to be published
on the App Store.
All right, so let's dive in
with setting up your app.
In App Store Connect, you have
three options to choose from
when setting up your app.
You can create a new app
with the xrOS platform.
This is the option to select
if you're introducing a new app
to the App Store
for the first time,
or if you want to configure
your xrOS app
to have a different
price or availability
than your other apps.
You can also add the xrOS
platform to an existing app
to create a universal purchase.
This allows your users to enjoy
your app and in-app purchases
across all platforms.
Your app will have the same name
and URL across all platforms,
making it easier
for users to find it.
Your app will
automatically install
for users across their devices
when they have
automatic downloads enabled.
And finally, you can choose
to make your compatible iPad
and iPhone apps
available on xrOS
without making any code changes
or submitting a new build.
This is a great option if you're
still working on your xrOS app,
but you want users on xrOS
devices to enjoy your app
as soon as possible.
OK, let's look at each of these
options in App Store Connect,
starting with creating
a new app.
Let's say I'm a developer
on the Nature Lab team,
and I'm excited to create
a fully immersive app
for my customers.
I'm planning to introduce
Backyard Birds to the App Store.
Since Backyard Birds
is a new app,
I'll first need to create
a new app record.
I can do this by clicking
the plus (+) button
in the upper-left area
of the Apps page,
and then selecting New App
from the drop-down menu.
From the New App dialog,
I'll select xrOS
under Platforms,
and then fill in
the remaining fields
like Name, Bundle ID, and SKU.
That's it!
I'll just need to click Create
to complete the new app record
for Backyard Birds, then I can
begin uploading builds.
Next, let's look at adding xrOS
to an existing app.
I'm back on the Apps page
for my Nature Lab team.
My customers love tracking
their favorite
mountain climbing routes
with Mountain Climber on iOS,
so I decided to introduce
a new experience on xrOS.
To add the xrOS platform, I'll
select my Mountain Climber app.
And from here,
I'll click Add Platform
from the left sidebar.
On the Add Platform dialog,
I'll just need to select xrOS,
then click Add.
Once the platform is added,
I can then begin uploading
builds for Mountain Climber.
And finally, all compatible
iPad and iPhone apps
are automatically made available
on the App Store on xrOS.
If there's any reason
why you think your app
doesn't make sense
on the platform,
you can manage
its availability on xrOS.
Let's take a look.
On the Apps page,
click the ellipsis (…) button
in the upper-left area,
then select
"iOS Apps on xrOS Availability"
from the drop-down menu.
From here, you have full control
over managing which apps
are made available on xrOS.
If your compatible iPad
and iPhone app is made available
by using this option and
you later add the xrOS platform,
releasing it will replace
the iOS app version
on the App Store.
For the Nature Lab team,
I wanted to make sure
that all of our compatible apps
are made available,
so I'll keep
the default settings here.
You can also manage
an individual app's availability
from the
Pricing and Availability page.
Under the iPhone and iPad Apps
on xrOS section,
you have the option
to “Make this app available”.
You can also verify
if your current
and upcoming app versions
are compatible with xrOS.
To learn more about
compatible iPad and iPhone apps
and how to make sure
your apps run properly,
check out the sessions
"Run your iPad and iPhone apps
in the Shared Space" and
"Enhance your iPad and iPhone
apps for the Shared Space".
So we just covered all the ways
for setting up an xrOS app
in App Store Connect.
Next, you'll want to test
your xrOS and compatible iPad
and iPhone apps to ensure
a solid user experience.
And with that,
I'll pass it over to Maciej
to talk to you about TestFlight.
Maciej: Thank you, Justin!
TestFlight is an essential tool
to help you distribute
and install beta versions
of your apps.
You can create
your teams of testers,
define distribution rules,
and incorporate feedback
to create best-in-class
applications for the App Store.
To manage your beta testing,
go to the App Store Connect
website.
Check the TestFlight tab,
where you can create groups,
add testers,
and distribute builds.
You can also manage
testers and groups
using App Store Connect on iOS
or the App Store Connect API.
To get a general overview about
how to run your beta program,
check out our Tech Talk on how
to get started with TestFlight.
For more information on how
to automate distributing builds
in continuous
integration services,
watch our previous session
"Explore Xcode Cloud workflows."
TestFlight is available for all
existing operating systems
and provides
a consistent experience
for installing beta apps.
Additionally, testers can send
screenshots and crash feedback
on iOS and macOS.
And today we are introducing
support for xrOS.
TestFlight on xrOS will help you
test your immersive apps
to make sure they offer
the best possible experience
on the device and are ready
for the App Store.
It also lets you install and run
iPad and iPhone apps
to verify they are
fully compatible
and work great on xrOS.
In this section, I will walk you
through the major use cases
of TestFlight to help you
distribute builds,
install apps,
and collect feedback.
Let's start
with distributing builds.
Creating groups
and inviting testers
is a feature available
for all platforms.
It's no different for xrOS.
You have an option to use
internal or external groups
and invite testers
by email or public link.
In this example,
the xrOS platform has been added
to an existing app record.
You can create
a new group of testers
and start uploading
builds there.
You can also distribute
xrOS builds
through any existing group.
In this scenario, testers
will have access to builds
for multiple platforms.
TestFlight gives you
full control over which group
can install iOS apps on xrOS.
Each group has an option
to enable or disable
the ability to install
iPhone and iPad apps
by testers from this group
on the headset.
This option can help you
expand the team of testers
while you progress
with testing the compatibility
of your iOS apps.
Now that you know
how to distribute your builds,
let me walk you
through the process
of installing and running beta
apps on xrOS as a tester.
After launching TestFlight,
I can browse all the apps
developers invited me to test.
My list in the sidebar includes
both xrOS and iOS apps
that can be installed
and tested on my device.
Applications not compatible
to install
are listed in a separate
category of iOS-only apps.
When a developer
invites me to test
both the xrOS and iOS version,
TestFlight allows me to switch
between each type of the app.
Toggle at the top of the app
page allows me to choose
which version I would like
to install and test.
From this page, I can check
the details of each app,
review the description,
confirm whether the app is
compatible with my device.
Additionally, I can scroll down
the list to App Settings
and customize notifications
or opt in for automatic updates,
in which case all new versions
of the app are downloaded
and installed automatically
by TestFlight on my device.
Once the beta app is installed,
I can launch it directly
from TestFlight
or from the Home Screen.
All beta apps are distinguished
by a yellow dot
displayed next to the app name,
like on other platforms.
Compatible iPad and iPhone apps
are grouped together
in a dedicated folder,
where the yellow dot is also
presented for beta versions.
When I launch the updated app,
TestFlight displays information
provided by the developer
to describe changes
in the latest build.
This is a good opportunity
for the developer to recommend
which areas I should focus on
while testing the app.
Now, let's talk about how you
can get feedback from testers
about their experience
with your apps on xrOS.
Testers can send feedback
when they notice issues
within your app or if they want
to suggest some improvements.
As a tester, If I want to share
feedback with the developer
about my experience on xrOS,
I can quickly press
the Digital Crown
and top buttons together
to capture screenshots.
Next, I open TestFlight,
select the app,
and touch the Send Feedback
button to initiate the process.
I start with describing
the problem.
I attach all the screenshots
I have captured
to support the feedback.
I can crop or annotate images
to focus the feedback
on the relevant part
of the screenshot
or to hide any sensitive
information.
Another situation
where I can provide feedback
is when the beta app crashes.
In this case,
TestFlight asks me
if I want to send
more information
to help debug the issue.
I can describe what steps
caused the crash,
and the information
will be submitted
along with the crash log
captured on the device.
So far, I have presented how
testers can leverage TestFlight
on xrOS to install,
run beta apps,
and share feedback.
Now let's take a look how
App Store Connect and Xcode
can help you analyze the data
and track tester engagement.
You can review all submitted
feedback in App Store Connect
and Xcode Organizer,
with filters to view
by platform or a build.
You can check the details
of each feedback,
review screenshots,
download crash logs,
or open the feedback directly
in Xcode Organizer.
App Store Connect web and mobile
also provide information
about how many testers
installed and launched
a specific version of your app,
or how many of them submitted
crash or screenshot feedback.
This is an excellent tool
to track tester engagement.
You can analyze the statistics
for a specific build
or look over a specific group
to see the engagement
of each tester.
So that's a quick look at how
TestFlight can help you build
high-quality apps and offer
a great user experience
on the xrOS device.
Now I will hand back
to Justin to tell you more
about getting your apps
ready for the App Store.
Justin: Thanks, Maciej.
With beta testing wrapped up,
let's jump back
to App Store Connect
and put the finishing touches
on your app.
You're able to manage your xrOS
apps using the features
you've come to expect
from App Store Connect,
from in-app purchases, to
screenshots, to app analytics.
Let's take a closer look
at a feature we've updated
for spatial computing,
Privacy Nutrition Labels.
With the release of xrOS,
we added a few new data types
that your app may collect.
These new data types
are relevant for xrOS apps,
but they can also be applied
to other platforms.
In the App Privacy section,
check “Environment Scanning”
if your app collects data
about the user's surroundings,
such as mesh, planes,
scene classification,
or image detection
of the user's surrounding.
Under the “Body” section,
check “Hands”
if your app collects data
about the user's hand structure
and hand movements,
and “Head” if your app
collects data
about the user's head movement.
Once your app is published
on the App Store,
customers can learn
from your app's product page
about the data types
that your app collects
and how they are used.
We covered a lot today,
from setting up,
to beta testing, to updating
your app's privacy details.
Before I let you go,
let me give you a quick wrap-up
for what you'll need to do next.
First, decide how you want
to get your app on xrOS.
Are you going to create
a new app,
add the xrOS platform
to an existing app,
or choose to make
your compatible iPad
and iPhone apps
available on xrOS?
Beta test your xrOS and
compatible iPad and iPhone apps
with TestFlight.
Be sure and look
for submitted feedback
and crashes from
your beta testers.
Next, update your app's
privacy details
so your customers are well
informed of the types of data
that your app collects.
And finally, check out the
"What's new
in App Store Connect" session
to learn more about updates
across App Store Connect.
Also, see "Get started
with building apps
for spatial computing"
for development tips.
And, as always,
we look forward
to hearing your feedback.
Maciej: Thanks for watching!
♪