♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Shilpa Chirackel:
Hello, my name is Shilpa.
Ryan Golbeck: And I'm Ryan.
Shilpa: Today, we're very
excited to show you
everything we've been working on
in Xcode 15.
Ryan: Xcode is the center
of your development experience.
In Xcode, we pull together
all aspects
of your development workflow
into one place,
making it easy and fun
to build apps
while keeping you focused
in a single tool.
Today we will touch on
many of the improvements
this year with Xcode 15,
starting with editing,
navigating, and sharing,
through to testing,
debugging, and distributing
your app.
Shilpa: Before showing you
what's new in Xcode,
we need to download it.
And the best way to get
the released versions of Xcode
is from the Mac App Store.
This guarantees you will always
use the newest version
of the tools
and can take advantage
of the latest features.
Last year, we made it easier
to get started
by making the watch and TV
simulator optional downloads.
This year,
we're going even further
by making all simulators
downloadable,
including iOS and Apple's
new spatial computing platform,
allowing you to configure
Xcode to match your needs.
Now, when you get Xcode,
it will be smaller,
making it easier to write code
even before you get
all the simulators.
Alternatively, if you need
to download Xcode
from the Developer website,
such as the latest beta,
you can choose up front
which simulators to include.
Now that we've got Xcode,
let's jump right in
and see what's new
in the source editor.
Code completion helps you get
to the code you want
faster and with fewer mistakes.
In Xcode 15,
it gets a whole lot smarter.
Let's take a look.
Completions take advantage
of new sources of information.
Here I have Backyard Birds.
I'll start by creating
a new file
and name it PlantSummaryRow.
I'll add the required
import statements.
Now when I create a new struct,
completion suggests
PlantSummaryRow
for the type name,
and that's because that's
the name of the file I created.
Let me finish
implementing this file.
I'm done with
the implementation.
The way some completions
are presented has improved too.
When you're calling a function
that has default arguments,
it can be challenging to get
exactly the parameters you want.
You can see all possible
permutations
of default arguments to help you
pick the one you want.
I'll add a frame modifier
to this VStack
and press the right arrow
on the keyboard.
I'll select the one I need,
in this case width.
And completions now have
more context awareness,
giving you even
better suggestions
for the code you're writing.
Coming back to the VStack,
when I type a dot
to add a modifier,
padding is the top suggestion
because Xcode knows
it's one of the most frequently
used modifiers for this view.
But when I add
a modifier to a Text,
I get font
as the top suggestion.
These editor suggestions also
consider the surrounding code.
I already changed
the font on this text.
When I want to add
another modifier,
the top suggestion is bold,
as I wouldn't want to use
the same modifier twice
when working on text.
Here's another example.
In this file,
I'm using CLLocation to find
where my birds are.
As I already typed in latitude,
now it will suggest longitude,
as these two properies
are commonly paired together.
All this means you'll have
better top suggestions,
leading you to type
safer code faster.
Hey Ryan, I heard that we're
bringing the power completions
to asset catalogs too.
Can you tell me some more?
Ryan: Sure, Shilpa.
Color and image assets
are now backed by Swift symbols.
This means that they can now
be code completed.
In my asset catalog, I have
some custom colors and images.
Xcode 15 automatically generates
symbols for each of them,
and I can reference these
in my code
instead of using string names.
If I change the name
of this image to MultipleClouds
and build my project,
I get an issue in another file
where we use this asset.
And I can correct it using
CodeComplete.
These symbols give me
type safety,
so I don't have to worry about
mysteriously missing colors
or images at runtime.
And Xcode 15 brings the power
and flexibility of catalogs
to your localization
experience too.
String catalogs pull together
your localizations
into a single place,
giving you a centralized way
to review and update them.
To get started, you can convert
a project to use string catalogs
by selecting Edit > Convert
to string catalog.
This brings up a sheet showing
all of the storyboards,
.strings, and .stringsdict files
that can be migrated.
And once migrated,
all of your translations
are organized
into a single editor.
In the sidebar on the left,
you can review
the translation progress
for each of the languages
that you support.
And keeping up to date is easy.
All of the strings are pulled
directly from source
each time you build.
When new strings
are added or removed,
the editor annotates
the affected languages
and badges the relevant strings.
Get started migrating today
by heading over to the session
"Discover String Catalogs."
Shilpa, what's new in Xcode
for documentation this year?
Shilpa: A lot.
Clear, concise code is made
even better with documentation.
Whether you're explaining
something to your future self
or one of the consumers
of your API,
writing great documentation
is key.
And great documentation
deserves great presentation.
Xcode 15 has beautiful
new styling and spacing,
making documentation
easier to read.
But the biggest improvement
is a new assistant
that shows a real-time preview
of your documentation.
While crafting documentation,
I can display the assistant
by choosing Editor > Assistant >
and then Documentation Preview
in the jump bar.
As I type in the source editor,
the preview is updated
in real time.
This will show me exactly
how my docs will look
in a fully built
documentation archive.
I'll add a code example to show
how it could be used
in practice.
I'll begin by writing
"Use this initializer
to display an image
of a given bird."
Then I'll paste in
my code example.
Since this example involves UI,
I'll add a screenshot
of what the resulting view
would look like.
I can reference the image
named BirdIcon
because I included it
in my documentation catalog.
The new documentation preview
is a huge help
to make sure your docs are
presented exactly how you want.
If you're passionate about
writing documentation,
like I am, watch the session
"Create rich documentation
with Swift-DocC" to learn more.
Just as important
as documentation
is that your code should be
concise and understandable.
New in Swift this year is
a powerful new language feature,
Swift macros.
Macros makes
for more expressive APIs
and helps eliminate
repeated code.
And Xcode's integration
gives you complete visibility
into macros, allowing you
to treat macro-generated code
like all other code in your app.
Macros are part of the Swift
packages in the SDK.
Now we're utilizing
the power of macros
in a number of Apple's
own frameworks,
like Swift standard library,
foundation,
and the new
Swift data framework.
I can also create my own macro
package to share with others.
To create a package,
I'm going to use quick actions,
a new feature
that lets me access
all of Xcode's menu options just
by pressing Command-Shift-A.
The new macro package
will come with great examples
to get me started.
I've already created
a macro package, EnumHelper.
Inside EnumHelper, I implemented
CaseDetection as a macro.
The beauty of macros is that
they generate normal Swift code.
It wraps up and neatly tucks
away the code they provide.
But when you want to see
what a macro is doing
or when you want to debug
in macro-generated code,
you can expand the macro
right in line
with the help
from quick actions.
You can even set a breakpoint
on the code inside a macro
if you need to debug it.
Watch the session
"Expand on Swift macros"
to gain a deeper technical
understanding of Swift macros.
Equipped with this
new knowledge,
you can code along to write
a few macros from scratch
in the session
"Write Swift macros."
Let's explore
another area of Xcode
that's taking advantage
of macros, previews.
With the help of macros,
the new Previews API
is simple and easy to remember.
I'll add a preview
by typing #Preview.
I want to preview
the account screen.
App detail column
has various states,
which I can show
by creating another preview.
I'm able to see
both of these scenarios.
But now I have
two previews in UI.
To tell them apart, I'll add
a title, "Placeholder View".
But wait, there are
more improvements.
We're bringing previews
to UIKit and AppKit.
So even in my older
Food Truck app,
I can add a preview
for my UIViewController
and iterate as quickly
as I have in SwiftUI.
Now let's look at developing
widgets with previews.
The API also introduces
new workflows
for building time-based widgets.
The canvas has a new area
that shows all of the entries.
And as I navigate through them,
I can see how the widget's
transitions animate.
Check out the session
"Build programmatic UI
with Xcode Previews"
to learn how to adopt
the new and exciting
preview features
in your project.
I'll hand it back to Ryan
to talk about
the improvements in navigation.
Ryan: Thanks, Shilpa.
As your project grows,
it becomes more complex,
making it difficult
to keep track of landmarks
that you want to reference
during a task.
To help, Xcode 15 introduces
the bookmarks navigator.
I'll open it by clicking
right next to
the source control navigator.
I've been adding bookmarks
to places in my code
that I need to add
documentation.
I want to add another one in
this file, and it's easy to do.
I'll just right-click on this
location and select Bookmark.
The bookmark shows up
in the navigator
with a preview of its location,
but I can change this display
if I want by clicking it
and entering
a different description.
Xcode annotates a line of code
with my description,
making it easy to see and
remember what I want it to do.
My list of bookmarks
is starting to grow,
but I can manage them
by sorting and grouping them
however I like.
I want to group all of my
documentation-related
bookmarks together.
I'll select the ones
I'm interested in,
and with a secondary click,
open the context menu
to select
New Group From Selection.
This creates a new group
that I'll call
Places to Add Documentation.
Bookmarks are great reminders
in my code,
but they can also be used
as to-do lists.
I can mark one as complete
by clicking to its left.
Or I can delete it altogether
by selecting
Delete Bookmark
in the context menu.
This removes the bookmark
annotation in the editor.
Lines of code aren't the only
thing I can bookmark, though.
Bookmarks are also a great way
to keep track of Find queries.
Before Xcode 15,
I've added to-dos in my code,
but they are hard to find,
so I've already bookmarked
a query to find all of them.
But I can bookmark
any Find query.
I want to keep a handy
list of all the view modifiers
in my code.
I'll use the new
Conforming Types query
to find all conformances
to the viewModifier protocol.
Then, I can bookmark this query
by right-clicking in the results
and selecting
Bookmark Find "viewModifier".
My query is available
in the bookmark navigator.
If the results of my query
ever change,
I can refresh the list with just
one click on the refresh button
next to the bookmark.
Xcode 15's new bookmark
navigator keeps track
of your work
so you don't have to,
keeping your focus
on the task at hand.
Another important
part of development
is sharing your work.
Bringing your changes together,
especially when
crafting a commit
to share with your colleagues,
can be as important
as the changes themselves.
Xcode 15 introduces
a new changes navigator
and commit editor,
which together are a great way
to review all of your changes.
I've been working on adding
documentation to my project.
I can review these changes
in the source control navigator.
The first thing you'll notice
is an improved
reporting and presentation
of each file's status.
My stage modifications show up
as an icon
next to the file name.
I want to start reviewing
these changes,
so I'll click on
the uncommitted changes item
to bring up the commit editor.
I can now review
all of my modifications
in a single scrolling view.
Each section shows
just enough context
to understand
the surrounding code.
And If I want to see more,
I can use the drag handle
to expose more of the file.
Each change is also presented
in a source editor,
giving me access
to the annotations and controls
that I'm used to.
During my review,
I notice that there's an issue
in the BirdsNavigationStack
file.
It looks like I made a typo
in my documentation,
but I can fix this
without leaving the view.
Xcode processes my change
and removes the issue.
My edit is also immediately
indicated as unstaged
in the changes bar.
[no audio]
The status indicator highlights
that the BirdsNavigationStack
now has both staged
and unstaged changes.
I want to include my fix
in the next commit,
so I'll stage it by clicking
the changes bar next to the fix
and selecting Stage Change.
I also notice I've accidentally
staged a log statement
that I was using for debugging.
I'll use the changes bar
again to unstage this change.
These staging controls
are easy to use
and they're integrated
throughout Xcode.
I'm ready to check in
my changes.
I'll start by adding
a description
in the commit message box,
and then clicking
the Commit button.
Xcode creates my commit
and opens it immediately
in the commit viewer,
summarizing what was included.
[no audio]
And lastly, I can share
my commit with my teammates.
I'll click on the status
indicator next to my commit,
select Push,
and follow the prompts.
These source control features
are a great improvement
to keep you focused in Xcode 15.
But hey, Shilpa, I think
we have some new features
that help with testing too.
Can you tell us about those?
Shilpa: Sure, Ryan, testing
is an important part of shipping
a high-quality app.
It allows you to catch
regressions quickly
and maintain your app's quality
as it grows in complexity.
Testing gets some
big improvements this year,
starting with an updated
test navigator,
rewritten from the ground up
in Swift to be more efficient.
When running or reporting
your test results in real time,
Xcode is now 45 percent faster.
The test navigator is organized
around your test plan,
making it easier to find
the test you care about.
You can also use filters to find
tests based on any result type,
such as expected failure.
Once you run your test
in Xcode or Xcode Cloud,
the test reports help you
explore the results,
showing you where to focus next.
It starts with a high-level
summary of the entire test run.
This includes Insights,
a pattern-based analysis
of the results.
Within the Test section,
you can understand
how the test performed.
It's easy to figure out how many
tests passed and failed
across different devices
and configurations.
Insights analyze test results
to identify
potentially related failures
that might have been difficult
to see before.
It also alerts us to test runs
that may cause the entire suite
to take longer
to return results.
The second insight
sticks out to me.
The test failed while attempting
to tap the Account button.
I want to investigate
this further.
From the overview,
I can navigate to the test list,
which shows
all of the test runs,
with filters for result type,
run destination,
and test plan configuration.
I see the test failed to tap
the Account button
across multiple languages
with the same error message.
To learn more, I can look
at the individual class
or navigate to a new dedicated
Test Details view
for individual test methods.
The Test Details view contains
tabs for different ways
of exploring the results data,
including a breakdown
of all runs and a dedicated
performance metrics tab.
Debugging UI test failures
is more fun than ever
with the new
automation explorer.
The explorer is interactive,
so you can watch
your test playback
or can scrub through
the timeline.
Touch or mouse events
are overlaid on the video.
At the point of failure,
like when my test failed
to tap the Account button,
I can inspect the UI hierarchy
of my app.
This will make fixing UI test
failures a whole lot easier.
For an in-depth study,
watch the session
"Fix failures faster
with Xcode test reports"
to learn more.
Now back to Ryan
so we can talk about debugging.
Ryan: Testing and debugging
go hand in hand.
They are both about crafting
a high-quality app.
And debugging also gets some
great improvements this year,
starting with OSLog integration
into Xcode.
OSLog is a great tool for
capturing runtime information.
It provides a structured and
customizable logging mechanism
that keeps your log output
organized.
And Xcode 15's console
introduces full support
for OSLog,
including the ability to perform
complex filtering on log data,
like subsystem category
and severity.
The presentation of the logs
is cleaner than ever.
The focus is on
your log content,
with extra data
neatly hidden away.
The background color of each log
entry indicates its severity,
making it easy to scan
long streams of log output
for critical messages.
And while the metadata fields
are hidden by default,
they're just a couple
of clicks away.
You can choose just
the fields you want to see.
And when you're looking
for something specific,
the filter field lets you narrow
your search.
You can filter on the metadata
or on the full text of the log.
And a feature
that I really like,
you can jump from a log entry
directly back to the line
of code that created it.
We do a deep dive into these
logging features in the session
"Debug with structured logging".
Lastly, let's talk
about distribution.
Distribution is about getting
your app out into the world,
to your teammates,
to your beta testers,
and to your users.
And Xcode 15 has
some improvements
to make this process
easier and safer.
Let's start with Xcode Cloud.
Xcode Cloud is a great way
to distribute your app.
It manages things like build
versioning, app signing,
and the distribution profile
for you automatically.
This year, Xcode Cloud handles
two more details for you.
First, TestFlight test details.
Xcode Cloud adds support
for including test notes
right alongside
your source code.
These will be
automatically attached
to the TestFlight build
for distribution,
and so the notes will
appear to your testers
right alongside your app.
And secondly,
Xcode Cloud now supports
notarization for your Mac apps.
All you need to do is add
the notarization post action
in your workflow, and Xcode
Cloud will do the rest.
When your build is complete,
your app will be automatically
notarized and stapled,
and be ready to download.
Notarizing your app
is vital for your users.
It lets them know that your app
hasn't been tampered with.
But it's just as important that
you can trust the integrity
of the SDKs and frameworks
that you depend on.
To provide this assurance,
Xcode introduces
signature verification
for XCFrameworks.
Authors can digitally sign the
contents of their frameworks,
and you can verify these
signatures right in Xcode.
The framework inspector
has a new signature slice.
It tells you exactly
who produced and signed
the framework.
And Xcode will
remember this identity.
So if it ever changes
when updating the framework,
you get a clear warning
about the problem,
but there's more to it
than that.
Authors can now include
a privacy manifest
in their framework.
This manifest details exactly
how the framework
uses and protects
sensitive data.
Since the privacy manifest
is bundled with the framework,
it is also part of
the signed package,
and you can trust
that its contents
came directly from the author.
I can use Xcode to summarize
all of the manifests
into a complete privacy report
for my app.
Here's a report
that I've generated.
This report is designed
to make it easy
to fill in the privacy nutrition
label in App Store Connect,
making sure I provide accurate
information to my users.
And Apple is working with
privacy-impacting SDKs
to ensure that all of
your critical dependencies
provide this valuable
information.
We cover these topics in a lot
more depth in the sessions
"Verify app dependencies
with digital signatures"
and "Get started with
privacy manifests".
Privacy manifests
are a great tool
when distributing
your app to your users.
When you're working on a bug fix
or a new feature branch,
you want to distribute
your app to your teammates
and only your teammates.
So Xcode 15 now supports
the TestFlight internal
testing distribution option.
TestFlight internal builds
are available to your team only,
so you can never accidentally
release them to customers.
They're easy to create.
Just select the "TestFlight
internal testing" option
when distributing your app
through App Store Connect.
But it's actually
even easier than this.
Xcode now bundles a set of the
most common distribution methods
and recommended settings.
Step one, select any
of these new options,
including
TestFlight internal only.
Step two, click Distribute
and you're done.
There is no step three.
And if you're distributing
through App Store Connect,
you will also now get
desktop notifications
about your build status.
So when your app
is ready to test,
you'll be notified right away.
These updates make it easy
to iterate
and distribute your app quickly,
which makes working closely
with your teammates,
testers, and users
smooth and fast.
Start exploring these features
by having a look at the session
"Simplify distribution with
Xcode and Xcode Cloud".
Well, that was a quick overview
of what's new in Xcode 15.
It is easier to get,
faster to use,
and has a ton of improvements
to make your development
more focused, smooth, and fun.
Shilpa: Go download Xcode 15
so you can start trying out
these cool new features.
Thanks for watching.
♪