♪ ♪
Will: Hello and welcome
to "Design with SwiftUI."
My name is Will,
and I'm a designer on the Apple Maps team.
Later, I'll be joined
by my colleague Philip, and together,
we're going discuss some
of the unique benefits and applications
we've found from using SwiftUI.
We will speak
from our perspective as designers
and share personal insights about how
SwiftUI has enhanced our design process.
We will also provide
real examples from our work
on the newly redesigned Maps app
in watchOS 10.
On the Maps Design team,
we're huge fans of SwiftUI.
It's helped us validate design concepts,
provided us with unique capabilities
that no other tool offers,
and given us a better understanding
of how interfaces
are constructed and brought to life.
For this year's watchOS app,
we developed all our designs in SwiftUI,
right on device.
This gave us control over every detail,
from spacing and typestyles
to animations and interactions.
In today's session, we'd like to share
how SwiftUI impacted this design work.
Along the way,
we'll cover how SwiftUI can be a powerful
yet approachable tool for designers,
how it helps you think
through the details of your concepts,
design rich interactions,
accurately test your ideas,
and effectively present
your work to others.
Let's begin by understanding
how SwiftUI functions as a design tool.
While SwiftUI is a powerful framework
for building applications,
it's also a uniquely powerful tool
for designers,
enabling us to create interfaces
with higher levels of speed and precision.
Many people with no programming
background, just like myself,
find that they are able to learn SwiftUI
and design productively
in a short period of time.
That's because SwiftUI
is built on the idea
that common things should be easy
and complex things should be possible.
In practice, this means you don't need to
spend time recreating common UI elements.
And at the same time,
you won't feel limited when it's time
to create something brand-new.
Here's another way
we like to think about this concept.
Some tools are really good
at making things easy.
They lower the floor.
A microwave is a good example.
Most everyone can use one,
and it's great for lots of simple things.
However, if I need to make a fancy dinner,
a microwave isn't the right tool.
Other tools are focused on being powerful.
They raise the ceiling and enable you
to make things that are complex and rich.
A good example of this
is an industrial espresso machine.
While these machines enable you
to make incredible drinks,
they can be unapproachable,
hard to learn,
and difficult for doing something simple,
like making a basic cup of coffee.
SwiftUI strikes the balance
between these two types of tools.
It lowers the floor for simple tasks
and raises the ceiling
for creating new and novel things.
When writing SwiftUI,
you use a tool called Xcode.
In recent years, Xcode has
become even more useful for designers,
thanks to the addition of a visual canvas
that allows you to view and interact
with your designs in real time.
Here I am, changing a simple line
of text by adjusting the font size,
weight, string, and color.
Each time I make one of these changes,
it updates immediately on the canvas.
Equally helpful for designers
is the declarative way
that SwiftUI is written.
This language model builds
on intuition that many of us already have
for how interfaces are put together.
When writing SwiftUI,
you just declare what you want to create.
For common elements like a button,
we'll just write Button.
And for an image, we'll just write Image.
When it comes to styling these elements,
it's just as straightforward.
SwiftUI provides you with Modifiers
to change the appearance of things
just as you would
in any other design tool.
This could be adding effects
like drop shadows or borders,
changing format of text
though unique fonts,
or manipulating the layout of elements
by changing properties
like aspect ratios or paddings.
SwiftUI also provides easy access
to system controls,
like color pickers,
and behaviors, like push transitions.
These are built directly
into the framework,
giving you native functionality
right out of the box.
If you're using SwiftUI,
it also means you now have access
to the unique capabilities
of Apple hardware.
With a bit of work,
you can take advantage of things
like haptic feedback,
audio feeds, cameras, gestures,
and sensors like accelerometers.
You can also take advantage
of all the work
that's gone into the dozens
of Apple Frameworks .
That means, you can design
with dynamic maps using MapKit,
pull in live weather information
from WeatherKit,
or render objects
in augmented reality using RealityKit.
All of this can happens
across Apple platforms
because SwiftUI works with iPhone,
as well as iPad, Apple Watch, and Mac.
In most cases,
you can even share code too
and take of advantage of how
system elements adapt on their own.
Now that we've discussed SwiftUI
through the lens of a design tool.
Let's get specific about how
it helps you actually design better,
starting first with getting
the details of your designs right.
Modern interfaces are dynamic.
The products that we build
contain complex flows
and highly interactive elements.
As a result, there's so many
important decisions that we need to make.
SwiftUI helps by quickly surfacing
all of those important details
that need your attention,
for example,
how an image should look when it's loading
or how a button appears when it's pressed.
These are the types of things
that make a product feel complete.
They're easily hidden
in static design tools
but are quickly surfaced when working
in a dynamic tool like SwiftUI.
That's because SwiftUI makes it easy
to build your designs on device.
In doing this, you gain a more complete
understanding of what you're making.
Separate parts now interact together,
and you can begin to evaluate
the experience as a whole.
This process quickly reveals
what's working in your design
and what still needs attention or polish.
On Maps, we've found this
to be tremendously helpful.
When we first began designing
this year's watchOS App,
we thought it would be great to create
a more map-centric experience
for people's wrists.
To begin testing what that felt like,
we put a simple map view onto a watch.
Because we were testing on device,
we immediately discovered an issue:
The speed at which the Digital Crown
zoomed into the map was much too fast.
To improve this experience, we tested
multiple values in our SwiftUI prototype,
adjusting the sensitivity
of the Digital Crown
until we found a zoom speed
that felt natural.
Once we improved the zoom speed,
we started adding to the map,
first adding points of interest,
then UI controls,
and finally,
to better contextualize the map,
a walking radius
around your current location,
helping show what's around you
and roughly how long
it'd take to walk there.
We took this work back on device,
adding to our SwiftUI prototype.
This surfaced new things
that needed our attention,
like the interaction
of the walking radius.
Specifically, we felt like
the walking time could use more detail
as the Digital Crown was scrolled.
To explore what that could look like,
we prototyped several different options.
Our favorite was this ticker animation,
which we developed
as a separate SwiftUI prototype.
We took these separate prototypes
and integrated them together.
This led to even more questions
and surprised us
in just how much complexity was hidden
in such a seemingly simple design.
All of these details were initially opaque
when we began designing.
But the moment we started
making prototypes, they were obvious.
SwiftUI is built for modern interfaces.
It helps us
address specific design details
and experience how everything
works together as a whole.
Next, Philip will discuss one
of our favorite topics: interactions.
Philip: SwiftUI is a powerful tool
for designing interactions,
with first-class support for gestures,
transitions, and animations.
Everything feels native because you're
working in a truly native environment.
What designer doesn't like
a great looking animation?
Animations in SwiftUI are performant,
easy to use, and fully interruptible.
This is helpful
because interactions give you a sense
of how your designs feel,
not just how they look.
Often, interactions involve gestures,
like dragging, scrolling, or tapping.
But there are other input sources,
like hardware sensors,
you can use for interactions.
On the new Maps home screen,
when you tap the location button,
it activates a compass.
As you move around,
the compass displays
the cardinal direction
you're currently facing.
In order to get a sense
of how this interaction would feel,
we created a SwiftUI prototype
with a magnified compass
to test out transitions using
the watch's internal sensors.
It only took a few hours
to get this prototype working.
SwiftUI made it easy
to use the watch's real sensors,
which made the compass accurate and helped
us refine this small interaction.
Another interaction we wanted to create
was related to the search experience.
If you're searching for a location,
like a restaurant,
this new split screen shows a map
and list of results.
This design required
a unique scroll interaction
that would have been difficult
to achieve in other tools.
Here's the SwiftUI prototype we made
to get a feel for this interaction.
Our goal was to make it
immediately responsive
without being too sensitive.
The platter responds
to slow movements of the Crown,
and once a threshold is hit,
a new platter quickly transitions
into place,
along with a haptic response.
Fast movements, on the other hand,
use a tighter spring animation.
This helps the interaction feel snappy.
These adjustments create
an experience that feels right
when scrolling
at both slow and fast speeds.
SwiftUI provides a great out of the box
experience for many interactions.
And when you want something custom,
it's a highly capable tool,
giving you the power to fine-tune things
until they feel just right.
Design isn't just about how something
looks or feels though.
It's also about how it works.
One thing that's easy
to overlook in the design process
is testing your ideas
in realistic scenarios.
I know for myself, I can get carried away
designing for ideal scenarios,
using nice photos and short labels,
and in general, making sure my design
looks the best it possibly can.
However, as design work progresses,
it's important for me to find out
where my designs break,
testing them in the real world
to see how they hold up.
SwiftUI makes it easy to design
and evaluate your work
in realistic scenarios.
On Maps, we think about this a lot,
as people use our product in the outdoors
in a wide range of conditions.
SwiftUI enables us to take our designs
on the go and test them in real time.
For example, we pay attention to how glare
and sunlight impacts the readability
of the cartography and interface.
This often leads us
to adjust contrast levels across the app
to provide a more legible experience.
Another practice we find helpful
is to use real data in our designs.
In Maps, we consider the different types
of terrain and routes
people will encounter
when using our product.
If you're biking or walking
with the Watch app,
the new elevation graph gives an overview
of the elevation range for your route
and your progress in real time.
When we built this chart in SwiftUI,
we were able to import real data
from different types of routes.
For hilly routes,
like those found in San Francisco,
the chart worked just as we expected.
However, when we use data for flat routes,
like those you might encounter
in New York City,
we found that it looked much more extreme
than it actually was,
as if you were hiking a mountain.
We realized we needed to revisit the chart
so that it accurately reflected
a diversity of routes
and elevation profiles.
In this case, we needed
to adjust the scale of the Y-axis
so that flat routes appeared
more like you'd expect.
One more practice we often use is creating
one-off design tools using SwiftUI.
For the new walking radius
that Will shared earlier,
we needed a design
that rendered properly over the map,
which is a very dynamic surface.
We created this mini design tool
to better understand how the radius would
look over different map environments.
Here I am exploring styles
by changing things like line width,
opacity values, and blend modes.
Small parameterized tools
like this one allow us to scrub
through way more variations
than we'd be able to do efficiently
in a static design tool.
They're easy to build in SwiftUI
and can help answer specific questions
or solve complex problems.
SwiftUI helps you design
in real-world scenarios
with diverse data sets
and a holistic understanding
of different environments.
By testing your designs,
you're able to better account
for how they will perform
in people's day-to-day lives.
Another way to test ideas
is to share them with others.
SwiftUI is a great tool
for presenting your work.
There are many great ways
to share designs,
but on device demos are uniquely effective
at bringing your ideas to life.
When people can hold a demo
of your work in their hands,
designs explain themselves.
This helps build consensus
and can save everyone
the hassle of more meetings.
For our work this year,
we prioritized building demos
and brought them to design reviews
as often as we could.
In these reviews, we put multiple demos
into a single SwiftUI app.
This included ones we shared earlier,
like the walking radius
and search results,
and many others, like the cards
that appear with business information.
Everyone was excited
to play with the demos
and provide feedback about the experience.
Instead of spending time
explaining the designs,
we were able to spend more
of our time evaluating them.
The demos you build with SwiftUI
can de-risk a project
and prevent confusion,
both for yourself and for your team.
At the end of the day,
no slide deck in the world
can compare with one spectacular demo.
These are some of the benefits
we've discovered using SwiftUI.
We encourage you to think
of SwiftUI as a design tool,
one that helps you surface
important design decisions,
enables you to design how things feel,
get realistic about how they all work,
and share your designs with others
using on device demos.
It was these benefits that helped us
design the new Maps app in watchOS 10.
The tools we use for our creative work
have a tremendous impact
on the end experience.
By using SwiftUI in your design process,
we think you'll find that it leads
to a more considered, complete,
and well-crafted final product.
There is also one more amazing benefit
of using SwiftUI
that we haven't spoken about yet.
When you use SwiftUI,
you're not just creating a prototype.
You're making an app.
And that means,
you can ship what you design.
The app that you're creating
can be more than just a design artifact.
Because you're working with the same
materials an engineer uses,
you can build and submit apps to
the App Store and share them with others.
We hope you enjoyed learning
how we've used SwiftUI
as designers on the Maps team.
If you're interested
in learning more about SwiftUI,
there's a lot of resources
for you to discover.
We'd encourage watching
"Introduction to SwiftUI"
if you're just getting started.
Thank you for joining today.
♪ ♪