♪ ♪
Adam: Hi, I'm Adam.
In this video, I'll be covering
how your app can help people
manage their time
with Calendar and EventKit.
First, I'll go over some ways
that apps can integrate with Calendar
and give an overview
of the frameworks involved.
Then I'll walk
through some specific examples of how
to use these frameworks
to implement common features,
like adding events,
fetching events with full access,
and implementing
a virtual conference extension.
People rely on their calendar
to keep track of their time
and plan for their future,
but Calendar is more than just one app.
There are different roles that apps
can fill when integrating with Calendar,
and when put together,
these different roles provide
for a richer Calendar experience.
Some apps support making reservations,
buying tickets, or arranging meetups.
They take part by adding events.
Some apps participate
by displaying events,
maybe for a custom
calendar widget or a planner.
Other apps contribute in both directions.
They help people manage their schedule
by viewing and editing events.
Apps that support voice
or video calls can also take part.
A virtual conference extension
not only improves the experience
in the Calendar app,
but it also provides a shortcut
back into your app.
All of these fit together to provide
a cohesive experience for managing time.
Later, I'll walk
through some specific examples
to get started in each of these areas.
There are two frameworks
that you can use
to integrate with Calendar.
The EventKit framework is used
to work directly with calendar data.
EventKitUI is an iOS
and Mac Catalyst framework
that provides view controllers
for showing calendar UI in your app.
Let's take a closer look at each...
Starting with some
of the basic types in EventKit.
The EKEventStore is the main point
of contact for your calendar data.
You use an event store to request
access and to fetch or save.
You should only have one of these
for your application.
The EKEvent class
represents a specific event,
and it has properties like title,
start date,
end date, and location.
Each event belongs to a calendar,
which is represented
by the EKCalendar class.
Calendars have a title and color,
which can be useful
for coloring the events.
Finally, each calendar account
is represented by an EKSource,
which is a collection of calendars.
Sources are useful for grouping calendars
in your UI.
EventKit is a foundational framework
for interacting with calendar data.
EventKitUI is built on top of EventKit
to provide some useful built-in views.
There are three view controllers
provided by EventKitUI.
The EKEventEditViewController
shows an event editor.
Use this to add a new event
or make changes to an existing event.
The EKEventViewController
shows event details.
Use this to show information in your app
about an existing event.
And the EKCalendarChooser shows
a calendar list and supports either
single selection or multiple selection.
Use this to let people choose
a calendar to add an event to
or choose which calendars
should be visible in your app.
Calendars are private,
so the system prevents apps
from reading or writing Calendar events
without permission.
There are three levels of access
that an app can have for Calendar:
No access,
write-only access, or full access.
Apps with no calendar access
can add events using EventKitUI
or Siri Event Suggestions.
Apps with write-only access
can add events directly using EventKit.
And apps with full access
can fetch or modify existing events,
access existing calendars,
and create new calendars.
One of the most common ways
to integrate with Calendar
is to add new events.
Events can be added
to the calendar in a few different ways.
Use EventKitUI or Siri Event Suggestions
to add one event at a time.
Or, to save events directly, use EventKit.
The simplest way
to add an event to the calendar
is to let EventKitUI do most of the work.
Present an EKEventEditViewController
to show an editor
with the event details filled out.
This gives people a chance
to choose a calendar or make other changes
before deciding whether to save the event.
In iOS 17,
this UI runs in a separate process,
which means you don't need
to request Calendar access.
Adding an event with EventKitUI
is a four-step process.
First, create an event store.
Next,
create an event and fill in the details.
Then create a view controller
configured to edit the event.
And finally, present the view controller.
Let's walk through this in more detail
with some code.
Start by creating an eventStore.
Next,
create an event and fill in the details.
The details you set here
will be used in the editor UI.
Once the editor is presented,
people will have a chance to make changes,
but ideally, they can just tap
the add button to confirm,
so filling in the right details
saves them time.
Every event needs a title.
The title is used in many places
including widgets and notifications,
so keep it simple.
The most important properties
are the start and end date.
Use date components
to make the start date.
Once you have the start date,
calculate the end date
by adding the duration.
Use Foundation's Calendar
and DateComponents types for date math,
or else, you'll hit surprising results
around Daylight Saving Time.
Here the sample adds
two hours to our start date.
If the event takes place
in a specific time zone,
then be sure to set that as well.
The default time zone
will be the current system time zone.
Set a location to let people know
where the event takes place.
Including a full address
or using a MapKit handle
will enable features like Maps suggestions
and Time to Leave alerts.
Finally, add some notes
to provide some extra detail.
Once you've set the event properties,
the next step is to create
the EKEventEditViewController.
Assign the event
and event store properties.
In the editor, people can
either add the event or cancel.
If you want to know
whether they added the event,
then use the delegate property
and implement
the EKEventEditViewDelegate protocol.
Finally, present the editor.
At this point,
the event isn't in the calendar yet.
Tapping the Add button will save it,
while tapping on cancel will dismiss
the editor without saving anything.
For a more complete example
of adding events with EventKitUI,
check out the "DropInLessons" target
in the "Accessing Calendar using
EventKit and EventKitUI" sample code.
Another way to add events to the calendar
is to use Siri Event Suggestions
for reservations made in your app.
The Siri Event Suggestions API
is part of the Intents Framework.
It doesn't require prompting
for Calendar access,
and it doesn't show any UI in your app.
Instead, these events will appear
in the Calendar inbox like an invitation.
They can then be either added
to a calendar or ignored.
Siri Event Suggestions support
reservations for restaurants or hotels,
travel bookings
like flights or rental cars,
and ticketed events
like concerts or sporting events.
If the reservation
is later canceled or modified,
the events can be updated.
Using the Siri Event Suggestions API
is a four-step process.
First, create an INReservation.
Then, wrap the reservation
in an intent and response.
Next, create an INInteraction.
Finally,
donate the interaction to the system.
Let's dive into some sample code.
A reservation requires a unique reference
that the system will use to identify it.
Create that reference by making
an instance of INSpeakableString
with a unique vocabulary identifier
and a spoken phrase.
The phrase can be used to refer
to this reservation when talking to Siri.
Use INDateComponentsRange to set the start
and end time for the reservation.
Give the event a location
using the CLPlacemark type.
Then, put that all together
by creating an instance of one
of the subclasses of INReservation.
For a restaurant reservation,
use INRestaurantReservation.
This initializer has a few
more optional arguments that aren't shown,
and each subclass
has its own specific options.
Check out the documentation to learn more.
The next step is to create
an INGetReservationDetailsIntent
with the reservation reference.
Then create
an INGetReservationDetailsIntentResponse
with the reservation object.
Next, create an INInteraction
with the intent and response.
Finally, invoke
the interaction's donate method.
This example only scratches
the surface of what can be done
with Siri Event Suggestions.
For more information
about creating Siri Event Suggestions,
check out the "Broaden your reach with
Siri Event Suggestions" video from WWDC20.
EventKitUI or Siri Event Suggestions
provide the best experience
for adding events.
Use write-only access only if your app
needs to show a custom editing UI,
add multiple events at the same time,
or add events to the calendar
without user interaction.
To request write-only access,
include the NSCalendarsWriteOnlyAccess
UsageDescription key
in your Info.plist to explain
why your app needs access.
This string will be shown
in the request prompt.
Here is the prompt
for our sample application:
"Save repeating lessons
to a calendar that you choose."
Write-only access
also has some limitations.
For one,
people may choose not to allow access.
If access is granted, then the app
still cannot read any existing events
from the calendar,
including events added by the same app.
The app also can't read the calendar list
or create new calendars.
Write-only access is new
in iOS 17 and macOS Sonoma.
To learn more
about how this affects existing apps,
check out
the "What's new in Privacy" video.
Adding a new event
with write-only access will look similar
to adding a new event using EventKitUI.
It starts out the same:
Create an event store.
Then request write-only access.
If access was granted,
create a new event
and fill in the details.
Lastly, save the event.
Let's check that out in more detail.
Start by creating an event store.
Then, request write-only access by calling
the requestWriteOnlyAccessToEvents method.
The return value indicates
whether access was granted.
People can choose to deny access,
so be sure to handle that gracefully.
Access requests are most likely
to be approved when people understand
why your app needs access,
so you should request access
when someone has first interacted
with a feature that requires it.
Next,
create an event and fill in the details.
There's another important difference here.
When using EventKitUI,
the details you fill in
will show up in an editor,
and anything not filled in
gets a default value.
When saving an event directly
with EventKit,
nothing will be filled in for you.
What you set is what will be saved.
There are some properties
that must be filled in,
or the save will fail.
One required property is the calendar.
Use the event store's
defaultCalendarForNewEvents property
to use the calendar
configured as the default in settings.
The other required properties are title,
start date, and end date.
Everything else is optional,
but it's good to fill out
as much as possible.
Once the details are filled in,
save the event using
the event store's save method.
To see a full example
of adding events with EventKit,
check out the "RepeatingLessons" target
in the "Accessing Calendar using
EventKit and EventKitUI" sample project.
Apps that want to add events
to the calendar should use EventKitUI,
Siri Event Suggestions,
or write-only access.
For the very few apps
that need to read calendar data,
there is full access.
Only request full access if your app has
a core feature that requires displaying,
updating, or removing existing events.
To request full access,
include the NSCalendars
FullAccessUsageDescription key
in your Info.plist.
This string will be shown
in the request prompt.
Calendars contains sensitive information,
and the prompt for full access
describes how much data is included.
It takes a lot of trust for people
to allow an app to read their calendar.
If people don't yet trust your app,
then the request may be denied.
Only request full access
if it is essential
to the core experience of your app,
and only request at a time
when it is clear why the access is needed.
If your app does need full access
for a core feature,
then it will probably need
to fetch events.
To do this, first create an event store.
Next, request full access.
Then, create a predicate.
And finally,
fetch the events from the event store.
Let's check out the code for that.
As with our other examples,
start by creating an event store.
Apps should only have one event store,
so be sure to reuse this.
Next, request full access by calling
the requestFullAccessToEvents method.
This will show a prompt and return
whether the access was allowed.
Full access prompts
will be denied more often,
so be sure to handle that.
Once you have full access,
create a predicate
by calling the event store's
predicateForEvents method.
The predicate describes
which events you want to fetch
with a date range
and an optional list of calendars.
This code uses a range
for the current month.
Use the shortest range possible
for the best performance.
If the calendars argument is left nil,
the results will include events
from all calendars.
Finally, fetch the events
by passing the predicate
to the event store's
events(matching:) method,
which returns an array
of matching events.
The events in this array
are not necessarily ordered,
so sort the results if needed.
If you want to play around
with a full example of fetching events,
then check out the "MonthlyEvents" target
in the "Accessing Calendar using
EventKit and EventKitUI" sample project.
To support releases earlier
than iOS 17 and macOS Sonoma,
perform a runtime availability check.
Call the new requestAccess methods
on iOS 17 and macOS Sonoma and beyond.
On earlier OSes,
call the legacy requestAccess method.
Additional usage strings are required
prior to iOS 17 or macOS Sonoma.
Include the NSCalendarsUsageDescription
key for requesting calendar access.
Apps that use EventKitUI
also need to include
the NSContactsUsageDescription key
because EventKitUI
will request contacts access for the app.
If an app is missing these strings
when requesting access,
then it will crash.
So far we've covered a few ways
to add events and how to fetch events,
but working with events is not
the only way to integrate with Calendar.
If your app supports
voice or video calls,
use a virtual conference extension
to let people add your calls
directly to their events.
There are two ways
that these extensions are used.
When adding a location to an event,
custom virtual conference options
will appear in the location picker.
This example has the options
provided by the FaceTime
and Skype virtual conference extensions.
Tapping on one of these will add
that virtual conference to the event.
An event that has a virtual conference
will show a custom join option
in the event details.
Making a virtual conference extension
takes just a few steps.
First, create a new Virtual Conference
Extension target in Xcode.
Then, there are two methods
in the extension protocol to implement.
Implement fetchAvailableRoomTypes
to provide your available room types,
and then implement fetchVirtualConference
to provide a virtual conference object
for a selected room type.
Let's walk through an example.
First, create a Virtual Conference
extension target in Xcode.
The new target will have a stubbed
subclass of EKVirtualConferenceProvider.
The first method to override
is fetchAvailableRoomTypes.
The room types are shown
in the location picker.
Choose a title for each room type.
This will be shown
in the UI next to your app icon.
Also choose a unique identifier
for each room type.
The identifier is used
to let your extension know
which room type was chosen.
Create an instance
of EKVirtualConferenceRoomTypeDescriptor
using the title and identifier.
If your app supports multiple room types,
then make an instance for each one.
Finally,
return an array of your room types.
The next method to implement
is fetchVirtualConference.
This is called when one
of the room types is selected.
The identifier argument tells you
which room was selected.
Virtual conferences have one
or more URL descriptors,
which tell Calendar how to join.
Create an EKVirtualConferenceURLDescriptor
with the URL to open
and an optional title.
Use Universal Links for your URL
to allow your app to be opened directly.
The title helps to distinguish
between multiple join options.
Here it's not needed
because there's only one way to join.
Provide any additional information
in a details string.
This text will be included
in a special virtual conference section
of the event details UI.
Finally, put all of this together
to create and return
an EKVirtualConferenceDescriptor.
The title here helps distinguish
between multiple room types.
This example only has one room type,
so the title is left nil.
With just these two methods,
your app will appear
in the Calendar app's location picker
as an option for virtual conferences.
Now that we've covered
a few different ways
of integrating with Calendar,
think about how your app can contribute.
Use EventKitUI or Siri Event Suggestions
to add events without requesting access.
If you do need to request access,
request the minimum access needed,
and only when it's needed.
And if you have a voice or video call app,
then implement
a virtual conference extension.
I can't wait to see how your app
integrates with Calendar.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪