♪ ♪
Nina: Hello.
My name is Nina Paripovic,
and I'm a watchOS software engineer.
In this code-along session,
we'll take an existing app
built with the watchOS 9 SDK
and update it for watchOS 10.
We'll talk about the new design paradigms
and SwiftUI APIs you can use
to make your app look beautiful
alongside the system-wide redesign.
The sample project is linked
in the Resources list
associated with this session.
I encourage you to start that download now
so that we're ready to build
for watchOS 10 together.
Before we jump in,
let's take a look at our existing project.
The app we'll be updating
is Backyard Birds,
an app that lets you create and manage
beautiful backyard gardens
and their curious visitors.
In the app today,
there is a list of backyards.
Each backyard has a detail view
which shows us its activity and condition.
If food or water is running low,
they can be topped up.
We can also see all of our bird visitors
in each backyard.
watchOS 10 brings an exciting,
fresh new look to watch apps.
If you haven't already,
check out "Meet watchOS 10"
as well as "Design and build apps
for watchOS 10"
to get more info on the design principles
we are going to apply in this session.
Now, let's open up Xcode
to get started with updating our app.
Here is our current Backyard Birds app
built for and running on watchOS 9.
We see the list of backyards,
which transition to a backyard detail.
First, let's build
against the watchOS10 SDK.
The app is already looking great.
We see new system features,
like the large title that transitions
as we scroll
and the new material that blurs content
underneath the navigation bar.
Tapping on a backyard animates the cell,
and we have automatically adopted
the systemwide toolbar button styling
we see in the top left.
If we scroll and then tap on Refill,
it presents a modal with our new
blurred background material.
People who use Backyard Birds
care most about what's happening
in their own backyard.
Currently, when they launch the app,
the first thing they do is tap
on a backyard in the list to see
what's happening in the detail view.
In watchOS 10, we can make things easier
by modifying the structure of the app
with NavigationSplitView.
This will allow people to launch directly
into the detail view of their backyard
and then pop back up to the list
when they want to visit
their friends' yards.
Since the detail view is
the most important part of our app,
we can bring emphasis to it
by implementing NavigationSplitView.
NavigationSplitView is great
when we have this strong source list
and detail relationship.
It allows people to focus on the detail
by directly launching to it,
while still being able to easily switch
over to another yard from the source list.
We're already using it for Backyard Birds
on iOS and iPadOS.
Looks like NavigationSplitView
would be a great fit for our app.
In ContentView, we are going
to swap out the NavigationStack
for a NavigationSplitView.
Then we are going to move
the contents of our navigationDestination
into the detail
of the NavigationSplitView.
Finally, we'll adopt
the new list selection APIs,
available in watchOS 10,
that will drive which detail view is
presented by the NavigationSplitView.
To start,
let's swap out the NavigationStack
for a NavigationSplitView.
We can leave the Backyard List where it is
at the root of the NavigationSplitView.
Let's remove
the navigationDestination modifier
and move BackyardView
into the detail view builder.
Since selectedBackyard is an optional,
let's make sure to unwrap it
and provide a fallback view.
Finally, let's use a list initializer
that takes a selection binding.
When you provide a value
for the selection parameter of a list,
the selection binding drives
which detail view we present
within our NavigationSplitView.
Nice.
We now see the detail view
for our selected yard by default.
Since we launch directly to the detail,
we can remove the navigationTitle.
We can navigate back
to see the rest of our backyards
using the source list button.
And tapping back into the detail view
gives us
a beautiful full-screen animation.
Right now, the backyard view
is a long list of scrollable content.
Our list is already broken up
into three different sections
with distinct sets of functionality,
the today view, the habitat view
and the visitors view.
We'll be able to improve
the visual clarity of our app
by instead using a TabView
and creating tabs for each section.
TabView gives us a way to break up content
into full-screen views,
with each tab having
a clear and distinct purpose.
I want to keep Digital Crown functionality
for quick scrolling through views.
The new vertical page style
lets me do this with TabView.
People can quickly navigate between tabs
and even scroll within a single tab.
Let's jump back to Xcode and update
the detail view to use a TabView.
In BackyardView, let's move each section
into its own respective view
and replace the List with a TabView.
Since each page of the TabView
takes up the full size of the screen,
we don't need the sections and dividers.
Let's make sure to add the section headers
back in as navigationTitles.
Lastly, let's use
the tabViewStyle modifier
and specify that we want verticalPage.
We're almost there.
As we paginate,
we see views settling into each tab.
To make it easier for people
to quickly view all of the visitors,
we can wrap our VisitorView in a List.
Now, the TabView will designate one tab
to its child List view.
If the list exceeds
the height of the screen,
the view will become scrollable.
If you have scrollable content
within a vertical TabView,
place it in the last tab
whenever possible.
I'm also going to break up
the habitat view into two separate tabs,
so that people can easily distinguish
between food and water levels.
For this, I've created my own gauge
that fits better within a TabView.
In our TabView, let's replace HabitatView
with our new GaugeView
by creating one instance for food
and one for water.
That's looking great.
Now all we need to do
is add back the refill functionality.
For this, I am going to use a toolbar.
Toolbar has been elevated in watchOS 10
with brand-new placement options,
consistent across all screen sizes.
The new bottom bar placement
is a great place to put controls.
I'm going to make use
of this placement option
by adding in the Refill button
to the bottom bar.
Back in the new HabitatGaugeView,
we'll add a toolbar
and then use a ToolbarGroup to specify
we want bottom bar placement.
I'll use a spacer to add the button
to the trailing corner of the toolbar.
We now have a lot more space,
and it's easier to focus
on the Habitat summary.
I want to do more to help orient people
as they navigate through the TabView.
Additionally, if the food and water
of a backyard is low,
I want to bring attention to this.
We can achieve this by applying
a background gradient.
The title for each tab is helpful,
but color would be a great way
to increase glanceability and reinforce
where we are within the detail view.
We can also use it to highlight
the state of our backyard
if food or water is running low.
The system gradient is a nice way
to relay this
while maintaining contrast
against foreground elements.
Let's use the container
background modifier
with a color gradient to achieve this.
Let's first remove
our original background.
We can add a function to the BackyardView
that determines the background color
based on the current food and water level.
If levels are low,
the background will be red
to indicate that it's time for a refill.
I'll also add
some helpful computed variables.
Now we can pass this computed property
to the containerBackground modifier.
The modifier takes in a ShapeStyle
where we'll pass in the color gradient
as well as a ContainerBackgroundPlacement.
Here, we'll specify it's for a TabView.
I also want to change the gauge color
when the background changes.
Let's pass in
the same computed color variable.
Let's apply
the containerBackground modifier
to the other views within the TabView,
using the app's accent color.
As we scroll,
you can see that the gradient
contrasts nicely
against the foreground elements.
And as we tap on the toolbar button,
we can see
how the background gradient changes.
As a final touch,
I want to make use of materials
to highlight important information.
Materials have been available
across platforms
and are new to watch apps in watchOS10.
They're a nice way to distinguish
between foreground and background elements
while also adding a visual flourish.
Finally, they can surface
or reinforce information on screen.
There's a couple places in the app
where we can use materials and vibrancy.
Let's take a look.
To start, I want to replace
the shadow backdrop
from the backyard title
and instead use a material background.
The background of the cell is colorful,
and adding in a material will
help provide clarity to the title.
People really care
about the number of bird visitors
in each backyard, which you can see
in the summary view.
It would be great to surface it
in the list view,
so that people can see it without going
into the detail view of a backyard.
I'll add it as another overlay and provide
a material background to the number.
watchOS apps tend to use dark backgrounds,
so the material defaults to dark variants.
Because the backyards are
light and colorful,
I'm going to switch these
to the light variant.
And with that, our Backyard Birds app
has now been updated for watchOS 10.
Let's review
all the big changes we've just made.
We've added in
the NavigationSplitView to our list.
We then replaced the List
with a Vertical TabView.
We added functionality to the toolbar
with each backyard,
as well as some beautiful gradients.
To finish, we made use of materials
to surface useful information.
Thanks for coding along with me.
This is a big year for Apple Watch,
and I encourage you to explore
more sessions.
To go further with Backyard Birds,
head over
to "Build widgets
for the Smart Stack on Apple Watch".
I can't wait to see
the updates you'll make
so your app shines on watchOS 10.