♪ ♪
Person: Hello, and welcome to
Wind your way through advanced animations
in SwiftUI.
I’m Tim, a member of the SwiftUI team.
SwiftUI comes with a powerful set of
animation tools that make your app shine,
with animations that are interruptible,
physics-based for believable motion,
and deeply integrated
throughout the framework.
Today we’re going to talk
about some exciting new tools
that let you take animation
in your app to the next level.
Before we begin,
let’s do a quick review
of the animation tools
that you already know in SwiftUI.
You might have seen this app
that allows you to vote
for your favorite kind of pet
in other sessions.
To simplify this demo,
I went ahead and removed
all of the other options,
because cats are clearly the best choice.
Adding animation to your app is as easy
as using "withAnimation" or adding
an "animation" modifier, which gives
you great behavior out of the box.
After the state of your application
changes, SwiftUI applies animations
that interpolate from
the previous state to the new state.
But with animation, as with life,
sometimes the most rewarding experiences
are found when you aren’t so focused on
where you came from or where you’re going.
Sometimes you have
to get off of the beaten path
and focus on the journey itself
to make something special.
And some animations don’t simply animate
from a previous state into a new state.
Today, I’ll talk about
some powerful new tools
for building complex,
multistep animations.
Rather than animating between two states,
these animations can define
multiple steps that happen in sequence.
And they are especially great
in two situations:
repeating animations, that loop
continuously while a view is visible...
and event-driven animations, such as
a view that pulses when an event occurs.
In this talk, I’m going to introduce
a new family of APIs
that makes animations like these
even easier to build.
I’ll start by introducing you
to animation phases,
which let SwiftUI automatically advance
through a set of pre-planned states
that make up your animation.
Next, I’ll demonstrate how to take
animations even further with keyframes.
And finally, I’ll show
some advanced tips and tricks
to get the most out of this API.
I think we’re ready to go.
Let’s jump right in.
When I’m not writing Swift,
I like to get out trail running.
Trail races can be very long.
Ultramarathons can take a whole day,
or even multiple days to finish,
so I’ve been building an app
to plan for upcoming events,
and to help me remember
important details during a run.
Nutrition is super important
when you’re on the trail.
Unfortunately, it can be easy to forget to
eat late in a race as exhaustion sets in.
I’ve added a feature to my app
that reminds me to eat at the right times.
Here, the reminder at the bottom
of the screen is letting me know
that I’m overdue for a meal.
But there’s a problem.
Later in a race, I can get so tired
that I could miss a subtle indicator
like this.
I really don’t want
to accidentally skip a meal,
so I’ll add some motion
to make this reminder stand out.
Let’s focus on this one view.
We want to give it an animated
highlight effect to make it extra visible.
To make this view animate, we will apply
the ".phaseAnimator" modifier.
When you use the phase animator modifier,
you provide a sequence of states
that define the individual steps
in a multipart animation.
SwiftUI then animates
between these states automatically.
In this case, we’ll just be
animating between two states:
highlighted, and not highlighted,
so we can simply use boolean values.
Next, we’ll apply some modifiers
to change the appearance of the view
depending on the current phase.
We’ll start with an opacity modifier:
we’ll make the view fully opaque
when highlighted,
and 50% transparent otherwise.
And right away, the view starts animating.
Let’s talk about what SwiftUI
is doing on your behalf.
In our view, we provided two phases
to the phase animator modifier:
false, and true.
When the view first appears,
the first phase is active,
causing the view to be 50% transparent.
SwiftUI then immediately begins
an animated transition
to the next phase,
where the view is fully opaque.
Then when that animation is finished,
SwiftUI advances again.
We only have two phases,
so we loop around to the beginning.
This causes our animation
to cycle between the two states.
Of course, you can also define animations
that include more than two phases,
and any number
of additional view modifiers,
which I'll demonstrate later on.
Now while the view is animating,
the effect is really subtle.
Instead of changing the opacity,
let’s try changing the foreground style.
We’ll use red when highlighted,
and otherwise fall back
to the primary foreground style.
And that’s much more visible.
The animations are a bit abrupt, though.
By default,
SwiftUI uses a spring animation.
And while springs are great
for handling dynamic state changes,
in this case we want a smoother,
more consistent animation.
We can change the animation
by adding a trailing "animation" closure.
The phase that is being animated to
is passed in,
in case we want to use a different
animation for each phase.
But in this case, I always want to use
the same ease in out animation
with a custom duration,
to slow things down.
Now, you wouldn’t typically
use an animation
with a duration of a full second
for an interactive state change
because you wouldn’t want to make
people wait for an animation to finish.
But in this case,
we are building an ambient effect,
so it’s ok for things
to move a bit slower,
just like my pace if I miss that meal.
Now that we’ve solved the urgent problem
of mid-race nutrition,
let’s look at one more way
to use animation phases:
animations that are triggered by events.
I’ve been working on my app for a while,
and I’ve added the ability to see
which races my friends have run.
The emoji show reactions left by others.
Every runner sometimes asks themselves:
why do I do this?
Why did I sign up to run so many miles?
And the least that our app can do
is to feed the need
for external validation
by adding some excitement
when someone else likes a race.
We’ll add an animation that plays
every time someone adds a reaction.
The first thing that we will do is define
the phases of our animation.
Unlike in the previous example
that simply alternated
between two states,
we want a more complex animation.
An enum is a great way to define
a list of steps for the animation.
We’ve added three cases:
a case for the initial appearance,
then cases to move the view up,
and scale up the view.
To simplify our view body,
we will add computed properties
to this enum
that define the different effects
that we will apply.
I want the view to jump up
during the animation,
so I’ve added
a computed vertical offset property.
I switch over the enum
to return the right offset for each case.
Likewise, I’ve added
two additional computed properties
to determine the view’s scale
and foreground style.
I won’t show the implementations here,
but they also use a switch statement,
just like the vertical offset property.
Now, let’s get back to our view
and add the animation.
We add the phaseAnimator modifier,
but this time,
we give it a "trigger" value.
When we give the phase animator modifier
a trigger value,
it observes the value
that you specify for changes.
And when a change occurs,
it begins animating through the phases
that you specify.
Using the computed properties
that we defined on the phase type,
we apply modifiers to the view.
And this animation
technically does the right thing,
but it doesn’t feel great.
It’s a bit sluggish.
We’ll customize the animation
for each transition
to get the effect that we want,
including a couple
of different spring animations.
And this looks much better!
But what if we want to take
this animation even further?
When someone has finished 50 or 100 miles
on the trail,
we want to give them an animation
that leaves no doubt in their mind
that all of those miles were worth it when
they receive some well-deserved kudos.
When you need even more control,
there’s another powerful tool: keyframes.
Next, I’ll show you how to
use keyframes to define complex,
coordinated animations with
complete control over timing and movement.
First, let’s talk about
how keyframes are different
from the phases that we have used so far.
Phases define discrete states that are
provided to your view one at a time.
And SwiftUI animates between those states,
using the same animation types
that you already know,
and this works really well for animations
that can be modeled as discrete states.
When a state transition occurs,
all of the properties are animated
at the same time.
And then, when that animation is finished,
SwiftUI animates to the next state.
And this continues across
all of the phases of the animation.
But what if we want to animate
each property independently?
That’s where keyframes come in.
Keyframes let you define values
at specific times within an animation.
To demonstrate, I’ll animate this view,
starting with a rotation effect.
The dots here indicate keyframes: angles
to use at each point during the animation.
When the animation plays back,
SwiftUI interpolates values
in between these keyframes,
which we can then use to apply modifiers
to the view.
And keyframes allow you to independently
animate multiple effects at the same time
by defining separate tracks,
each with their own unique timing.
This is really powerful,
because you can use keyframes
to drive any modifier in SwiftUI.
In this example, we are using keyframes
to drive several other tracks,
including vertical stretch,
scale, and translation.
Let’s get back to our view
and see what this looks like in code.
I already have an idea of the animation
that I want to build,
so my first step is to define the
properties that will drive the animation.
To do this, I’ll create a new struct
containing all of the different properties
that will be independently animated.
Keyframes can animate any value
conforming to the "Animatable" protocol.
Notice that several properties
use "Double",
which now conforms to "Animatable."
Unlike phases,
in which you model separate,
discrete states,
keyframes generate interpolated values
of the type that you specify.
While an animation is in progress,
SwiftUI will provide you with a value
of this type on every frame
so that you can update the view.
Next, we add
the keyframeAnimator modifier.
This modifier is similar to
the phase animator that we used earlier,
but accepts keyframes.
Notice that we provide an instance
of our struct to use as the initial value.
The keyframes that we define
will apply animations onto this value.
Next, we’ll apply modifiers to our view
for each of the properties on the struct.
And finally,
we’ll start defining keyframes.
As I mentioned, keyframes let you
build sophisticated animations
with different keyframes
for different properties.
To make this possible,
keyframes are organized into tracks.
Each track controls a different property
of the type that you are animating,
which is specified by the key path
that you provide when creating the track.
Here, we are adding keyframes
for the scale property.
We first add a linear keyframe,
repeating the initial scale value
and holding it for 0.36 seconds.
And if you’re wondering
how I settled on 0.36,
I found that duration
by trying out different values
to change the feel of the animation,
and that’s an important point
about keyframes.
Making an animation that suits your app
can take some experimentation.
Previews in Xcode can be a great way
to fine-tune your animations.
Next, we add a "SpringKeyframe."
This uses a spring function
to pull the value toward the target.
And we’ve specified a duration.
For a spring keyframe with a set duration,
this means that the spring function
will only animate the value
for that duration.
After that, interpolation will begin
to the next keyframe.
Finally, I’ll add another spring keyframe
that animates the scale back to 1.0.
The different kinds of keyframes control
how values are interpolated.
Alrighty, we’ve seen
LinearKeyframe and SpringKeyframe.
There are actually four different types
of keyframes.
I’ll explain how they are different:
LinearKeyframe interpolates linearly in
vector space from the previous keyframe.
SpringKeyframe, as its name suggests,
uses a spring function to interpolate
to the target value
from the previous keyframe.
CubicKeyframe uses a cubic Bézier curve
to interpolate between keyframes.
If you combine multiple
cubic keyframes in sequence,
the resulting curve is equivalent
to a Catmull-Rom spline.
And finally, MoveKeyframe immediately
jumps to a value without interpolation.
Each kind of keyframe supports
customization to give you full control,
and you can mix and match different kinds
of keyframes within an animation.
SwiftUI maintains velocity
between keyframes
to make sure
your animation remains continuous.
Coming back to our view,
we’re ready to add the next track.
Here, we’ve used linear
and spring keyframes
to animate the vertical translation.
Right before the view jumps up,
it pulls back in anticipation.
We have modeled that
with a spring keyframe
that pulls the view down briefly
before it moves up.
This is looking good, but we still have
two more properties to animate:
vertical stretch, and rotation.
We’ll start with vertical stretch,
and for this, we will use cubic keyframes.
Again, this can take some trial and error
to get right,
but don’t hesitate to experiment
with different ways
to model animations using keyframes.
The squash and stretch really
gives this animation a lot more energy.
Finally,
we’ll animate the rotation as well.
And this is looking great.
And those curves that we saw earlier?
Those are a visualization
of the animation that we just built.
You can add additional tracks
to apply any SwiftUI modifier.
I’ve had a lot of fun
exploring different combinations.
let’s take a moment to review
the model of keyframes.
Keyframes are predefined animations.
That means that they are not a replacement
for normal SwiftUI animations
in situations where
the UI should be fluid and interactive.
Instead, think of keyframes
like video clips that can be played.
They give you a ton of control,
but there’s a tradeoff.
Because you specify exactly
how an animation should progress,
keyframe animations can’t gracefully
retarget the way that springs can,
so it’s generally best to avoid
changing keyframes mid-animation.
Keyframes animate a value
of the type that you define,
which you then use
to apply modifiers to the view.
You can use a single keyframe track
to drive a single modifier,
or a combination of different modifiers.
It’s up to you.
And because the animation happens
in terms of the value that you define,
updates happen on every frame,
so you should avoid performing
any expensive operations
while applying a keyframe animation
to the view.
Finally, I’ll demonstrate how
how you can do even more with keyframes.
My app includes a race map,
showing the route that each leg takes.
I want to add an animation
that automatically zooms in
and follows the course.
Thankfully, MapKit now allows me
to use keyframes to move the camera.
Here, I’m using a "Map" view
to show the course.
My view already has a route,
which is a model that contains all of
the coordinates along one leg of the race.
To build our tour,
we’ll add a state property
and a button to change it.
Finally, we use the new
"mapCameraKeyframeAnimator" modifier.
We give it the trigger value,
then add keyframes,
just like we used for the heart icon
in the previous example.
Every time the trigger value changes,
maps will use these keyframes to animate.
The final value of the keyframes
determines the camera value
that is used at the end of the animation.
Finally, we hit the button,
and the tour starts.
If the user performs
a gesture while animating,
the animation will be removed and the user
will have full control over the camera.
By independently animating
the center coordinate,
heading, and distance, we’re able
to smoothly animate along this course
then zoom back out for a bird’s-eye view.
Finally, I’d like to demonstrate
how keyframes can be manually evaluated
to drive any kind of effect
that you can think of.
We’ve seen
the "keyframeAnimator" modifier.
Outside of the modifier,
you can use the "KeyframeTimeline" type
to capture a set of keyframes and tracks.
You initialize this type
with an initial value,
and the keyframe tracks
that define your animation,
just like with the view modifier.
KeyframeTimeline provides API
that gives you the duration,
which is equal
to the duration of the longest track.
And you can calculate values for any time
within the range of the animation.
This makes it easy to visualize
keyframes with Swift Charts,
which I used for the curve visualizations
that I showed earlier.
This also means that you can use
keyframe-defined curves however you want,
or to creatively combine keyframes
with other APIs,
for example, with a geometry proxy
to scrub keyframe-driven effects
using scroll position,
or with a "TimelineView"
to update based on time.
And if you’re not sure
when you would use this,
that’s ok, it’s an advanced tool,
and most developers will want
to stick to the view modifier.
But it’s here as a building block,
and I’m excited to see
what creative ways you find
to integrate it into your app.
That completes our journey.
I hope you’re excited
to use this new family of API.
Remember:
use phases for chained animations.
They use all of the existing
animation types that you already know,
so you can get up and running quickly.
Use keyframes for more complex animations
where you need complete control.
And finally: have fun exploring.
The world of animation is exciting,
and I hope these new tools lead you,
and your app, somewhere new.
Thanks!
♪ ♪