♪ ♪
Nadia Zouba: Hello, everyone, and welcome.
My name is Nadia Zouba and
I work on the Vision team here at Apple.
Today, I will be talking about a new
amazing API in Vision: Animal Body Pose.
I will also go over
some important updates in Vision.
Let’s start with Animal Body Pose.
Animal Body Pose can be used in
many possible applications.
For example, imagine you left your cat
and dog at home alone,
and you spent the day at work.
When you are back from work,
you find this mess in your house.
Don’t worry.
The Vision Framework can help you
figure out what happened,
what your pets were doing the whole day,
and who is making the mess.
But before I dig into that,
let’s talk about poses.
Three years ago, Vision introduced
Human Body Pose to detect human poses.
The request generates a collection of
human body landmarks
by detecting up to 19 body joints.
Developers around the world
used the API to create
many useful applications
for health, fitness, et cetera.
And since Vision interacts with
the real world,
we don’t only care about humans;
we also care about animals.
Vision has already a request
for animal recognition
that detects and recognizes cats and dogs.
The request generates a bounding box
with a label for the recognized animal
and a confidence level.
That’s a great API if you are trying to
locate and identify the animal,
but how about if you want to know
more about the animal?
It can be challenging to infer
what the animal is doing.
For example,
when I dog-sit for my neighbor,
I might like to know the specific pose
of my neighbor’s dog
when he wants a snack or needs a walk.
Guess what?
Vision expanded the body pose to animals.
That’s awesome.
Animal Body Pose is a new API in Vision.
It's offered in Vision via
DetectAnimalBodyPoseRequest.
This request, once processed,
returns an observation for each animal
which contains a collection of
animal body joint locations.
The request supports cats and dogs,
and detects 25 animal body landmarks
that includes the tail and the ears.
The Animal Body Pose API is
available in Vision
starting in iOS 17, iPadOS 17,
tvOS 17, and macOS Sonoma.
The input to Animal Body Pose can be
an image or a video.
After creating and processing the request
in Vision,
the request will produce
a collection of joints
which will define
the skeleton of the animal.
For Animal Body Pose,
six joint groups have been defined:
The Head group contains the ears,
the eyes, and the nose.
The Forelegs group includes
the front legs.
You guessed it; here comes
the Hindlegs group for the back legs.
Trunk group refers to the neck,
and the Tail group contains
three tail joints.
Finally, there is the All group,
which is composed by all the joints.
To demonstrate everything
I’ve talked about so far,
I have a sample app that draws
the skeleton of the animal
using the location of the landmarks.
I have this cute little chihuahua toy dog
sitting on my desk.
Since this dog can walk, I will use it
to show the results of the sample app.
I take the dog and put it
in front of my phone’s camera
and I start the sample app.
The app draws
a skeleton on top of the animal.
Let’s turn on the dog so he can walk.
The skeleton follows the animal
in his walk.
Oops!
The dog is walking away from the camera.
Let’s move it back to keep it
in front of the phone’s camera.
The skeleton is still following the dog.
That’s awesome.
Now I will go into the code to show you
how the sample app was done.
We start with the capture output
where we are receiving CMSampleBuffers
from the camera stream.
The first step is to create the request.
I will use VNDetectAnimalBodyPoseRequest.
The next step is to create a request
handler using imageRequestHandler.
Then I provide the request to the handler
via a call to perform.
If perform request succeed,
VNAnimalBodyPoseObservations
will be returned
in the request results property.
Each will contain
the location of the joints.
To access these joints from
Animal Pose Observation,
I will request a dictionary of
recognized points in the group
by calling .recognizedPoints.
Since I needed all the joints
to draw the skeleton of the animal,
I choose to use the All group.
You can use another group if you need to
only access some of the animal joints.
And finally,
to draw the skeleton of the animal,
I iterate over all the recognized points
and connect the joints.
Here is an example of how
the head joints were connected
to draw the head skeleton.
There are some considerations
to keep in mind.
Using the new Animal Body Pose,
you can detect up to two animals
in an image.
The input image size should be
at least 64 pixels on each side.
And by using the neural engine, the
performance can keep up with live capture.
Let’s go through a few examples of
what can be done with Animal Pose.
Using the new
Animal Pose API with still images,
you can develop your own analysis on
the joints
to recognize interesting poses
of your animal,
such as, stretching after waking up...
standing, begging for a treat...
running away from a dog...
or, curling up to take a nap.
As I mentioned before,
Animal Recognition allows you to localize
and recognize the animal,
and Animal Body Pose returns
the full body landmarks of the animal.
Combining those two requests will allow
you to know
what type of animal was detected,
the location, and the pose.
Now you can know who is messing up
with the dining table.
This will give you a lot of opportunities
to develop interesting applications
for your pets;
maybe something for a dog treat dispenser
activated on animal recognition
and animal pose detection.
The Animal Pose API can also be used
with videos.
You can bring your own algorithms to
your app to analyze the motion,
and determine what type of activity
your animal is doing.
You may even go further with your analysis
to understand your animal behavior
by tracking the poses over time.
Until Animal Body Pose,
I thought all those marks
in the wall were from my kids,
but it was the cat trying to catch
a laser pointer.
And whoa,
this dog can skateboard better than me!
Another use is to track the animal
with the camera.
To learn more about that kind of tracking,
please refer to the session
“Integrate with motorized iPhone stands
with DockKit.”
You can also
write funny apps for your pets.
For example,
putting a hat and sunglasses on a dog.
Wouldn’t it be super fun to create
a cute card for your animal’s birthday,
and send it to family and friends?
Happy birthday, Mr. Frenchie!
I do this by placing emojis where I find
relevant Animal Body Pose joints.
Let me demonstrate the emoji app
using this cute toy dog I have with me.
I will use the same sample app and switch
from the skeleton view to the emoji view.
[toy chirping]
Since this little dog is walking slowly,
I added some skates emojis on top of
his paw joints
to speed him up a little bit.
Oh, wait, safety first!
Let’s go back to the code
and give him a helmet.
Here I have already added the skates
emojis on top of the paw joints.
Let’s add the helmet emoji
on top of the ear joints.
I choose the size and
the position of the emoji.
Let’s also add some glasses
to skate in style.
I run the app again
after taking care of the dog's safety.
Better be safe than sorry.
Let’s switch to the emoji view.
The dog now has the gears he needed
to continue skating safely.
Looks cool, right?
Go, doggy, go! You nailed it!
That was it for Animal Body Pose.
I can’t wait for you to bring to your app
all the amazing things
you will create using
the new Animal Pose API.
There are more updates in Vision
that you may find helpful,
so let me introduce them to you.
There are new Stateful Requests.
VNTargetedImage-based requests are
available as Stateful Requests in Vision.
Vision has three new derived
Stateful Requests,
all named with the Track verb.
This makes it easier to use for tracking.
I am thrilled to announce that
Vision supports MLComputeDevice.
The new Compute Device API
allows you to query
where requests get executed
and specify which device to use.
Core ML and Create ML Multilabel
Classification
is now compatible with Vision.
This allows you to train
your own classifier
that supports more than one label.
Please refer to the session “Discover
machine learning enhancements
in Create ML” for more information.
There are also new revisions in existing
requests that bring great improvements.
For Barcodes, there is a new revision,
Revision 4.
The new revision includes
a new MSIPlessey symbology
and supports color inverted QR codes.
And by the way,
Revision 1 will be deprecated.
Text Recognition is adding support for
Thai and Vietnamese.
And finally, there is a new revision for
FaceCaptureQuality, Revision 3,
to improve the quality and the accuracy.
For additional information about
all those new updates in Vision,
please check the developer documentation.
Today, I talked about
the new Animal Body Pose
and all the amazing things that can be
done with this new API.
I also presented
some important APIs updates
and other enhancements in Vision
that I hope will be helpful
in your developments.
But wait, there is more.
Please check the session
“Explore 3D body pose
and person segmentation in Vision”
to learn about the new 3D body pose
and person segmentation APIs in Vision.
And if you want to segment
any selected foreground object,
please refer to the session
“Lift subjects from images in your app”.
Thank you for your attention,
and we can’t wait for you to
get your paws on Animal Pose.