♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hi, I'm Dhruv Govil,
a 3D Software Engineer.
And in this session,
I'll be walking you through
what's new and exciting
in our 3D Content Technologies
ecosystem on our platforms.
3D is an amazing form of media,
and it's even more important
with the introduction of xrOS,
where the third dimension
will allow for even more
immersive experiences.
It's become far more accessible
for everyone to get started
with creating amazing visuals
on Apple computers
they have at home or even the
ones in your hands like an iPad.
To enable this wave
of creative content,
we've been building on
the foundation based on
the key technologies that power
the creative industry worldwide.
The first of these technologies
is Universal Scene Description,
or USD for short.
It allows for a standard form
of representing 3D content
to share between applications.
And we're now also introducing
support for MaterialX on xrOS
to portably represent the visual
appearance of objects.
USD is an open source project,
created by Pixar,
recently renamed to OpenUSD.
It is production proven
and scales from creators
making single assets
to large studios
working on AAA games and films.
USD allows for expressing
complex and flexible
relationships
between asset data
via composition.
Apple was
an early adopter of USD,
adding it to our platforms in
2017 and growing support since.
Today, USD is at the heart
of 3D Content on xrOS.
MaterialX is also
an open source project,
created at
Industrial Light & Magic
for their work on Star Wars,
now developed in conjunction
with others like Autodesk
and adopted by
the Academy Software Foundation.
It allows artists to combine
shader logic into a node graph
within their 3D applications,
all without needing
to know how to code.
This graph can also be
embedded inside USD,
so it travels
with your scene data.
We're supporting MaterialX
first on xrOS with RealityKit,
Apple's real-time
3D rendering framework
for building immersive
spatial experiences.
We have four areas to cover
as we discover
how these 3D content
technologies can be used.
To start, we'll go over
how our applications
are enabling new uses
for 3D content.
Next, we dive deeper into
how we support MaterialX
as well as color management
in RealityKit.
Finally, we'll return to USD
and go over the changes
that you should be aware
of since last year.
Let's begin by looking
at the new ways you can use 3D
in our applications,
before we get into the
technologies that power them.
Building on the success
of Quick Look
for USDZ files on iOS,
we're now bringing
Quick Look to xrOS.
It's so simple to just open up
a USDZ file
and see it beautifully
and spatially represented,
walking around it
and connecting it
to your surroundings.
We have a great talk as well
on how to easily author content
that will look great
on this new platform.
Last year,
we introduced Freeform,
a powerful and easy-to-use
brainstorming app.
Freeform now gives you the
ability to embed USDZ content,
so you can now collaborate
on your 3D assets
just like you would
for other content types,
across all supported platforms
like macOS, iOS, iPadOS,
and now xrOS.
Safari also introduces
new support for 3D Content
with the Model element.
The Model element is available
on all Apple platforms
with Safari and can be enabled
under the Developer menu
on macOS or Settings
on other platforms.
Just as easy to use
as the audio,
video, and image elements,
the Model element
lets you embed a USDZ file
into your web page
with an interactive view,
with the ability to rotate
around objects.
This allows creation
of more interactive websites,
providing your users
incredible experiences
no matter which of the supported
devices they're on.
We're working with the W3C
Immersive Web Working Group
on standardization.
We also have
Reality Composer Pro,
a new macOS application
joining our suite of tools
for creators and developers.
Using USD's
composition features,
it lets multiple people
work in parallel,
enabling each person to tackle
a different aspect of the scene
and see them combined together
as each asset updates.
Assets can be authored to USD
in your own content creation
applications,
and Reality Composer Pro
lets you prepare them
for use in xrOS apps
and experiences.
Check out our
Reality Composer Pro sessions
to learn more.
As important
as the 3D models you make
is the shaders and materials
that give them
the individual
visual aesthetic.
MaterialX gives you the power
to have bespoke visuals
that can be transported
inside your USD scenes
into RealityKit applications
on xrOS.
Reality Composer Pro
introduces a Shader Graph
that authors MaterialX nodes
embedded inside of USD files.
This enables the creation
of shaders
using an interactive node graph
to compose the shader logic.
MaterialX shader graphs
are how creators
will be constructing custom
shaders for xrOS content.
In addition to many of
the standard MaterialX nodes,
Reality Composer Pro also has
a few custom MaterialX nodes
that enable a range of
xrOS-specific platform features.
Some of these shader nodes are:
RealityKit PBR,
our physically based
rendering shader
which enables
realistic-looking 3D content;
RealityKit Unlit,
an unlit shader
that lets you do more
stylized shading;
Geometry Modifiers
that allow us to modify
surface deformations;
as well as several
custom utility nodes.
We have a great
developer session
on how to use the Shader Graph
to get you up and running
with creating custom looks
for your assets.
Support for MaterialX
with USD grows
across established
third-party 3D applications,
like SideFX's Houdini
and LookdevX
in Autodesk's Maya, shown here.
Reality Composer Pro then
lets you preview your shaders
to see how they'll look before
deploying to your device.
As I mentioned, MaterialX
is an open source project
which enables creators
and developers to make use of it
in their own workflows
and applications directly.
The MaterialX project
includes support
for generating shader code
from your MaterialX node graphs.
Apple has added support
to the project
for creating Metal shader code
to make the most use
of our powerful GPUs.
This is now available
in the MaterialX 1.38.7 release.
For developers who use USD,
this also enables the future use
of MaterialX
within USD on macOS.
Having confidence in how your
shaders behave is important,
but so is having confidence
in what your colors look like.
So we've expanded our handling
of color space management
for RealityKit,
so you can make
accurate-looking 3D content
capable of using
our wide gamut color range.
But first, a quick recap of why
color spaces are important.
Color spaces are how
graphics programs understand
how to represent colors
from digital values,
including the range
of colors available.
This allows
multiple applications
to reliably display
and edit the same colors.
Apple displays primarily use
Display P3 as their color space,
whereas many other platforms may
use the more commonplace sRGB.
DisplayP3 marries the wider
primary range of digital cinema
with the sRGB gamma curves
used by computer displays.
In fact, it's capable
of displaying
up to 25 percent more colors
than traditional sRGB,
shown here as the black line
within the greater
Display P3 color space.
This allows for representing
more of the colors we see
in the real world,
such as the vibrant feathers
of a parrot,
or the deep colors
of your favorite clothes.
Most color and image workflows
tend to use sRGB,
which represents a standard
range of colors
used by many monitors
for decades.
These are still capable of
creating good-looking content,
but can't take full advantage
of the beautiful,
wider-range displays
that Apple products ship with.
If you instead make use
of the Display P3 color profile,
you're now able to use
the wider color range
that RealityKit can provide
on these displays.
Textures authored
with Display P3 in mind,
and appropriately tagged,
are able to express
a much larger range of colors,
with deeper and more
saturated tones.
This effect may be subtle,
but allows for the creation
of more vibrant
and authentic-looking assets.
Notice the richer reds
and the lush greens.
Most importantly,
color space tagging
means your colors are accurate
to what you saw
when you made your content,
avoiding accidental
color shifts.
MaterialX and Color Management
are great new additions
to our USD ecosystem.
We also have more to share
about what's new in USD
for our platforms
and the greater ecosystem.
All our first
party applications,
such as Motion and Quick Look,
now benefit from an updated
and more efficient USD version.
USD supports a wide range
of object types,
also known as schemas.
This update also allows
the Storm renderer in Preview
on macOS to support rendering
even more USD schemas
and features.
We also continue to update
our documentation
to highlight features and
schemas that are newly supported
on our renderers and which
platforms support them.
Additionally, we make note
of other changes in behaviors,
so we recommend that you
periodically refresh yourself
on the documentation
linked in the video description.
USD also allows
for custom schema types.
And this year,
RealityKit is introducing
new Component schemas
for its Entity Component System,
or ECS for short, on xrOS.
RealityKit's ECS splits
the systems that process data
from the Component data itself,
allowing it to live
alongside your 3D content.
Thanks to these custom schemas,
you can now use
RealityKitComponent
for built-in Components,
and RealityKitCustomComponent
for your own Swift
custom components.
Your Swift components structs
and dictionaries can be
represented by the equivalent
RealityKit USD schemas.
RealityKit also builds
upon USD's spatialAudio
with RealityKit's Audio File,
Audio File Group, and MixGroup
to create even more
immersive audio.
Let's take a look at a USD file
that represents
some custom component data,
as a USD prim,
which is what USD calls
objects in its hierarchy.
This allows your custom
component data
to live alongside your other
prims such as geometry.
Since this is all in USD,
you can use any app
that lets you author USD prims
directly to create them
alongside the rest
of your scene.
This aligns with your
corresponding Swift Component
that can then be used
to read these values
from your USD components,
such as here
where different objects
in your app may have
specific Engagement Points
associated with them.
Please check out our talks
on building applications
with Reality Composer Pro
to learn more.
We continue to contribute
to growing these technologies
in the industry,
as a growing ecosystem
makes content creation
easier for everyone.
So we've worked with Pixar
and the community
to list many of
the software packages
that now support USD
on the OpenUSD webpage.
This allows creators to see
how easily they can create
USD-based content with their own
existing workflows on a Mac.
We've also been working
on making it easy
to build USD for
our portable platforms like iOS,
so that as developers,
you, too, can integrate USD
into your own applications.
This enables you to create
applications that can author
immersive USD content.
Additionally,
we're collaborating
to reduce dependencies
in the USD library
so that it's easier to get up
and running with USD
across all platforms,
with minimal work.
USD includes a technology
called Hydra,
an abstraction framework
for renderers,
and Storm, a real-time renderer
that makes use of Hydra.
Apple has worked with Pixar
to add Metal support to Storm,
making use
of our modern graphics API
that enables developers
to create high-performance,
GPU-based applications
on our platforms.
Let's take a look
at one scenario
where this performance helps.
The Animal Logic ALab scene
is representative
of many feature
film-level assets.
When set to full resolution,
this scene can take
over 26GB of graphics memory,
previously requiring desktop
workstation GPUs.
Now, with Metal in Hydra Storm,
and unified memory
on Apple silicon,
a MacBook Pro lets you
work on the go,
even on demanding scenes
like this,
while retaining
interactive performance.
This high-performance rendering
in Storm also enables
Blackmagic Design to add fast
viewport rendering of USD
to Fusion in DaVinci Resolve.
Building on the collaboration
from previous years,
we continue to work
with Autodesk
on their open source
Maya USD plugin.
We've made several
contributions to the project,
including enhancements
to the export of geometry
and materials for your assets.
We also have improvements
to animation import.
All of this helps you have
more seamless workflows
to create spatial content
for xrOS.
Some of these features
may be released
in later releases of Maya USD,
so we recommend keeping
your plug-ins up to date.
We've also been working
with the Blender Foundation,
many individuals
and partners like AMD,
NVIDIA, and Unity,
to deliver updates to Blender,
an open-source 3D application.
This collaboration has enabled
significantly improved
USD import and export
in Blender 3.5.
This includes USDZ support
for the first time,
allowing you to go directly
to Quick Look.
Apple also worked
with the Blender Foundation
to introduce Metal support for
their Eevee and Cycles renderer.
Now with Blender 3.5,
you can run Blender
as a fully native
Metal application,
speeding up your UI, viewport,
and final render.
Final renders can make use
of your GPU to complete
in up to half the time when
compared to CPU based renders,
and the viewport can now render
up to 4 times faster than OpenGL
in certain scenes.
That wraps up this overview of
what's new in the USD Ecosystem.
xrOS adds a whole new,
exciting dimension to apps
and experiences,
built on a foundation
of technologies like USD.
I recommend continuing
by checking out
these related talks
about Quick Look
and Reality Composer Pro.
By collaborating
on these open standards,
we're building
a strong ecosystem
to make it faster and easier
to create content
for xrOS
and all our platforms,
and we can't wait to see
what you create.
♪