♪ ♪
Richard: Hello, I'm Richard.
Today, I'm thrilled to talk to you
about some exciting new features
in Swift Charts:
Pie charts, selection, and scrolling.
Let's start with pie charts.
Swift Charts provides composable
and customizable building blocks
for you to create
all kinds of data visualizations.
Today, new to the family of Swift Charts
are the delicious, beautiful pie charts.
Pie charts show how a total value
is made up by various categories,
via simple, familiar shapes.
For example, here's a chart
visualizing the pancake sales data
for my friends' food truck.
Pie charts do not have axes,
and they are great
for casual settings
where precisionis not critical.
With broad understanding
of how wedges make up a full circle,
they are intuitive for visualizing
part-to-whole relationships.
One important reason
people like pie charts
is because of their round,
approachable shapes.
You can create a pie chart
using the mark-based composition syntax
that you are already familiar with.
Introducing a new mark type, SectorMark.
A SectorMark represents
a slice in the pie.
It's positioned in polar space.
Not this polar,
but the polar coordinate system.
The size of a sector is proportional
to the value that it represents.
Along the radius,
you can customize the look of a sector.
If I increase the inner radius,
the pie chart becomes a donut chart.
With SectorMark, you can easily build
all kinds of pie charts and donut charts.
Let me show you an example.
Our friends' international
pancake food truck business
saw a big, revitalizing growth
in their daily sales
throughout the last year,
selling six styles of pancakes.
This summer, I took on another challenge
to help them improve their sales app.
I start with a chart visualizing
the best-selling styles of pancakes.
For that, the app currently has
a simple stacked bar chart.
It's got a BarMark, with sales being
stacked along the X dimension.
As it's categorical data,
the category is reflected
as the foreground style
of each stacked bar.
This chart gets the job done,
but let's turn it into a pie chart
to take advantage of the available space
on the screen
and make the data stand out.
All I need to do is to switch out
BarMark and argument x
for SectorMark and angle.
It is that simple!
With SectorMark, I use angle
to represent the sales quantity.
The angle values you provide
for a pie chart
are automatically normalized
to a full circle.
I can also apply
some style customizations.
angularInset can be set on a sector
to create a gap between sectors.
Here, I set the angular inset for sectors
to 1.5 points,
so the gap between two sectors
is double the inset, 3 points wide.
I also set a corner radius
which gives me a nicely rounded pie crust.
Thatalready looks stunning
with just a few lines of code.
To try a different look,
let's turn this chart into a donut chart.
I set the inner radius to be a ratio
of the full radius of the pie.
To me, the golden ratio
looks just about right,
but you might like a different thickness
for your donut.
Of all the sold pancakes,
we have a clear winner, cachapa,
that's currently displayed
above the chart.
But because donut charts
are hollow in the center,
I want to move the text
to the center of the chart.
I put the text in a chartBackground.
I use some position calculations
to make sure the text is centered
in the donut hole.
Now that's a nifty-looking donut chart.
So that's pie charts and donut charts.
They are a great way to make
an impression with your data,
and they are absolutely stunning
on a big screen.
Next, I'd like to dive deep
into some chart interactivity features,
starting with selection.
By enabling interactivity in your charts,
you are progressively disclosing
additional details.
Interactivity encourages people
to explore data naturally
using various forms of input,
such as touch.
Selection is a direct way
for you to communicate with a chart,
and Apple-designed charts,
like the heart rate chart,
are perfect examples of that.
By selecting a point along an axis,
the chart will reveal
additional information.
Let's bring this idea
over to the pancake sales app.
One chart in the app visualizes
the average sales
of each day of the week in two cities.
I'll enable value selection on this chart
to reveal the detailed sales numbers
via a popover that shows the number
of pancakes sold on the selected day.
This is how the chart is defined.
Each city has a data series.
Each element in the series has
a day of the week and a sales count.
The lines are then styled by city name.
You may be already familiar
with the chartOverlay modifier,
which allows you to overlay
a SwiftUI view to capture gestures.
But in iOS 17, I can use
the new chartXSelection modifier.
It handles
all the gesture recognition for me
and stores the selected value
to a binding.
The selection modifier gives me
the raw date value along the X axis,
so I define a computed property
to match it to a data point
in my line chart.
Let's extend the chart to display
a popover when a value is selected.
When a value is selected,
I add a vertical rule mark
as a selection indicator.
I set its Z index to be lower
than the default 0 value
to make sure the rule mark
stays behind the line marks.
Now let's make a popover
on top of the selection indicator.
I can do this as an annotation
using a custom SwiftUI view.
Annotations are usually positioned
within the chart,
but in this case, the popover extends
beyond the bounds of the chart.
This is where I need
an overflow resolution for annotations.
On the X axis, I make it fit to the chart
such that the popover never moves
past the horizontal bounds of the chart.
On the Y axis,
I disable overflow resolution
so that the annotation can be
just above the chart.
With a selectionbinding
and a rule mark with annotation,
I now have an interactive line chart.
Swift Charts supports selection
on macOS too,
where hover gesture is the default
for value selection.
Besides single value selection,
a variant of this chart selection modifier
allows you to select a range.
On iOS, the default is
a two-finger tap gesture,
and on macOS, it's a drag gesture.
Swift Charts also allows you to provide
a custom gesture for selection,
with ChartProxy helping you select a value
based on gesture locations.
Beyond charts in X and Y coordinates,
chart value selection works seamlessly
with pie charts and donut charts.
Tapping and highlighting sectors
is a lot of fun.
So selection was all about
revealing additional information
in your chart.
Another important part of interactivity
is about navigating the data.
Let's talk about scrolling.
I want to create a chart that visualizes
daily pancake sales for a whole year.
Fitting all 365 days on a screen
would be unrealistic,
so it has to be scrollable.
To enable scrolling, I simply call
the chartScrollableAxes modifier.
With chartXVisibleDomain,
I set a visible window
of 30 days as a time interval.
To be able to display the total pancake
sales in the current visible domain,
I use chartScrollPosition
to store the current date to a binding.
Now I canjust take my finger and scroll.
Not only can I scroll the plot,
the axis content scrolls with it,
and it's buttery smooth.
Scrolling can be customized
in a few different ways.
For example, I'd like scrolling
to always snap to a date unit.
This brings us to scroll behaviors.
ScrollTargetBehavior is a new addition
to SwiftUI and Swift Charts
that allows you to align
the scroll view content with values.
For the snapping behavior that I wanted,
I set it to match the first hour of a day.
majorAlignment customizes it
one step further
by defining the swiping behavior.
Here, I set it
to the first day of a month,
so that when I page through a chart
by swiping,
I'll always land
on the first of each month.
Scrollable charts are built on top
of some of the latest enhancements
to scroll views in SwiftUI.
For more information,
be sure to check out Beyond Scroll Views.
Swift Charts provides you
with endless possibilities
to visualize data.
Beyond charts in and X and Y coordinates,
pie charts are now part
of the family of APIs
to create Apple-designed charts.
Pie charts are simple
yet powerful visualizations.
They work the best when representing
part-to-whole data relationships.
Interactivity features
like selection and scrolling
enable a whole new dimension
in your data visualizations,
putting your user at the driver's seat
as they explore data.
Enjoy baking pie and donut charts.
♪ ♪