♪ ♪
Rasmus: Hi, I'm Rasmus.
I'm an engineer
on the Camera Algorithms team
working with Computational Video.
I'm already excited about Cinematic mode.
And now I'm even more excited
about showing
how you can integrate
the magic of Cinematic mode
in your very own app
using the new Cinematic API.
In this presentation,
I'll walk through the necessary steps
using the new API to build a sample app
which does playback and edit,
realizing the awesome capabilities
of Cinematic mode.
But before I start talking
about integration,
let me first show you
what Cinematic mode is,
how you can capture it,
and what you can do with it post-capture.
We introduced Cinematic mode in iPhone 13,
and it really is a tiny film crew
right in your pocket.
It brings you a camera
with beautiful shallow depth of field
and natural focus falloff,
a director, who directs the attention
and narrative by changing the focus,
and a focus puller,
who anticipates keyframes ahead of time
and creates smooth transitions
between focus points.
So how do you capture Cinematic mode?
It's captured right in the Camera app
on any device
in the iPhone 13 & 14 lineup,
and it gives you a rendering preview
as you record.
This makes it super accessible,
whether you're an aspiring indie filmmaker
or just like to add a magic touch
to your camping trip videos.
And while I did dream
of becoming a filmmaker,
I do love to capture Cinematic mode
of my own family.
But the magic doesn't stop here.
There's more to Cinematic mode
than meets the eye.
It allows you to make some pretty amazing
nondestructive edits post-capture.
You can change the aperture,
and thereby the amount of bokeh.
And you can redirect
the focus and narrative
using alternative detections.
This shows the post-capture editing
in Photos,
but editing can also be done in apps
like iMovie, Final Cut Pro, and Motion.
And now with the introduction
of the Cinematic API,
you can use Cinematic mode videos
for playback and edit
in your own amazing app.
The Cinematic API is widely available
on new macOS Sonoma,
iOS 17, iPadOS 17, and tvOS 17.
So this is really exciting.
First I'll start with some fundamentals
about the special Cinematic mode assets
and dataflow.
Then I will go through the specific steps
to get and play a Cinematic mode asset
with simple playback adjustments,
like changing the aperture.
And then how to do nondestructive edits
driving the focus in Cinematic mode
and how to save and load
these edit changes.
I will go through some of the new
Cinematic API calls
and also provide a sample code app
which can be used as a detailed reference.
But as promised,
let me start by explaining
some fundamentals about Cinematic mode.
Cinematic mode actually consists
of two files
and a dataflow from one to the other.
First there’s the rendered asset.
This is a baked file
with the Cinematic mode effect applied,
and it can be exported, shared,
and played as a regular QuickTime movie.
And then there’s the special
Cinematic mode asset,
which has all the information needed
to create the rendered asset.
It allows you to do nondestructive
post-capture edits,
such as change the aperture
and refocus to your narrative.
Let’s start by taking a look
at the rendered asset,
and break down a shot
with a little Cinematography 101.
Opening shot: we enter what’s clearly
an important game of street handball,
and by focusing on the main subject,
we really feel the tension
as he gets ready to make a big play.
He checks his team player.
He’s also ready.
Racking focus to him emphasizes
just how ready he is.
We rack focus back to our main subject.
This is it; you could cut
through the tension with a knife.
He makes the play and totally ruins it,
setting up some comic relief.
Now let’s change the narrative
to be about the team player
by focusing on him early in the shot,
and instead of going back and forth,
we keep him in focus.
I’ll be the voice of his thoughts.
“I love you, buddy,
but you always take forever."
"Yes, I’m ready,
but I have low expectations."
"What a waste of time. Bravo.”
So this was shot on iPhone 13, showcasing
the cinematography tools for storytelling
provided by Cinematic mode.
And to produce this rendered asset,
there’s the special Cinematic mode asset.
To support nondestructive
post-capture edits,
a Cinematic mode asset actually has
multiple tracks.
First is the video track,
which is the original QuickTime movie
as captured.
It can be HDR/SDR,
1080p at 30 frames per second,
and on iPhone 14, even 4K
at 24, 25, and 30 frames per second.
This track can be played
as a regular video,
but it lacks the aesthetics
and storytelling
compared to the rendered asset.
There’s no suspense and no comic relief,
and we're just watching
some people play a game in the back alley.
The second track contains disparity,
which is the pixel shift seen from two
cameras looking at the same scene.
Close objects are more shifted
than objects further away.
You can test this yourself
closing one eye and then the other,
and see how objects shift
at different distances.
Disparity is used for focus
and rendering the shallow depth of field.
The disparity map is at a lower resolution
than the video track.
The track, shown as a colorization,
contains relative
and not absolute disparity,
which means it can only be used relative
to other samples in the same map,
such as rendering relative
to a focus disparity
or transitioning
between two focus disparities.
For insights about relative disparity
and great depth puns,
I highly recommend WWDC17,
"Capturing Depth in iPhone Photography."
The third track contains important
metadata for rendering and editing.
The track consists of two things.
First, the rendering attributes,
which hold focus disparity
and aperture as an f-number.
These drive the rendering.
The focus, shown as an overlay,
is decided by the Cinematic engine,
while the aperture is chosen by the user.
And then there’s the Cinematic script,
which holds all the automatic
scene detections.
This scene shows face, head and torso,
which are grouped by an ID linking them
together over time when possible.
The script also holds the focus decisions,
deciding which detection to keep in focus.
The focus decisions can be changed
post-capture to follow other detections
and thereby changing
the narrative and rendering.
This is the dataflow
from the Cinematic mode asset
to the rendered asset.
As just covered, the Cinematic mode asset
holds all the information needed
for rendering and post-capture focus
and aperture changes.
Following is the optional editing,
where changes are nondestructive
and can always be reverted
back to the original.
If no editing is done,
the Cinematic engine controls
the focus disparity automatically,
and the aperture set by the user
at capture time remains unchanged.
With a focus disparity and aperture,
the rendering applies
the shallow depth of field
with accurate focus falloff
using the disparity map.
And finally, we get the rendered asset
with the effect applied,
which is a regular,
shareable QuickTime movie.
With a better understanding
of Cinematic mode,
it’s time to start building
the playback app.
But first we need to get hold
of a Cinematic mode asset,
so let’s look at the code to get it.
It’s quite easy to pick a Cinematic mode
asset from Photos library.
Just use a Photos picker
and filter for Cinematic videos.
The picker will get a local identifier
for the selected file.
As a non-code related side note,
if you don’t already have
a Cinematic mode asset,
it can be AirDropped
between different user devices
with the All Photos Data option
to include both the rendered asset
and the Cinematic mode asset.
Let’s get back to coding.
Using the asset identifier from the pick,
I can now fetch a photos asset
with information about the Cinematic mode
asset before I request it.
I need to make sure to set request options
to get the original version
and allow for network access
in case the asset is on iCloud,
and then finally request
the Cinematic mode asset as an AVAsset.
And now to the exciting part.
We have gotten the Cinematic mode asset.
Let’s integrate playback.
A rendered asset can be played back
using AVPlayer and AVPlayerItem
as a regular movie,
and so can the movie track
inside the Cinematic mode asset.
But to realize the potential
of Cinematic mode assets,
we need to add a custom video compositor,
which can handle multiple tracks,
user changes,
and finally, call the Cinematic renderer
to compose the output.
This custom compositor can also be used
for thumbnails and offline export,
but let’s focus on using it for playback
and editing of Cinematic mode assets.
I will only go into details specific
to the Cinematic API,
so for additional insights on custom
video compositor classes and HDR,
I recommend WWDC20, "Edit and Play Back
HDR Video with AVFoundation."
Let’s start using the Cinematic API.
The Cinematic API uses the prefix CN,
so you might be able to spot
the three API calls needed
to set up the rendering session which
will render the shallow depth of field.
The first call gets the rendering
attributes from the Cinematic asset.
The second sets up a rendering session
with these attributes.
The rendering session uses the GPU,
so I need to provide
a metal command queue.
And the last call sets
the rendering quality to export.
Quality can be set to different enums
like preview and export
depending on your performance
and quality constraints.
In these and following code snippets,
I have removed good practice error checks,
like guard let else error,
just to focus on the core code.
The custom compositor needs a composition,
which includes the Cinematic asset info
needed to render the output.
In a typical case, you would need
multiple steps to add the multiple tracks,
but fortunately, we provide an easy way
to do this in just one step.
You can add all the tracks,
from the asset info to the composition,
directly.
The Cinematic composition info
is just like the Cinematic asset info,
but points to composition tracks.
Then I get the Cinematic script
from the Cinematic asset.
The Cinematic script holds
all the detections and focus decisions.
And I will go into more detail
about this later.
For the custom compositor, I set up
instruction with rendering session,
composition with asset tracks,
Cinematic script,
and aperture as an f-number.
This custom instruction describes how
to compose the rendered Cinematic content.
To play the video,
I’ll need a video composition,
to which I’ll add track IDs
from the Cinematic composition,
add a sample custom compositor,
which is where the renderer is called
to compose the effect,
and add the composition instruction.
Let’s take a closer look at what goes on
in the custom compositor.
There are a few key things specific
to the Cinematic API
inside the startRequest function
in the custom compositor.
Using the track IDs
from the Cinematic composition,
I get the source buffers
for the current frame
from the original video track,
the disparity track, the metadata track,
and finally I create a buffer
for the rendered output.
These buffers allow us
to make edits and new renders.
From the metadata buffer,
I can get the rendering frame attributes,
which drive the rendering.
The metadata is an opaque structure,
so I’ll use CNRenderingSession
and get the frame attributes directly.
With the frame attributes,
I can now make optional playback changes,
in this case by changing the aperture
f-number according to the instruction,
which holds aperture changes
from a UI element.
Focus disparity can be changed
in a similar fashion,
but I’ll get back to making scene-driven
changes using detections later.
At this point, we're really,
really close to achieve playback.
I just need to get a command buffer
on the rendering command queue,
such that the composed output can be
rendered on the GPU.
Encode the rendering
using the updated frame attributes
and the image and disparity buffers.
Add a completion handler
for the output buffer,
which will be passed
to the video composition.
And finally commit the command buffer.
Now let’s try out playback
in the sample app.
I can now select a Cinematic mode asset
from Photos library.
And when I play back the asset,
the effect is applied in real time.
I can scrub back and forth
and make changes to aperture,
which changes the amount of bokeh.
Stopping down minimizes the effect.
Opening up increases it.
Maybe this is too much.
I think this looks good.
The app is already pretty cool,
but it will get even cooler
in the upcoming edit section.
And to remind you, as a reference,
code for each part is available
in the sample app.
I will now move on to extend the playback
app and custom video compositor
to do more advanced
and nondestructive edits
by changing the Cinematic script
and thereby the focus.
But let’s revisit the Photos app
editing environment for Cinematic mode
and look specifically at the focus,
which is automatically driven
during capture
by detecting objects
and deciding where and on what to focus.
These detections and decisions
are all in the Cinematic script,
and the script can be changed
to your narrative.
The focus detection is shown
as a yellow square,
and below the timeline, we have keyframes
and focus decision changes.
To better understand how this works,
let’s break down the Cinematic script
structure with a simple example.
Let’s start with just two Cinematic script
frames in a short sequence.
Each hold all detections
for a given point in time,
and in this case just two detections.
The detections are tracked over time
with a group ID,
which groups face, head,
and torso together.
In addition, cats, dogs,
and balls are detected and tracked,
but here we just have the face
of Actor 1 and Actor 2.
An automatic base decision puts focus
on Actor 1 in the first frame,
and focus will follow this track
until a new decision.
Even after Actor 3 enters the scene
and introduces a new face
and detection track,
the focus remains on Actor 1.
In frame 5, an automatic keyframe event
changes the decision and focus to Actor 2.
And after just four frames,
Actor 3 does a disheartened exit
without ever getting
the focused attention she deserves.
Focus remains on Actor 2
for the rest of the sequence.
These automatic base decisions are decided
on a range of parameters
like who faces the camera, who looks away,
who’s closer, and what’s interesting.
And while we do our best
to create a good narrative,
you might have another one.
Luckily, decisions can be changed,
and actually in two ways.
The first one is to add
a weak user decision.
This brings Actor 3 into focus
as she enters the scene.
However, a weak decision
only follows a track
until the next base or user decision,
which happens in frame 5,
where a base decision changes focus
to Actor 2 for the remaining frames.
So if we wanted focus to stay on Actor 3,
we could add another weak decision
in frame 5,
or we could use something stronger.
Yes, you might have guessed it,
a strong user decision.
A strong decision will keep focus
on a subject
until the next user decision
to focus elsewhere
or the end of the detection track.
Adding a strong decision
brings Actor 3 into focus
and overrides the following base decision.
After the detection track of Actor 3 ends,
the focus falls back to the base decision,
which is to focus on Actor 2.
The decision hierarchy works as follows:
user decisions on top of base decisions,
user decisions apply when possible,
base decisions fill the gaps.
So as done in this example, a user
can change just parts of the script.
And while both decisions revert to a base
decision when a detection track ends,
a strong decision holds it’s focus track
as long as possible.
Before moving to change the script,
let’s get a script frame
and draw the detection boxes.
First I need to grab the frame time
from the video composition request,
and then get the Cinematic script frame
for that current point in time.
This script frame holds all detections,
including the focus detection.
Now it’s easy to draw the detection boxes.
By iterating all the detections
in a script,
I can get each detection rectangle
and draw it to a texture
attached to a renderEncoder
using a draw command.
In this example,
the detections are drawn in white.
And to emphasize
what’s currently the focusDetection,
let’s draw that in another color.
I get the focus detection directly
from the Cinematic script frame,
get its corresponding rectangle,
and to make it stand out,
I draw the focus rectangle in yellow.
Let’s try the playback app
with the added detection overlay.
I can now enable the new detection overlay
to draw the detections.
This scene shows face, head,
and torso in white
and the focus detection in yellow.
You can customize the overlay to only show
a specific subset of detections
if that makes sense for your app.
When I start playback,
notice how the focus and rendering follows
the yellow focus detections
through the movie
while alternative detections
just show in white.
Let me show you how to use
these alternative detections
to change the focus.
Once we know
how to draw the detection boxes,
actually changing the script
with a UI tapping point is very similar.
Again I’ll iterate over all detections,
and if the tapping point is inside
a detection,
I’ll get it’s corresponding detectionID
and create a new decision.
The decision strength can be set
in the UI.
In the sample app, weak is set with
a single tap and strong with a double tap,
but the UI is really up to you.
Then finally I add this new user decision
to the Cinematic script,
and the script has changed.
So let me talk about
how the updated script drives the focus.
Let’s consider this a normal clip length
and look at three decisions
and their corresponding
focus detection tracks.
Let’s arrange the focus tracks according
to time and distance in a 2D plot.
Because the Cinematic engine knows
the whole updated script,
it can make smooth focus transitions
ahead of time.
It looks something like this,
where a focus rack starts ahead of time
to reach focus
at the beginning of each keyframe.
It’s pretty magical,
and it works like a focus puller,
who can direct attention and rack focus
ahead of time by knowing the set markers.
The racked focus disparity can be accessed
directly from a frame
in the updated Cinematic script.
I have already shown
how to extract a script frame,
and changing the frame attributes
for focus is similar
to changing the aperture.
Once I have a script frame
from the updated script,
I can update the frame attributes
for focus disparity directly.
This will pass focus
with smooth transitions
according to the updated script
to the renderer.
Let’s try out tapping to change the script
and focus in the sample app.
Going from playback mode to edit,
I can now update the Cinematic script.
I can change focus decisions
by either single-tapping
to get a weak decision,
shown as a yellow dashed box,
or by double-tapping to get
a strong decision and a solid yellow box.
You can see how the focus and rendering
changes according to my user input
when I tab on different players.
I think this is super cool.
Scrub, scrub.
Tap, tap, tap.
Change the aperture.
Scrub, tap, tap, double-tap.
And now that I have completed editing,
how can I save these edit changes?
The script changes can be saved
in a separate data file,
and saving the changes separately means
the original remains unchanged.
And changes can always be reverted
back to the original.
So I get the script changes,
get the changes
as a compact binary representation,
and write the changes to a data file.
The Cinematic API handles
the data representation.
And you will need to store this data
in your app
so it can be reloaded to your needs.
Loading script changes is done
in three equally easy steps.
I get the binary data from the data file,
unpack the script changes,
and reload the changes
into the Cinematic script.
Changes can also be loaded simultaneously
with the original script.
So that’s how we can edit and render
and save and load
the Cinematic script changes.
As mentioned earlier,
the custom video compositor can be used
to export rendered videos.
And these can be rendered
right back into Photos library.
This is covered in detail
in the sample code.
The API also includes a tracker,
CNObjectTracker,
which can be used
for objects without automatic detections.
The sample code covers
how the tracker can be engaged
by tapping
on an object without a detection.
And the tracker will provide
a detection track
and can be added to the script.
And now to some more advanced
possibilities.
You can also add custom tracking
by providing your own tracker
and add your own custom detection track
to the script.
And you can make custom changes
to the rendering attributes per frame,
allowing for custom transitions
and aperture changes.
I’m personally super excited
about what you can all do
with Cinematic mode and the new API.
And whether it’s a simple app
or a complex editor,
I’m sure you can come up
with ideas we haven’t even thought of.
This was an introduction
to the new Cinematic API,
which allows you to integrate
Cinematic mode video assets
for playback with playback adjustments,
change the Cinematic script and focus
to make nondestructive edits
and new renders,
and save and load these script changes.
Please check out this and more
in the included sample app.
Thank you for your focus,
and happy coding.
♪ ♪