♪ ♪
Alex: Hi, I’m Alex Abramets.
Welcome to "Integrate
your media app with HomePod."
I am here to present an exciting,
new Siri capability for the Home.
Starting with iOS 17,
any HomePod owner will be able to ask Siri
to play media using apps installed
on their iPhone or iPad.
This new Siri ability will allow apps
currently supporting SiriKit Media Intents
to seamlessly play content on HomePod.
First, I am going to introduce expanded
support for media apps to play on HomePod.
Then, I will cover supported use cases
and experiences
and show the best ways to implement them.
Lastly, I will talk about how
this capability integrates with the Home.
Let's get started by going over
HomePod support for more Media apps.
Once HomePod processes a request,
a SiriKit intent is sent to the iPhone,
where Siri starts your app and
AirPlays content back to the speaker.
We will talk more about AirPlay support
later in this session.
To fulfill the request,
HomePod will be communicating
with iPhone over Wi-Fi,
which means that devices
need to be on the same network
at the time of the request.
Devices don’t need to be
in physical proximity.
If I am in a living room
talking to my speaker
and my phone is charging in the bedroom,
HomePod will successfully play.
Siri requests to play media
work with multiple destinations,
including most
speakers supporting AirPlay.
Any app supporting
SiriKit Media Intents today
will be able to use this capability
with no additional changes.
Later, I will talk about a few things
that can make the user experience
and performance even better.
Requests to Play, Add,
and Affinity requests for the apps
not natively supported on HomePod,
will be routed to the primary iPhone.
Please note that on HomePod,
requests to find or search for media
will result in playback.
Siri will rely on voice recognition
to route requests to the device
of the recognized Home user.
In addition, requests
to "like" or "add" songs will work
even for content that was AirPlayed
without using Siri.
Now many existing media apps
will be available on HomePod,
and it’s not just music.
Many types of media are supported.
Music, audiobooks, podcasts,
radio, meditation, and more.
Any app adding new support
for SiriKit Media intents
will be automatically supported
on HomePod.
Everything your app can do on iOS today
will work on HomePod.
For example,
app users can ask to play artists,
albums, songs, music genres, and hits.
When the app name is used in the request,
Siri will check if the app is installed
on your iPhone.
If the app is installed,
Siri will establish AirPlay connection
and ask the app to start playback.
Maybe your app is about
listening to Podcasts or Audiobooks.
Now it will be possible
to catch up on the news
or continue listening to your current
audiobook on your HomePod.
Siri will understand requests
to change speed, fast-forward,
and control playback.
Requests specific to your app
and not covered by Media intents
can be implemented using App Intents.
Check out "Explore enhancements
to App Intents"
and other related sessions.
So how do I add Siri to my app?
Let’s go over what is needed
to support SiriKit Media Intents,
then talk about making sure
everything works reliably
and provides a great experience.
Apps with existing support
for Media Intents will just work.
For example, if SoundCloud
is installed on your iPhone
and you ask HomePod
to play something on SoundCloud,
media will play on the speaker.
Adding playback support via Siri
to your app
includes several simple steps.
You’ll need to add an intents extension
and implement a few methods
to wire up Siri callbacks
with search and playback.
You can find detailed instructions
in "Introducing SiriKit Media Intents"
video from 2019
and "Expand your SiriKit Media Intents
to more platforms" from 2020.
Let’s inspect the code from a sample app
that can play a song.
Here, I am checking that the request
was for an entity named "Push it"
and, if so, return the media item.
Let’s give it a try.
Hey Siri, play "Push It"
by Dukes on Control Audio.
Siri: "Push It" now playing
from your iPhone.
[Duke's "Push It" playing from iPhone]
Alex: The song plays as expected!
Now let’s ask something else.
Hey Siri, play jazz on Control Audio.
Siri: I couldn't find that
in your Control Audio library.
Alex: This time,
Siri said it didn’t find anything.
This happened because the function
returned an "unsupported" response
since my app doesn’t support
playing genres.
But I can make Siri respond better!
I can provide a more specific reason
for not being able to play,
like "unsupported media type"
or that the app requires a valid login.
For such cases, Siri will give responses
that will aid in resolving the issue.
Now, I am going to change my code
and add a guard statement
that will return
a more specific error code
if the request
was to play any music genre.
Hey Siri, play jazz on Control Audio.
Siri: Control Audio
doesn't support playing that.
Alex: So now, Siri says that the app
doesn’t support playing that,
which is a more helpful response.
You might be wondering
what will your app receive
when a Siri request is made?
In the previous examples,
we discussed the "mediaName"
and "mediaType" fields.
Let’s review some of the most
common intents that your app might get.
A simple "Play" with just the app name
will send an intent
without any search criteria.
Music apps could play
a personal mix or a station.
Podcasts and audiobook apps
may resume the last played item.
For "Play music in app" requests,
"music" translates into a "mediaType."
"Play" request with entity name
will provide a mediaName field only.
It will be up to the app to determine
the type of the entity,
whether that’s a song, artist,
podcast or something else.
Mentioning "song" and its name
will produce a mediaType
equal to Song and a mediaName field.
This is how asking for "popular hits"
will behave.
The media name will be set to "music"
and the sortOrder will be "popular."
Asking to play something next will tell
the app to add it to the queue.
Notice that "playbackqueuelocation"
has a value of "next."
If your app supports news,
podcasts or audiobooks,
you may receive requests
like "play my audiobook,"
"play the latest news,"
or "play tech news podcast."
You should explore and experiment
with the intents produced by Siri
for the requests you expect to be sent
to your app.
After resolving the results,
Siri will execute the "handle" step
in your intents extension.
You can return one of the two responses
"handleInApp" and "continueInApp."
"HandleInApp" will instruct the system to
start the app and play in the background.
"ContinueInApp" will ask the system
to start the app in the foreground.
For requests to play Audio,
background playback
will result in a better experience
since it doesn’t require you
to unlock the phone.
When a request is made to HomePod,
it is even more pronounced,
since your phone could be nowhere near.
Please keep in mind
that your app’s responses
to Siri callbacks
should be reasonably fast.
Slow requests are often abandoned
or simply time out.
Make sure that your app responds
in at most ten seconds.
It is preferable to be fast as possible,
but after ten seconds,
Siri's response will be generic
and not very helpful.
What if you’d like to tell Siri
that you like the song
or a podcast,
or wanted to add it to your playlist?
Supporting INAddMediaIntent
and INUpdateMediaAffinityIntent
will allow your app
to work with these requests.
The implementation is very similar
to INPlayMediaIntent.
For AirPlayed content,
Siri will send the request to the iPhone
of the speaking person.
Let’s go over a few things
that can make the integration
of your app with Siri more robust.
First up is personal app vocabulary.
Using personal app vocabulary,
your app can inform the system
of user-specific entities
that requests might include.
These can include personal playlists,
purchased audiobooks, podcasts,
favorite artists, or authors.
Normally, only foreground apps can
start playback, but during Siri request,
your app can start audio
in the background.
For this to work,
it is very important to have the audio
session properly configured
prior to activating that session.
This applies to all supported platforms,
including HomePod, iOS and CarPlay.
In this example,
by setting the audio category to playback,
the app will inform the system
that it will be playing audio.
Audio category, mode,
and route sharing policy
will affect how the system handles
audio playback and interruptions.
Setting the mode to "spoken audio"
will pause the playback
when interrupted instead of temporarily
reducing the volume of your content.
This is especially useful for apps
that play podcasts or audiobooks,
so that listeners don’t miss
any important parts of the content.
Let’s check out what happens
if the audio category
is not set to ".playback"
prior to activating the session.
Hey, Siri, play "Push It"
by Dukes on Control Audio.
Siri: "Push It" now playing
from your iPhone.
[Dukes' "Push It" playing from iPhone]
Alex: While the app is in the foreground,
the audio plays,
but once the app goes into the background,
for example when I lock the phone,
playback stops.
It works, but not
the way you would expect it to.
Let’s find out what happens
if I change my code
to correctly configure the audio session.
Hey, Siri, play "Push It" by Dukes
on Control Audio.
Siri: Here's "Push It" from your iPhone.
[Dukes' "Push It" playing from iPhone]
Alex: When I lock the phone,
the audio continues playing.
♪ ♪
[music stops playing]
HomePod and iPhone can do many things,
so it is not uncommon
for the audio playback from your app
to be interrupted by an incoming call,
navigation prompt, Siri requests,
or other apps playing something else.
It is important to handle interruptions
so that your app can continue playing,
especially when someone across the room
is talking to HomePod
and doesn’t have their iPhone handy.
Ok, let’s talk about AirPlay.
For the system to successfully
AirPlay content from your app,
make sure that you do the following:
set the audio category, mode,
and route sharing policy appropriately
as I talked about earlier,
use MPNowPlayingInfoCenter
to inform the system
about the currently playing item,
and MPRemoteCommandCenter
to receive remote commands,
like play, pause, and skip.
These steps will get the media
from your app playing on AirPlay speakers.
But since the audio data
is being delivered to another device,
the system needs a buffer
and will accumulate some data
to ensure smooth playback.
This may introduce a delay
each time media is resumed or stopped.
Using one of the APIs for buffered
playback will remove this concern.
Check out this year's session called
"Tune up your AirPlay experience"
for more on this topic.
Next, I will talk about additional
considerations for this capability.
What if I have multiple iPhones or iPads?
How will Siri know which one to use?
The answer is that Siri will route
SiriKit Media requests
to the primary iPhone,
which is the one that is set up
to share your location under Apple ID
and Find My settings.
Since Siri will communicate
with other devices
to fulfill these requests,
the requesting user
will need to be registered in the Home
and have Recognize My Voice enabled.
You can find this setting in the Home app.
Enabling Personal Requests
is not required for this feature to work.
Keep in mind that if you don’t
have "Recognize My Voice" enabled
or you are not registered in the Home,
you will not be able to play media
from your or anyone else’s devices.
If you just installed the app
or never asked Siri to play from it,
the first request to Play using the app
will direct you to your iOS device
and request permission
for Siri to access the app data.
This permission is only needed for the
first Siri request to Play from your app.
Before I let you go,
here are the things you should remember.
Adding SiriKit Media intents support
is the one thing that is required
for your app to work on HomePod.
You can further improve the user
experience by adding Buffered Playback,
supporting more complex queries,
and providing Siri with more context.
Thank you!
I cannot wait to see your apps
working with HomePod!
♪ ♪