♪ ♪
Ben: Hi, I'm Ben Levine,
an engineer on the Core ML team.
Today, I'm going to talk about what's new
when it comes to integrating Core ML
into your app.
Building intelligent experiences
in your app has never been easier.
The Xcode SDK provides a solid foundation
for leveraging and deploying
machine learning-powered features.
A set of domain specific frameworks
give you access
to built-in intelligence
through simple APIs.
The capabilities they provide are powered
by models trained and optimized by Apple.
These models are executed via Core ML.
The Core ML framework provides the engine
for running machine learning models
on-device.
It allows you to easily deploy models
customized for your app.
It abstracts away the hardware details
while leveraging
the high-performance compute capabilities
of Apple silicon
with help from the Accelerate
and Metal family of frameworks.
Core ML's mission is to help you integrate
machine learning models into your app.
This year, our focus for Core ML
was performance and flexibility.
We made improvements in our workflow,
API surface,
and also our underlying inference engine.
Before jumping into the workflow
and highlighting new opportunities
for you to optimize
your Core ML integration,
here's an idea
of the potential performance benefits
that you can get automatically
by just updating to the latest OS.
When comparing the relative
prediction time between iOS 16 and 17,
you'll observe that iOS 17 is
simply faster for many of your models.
This speedup in the inference engine
comes with the OS
and doesn't require
re-compilation of your models
or making any changes to your code.
The same is true
for other platforms as well.
Naturally, the amount of speedup
is model and hardware dependent.
Moving to the agenda, I'll start
with an overview of the workflow
when integrating Core ML into your app.
Along the way,
I'll highlight optimization opportunities
for different parts of the workflow.
Then I'll focus on model integration
and discuss new APIs and behavior
for compute availability, model lifecycle,
and asynchronous prediction
I'll start with an overview
of the Core ML workflow.
There are two phases
for integrating Core ML into your app.
First is developing your model,
and second is using that model
within your app.
For model development,
you have several options.
One of the most convenient ways to develop
your own model is to use Create ML.
Create ML provides various templates
for common machine learning tasks
and can leverage the highly optimized
models built into the OS.
It guides you through
the model development workflow
and lets you interactively evaluate
the results.
If you want to learn more,
check out this year's Create ML video.
Another way to develop a model
is to train one
using one of several
python machine learning frameworks.
Then, use the CoreMLTools python package
to convert to the Core ML model format.
Last, it's important
you evaluate your model
both in terms of accuracy
and performance on Apple hardware.
Using feedback from evaluation
often results in revisiting
some of these steps
to further optimize your model.
There are many opportunities
for optimization in these steps.
For training, how you collect and choose
your training data is important.
It should be consistent
with the data being passed to the model
when it's deployed
and in your users' hands.
The model architecture you choose
is also important.
You may be exploring multiple options,
each with their own tradeoffs
between training data requirements,
accuracy, size, and performance.
Many of these tradeoffs may not be
fully visible at training time
and require a few iterations
through the full development flow.
Next is model conversion.
Core ML tools offers various options
to help optimize
the converted model's precision,
footprint, and computation cost.
You can select input and output formats
that best match
your app's data flow
to avoid unnecessary copies.
If your input shape can vary,
you can specify that variation,
rather than choosing just one shape
or switching amongst
multiple shape-specific models.
Compute precision can also be
explicitly set for the whole model
or individual operations.
Both float32 and float16 are available.
In addition to the precision
of computation,
you also have some control over
how your model parameters are represented.
CoreMLTools comes with a set of utilities
for post-training weight quantization
and compression.
These utilities can help you significantly
reduce the footprint of your model
and improve performance on-device.
However, to achieve these benefits,
there is some tradeoff in accuracy.
There are some new tools
to help you in this space
There's a new optimize submodule
in the CoreMLTools package.
It unifies and updates
the post-training compression utilities
and adds new quantization-aware
training extensions for PyTorch.
This gives you access
to data-driven optimizations
to help preserve accuracy
for quantized models during training.
This is coupled with new operations
which support activation quantization
in Core ML's ML Program model type.
Check out this year's session
on compressing machine learning models
with Core ML to learn more.
Next is evaluation.
One option to evaluate your model
is to run predictions
on the converted model directly from
your python code with CoreMLTools.
It will use the same Core ML inference
stack that your app code will use
and lets you quickly check
how your choices during model conversion
affect the model's accuracy
and performance.
Xcode also provides some helpful tools
when it comes to evaluation
and exploration of your models.
Model previews are available
for many common model types.
This lets you provide
some sample inputs to the model
and preview the predicted output
without having to write any code.
Core ML performance reports
provide you a breakdown
of model computation performance
for load, prediction,
and compilation times
on any attached device.
Note that this can be useful
to evaluate model architectures
even before you've trained them.
Now, stepping back
to the overall workflow,
the next topic is model integration.
Model integration is a part
of developing your app.
Just like any other resource
you use in your app,
you want to carefully manage and optimize
how you use your Core ML model.
There are three steps
in model integration.
You first write
the application code to use the model.
You have code
for where and when to load the model,
how to prepare the model's input data,
make predictions, and use the results.
Then you compile this code
along with the model.
And third, you test, run, and profile
the model running within your app.
When it comes to profiling,
you may find the Core ML
and Neural Engine instruments helpful.
This is also an iterative process
of design and optimization
until you're ready to ship.
There are several new additions this year
for optimizing your model integration.
First is compute availability.
Core ML is supported
on all Apple platforms
and by default considers
all available compute
to optimize its execution.
This includes the CPU, GPU,
and Neural Engine when available.
However, the performance characteristics
and availability of these compute devices
varies across supported hardware
your app may run on.
This may impact your users' experience
with your ML powered features
or influence your choice
in models and configurations.
For example,
some experiences may require models
running on the Neural Engine
to meet performance or power requirements.
There's now a new API for runtime
inspection of compute device availability.
The MLComputeDevice enum captures
the type of compute device
and the specific compute device's
properties within its associated value.
With the availableComputeDevices
property on MLModel,
you can inspect what devices
are available to Core ML.
For example, this code checks
if there is a Neural Engine available.
More specifically,
it checks if the collection
of all available compute devices
contains one whose type is Neural Engine.
The next topic for model integration
is understanding the model lifecycle.
I'll start by reviewing
the different model asset types.
There are two kinds:
source models and compiled models.
The source model has a file extension
of MLModel or MLPackage.
It's an open format
designed for construction and editing.
The compiled model has
a file extension of MLModelC.
It's designed for runtime access.
In most cases,
you add a source model to your app target,
then Xcode compiles the model
and puts it in the app's resources.
At runtime, in order to use your model,
you instantiate an MLModel.
Instantiation takes a URL
to its compiled form
and an optional configuration.
The resulting MLModel has loaded
all the necessary resources
for optimal inference
based on the specified configuration
and device-specific hardware capabilities.
Here's a deeper look
into what happens during this load.
First, Core ML checks a cache
to see if it has already specialized
the model
based on the configuration and device.
If it has, it loads the required resources
from the cache and returns.
This is called a cached load.
If the configuration was not found
in the cache,
it then triggers
a device-specialized compilation for it.
Once this process completes,
it adds the output to the cache
and finishes the load from there.
This is called an uncached load.
For certain models, the uncached load
can take a significant amount of time.
However, it's focused on optimizing
the model for the device
and making subsequent loads
as fast as possible.
During device specialization,
Core ML first parses the model
and applies general optimization passes
to it.
It then segments the chain of operations
for specific compute devices
based on the estimated performance
and hardware availability.
This segmentation is then cached.
The last step is for each of the segments
to go through
a compute device specific compilation
for the compute device they were assigned.
This compilation includes
further optimizations
for the specific compute device
and outputs an artifact
that the compute device can run.
Once complete,
Core ML caches these artifacts
to be used for subsequent model loads.
Core ML caches
the specialized assets on the disk.
They're tied to the model's path
and configuration.
These assets are meant to persist across
app launches and reboots of your device.
When the device's free disk space
is running short,
there has been a system update,
or the compiled model has been
deleted or modified,
the operating system deletes the cache.
If this happens, the next model load will
perform the device specialization again.
In order to find out whether or not
your model load is hitting the cache,
you can trace your app
with the Core ML Instrument
and look at the load event.
If it has the label "prepare and cache,"
then it was an uncached load,
so Core ML performed
the device specialization
and cached the result.
If the load event has the label "cached,"
then it was a cached load
and did not incur a device specialization.
This is new
specifically for MLProgram models.
Core ML performance reports
can also give you visibility
into the cost of a load.
By default,
it shows the median cached load.
It now has the option to display
uncached load times as well.
Since loading a model can be expensive
in terms of latency and memory,
here are some general best practices.
First, don't load models
during your app's launch on the UI thread.
Instead, consider using
the async loading API
or lazily load the model.
Next, keep the model loaded
if the application will likely be running
many predictions in a row,
rather than reloading the model
for each prediction in the sequence.
Lastly, you can unload the model
if your app won't use it for a while.
This can help alleviate memory pressure,
and thanks to the caching,
subsequent loads should be faster.
Once your model is loaded,
it's time to think about
running predictions with the model.
I'll jump into a demo
to show the new async options.
To show the new async prediction API,
I'll be using an app which displays
a gallery of images and allows
for applying filters to the images.
I'll focus on a colorizing filter
that uses a Core ML model
which takes a grayscale image as input
and outputs a colorized version
of the image.
Here's an example of the app in action.
It starts by loading the original images,
which are in grayscale,
and then once I select
the Colorized image mode,
it colorizes the images using Core ML.
As I scroll down,
the model is definitely working,
but it's a bit slower than I expected.
Also, if I scroll far down,
I notice that it takes quite a while
for the images to be colorized.
As I scroll back up,
it looks like it was spending time
colorizing all of the images
along the way.
But in my SwiftUI code,
I'm using a LazyVGrid to hold the images,
so it should be cancelling tasks
when views go off screen.
Let me take a look
at my current implementation
to try to understand
why the performance is lacking
and also why it doesn't respect
tasks being cancelled.
This is the implementation.
Since the synchronous prediction API
is not thread safe,
the app has to ensure that predictions
are run serially on the model.
This is achieved by making
ColorizingService an actor,
which will only allow one call
to the colorize method at a time.
This actor owns the colorizerModel,
which is the auto-generated interface
that is produced for the model
bundled with the app.
The colorize method
currently performs two operations.
It first prepares the input for the model,
which involves resizing the image
to match the model's input size.
It then runs the input through the model
and gets the colorized output.
I went ahead and captured
an Instruments trace of the app
running with the Core ML
Instruments template.
When looking at the Instruments trace,
it shows that the predictions
are run serially,
which is ensured by the actor isolation.
However, there are gaps
around each prediction
before the next one is run,
which is contributing
to the lack of performance.
These are a result of the actor isolation
being wrapped around
not only the model prediction
but also the input preparation.
One improvement would be to mark the input
preparation as a non-isolated method,
so it won't block the next
colorize request from entering the actor.
While this would help,
the Core ML predictions themselves
would still be serialized,
which is the bottleneck of my processing.
To take advantage of concurrency
for the Core ML predictions themselves,
an option I can consider
is the batch prediction API.
It takes in a batch of inputs
and runs them through the model.
Under the hood, Core ML will take
advantage of concurrency when possible.
Making a batch version
of the colorize method
is pretty straightforward.
However, the challenging part
is figuring out how I'll collect
the inputs into a batch
and pass them to this method.
There are actually multiple aspects
of this use case
that make it difficult
to use the batch prediction API.
The batch API is best used when there's
a known quantity of work to be done.
In this case, the amount of images
to be processed is not fixed
but a function of screen size
and the amount of scrolling done.
I can pick a batch size myself,
but I'll have to handle cases
where the batch size isn't met
but still needs to be processed.
Also, I'll have a different UI experience
where images are colorized in batches.
Lastly, I won't be able to cancel a batch
even if the user scrolls away from it.
Because of these challenges,
I'd rather stick with an API
that handles one prediction at a time.
This is where the new async prediction API
can be very useful.
It's thread safe and works well for using
Core ML alongside Swift concurrency.
To switch to an async design for the code,
I first changed the colorize method
to be async.
I then added the await keyword
in front of the prediction call,
which is required to use
the new async version of the API.
Then I changed ColorizingService
to be a class rather than an actor.
That way, multiple images can be
colorized concurrently.
Lastly, I added a cancellation check
to the start of the method.
The async prediction API will do its best
to respond to cancellation,
especially when multiple predictions
are requested concurrently,
but it's best to include an extra check
at the start in this case.
That way, it also avoids
preparing the inputs
if the task was cancelled before
the colorize method was even entered.
Now I'll make these changes
and re-run the app.
Just as before,
I'll set it to Colorized mode.
I can already see the images are
being colorized much faster.
And if I do a quick scroll to the bottom,
the images load almost immediately.
Scrolling up a bit,
I can verify the images are being
colorized as I scroll back up,
which means that the colorize calls
were successfully cancelled the first time
when I did the quick swipe to the bottom.
When looking at a trace
using this new async design,
it shows the predictions are being run
on multiple images concurrently.
This is denoted by multiple
prediction intervals stacked vertically.
Since this model runs
partially on the Neural Engine,
it can also be observed
in the Neural Engine Instrument as well.
With the initial implementation,
which colorized the images serially,
colorizing the initial view of images
without scrolling took about two seconds.
After switching
to the async implementation,
which colorized the images concurrently,
that time was cut in half
to about one second.
So overall, I was able to achieve
about a 2x improvement
in total throughput by taking advantage
of the async prediction API
and concurrency with my Colorizer model.
However, it's important to note
that the amount a given model and use case
may benefit from a concurrent design
heavily depends on several factors,
which include the model's operations,
the compute units
and hardware combination,
and other work
that the compute devices may be busy with.
Also, the ML program
and Pipeline model types will provide
the best performance improvements
from running predictions concurrently.
Overall, when adding concurrency
to your app,
you should carefully profile the workload
to make sure it's actually benefiting
your use case.
Another important thing to keep in mind
when adding concurrency to your app
is memory usage.
Having many sets of model inputs
and outputs loaded in memory concurrently
can greatly increase the peak memory usage
of your application.
You can profile this by combining
the Core ML Instrument
with the Allocations Instrument.
The trace is showing that the memory usage
of my app is rising quickly
as I load many inputs into memory
to run through the colorizer model.
A potential issue is that the colorize
method from my code has no flow control,
so the amount of images being colorized
concurrently has no fixed limit.
This may not be an issue
if the model inputs and outputs are small.
However, if they're large,
then having many sets
of these inputs and outputs
in memory at the same time
can greatly increase
the peak memory usage of the app.
A way to improve this would be
to add logic which limits
the maximum amount
of in-flight predictions.
This will result in less inputs
and outputs loaded in memory concurrently,
which will decrease the peak memory usage
while running predictions.
In this example, if there are
already two items being worked on,
it defers new work items
until a previous one has completed.
The best strategy will depend
on your use case.
For example,
when streaming data from a camera,
you may simply want to drop work
instead of deferring it.
This way, you avoid accumulating frames
and doing work
that's no longer temporally relevant.
Stepping back a bit,
here's some general guidance
on when to use
the different prediction APIs.
If you're in a synchronous context
and the time between each input
being available is large
compared to the model latency,
then the sync prediction API works well.
If your inputs become available
in batches,
then the batch prediction API
is a natural fit.
If you're in an async context
and have a large amount of inputs
becoming available individually over time,
that's when the async API
can be most useful.
To wrap up,
as you move through the Core ML workflow,
there are many opportunities
for optimization
during both model development
and model integration.
New compute availability APIs
can help you make decisions at runtime
based on what hardware is available
on the device.
Understanding the model lifecycle
and caching behavior
can help you best decide when and where
to load and unload your model.
And lastly,
the async prediction API can help you
integrate Core ML
with other async Swift code
and also improve throughput
by supporting concurrent predictions.
This was Ben from the Core ML team,
and I am not an AI.