♪ ♪
Jerry: Hi, I'm Jerry,
an Engineering Manager
for Siri and App Shortcuts.
Today, I'm gonna share with you
how you can spotlight your app
with App Shortcuts.
I'll start by looking
at why you should adopt App Shortcuts
to help your app create quick,
habitual actions
that can be used
from all over the operating system.
Then I will go over the basics
of implementing an App Shortcut.
After that, I will go over how
to make your App Shortcuts great
for both visual and voice use,
as well as new ways
App Shortcuts have improved in iOS 17.
And finally,
I'll wrap by looking at new ways
App Shortcuts can be extended
across a number of Apple devices
beyond iPhone.
To start, App Shortcuts
make it easy to discover
and use your app's functionality.
They are automatically available
as soon as your app is installed
and require zero user setup.
Unlike in iOS 15 and before,
there's no need to use the Shortcuts app
or use the Add To Siri button
to set up an App Shortcut before using it.
App Shortcuts can be run from Siri
by speaking one of their trigger phrases.
They're also featured prominently
right in the search results
when searching in Spotlight,
and they're found in the Shortcuts app
where they can be part
of powerful user Shortcuts
and Automations.
App Shortcuts can help raise
the visibility of your app's features
to your users throughout the system
and be great launching points
for both functionality that opens your app
or simply do things in the background,
so the user can maintain their focus.
They are fast,
memorable ways to lower the friction
for using your app's core features,
and also make them usable
for more contexts,
including hands-free with just your voice
or in the home with HomePod.
With memorable App Shortcuts targeting
your app's most important features,
you can help people discover, remember,
and build a habit around using your app.
For example, throughout this session,
I will be working
with a hypothetical app called "Demo"
for managing my to-do lists.
I want to expose
a new bit of functionality,
summarizing my lists, to the system.
This will let me get a quick idea
of what's left to do
either via Shortcuts or by asking Siri.
This sort of quick and lightweight feature
is perfect for App Shortcuts.
They let people get what they need
from my app seamlessly
and be on their way.
I'll quickly walk through how
you would implement an App Intent
for summarizing a to-do list,
and then implement an App Shortcut,
so my users can summarize a list
with a verbal command
from Shortcuts
and be highlighted in Spotlight.
App Shortcuts are built
with the App Intents framework,
our Swift only framework built
from the ground up
to make it faster and easier
to build great intents
right in your Swift source code.
All App Shortcuts begin
by defining an intent in your source code.
Intents represent individual tasks
that can be completed with your app,
like creating a to-do list,
summarizing its contents,
or checking off an item.
After you create an app intent,
you can create an app shortcut with it,
so it can be used from Spotlight or Siri.
This associates your intent
with Siri trigger phrases,
titles, and symbols that are needed.
Once you have both definitions,
all you have to do is build
and test your app to see it work.
I'm going to start by creating
a very simple app shortcut.
This app shortcut
will let me create a new empty to-do list
right from Spotlight or Siri
by entering the name of the list.
Implementing this will be
a simple two-step process:
define the app intent
and define the app shortcut.
I start by importing
the App Intents framework.
And then I implement a new struct
for my intent,
conforming to the AppIntent protocol.
I include my intent's actual functionality
in the perform method
that will be called by the system.
And finally, I implement
an AppShortcutsProvider struct.
Each app can have at most one struct
conforming to this protocol.
In the AppShortcutsProvider,
I can specify all the app shortcuts
my app supports.
Here I've added
the Create List app shortcut.
Each app shortcut has a few components:
The intent that will be invoked
when triggered.
The phrases that Siri should recognize
to perform this app shortcut.
You can have multiple
of these per App Shortcut.
A short title and system image name,
so the system knows how
to represent this app shortcut visually.
That's all I need to implement
for a simple app shortcut.
By running my app I can
immediately start creating to-do lists
right from Siri or the Shortcuts app,
all by only creating two structs
in my code.
I want to try something
a bit more advanced though,
where I can get
a quick summary of my tasks
by providing a specific list
to be summarized.
This will touch
on two key concepts in App Intents:
Entities and queries.
Let's try it out.
First, I need to implement
a SummarizeList App Intent.
Like before, I need to create a struct
that conforms to the AppIntent protocol.
For the TodoList struct,
I've left a stub implementation.
I'll come back to that.
I have a convenient function already in
my app that returns the summary of a list,
so I will just use that.
I can return this summary
as a custom dialog as part
of the app intent's results.
This will let Siri speak
or show the result.
Every intent needs a title
that the system can display.
Intents can take inputs
by simply declaring variables
and annotating them
with the @Parameter property wrapper.
In this case,
I've referenced a ToDoList struct that,
as mentioned, is just a stub for now.
Now I'd like to tell you
about two concepts that are useful
for many app intents:
entities and queries.
Entities are concepts relating to your app
that your users will want to reference.
In my app, it makes sense
to have a to-do list entity,
since that's a logical object
that people will want to refer to
when performing tasks in my app.
In other apps, you might have entities
for users, documents, orders, and so on.
Entities from your app
can be put to use in app intents
when those intents use the entities
as input parameters.
In my app, my "SummarizeList" intent
takes a to-do list entity as a parameter.
In order to find entity instances
that fit into the parameters
of an app intent,
the system relies on queries.
At runtime, the system instantiates
and calls query objects
to find entities based
on various search parameters.
Queries return instances
of relevant entities to the system.
The system later uses these entities
when running an intent.
For my app I'll need
to implement the to-do list entity,
as well as a query to help the system
search for relevant to-do lists.
Back to the list summary app shortcut
I was working on.
I'll expand
my stub implementation of ToDoList
by conforming it to AppEntity.
I'll implement
the typeDisplayRepresentation property
so that the system knows
how to describe this entity type.
Likewise, I'll implement
a displayRepresentation,
so the system knows how
to describe this specific instance.
Note that if I want the entity shown at
the top level in Spotlight or Shortcuts,
my entities need to have an image
or symbol in the display representation.
And finally,
I declare a default query for this entity.
I've implemented a simple query
for my to-do list entity.
At a minimum, my query must be able to
retrieve a to-do list by its identifier.
I'll also want
to implement suggestedEntities.
This lets my app have control
over what to-do lists
I think are most relevant to my user.
The system
will use these suggested entities
to populate my app shortcut automatically.
With just the SummarizeList app intent
and its associated entity
and query structs,
I can now use this function
from inside the Shortcuts app
and as part of Automations.
I'm not done yet though.
I want to make sure this functionality
is accessible from Siri
and is fully featured in Spotlight.
To do this,
I need to implement an app shortcut.
I will start by extending
the AppShortcutsProvider
I started earlier.
I'll add a new App Shortcut
to the existing one.
I'll also include an array
of spoken phrases that will invoke
my App Shortcut from Siri.
Notice that rather
than using my application's name
directly in the string,
I've used a special token.
This allows Siri
to not only recognize my app's main name,
but any app name synonyms I've defined.
I've also added the intent's parameter,
"list," into some of the phrases.
App Shortcuts supports extending trigger
phrases with pre-defined parameters
so that users can provide a parameter
immediately upon invoking Siri.
In this case, the system will
call the suggestedEntities method
on my ToDoListQuery
to get the array of possible values.
Note that I've also provided a phrase
that does not have the "list" parameter.
This is a good idea in general
so that if my App Shortcut
is used without a list, Siri or Shortcuts
can prompt the user to select one.
App Shortcuts automatically prompts
for a value prior to performing the intent
if the parameter is not optional.
For optional parameters,
you can manually prompt
for a value inside your perform method.
As before, we need to include
a short title and system image.
Picking a good short title
and system image are important,
since they're the first things
my users will see
when they search for my app in Spotlight.
App Shortcuts supports parameters
that have a fixed set
of well-known parameter values that
you can specify to Siri ahead of time.
They do not support open-ended values
like "Search my app for X,"
where X can be any input from the user.
You can use parameters that are App Enums,
in which case,
the values are known ahead of time,
or you could use parameters
that are App Entities to be fully dynamic.
All you need to do is return a list
of entities in your query
via suggestedEntities, like in my app.
And as a final step,
I need to call updateAppShortcutParameters
on my AppShortcutsProvider object.
Calling this method signals to the system
that your App Shortcut parameters
have changed and will cause the system
to call suggestedEntities
on any relevant queries to re-fetch them.
I need to do this each time
my to-do lists have changed.
That includes additions and deletions,
but also mutations such as renaming.
For example, if any part
of my entities' displayRepresentation
has changed,
I'll need to call this method.
It's important to remember to also
call this upon your app's first launch.
App Shortcut phrases
referencing entity parameters won't work
until the system has successfully
fetched entities for the first time.
And that's everything I need to implement
for my Summarize List App Shortcut.
Now when using my app, I can say,
"Hey, Siri.
Summarize my groceries list with Demo."
And immediately get a verbal
and visual response.
With just a small amount of code,
I've now made it easier for people
to get the information they need
in a quick, seamless way.
When you've implemented
a great full-fledged App Shortcut,
it's important
to help your users discover it.
There are two powerful ways
people can discover your App Shortcuts
throughout the course
of simply using their device:
Spotlight and Siri Tips.
Spotlight is one of the most popular ways
people launch apps on iPhone and iPad.
The Spotlight Top Hits section shows not
only apps, but also their App Shortcuts.
This is a great way to make
your App Shortcuts discoverable.
People can find your App Shortcuts
right away when they search for your app,
and your app is the top hit.
Or they can find them by searching
for the title of the App Shortcut itself,
like "Summarize List" here.
In addition to Spotlight,
the Siri Tip is a great way
to let your users
discover your App Shortcuts
while they are still using your app.
Here I've added one in the list view,
since that feels like the place
where people would find this tip useful.
The Tip View is available
in both SwiftUI and UIKit,
and we've provided a number of styles,
so they look great in any application.
Siri Tips are best placed contextually
so that they are relevant
to the content onscreen.
Between Spotlight and Siri Tips,
there are ways for your users
to find out about App Shortcuts
both in and outside your app.
If you want to dig more deeply
into both App Intents and App Shortcuts,
check out two sessions from WWDC22.
"Dive into App Intents" is great for
an overview of the App Intents framework,
and "Implement App Shortcuts with App
Intents" explores a greater variety
of user experiences
available throughout App Shortcuts,
such as disambiguating between
multiple possible parameter values.
Now that I've implemented
my first App Shortcut,
I'd like to tell you about what's new
this year to help you make the most
out of App Shortcuts and all
of the great new features of iOS 17.
In iOS 17, we've updated how App Intents
and App Shortcuts
are shown in the Shortcuts app.
This new design lets people
find your app's intents more easily,
and gives one-tap access
to the app's most important actions.
App Shortcuts also now get
prominent placement in Spotlight.
Not only are frequently-used
App Shortcuts shown here,
but we've also added new APIs this year
to make your App Shortcuts
more visually distinctive,
and also introduced the ability
for Spotlight
to highlight entities of interest.
The Shortcuts Automation setup
has been redesigned to be easier to use,
and your App Shortcuts are featured,
so people can get started
with them more simply.
To take advantage of all
of these great new features
and bring attention to your App Shortcuts,
we've introduced new APIs around colors,
entity thumbnails,
and short titles with symbols.
These new APIs are required
for all App Shortcuts
and will help your app really stand out.
I'll start with colors.
You can now set up
to two colors in your app's Info plist
that the system will use
when your app appears
in Spotlight or Shortcuts.
Consider adopting colors
similar to your app's in-app style,
so you can bring a little bit
of your in-app experience
into the rest of the system.
Next, each entity instance in your app
can now have an optional thumbnail image.
This is an extension of the existing
DisplayRepresentation API.
Your thumbnail can be provided
either as a URL where the image resides,
a Data object representing the image,
a named bundled image resource,
or a system image name.
Choosing a unique and distinctive image
for your entities
will help make
your Spotlight appearance more engaging.
And finally, every app shortcut now
requires a short title and system image.
When shown in Spotlight or Shortcuts,
the short title and system image
are used to style the action.
Pick something that's distinctive and
represents what your app shortcut does.
In addition to all of the great new ways
App Shortcuts are visually featured
in the system,
we've also made big improvements
this year to how App Shortcuts
can be used with Siri.
In iOS 16, Siri will only recognize
your App Shortcut trigger phrases
if they are spoken
exactly as you've defined them
in your source code and strings files.
But people using your app may
use different words and phrasings
when trying to access your App Shortcut.
For example, in my app, I provided,
"Summarize my groceries list with Demo,"
as a phrase,
so it triggers my App Shortcut
as expected when spoken, but something
quite similar and reasonable like,
"Tell me the summary of my groceries list
with Demo," would not work.
In iOS 17, we're giving you the ability
to speak more naturally
to trigger your App Shortcuts.
This takes advantage of on-device
machine learning to allow phrases similar
to the ones you've provided
in your App Shortcut to also just work.
This is powered
by a new Semantic Similarity Index.
With this new flexible matching feature,
people can use more natural ways
of invoking app shortcuts,
and you don't have to provide
every possible different phrasing.
And most importantly, there are no code
changes required to get flexible matching.
Simply rebuild your app with Xcode 15,
and phrases similar to the ones
you already have will just work.
If you're not yet ready
to adopt flexible matching,
you can opt-out by disabling
the "Enable App Shortcuts
Flexible Matching" build setting,
and revert to having exact-match only
on your app shortcuts phrases.
To help further broaden the naturalness
of App Shortcuts phrases,
there is also a new synonyms API.
This is a small addition
to the DisplayRepresentation API
so that you can define additional synonyms
for AppEntities and AppEnum cases.
This will further broaden the reach
of your App Shortcuts
by making it possible
to speak more naturally to Siri.
For example, in my app,
I can now refer to my lists
by alternate names
right in the trigger phrase.
The synonyms also work
if Siri prompts me for a list,
if I didn't specify one upfront.
These synonyms are associated
with each instance of an entity,
and if they change, you should
call updateAppShortcutParameters again.
In order to support Flexible Matching,
there is also a new Negative Phrases API.
You only need to use this if you find
that phrases that do not belong
to your App Shortcuts are nonetheless
incorrectly invoking your app.
In this case,
"Send a Demo summary to my grocery store,"
might incorrectly trigger my App Shortcut,
so I will include this
in my negative phrases.
And finally,
testing App Shortcuts with Siri
can be slow-going,
requiring you to build and launch your app
and speak to Siri each time.
This is especially time-consuming
if you want to test in multiple locales.
To help make authoring
App Shortcuts faster and easier,
we're introducing a powerful new tool
in Xcode called App Shortcuts Preview.
You should note that App Shortcuts Preview
is only available
when running Xcode 15 on macOS Sonoma.
Let's take a look at a demo.
Here I have the project for my Demo app,
where I've
previously implemented App Shortcuts.
I can test my App Shortcuts
by launching my app and speaking to Siri,
but I want to show you a faster way of
quickly previewing the effects of phrases.
This new feature can be found in Product,
App Shortcuts Preview.
It requires building my app first
so that the Semantic Similarity Index
has an opportunity to generate.
After building,
I can simply select my app on the left
and immediately start entering phrases
that I think people may speak to Siri.
Let's try a couple of phrases
that I know will work,
since it's the one I defined in my code.
Summarize the shopping list with Demo.
That correctly matches
with my SummarizeList intent.
Let's try a phrase
that's similar to the first,
but not one I provided.
Give me the summary
of the shopping list with Demo.
Thanks to Flexible Matching,
this phrase also matches
with the same intent without me
having to do any additional work.
Now let's try with a third phrase
that might be a little bit too different
to be recognized reliably.
Give me the gist
of the shopping list with Demo.
This has no match
with any App Shortcuts in my app.
I can very quickly add a new phrase
to my App Shortcut,
rebuild, and test the phrase again.
Give me the gist
of the shopping list with Demo.
And the new phrase matches,
and I am able to verify that
without running my app.
Now I want to test my app in Mandarin.
Rather than switch my phone's language,
run my app, and ask Siri,
I can simply use the locale selector
in the Preview.
This lets me immediately test
a new phrase.
[speaking Mandarin]
And there,
the Mandarin phrase works as expected,
all without me needing
to use a development device.
App Shortcuts Preview
is a faster alternative
to manually testing
how your App Shortcuts work with Siri,
and it's gonna make developing
your App Shortcuts easier.
In iOS 17,
we're also improving how you can localize
your App Shortcuts trigger phrases,
along with the new
String Catalog file format.
Previously,
you were limited in how many phrases
you could have
for each App Shortcut in each locale.
If you define five phrases
for an App Shortcut in your Swift code,
for example, you would be limited
to five phrases in each locale.
In iOS 17,
with the help of String Catalogs,
we're lifting this limitation
so that you can have as many phrases
as is naturally needed
for each and every locale.
You should note
that this feature is available only
to apps targeting iOS 17 later.
Taking advantage
of this new feature is simple.
If you have not adopted App Shortcuts
in your app before this year,
simply create a new String Catalog
called "AppShortcuts."
After rebuilding your app,
you will see the phrases you defined
in your AppShortcutsProvider
populated automatically.
As you edit your Swift source code
and rebuild,
the new String Catalog format
will keep up with any phrases
you add or remove automatically.
Alternatively, if you've already adopted
App Shortcuts prior to this year,
simply migrate your AppShortcuts.strings
file to String Catalog.
Right click on it in Xcode
and follow the migration assistant.
Upon completion and rebuilding,
you will see your phrases
populate automatically,
preserving any localization
you may have done already.
Once migrated to String Catalog,
you can add additional phrases
for each locale without limitation.
Flexible matching,
the new App Shortcuts Preview,
and String Catalogs will make
App Shortcuts far better with Siri.
Here are a few tips
on making your trigger phrases great:
It’s important
to choose memorable phrases.
Your app's users will have lots
of other apps on their phones
that support App Shortcuts,
and in practice,
they'll have a hard time remembering
exactly how to phrase their shortcuts.
Take advantage of app name synonyms.
This will help further broaden how
your users can invoke your App Shortcuts.
Avoid using
non-human-readable placeholder keys
in your Swift source code.
If you refer to any parameters
in your phrases,
they must be defined
by the interpolated string placeholders
I demonstrated earlier.
This is necessary for the runtime
to load and fill these placeholders
correctly at runtime.
In addition, there are some limitations
to App Shortcuts you should be aware of
as you are adopting them in your app.
Your app can have
at most ten App Shortcuts.
You may have at most 1,000
trigger phrases for your entire app.
Note that this includes
all combinations of parameters.
So for example,
a parameter with ten possible values
would expand the number
of effective phrases by a factor of ten.
You can avoid hitting this limit
by making sure any parameters
in phrases
don't have too many possible values.
Testing with App Shortcuts Preview
will also help ensure you don't define
redundant phrases that might be
covered by Flexible Matching already.
All trigger phrases must contain
your app name or an app name synonym.
For a guide on how to define
additional app name synonyms,
refer to the link
associated with this video.
App Shortcuts that open the app
are now eligible to be shown in Spotlight.
If you have an app intent
that opens your app with an entity,
you should conform that app intent
to the OpenIntent protocol.
Now that I've gone over how to create
a great App Shortcuts experience,
let's talk about how you can bring
this same great experience
across a wider variety
of devices beyond iPhone.
App Shortcuts now work on Apple Watch,
but you should be aware
of some limitations
to get the best possible experience.
App Shortcuts on Apple Watch
must come from a watchOS app
installed on the device itself.
App Shortcuts from a paired iOS device
cannot be run on the Watch.
This means that if you have
an iOS app installed on iPhone,
but not the corresponding watchOS app,
your App Shortcuts
will not work from watchOS.
Flexible matching with Siri
is not available on Apple Watch,
so phrases must be spoken exactly.
Apple Watch support was introduced
in watchOS 9.2 and is available
on all devices
running that version or later.
App Shortcuts are also now
discoverable on Apple Watch.
Just like on iOS,
the Shortcuts app on watchOS
prominently features App Shortcuts
available on the device.
Secondly, App Shortcuts are
now supported on HomePod.
This requires an App Shortcut enabled app
to be installed
on a companion iOS or iPadOS device.
Unlike running on iOS or iPadOS,
where App Shortcuts can result
in launching the app, on HomePod,
App Shortcuts
may not launch the app at all.
For example,
by simply having my Demo app on my iPhone,
I can say to my HomePod, "Hey, Siri.
Summarize my groceries list with Demo."
HomePod support for App Shortcuts
is available from version 16.2 and newer.
When designing App Shortcuts for HomePod,
consider that it is a voice-only device.
Make sure you are returning clear
and concise dialog to be spoken by Siri,
since there won't
be any corresponding visuals.
The IntentDialog class has an initializer
that takes both a "full"
and "supporting" string.
The HomePod will use the "full" dialog,
while visual devices like iPhone will
use the alternate "supporting" dialog.
This allows you to be more brief
when a user can reference a visual output,
but remain fully descriptive
if no screen is available.
For more guidance on how
to design App Shortcuts,
including voice-only use cases,
check out the "Design App Shortcuts"
session from WWDC22.
I want to wrap up
by reiterating some key takeaways.
App Shortcuts help raise the visibility
of your app's features
throughout the system,
and lowers the friction
to habitual usage for your app.
App Shortcuts
are more discoverable than ever,
with prominent placement right
in Spotlight helping drive more usage
of your app and more styling options
to help your app stand out.
App Shortcuts with Siri are
hugely improved with Flexible Matching,
allowing users to trigger App Shortcuts
with their voice more easily.
And developing and testing
App Shortcuts is faster and easier
with the new App Shortcuts
Preview tool in Xcode.
For deeper dives into App Intents
and App Shortcuts,
there are two more sessions
from this year you should check out.
With all of these improvements,
I think App Shortcuts will be a great fit
for your app and your users.
I'm looking forward to seeing
all the great App Shortcuts you'll create.
♪ ♪