♪ ♪
Jen: Hello, I'm Jen Simmons,
a Safari and WebKit
Evangelist here at Apple.
It's been a fantastic year for WebKit.
We've already shipped more than 140
new web technologies
in multiple releases of Safari
throughout this year,
and we have several dozen more
new web technologies coming this fall.
There's so much,
there's no way we can cover it all,
so we decided to focus on CSS.
In this session, we'll take a look at some
of the most exciting new features in CSS,
including brand-new possibilities
with layout,
a whole generation of color tools
that make full use
of today's amazing displays,
productive ways to solve tricky problems
with new pseudo-classes,
and CSS that lets you take your typography
to the next level.
I'm going to share things
that have already shipped,
things that will ship in Safari 17,
and things we're working on
for the future.
To see the future today,
download Safari Technology Preview.
It's there you'll find Masonry Layout.
For years, this has been
a popular layout pattern on the web.
It's a great way to pack
content of different sizes.
You can accomplish a layout with
this shape by using CSS Multicolumn,
if it's OK that the content order
starts in the first column,
flows down below the viewport,
goes back up to the top the second column,
flows down it,
then on to the third column, and so on.
If this works for your project, great.
CSS Multicolumn is a layout mechanism
that's been in browsers for decades.
But often this doesn't work.
Instead, designers want their content
to flow across the page,
placing each item in whichever column
puts it as close to the top as possible.
Which is especially needed when
more content gets loaded at the bottom
as the user scrolls.
So websites have had to use JavaScript
to accomplish this.
But JavaScript is slower at layout
than CSS, and it's more fragile.
It's harder to code.
Layout really belongs in CSS.
A proposal for creating Masonry as part
of CSS Grid was started several years ago
and implemented in Firefox
as an experiment behind a flag.
We believe in this idea
and we'd like to see it come to the web,
so now it's in Safari Technology Preview--
on by default--
where you can try it out,
tell us what you think,
and help us move it forward.
Here's an example.
I created this typical Masonry layout
with very little CSS.
display: grid gets us started,
and grid-template-columns gives us
flexible columns
that automatically increase in number
when more space is available.
Then grid-template-rows: masonry
packs items into a Masonry pattern
in the row direction
with just one line of code.
Making this part of CSS Grid gives us
tremendous flexibility.
You can define Masonry in one dimension,
and use the power of Grid to do
anything you want in the other dimension,
like making the columns different sizes
with fr units,
or making the first column fixed-width,
while the middle is flexible
using an fr unit,
and the third is made flexible
with a minmax value.
Combining Masonry with Grid makes for
a far more powerful mechanism
than the popular JavaScript library.
This is all still a work in progress.
More discussion is needed
in the CSS Working Group,
where browser makers and others
come together to agree on a path forward,
including work to make sure
that it's fully accessible.
We look forward to shipping
Masonry in Safari once it's ready.
What is ready
to be shipped in browsers today?
Margin trim.
The new margin-trim property makes it easy
to remove margins from elements
that push up against their container.
Let me explain.
Imagine we have a headline
and three paragraphs.
They all have top and bottom margins,
which provide space between them,
as well as space above and below
the whole group.
There's also padding
applied to the container,
the article element with a class of card.
The margin above the headline
and the top padding on the container
get added together to determine
how much space there is
between the top edge of the box
and that first line of text.
Same on the bottom.
The margin below the last paragraph
gets added to the bottom padding
on the container,
which probably adds up
to more whitespace than intended.
What we want instead is to only have
the padding on the top and bottom
and to not have any margins involved.
This will give us more uniform space
around the box.
What we need is a way to eliminate
any margins
that push up against the container.
You've probably attempted to handle this
by manually removing the top margin
from the headline
and the bottom margin
from the last paragraph
and, well, hoping for the best.
But then unexpected content shows up.
Maybe another instance starts with an h3,
and no one wrote that code,
or somebody sticks an h2 in the middle
and it's missing its top margin.
Margin trim gives us a better solution.
Instead, you can ask
for exactly what you want
by applying margin-trim: block
to the container.
We've added support for margin-trim
in Safari 16.4.
You can also use margin-trim: inline
to trim margins in the inline direction.
That's margin trim.
It simply solves a common need
in a more robust manner.
CSS for layout has really matured
over the last six years
since the advent of CSS Grid
in March of 2017.
Today's layouts are a radical improvement
over what we did a decade ago.
In the same timespan,
there's been another radical leap forward
that's gone a bit unnoticed
by web designers and developers:
a leap in color.
The world is full of color,
especially outside.
The dynamic range, the saturation,
all the nuances and possibilities.
Imagine this diagram represents
every color
the human eye might possibly see.
A line around a subset of these colors
shows what can be represented in sRGB,
the default color gamut on the web,
which has served us well.
It's certainly better
than what we used the '90s,
but it'd be great to move
past the limitations of sRGB
and convey more of the visual spectrum.
P3 color does just that.
Apple started supporting
wide gamut Display P3
on our hardware and software
over seven years ago,
first on iMac in late 2015, then iPad,
and iPhone, beginning with iPhone 7.
The P3 color gamut is capable
of displaying
50% more colors than sRGB.
The displays on modern devices
are stunning.
These all support wide gamut P3 with
brighter colors and deeper saturation.
And it's long past time for web design
to take full advantage.
There's a media query in CSS
for testing color gamut support,
when you need a way
to conditionally specify CSS,
depending on what the user's hardware
and software can do.
We shipped support for
the Color Gamut Media Query back in 2016,
in Safari 10.0.
When it comes to picking a color,
there are, of course, many ways to do it;
named colors, hexadecimal values,
the RGB function,
which thinks in red, green and blue.
HSL, for hue, saturation, and lightness,
and HWB, with its hue, whiteness,
and blackness.
All of these ways of modeling color are
capable of creating the same result.
All of these models are limited
to the sRGB color gamut.
It's impossible to represent the colors
that only exist in P3
if you use these color models.
Because of that, there are
four new ones now defined in CSS.
LCH, OKLCH, LAB, and OKLAB.
These models can represent colors
in any gamut, including Display P3,
or any other color gamut that might
come to the web in the future.
They're defined with three values each.
In all four, the "L" represents Lightness
LCH and OKLCH also take values
for Chroma,
or how intense that color is,
and for Hue,
or where on the color spectrum it lies.
LAB and OKLAB declare a value
along an A axis--
or where the color is along an axis
that runs from green to red--
and a B axis--or how blue to yellow is it.
You can create colors
with LCH, OKLCH, LAB, and OKLAB
by using new functions for each.
If a browser has added support for P3,
then these functions can represent colors
that only exist in P3
as well as those within sRGB.
We shipped support for these functions
in Safari 15.0 and 15.4.
Chrome, Edge, and Firefox are
adding support this year,
thanks to the Interop 2023 project.
You can also define a color
with the color() function
and specify which color gamut to use.
The color function takes values
in red, green, and blue,
plus alpha, after a slash.
But what which color 100% green creates,
for example,
depends on the color gamut.
We first shipped the ability
to create P3 colors in CSS
through the use of this color function
in Safari 10.1, over six years ago.
With the advent of these color gamuts
and color models,
the CSS Working Group defined additional
tools that make use of their power.
Their web standards are
finally mature enough
for us to ship these tools this year.
Have you ever wanted to define a color
in CSS, while referring to another color?
It's been possible to do similar things
in preprocessors for a while.
Now, relative color syntax lets you do
just that.
Just like many ways to define a color,
you start with one of the color functions.
This determines which color model
is used to do
the mathematical calculations involved
in creating the new color.
Next, state which existing color
you want to start from.
Then take the channels from the function
and manipulate them.
In the first example,
the R, G, and B channels are left alone,
while / 0.7 tells the browser
to give this color an opacity of 70%.
In the second example in LAB, I've told
the browser to calculate L divided by 2,
which cuts the lightness in half
and makes the color darker,
while leaving the A and B channels alone.
And in the third example, in OKLCH,
I'll leave the L and H channels alone,
while cutting the C, the chroma,
by one third,
which drains the intensity
out of the color.
Relative Color Syntax makes it quick work
to define an entire palette of colors,
handy when creating a design system.
The new color models also improve
how we can define gradients.
Here's a simple linear gradient
that goes from white to blue.
For years, these kinds of gradients were
always calculated
using the sRGB color space.
Now, starting in Safari 16.2,
we can explicitly state
that we want the gradient to be calculated
in sRGB, if that's what we want.
Or we can change the color space.
sRGB-linear is similar to sRGB,
but smooths the transitions between colors
in a more linear fashion.
But you might notice that both of these
transition through purple tones.
If we switch to OKLAB,
the colors calculated in the middle
are far more blue,
and perhaps that's what we'd prefer.
LCH happens to create similar results,
although not identical.
OKLCH transitions through
a spectrum of yellow, green, and teal.
LAB happens to be far more purple.
or we can use HSL or HWB
if we like these results.
It really depends on the project
and the design effect we want.
None of these are right or wrong.
None of them is the best.
It depends.
There are a lot of new options
for defining gradients.
Switching color spaces has a huge impact.
This also goes for animating
changes in color.
The color space affects the interpolation
of what happens in between.
The same impact applies
when mixing colors together.
Yeah, you can now mix colors in CSS.
Starting in Safari 16.2,
there's a new color-mix function.
You list two colors to mix
and specify which color space to use,
and the browser mixes them together.
You might recognize this purplish-blue
from the middle of the gradient.
We can instead switch to any of
the other color spaces that we looked at
for using with gradients.
These all create different results.
By default, color mix makes the new color
from 50% of one color
and 50% of the other.
But you can change it to be
any ratio you would like, 80/20, or 30/70.
You can also set the two numbers
to be less than 100% total,
which makes the color translucent.
Here, I've set white to 30%
and blue to 30%,
giving the resulting color
an opacity of 60%.
You can even use the currentcolor keyword
to mix the current text color with
whatever you'd like.
In this case, I'm mixing a dark green
link color with 40% white
to create a lighter green
to use with the hover color.
There's a lot here.
The P3 color gamut,
new color models and functions,
the ability to change color spaces
for gradients and animations,
new ways to define colors by altering
the channels of an existing color
or through mixing--
there's a lot of potential here
when it comes to
leveraging color in our designs
for the web.
One last thing to know
about support for P3 color.
Not only does the browser need to support
certain features in CSS or JavaScript
that make use of P3 color,
and of course, the user's operating system
and display need to support it,
but also the browser needs to support
rendering in P3
for each particular part of the web page,
in different portions of the DOM.
You'll want to check into
the details for each browser
before assuming that it works universally.
Let me give you an update on P3 in Safari.
We shipped support for images in P3
seven years ago in Safari 10.0.
In Safari 10.1, we added overall support
for P3 for most of the web page.
In Safari 15.2, we added support
inside the Canvas element.
And in Safari 16.4, we added support for
P3 in WebGL Canvas
through the use of
drawingBufferColorSpace.
As for developer tools, in Safari 13.1,
we shipped a color picker in Web Inspector
that makes it easy to find colors
that are only available in P3,
or to convert a color from
one color model to another.
And in Safari 15.2, we added support for
P3 to the Web Inspector graphics tab.
We still have a little bit more work
to do.
First, to extend support
inside WebGL Canvas
to include the use of unpackColorSpace.
And to add support for P3 in SVG filters,
which we've not done yet,
because there's still ongoing debate
about the web standard.
For now, if you apply an SVG Filter,
colors will be flattened into sRGBin
every browser.
It's truly an exciting time
to rethink color on the web,
especially since so many of these features
will finally be available across browsers.
Advancements in CSS not only change
what's possible to design,
but they also make it easier
to code those designs.
The :user-valid and :user-invalid
pseudo-classes
provide a way to style forms
depending on whether or not
a user has correctly filled out a field.
For years, the :valid and :invalid
pseudo-classes seemed like
they'd be really helpful.
I want to style this form field to alert
a user when they've made a mistake.
So I'll try the :invalid pseudo-class
to select an invalid input.
With :has input:invalid,
I'll target the label.
And with a ::before pseudo-element,
I'll insert an "x",
so communication
doesn't depend on color alone.
Let's look at the result.
When someone starts to--
yeah, that's not great.
As soon as a user starts to type,
the browser marks it invalid
because it's not yet
a valid email address.
Because :invalid marks input wrong
before users even have a chance
to get it right,
developers have been using JavaScript
for this instead.
user-valid and
user-invalid fix this problem.
They use a more complex algorithm
to determine
when a form field is considered valid
or invalid.
We shipped it in Safari 16.5.
Now we can see the improved result.
No red warning
if they've if they've got it right.
And if someone does
fill out the field incorrectly,
the red warnings appear
after they've left the field,
when we want to warn them
to go back and fix it.
As you can see,
:user-invalid is especially powerful
when it's combined with :has().
In fact, this year we increased
the power of :has()
by making it work with
even more pseudo-classes.
:has(:lang()) makes it possible to style
anything on the page
depending on the presence of
a particular language.
And :has() support for media
pseudo-classes provide
conditional styling depending on
the states of audio and video playback.
The :dir pseudo-classfills in a gap when
it comes to supporting language direction.
Depending on the language being typeset,
text can flow from left to right,
or from right to left.
This is often abbreviated LTR and RTL.
These days,
CSS has more and more logical properties,
which allow you to refer to
the start and end of the text flow,
instead of left or right.
For instance, use margin-inline-start
and margin-inline-end,
instead of margin-left and margin-right,
to easily write CSS
that works for every language.
But not everything in your design can
be handled using logical properties.
This is where the new
direction pseudo-class can be helpful.
Here, I have an icon I'd like to transform
depending on the direction of text.
When the header has a direction of LTR,
I'll rotate the SVG one way,
and when the header is RTL,
I'll rotate it the other way.
This is a far simpler technique
than what was used in the past
to support multiple language direction.
:user-valid and invalid,
additions to :has(),
and the :dir pseudo-class all make it
easier to write robust and succinct code.
This year also brings several features
that make it possible
to refine the details in your typography
to absolute perfection.
Let's start with a look at
the new line-height units.
In CSS, we have many different kinds of
units we can use to define a length.
Some units are relative to
the viewport size, like svh and lvh,
or relative to a container's size,
like cqb and cqi.
Other units are relative to sizes
in typography.
One ex equals the x-height of the font.
One ch, for character,
matches the inline size
of the zero character in a font.
And one ic is the inline size of
an ideographic character
in CJK scripts--
inline size being width in
a horizontal writing mode
or height in a vertical writing mode.
These units have been supported
in browsers for a while.
Well, there's a new unit that's also
relative to a size in your typography:
the lh unit,for line height,
and rlh for root line height.
These units let us connect
anything in our layout
to the amount of space between lines.
For example, I set line-height to 1.4
on the root HTML element.
Then I put a padding of 2rlh on
the section element, this white card.
Then I set headline and paragraph margins
in the block direction to 1rlh.
Now there's exactly as much space
between the lines of text
as if there were text there
instead of space.
That sets up what's known in typography
as vertical rhythm.
Line height units don't prevent situations
that can disrupt vertical rhythm,
but they do bring
an incredibly simple tool to the web
that gets us much closer to unlocking this
long-standing typographical tradition,
letting us create an intimate connection
between type
and the whitespace around the type.
There are many challenges in polishing
digital typography on the web
to the high standards of
traditional typesetting.
One of these has to do with font sizing.
If you're a web designer,
it's likely you're carefully choosing
your font families and font sizes.
But the font you want might not download
or it might not be available on
the user's operating system.
That why it's best practice to declare
a stack of fonts in font-family
to provide a fallback plan to the browser.
The first font that's found
is the one that gets used.
Similarly, how big a font appears visually
at a specific size
is not something
a web developer can control.
Here is SF Hello on the left,
and Baskerville on the right.
They're typeset to be
exactly the same size,
but SF Hello looks much larger
because it fills more space
inside its line box.
It has a larger x-height.
This difference is caused by
choices that were made
when the font files were created.
Here, I've got an example
where I'm typesetting an article
with font-size: 1.4rem,
and I'm defining a simple font stack
for any code that's inside that article.
You can see how the code looks smaller
than the paragraph text.
It's especially noticeable
if you compare the Fs.
If the code falls back to monospace,
then it looks bigger than
the paragraph text.
We can try to compensate by adjusting
the font-size for code to be 120% of
the article font-size,
which might even out the sizes
when Courier is used,
but if the browser falls back
to monospace,
then the code ends up even bigger
than the paragraph text.
What we need is a way to tell the browser,
"Please just make these two fonts
look like they're the same size,"
and let it figure out how.
That's exactly what font-size-adjust does.
It adjusts how big a font looks
to create visual consistency.
I've added one line of CSS--
font-size-adjust: 0.47--
and now my typeset code is visually
consistent with the paragraph text,
even for both fonts in the stack.
But why 0.47? What does this number mean?
For any Latin font
you might use on the web,
there's a ratio between
the font's size and its x-height.
It's a bit arbitrary what that ratio is,
but usually it's around 50%.
By applying font-size-adjust: 0.47
to the article element,
I'm actually telling the browser to resize
every font inside the article--
paragraph font, code font,
no matter which font is used
from either stack--
so the x-height of each is always
47% of the specified font-size.
I picked 0.47 because it's what made
Iowan Old Style look the same as it does
without font-size-adjust applied.
We shipped support for
these basic capabilities
of font-size-adjust in Safari 16.4.
In Safari 17, we're adding support for
more advanced capabilities.
Wouldn't it be better if you didn't have
to track down a magic number like 0.47
to try and make every font
match your main font?
The from-font value lets you tell
the browser to just figure it all out.
Also in Safari 17, we're adding support
for the two-value syntax,
which lets you specify which metric should
be used when creating size consistency.
By default, it's ex-height,
but you can instead use cap-height,
ch-width, ic-width, or ic-height.
Safari 17 also adds support for
the size-adjust descriptor,
which lets you make
a similar kind of adjustment
when you set-up a font with
a @font-face rule.
That's font-size-adjust.
It let's you have a bit more control
over something that
cannot easily be controlled
with font-size alone.
But even with new line height units,
and the ability to adjust
the visual size of your type,
there are still things that can create
wonky unevenness in your line box sizing.
We are working on
a few solutions to this problem.
Text-box trim is one of them.
In some ways, text-box-trim
is similar to margin-trim.
They both let you trim away
unwanted white space,
but in this case, on a text box.
Have you ever struggled to get something
to line up vertically on the web?
This name is not vertically centered.
Maybe it's clearer if I draw a line
through the middle.
The text is visually lower than center.
This happens all the time on the web.
But why?
Well, actually the text box is
vertically centered.
But the glyphs are sitting lower down
inside of this box.
There's extra space above and below
the letters that's reserved by the font.
The amount of extra space above and below
is not the same
because the font doesn't need
as much below as it does above
and that's throwing off
vertical centering.
This extra space is incredibly important.
It reserved for accent marks,
vowel marks, and much more.
But it can throw off
typographic layout on the web.
Text-box-trim gives us a way to
trim away this extra space
for the purposes of layout while still
showing the entirety of all the glyphs.
This doesn't just help with
vertical centering.
Here's an example where the extra space
reserved for the font above the cap height
makes it impossible to easily get the top
of the headline
to line up with the top of the image.
By trimming away the extra space,
lining things up becomes easy.
This is all a work in progress.
The property name already changed from
leading-trim to text-box-trim.
As of Safari Technology Preview 171,
the code you see on the screen
is how it works,
but don't get too attached to
these details.
We expect it to keep changing.
Perhaps it will become like this.
Do try it out in Safari Technology Preview
and let us know what you think.
Early feedback from web designers
and developers like you is
how CSS becomes the best it can be.
Meanwhile, here's something that has
great support across browsers
and will soon come to Safari 17,
Counter styles.
You're probably very familiar with
ordered lists in HTML,
where using the  element
automatically numbers a list of items.
CSS provides an easy mechanism for
changing which numbering system is used.
Here I'm applying list-style: devanagari.
There are dozens of different
predefined numbering systems
that can be applied with one line of CSS,
covering many languages around the world.
But not all.
What about Serbo-croatian?
If I specify
list-style: upper-serbo-croatian,
I just get the default
western Arabic numbers.
This is where Counter Styles come in.
I can define a numbering system,
similar to how the browser does it.
@counter-style,
then the name I want to give it,
then I define the qualities of the style.
In this case, setting system to
alphabetic, and listing the symbols.
The W3C Internationalization Working Group
has published
a document of Ready-made Counter Styles
that cover hundreds of cultures
around the world.
We've increased the number of languages
supported by WebKit,
and opened a discussion at
the CSS Working Group about
having all browsers ship support
for all of these.
But until that happens, you can copy
code snippets from this document
and paste them into your code.
You can also style list counters to be
something entirely custom.
I've styled this list to count items
in binary, with a minimum of four digits.
And this one to cycle
a set of emoji over and over.
CSS Counters can also be used to number
other content on the page, besides lists.
Like headlines that begin each section
in a long document.
Here's an example.
I've got three H2 headlines,
with just words for each headline.
In CSS, I create a counter
by declaring counter-reset.
I've named it "numbering" and I've set it
to start counting after zero.
Then, using a :before pseudo-element,
I tell the browser to increment the
counter and to display it in the content.
By default, counters use western Arabic
numbers--1, 2, 3--
but we can change that.
Just like before, I can style the counter
to be anything I want.
That's how to create and style counters.
But that's not everything
we're doing this year
to help you take your typography
to the next level.
In fact, there's a lot more CSS
coming this year.
In Safari 16.2, we also shipped support
for last baseline alignment
for Grid and Flexbox,
plus several functions inside
font-variant-alternates
and @font-feature-values to
further support Open Type features.
Safari 16.4 also added support for
the Media Queries range syntax
and boolean logic,
@property, and much more.
Safari 16.5 also added support for
CSS Nesting.
And in Safari 17, we're also adding
feature detection of font tech
and font formats,
contain-intrinsic-size,
text-transform: full-width
and full-size-kana
and a lot more.
We want to say a huge thank you
to everyone who files issues,
pings us on social media,
or writes blog posts
to let us know which web technology
you needed implemented or improved most.
We are listening,
and your input does have impact.
Please let us know what else you need.
You can file bug reports and
feature requests for web technology
at bugs.webkit.org‚
the issue tracker for WebKit.
Issues about the interface of Safari or
anything about iOS, iPadOS, and macOS,
file those at feedbackassistant.apple.com.
Make sure you have the latest information
about what is supported in Safari.
We often hear from developers
asking us to implement something
that has actually already shipped.
Caniuse is a fantastic resource for this.
You can also keep up with the latest news
on webkit.org,
where you'll find in-depth articles
about each release of Safari,
the release notes for
Safari Technology Preview,
extensive documentation on
Web Inspector, and more.
Download Safari Technology Preview to
keep up with what's coming in the future.
It's updated about every two weeks,
so it's got the very latest additions
to WebKit.
Safari Technology Preview also has
all the new features
that are ready to be previewed
on by default.
Or you can turn features on and off in the
new Feature Flags pane in Safari Settings,
starting in Safari 17,
which you can get to from the completely
redesigned Develop Menu,
with its quick access for connecting
Web Inspector on your Mac
to websites and web apps on
your iPhone, iPad, or other devices,
including wirelessly,
or test on devices you don't have in hand,
by downloading free device simulators,
and jumping into them
from the Develop Menu,
or from the redesigned
Responsive Web Design Mode.
Watch "Rediscover Safari
developer features" at WWDC23
to learn about it all.
Web apps are coming to Mac.
Plus we've packed the year full of
improvements to web apps
on iPhone and iPad.
"What's new in web apps" covers it all.
And learn about new image formats coming
to Safari and WebKit, including JPEG XL,
and all about the new
Managed Media Source API
in "Explore media formats for the web."
We are thrilled about just how much
new web technology is shipping
in WebKit and Safari this year and we hope
you are too.
And we can't wait to see
what you make with it all.
Thanks for watching.