♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hi there!
I'm Michael from
Privacy Engineering,
and welcome
to "What's new in privacy."
At Apple, we believe privacy
is a fundamental human right.
To respect and protect it is all
of our shared responsibility.
For this reason, privacy
is a central component
to how we approach designing new
and improved features at Apple.
Many products and services
have become a central mainstay
in all our lives,
and so you have become
a vital partner
in protecting people.
Providing a great privacy
experience in your app,
where people
understand and control
what data is being accessed
and for what purpose,
helps them trust your app,
especially in sensitive parts
of their lives.
The privacy pillars
are a great guide for you
when building privacy
into your app.
You might have heard us
talk about them before,
as these are four central ideas
we use at Apple
to think about the privacy
of our products and services.
The first pillar
is data minimization:
use only the data needed
to build a feature.
This applies throughout
your app's architecture,
from the amount
of data features accessed,
to data shared
with application servers,
to data that might be shared
with third parties.
Second is on-device processing:
tap into the power of the device
to process data locally
and avoid sharing it
with any servers.
Third, transparency and control
is about making sure
people understand
the what, why, when, and where
of data access and processing,
and to give them
adequate controls
before that happens.
And also, enable them
to change their mind later.
The last pillar
is security protections:
apply strong
technical mitigations
to enforce the other pillars,
such as end-to-end encryption.
To help you implement
the privacy pillars in your app,
I will tell you about new tools
with privacy-centric design
that you can adopt,
give the latest updates
on important platform changes
for privacy,
and finally, I will talk about
how the spatial input model
on Apple's newest platform
was designed to protect privacy.
I will start with new
privacy-enhancing technologies
coming to Apple's platforms
that make it easier for you
to build great apps
with great privacy.
This includes a set of new APIs
that allow your app
to obtain access
to content seamlessly,
while giving users fine-grain
control over sharing,
as well as new APIs to better
protect communication
with servers and people.
I will begin with improvements
to the Photos picker,
designed to provide
low-friction access to photos.
Over the years, our photo
libraries have grown massively
as more and more of our precious
moments are captured there,
starting with embarrassing
childhood photos,
to the last hiking trip.
For this reason,
a fundamental way
to build up trust in your app
is to empower people
to make fine-grain decisions
about which data they share
with your app
and when they share it.
So if someone wants
to use your app
to share the most scenic photos
from their last trip,
they can do so without granting
your app access to all photos.
This is what the Photos picker
allows you to do.
This API gives your app access
to selected photos or videos,
without requiring permission to
access the entire photo library.
And in iOS 17 and macOS Sonoma,
you can fully embed the picker
into your app for a completely
seamless experience.
Even though the photos look
like they are part of your app,
they are rendered by the system
and only shared when selected,
so the user's photos always
remain in their control.
With the new
customization options,
you can choose whether you want
to show the picker
without any chrome, like this,
or as a minimal,
single row of photos
that can be scrolled
horizontally,
or as an inline version
of the full picker,
with a new Options menu,
providing controls
about sharing photo metadata,
such as captions
or location information.
The Photos picker is a great
and fast way to obtain photos,
as you don't need to worry
about obtaining permission
for accessing
the entire library,
or designing and implementing
a photo-picking flow.
Consider adopting the picker
to individually access photos
instead of requesting
full access.
For an in-depth explanation of
the picker's new capabilities,
watch the video "Embed
the Photos picker in your app."
And in case you are
developing an app
that has a strong requirement
for accessing
the full photo library,
iOS 17 has a redesigned
permission dialog
that includes
the number of photos
and a sample
of what will be shared.
This helps people
make the decision
that is right for them
about what to share.
Because the preferences
might change over time,
the system also
periodically reminds people
if your app has full access
to the photo library.
Next up is
the Screen Capture picker,
a new API in ScreenCaptureKit
for macOS
that enables people to share
only the windows or screen
your app needs
when screen sharing,
while providing
a better experience.
Prior to macOS Sonoma, when
a user wants to screen share
their presentation
in a virtual video conference,
they need to grant
the conferencing app permission
to record the full screen
via the Settings app,
resulting in a poor experience
and risk of oversharing.
With the new
SCContentSharingPicker API,
macOS Sonoma shows
a window picker on your behalf
where people can pick the screen
content that they want to share.
macOS makes sure to only share
the selected windows or screen
as soon as they are picked.
Because of the explicit action
to record the screen,
your app is permitted
to record selected content
for the duration of
the screen capture session.
This means
your app is not required
to obtain separate permission
to capture the screen
or build its own
screen content picker --
this is all handled
by SCContentSharingPicker.
To make sure that people
are always aware,
macOS Sonoma also includes a
new screen sharing menu bar item
serving as a reminder that your
app is recording the screen.
Keep this in mind and only
record screen content
when it is expected.
When clicked, the menu expands
to provide a preview
of the shared content.
This also allows quickly adding
or removing screen content
to the capture session
or ending it altogether.
SCContentSharingPicker
also provides options
for customization
in order to adjust it
based on your app's needs,
such as preferred selection
modes or applications.
For more details,
watch "What's new
in ScreenCaptureKit."
Calendar is another area
that now enables
seamless experiences
in your app,
especially for apps that
only create new events.
The calendar provides
a detailed view
into people's lives,
such as doctor appointments
or flight information,
which is why people
may be surprised or even say no
when your app asks for access.
For apps that are only
seeking access
to write calendar events,
this can result in a failure
to add events, frustration,
and maybe even people
missing a concert or
a good friend's birthday party.
In order to avoid this issue,
there are two important changes
to Apple's platforms
for Calendar access.
First, if your app only creates
new calendar events,
I have great news for you:
with EventKitUI, your app
does not need any permission.
This is made possible
by rendering
EventKitUI view controllers
outside of your app,
without any changes
to the APIs or functionality.
Second, if you prefer to provide
your own UI for creating events,
there is a new add-only
calendar permission,
allowing your app to add events
without access to other events
on the calendar.
This is another great way
to integrate your app's events
into the user's day,
without them having to worry
whether your app might be
fetching content
of their calendar.
And, should your app need
full Calendar access later,
you can ask once to upgrade.
It is best to make this request
when linked to user intent.
When asked
at an unexpected time
or for an unexpected reason,
it might be rejected
and can degrade
the experience in your app.
Help people understand
why the access is needed,
by defining a meaningful
purpose string.
In order to provide the benefits
of write-only access
to all apps,
there are two important things
to remember.
If your app has been granted
Calendar access previously,
it defaults to write-only
permission on upgrade to iOS 17
or macOS Sonoma.
Similarly, if you are linking
against an older version
of EventKit and your app asks
for Calendar access,
the system only prompts
for write-only access.
In this case,
when your app attempts
to fetch Calendar events,
the system automatically asks
to upgrade your app
to full access.
For more information about
how to integrate EventKit
and EventKitUI into your app,
watch "Discover Calendar
and EventKit."
Next is the new
Oblivious HTTP API,
which helps you to hide client
IP addresses from your servers
and potentially sensitive
app usage patterns
from network operators.
Knowing when and which apps
people use on a daily basis
can provide deep insight
into their lives.
Because cellular and Wi-Fi
network operators
can observe what servers
someone connects to,
they can observe their personal
app usage and life patterns.
And some network operators
may be interested
in using their position to learn
about how people use your app.
This could be especially
sensitive to them,
such as dating apps or apps
for specific health conditions.
IP addresses are
an essential element
for communication
on the internet;
however, the IP address
can be abused
to determine someone's
location or their identity.
Exposure to IP addresses
can result
in additional challenges for you
if you want
to implement features
with anonymity guarantees
in your app,
such as client analytics.
Apple platforms now
support Oblivious HTTP,
or OHTTP for short,
in order to help you
protect people's app usage
and IP address
by separating
the who from what.
OHTTP is a standardized
internet protocol
that is designed
to be lightweight,
proxying encrypted messages
at the application layer
to allow for fast transactional
server interactions.
With OHTTP, the network
operator can only observe
a connection
to the relay provider,
instead of your
application server.
The cornerstone of
this architecture is the relay,
which knows the client's
IP address
and the destination server name,
but none of
the encrypted content.
It is assumed that the relay
always sees connections
to your application server, so
the only meaningful information
the relay gains
is the client IP.
The final connection
to your application server
is made by the relay.
When the relay is operated
by a third party,
no single party has full
visibility of the source IP,
destination IP, and the content.
This also enables you
to add technical guarantees
to features where
you don't want to be able
to identify or track users,
such as anonymous analytics.
With OHTTP support,
you have the chance to build
stronger internet
privacy protections
that impact people meaningfully.
Services like
iCloud Private Relay
already make use of OHTTP
for its great performance
and strong privacy protections.
For example, Private Relay uses
it to protect all DNS queries.
To learn more about
how you can adopt OHTTP,
watch the network relay video.
Adopting OHTTP also means
you will need to think about
how to replace IP addresses
in your system architecture --
for example, to perform
real-user detection.
Refer to "Replace CAPTCHAs
with Private Access Tokens"
from WWDC22 to learn how
to replace IP reputation systems
with a privacy-preserving
alternative.
Encrypting DNS queries
is another essential part
of protecting app usage
from networks.
To learn how, watch "Enable
Encrypted DNS" from WWDC20.
The last new tool
is Communication Safety
and the new Sensitive
Content Analysis framework,
which utilizes
on-device processing
to help you protect children
in your app.
Apple platforms
and the apps you build
have become an important part
of many families,
as children use our products
and services
to explore the digital world
and communicate
with family and friends.
Communication Safety helps
families to keep children safe,
by warning children
and providing helpful resources
if they receive or attempt
to share photos
that likely contain nudity.
And it is important that
these protections are applied
throughout Apple's platforms,
as well as in your app.
To this end,
Communication Safety
expands beyond Messages
to also detect sensitive content
when sharing via AirDrop,
when leaving a message
on FaceTime,
when sharing contact posters
in the Phone app,
and in the Photos picker.
We also make these features
available to everyone,
no matter their age,
with Sensitive Content Warning.
And now, with the new Sensitive
Content Analysis framework,
you can detect sensitive
content in your app too.
It taps into the same
on-device technology
with system-provided ML models,
so you don't have to share
any content with any servers.
And with this framework,
this is possible for you
without having to deal
with the complexity
of training large ML models
and packing them into your app.
Integration into your app
is possible
with just a few lines of code.
To get started,
create an instance
of SCSensitivityAnalyzer.
You can check
the analysisPolicy attribute
to decide whether
analysis is needed,
and what kind of intervention
should be shown
if the image or video
contains nudity.
Then, call the analyzeImage
method with the URL
of the photo, or the CGImage,
that you want to analyze.
For analyzing a video, call the
videoAnalysis method instead.
This returns a handler,
so you can track progress
and cancel the analysis
if needed.
To obtain the analysis result,
call hasSensitiveContent
on the handler.
If isSensitive is true,
the image or video
likely contains nudity.
In this case, your app should
provide its own intervention --
which can consist of blurring
or otherwise obfuscating
the image or video --
and an option
to view the content.
Also, check the analysis policy
to tailor the intervention
depending on whether
Communication Safety
or Sensitive Content Warning
is enabled.
You can find more detailed
design guidelines
for interventions in the
Apple Developer documentation.
Those are the new APIs to adopt
to offer great privacy
in your app.
In addition to that,
there are a few privacy changes
to existing features
on Apple platforms.
This includes new ways you can
protect data in your app
as well as privacy improvements
for Safari
and Safari app extensions.
First, our new privacy
protections for macOS,
designed to help you
protect data in your app
from other apps
on the same device.
Locations on disk like
the Desktop, Documents,
and Downloads folder have
a system-managed permission.
This ensures
people are in control
over when apps have access
to their private data.
This model works well
for files that people
directly interact with,
like a project presentation
or a spreadsheet with a budget.
Some applications might
store private data
in different locations,
such as a messaging app
that has a database of sent
and received messages,
or a notes app
with vacation plans.
These files are often
stored in locations
like the Library folder,
or for App Sandboxed apps,
the app's data container.
macOS Sonoma gives users
additional control
over who can access their data.
Specifically, macOS ensures
that they give permission
before an app can access data
in an application data container
from a different developer.
This can impact your application
in two ways.
First, if your application
stores data
outside of system-managed
data stores,
adopt App Sandbox
in order to extend
this new protection
to data of your users.
Then, all files created
by your app will be protected.
Apps that are already
using App Sandbox
get this new protection
automatically.
Second, if your app
accesses data from other apps,
there are a few ways
that you can ask for permission.
Without any changes
on your side,
macOS Sonoma will ask
for permission
when your app accesses a file
in another app's data container.
The permission is valid for as
long as your app remains open,
and once the app is quit,
the permission resets.
You should only attempt
to read other apps' files
when it is expected.
If the timing of the prompt
is surprising,
or the purpose is unclear, your
app's access might be denied.
A meaningful purpose string
will help people
understand why your app
is requesting access.
There are a few alternative ways
you can get explicit permission
to access files from other apps.
For seamless access
to individual files and folders,
use NSOpenPanel.
This shows the macOS file picker
outside of your process,
and your app can read or write
selected resources
once the user confirms
the selection.
NSOpenPanel also allows you
to specify the path
that is shown by default
in the picker
to make the selection
even easier.
For backup utilities
or disk-management tools
that have already been granted
Full Disk Access,
no additional prompt will be
shown at time of access,
since people have already chosen
to allow these apps
access to all files.
In addition, all apps signed
with your Team ID
can access data in your other
app's containers by default,
without a permission prompt.
So if you release a new app
that imports data
from a previous version
of your app,
this will work seamlessly.
However, there may be instances
where you want to define
a more restrictive policy.
For example, if you build
a code interpreter
such as an editor,
browser, or a shell,
you might want macOS
to ask for permission
when this app accesses data
from a messaging app
that you also developed.
To do so, you can specify
an NSDataAccessSecurityPolicy
in your app's Info.plist,
to replace
the default same-team policy
with an explicit AllowList.
When specified,
listed processes
and installer packages
are permitted to access
your app's data
without additional consent
while other apps
require permission.
Advanced Data Protection
is another opportunity for you
to protect data of your users.
Advanced Data Protection
was added in 2022,
providing a way for people
to enable end-to-end encryption
for the vast majority
of their data stored in iCloud.
By adopting CloudKit,
you can end-to-end encrypt data
stored in CloudKit by your app
whenever someone enables
Advanced Data Protection.
And this is possible without any
changes required on your end,
in order to manage
encryption keys,
encryption operations,
or complex and risky
recovery flows.
To extend the great
privacy benefits
of Advanced Data Protection
to your users,
you only need to follow
a few steps.
First, make sure to use
encrypted data types
for all fields
in your CloudKit schema.
This includes
CKAsset fields by default,
and for most data types
in CloudKit,
there is an encrypted variant,
such as EncryptedString.
Then, you can use
the encryptedValues API,
to retrieve or store data
on your CloudKit records.
All encryption and decryption
operations are abstracted away
by this API
for your convenience.
As a result, your app's data
receives the full benefit
of security breach
and privacy protection
that is available
from Advanced Data Protection,
whenever someone
enables this feature.
For an explanation of how you
can adopt CloudKit in your app,
including code samples,
watch "What's New in CloudKit"
from WWDC21.
Next up are new fingerprinting
and tracking protections
in Safari Private Browsing mode.
Safari is designed
with privacy at its core.
Private Browsing Mode enables
additional privacy protections
in Safari,
such as making sure
that when a tab is closed,
Safari doesn't remember
the pages you visited,
search history,
or AutoFill information.
Private Browsing mode
in Safari 17
adds advanced tracking
and fingerprinting protection,
which includes
two new protections
for preventing tracking
across websites.
First, Safari prevents
known tracking
and fingerprinting resources
from being loaded.
If you are a website developer,
make sure to test your website's
functionality in
Private Browsing mode:
focus testing on login flows,
cross-site navigation
from your website,
and use of browser APIs
related to screen, audio,
and graphics.
You can reload without
advanced tracking
and fingerprinting protections,
to confirm if a change
in behavior of your website
is due to the new protections.
Do this by right-clicking
on the reload button on macOS,
via the page settings
button on iOS,
or by testing in Safari
in normal browsing mode.
You can also open
the Web Inspector
to examine any output
to the JavaScript console.
Network requests that
were blocked as a result
of contacting known trackers
show up as a message
beginning with "Blocked
connection to known tracker."
Another common method
for cross-website tracking
are unique identifiers
embedded into URLs,
for example,
in query parameters.
To give people control over
where they can be tracked,
another new protection is
removal of tracking parameters
as part of browser navigation,
and when copying a link.
When a tracking parameter
is detected,
Safari strips the identifying
components of the URL,
while leaving
nonidentifiable parts intact.
Remember that ad attribution
can be done
without identifying individuals
across websites.
For example,
Private Click Measurement
is a privacy-preserving
alternative
to tracking parameters
for advertising attribution.
And it is now also available
in Private Browsing mode
for direct-response advertising,
where no data is written to disk
and attribution is limited
to a single browsing context,
based on a single tab.
This follows Safari's
existing strict model
of ephemeral browsing
and separation of tabs
in Private Browsing.
For more information,
check out the video
"Meet privacy-preserving
ad attribution" from WWDC21.
The last platform change
is the new permission model
for app extensions in Safari.
With Safari 17,
the permission model
Apple pioneered
for web extensions
is coming
to app extensions as well.
This means that people are able
to choose which webpages
your extension is able
to access on a per-site basis.
We're also
giving them control
over which extensions can run
in Private Browsing mode.
To learn more about
these changes to extensions
and how permissions
for your extensions
can be granted per-site,
you can watch the video
"What's new
in Safari extensions."
The privacy principles behind
new tools for developers
and our platform changes extend
across all of the features
we build at Apple,
including the input model
on our new
spatial computing platform.
The system is really
simple to use:
just look around,
decide what you want
to interact with,
and tap.
There are no new permissions,
no extra work
for every app developer,
and no worrying about apps
tracking where you look.
The results are a great new
product with great privacy.
Let's go through the privacy
engineering approach
to the development
of eye and hand control.
First, there are
high-level goals
the input model
needs to achieve.
The input experience
should be fast and fluid,
enabling natural interaction
with UI elements.
It should give
real-time feedback
about what people are looking at
in order to provide confidence
in interacting with UI elements
of all kinds and sizes.
In addition, existing iPhone
and iPad applications
should work out of the box.
And last, it should not
require new app permissions
just for apps to receive
basic inputs.
Next are the privacy goals
for the input model.
To prevent apps
from learning sensitive details
about your eyes,
including medical conditions,
only relevant system components
should be able to access
the eye cameras.
To enable permissionless access,
apps should be able to work
without learning details about
people's eyes or hands.
And what people look at can
reveal what they're thinking,
so it is important that apps
work without learning
what people look at and only
learn what they interact with.
Let's go over the system
Apple engineered
to achieve all of these goals.
The internal and external
camera data
that measures eyes and hands
for the input system
is processed in
an isolated system process.
This delivers a measurement
of where the eyes and hands
are located to the eye and pinch
detection systems,
and abstracts away
complex camera processing
from all other system
components, including your app.
The hover feedback
system combines
what is shown onscreen
with the eye position
to determine what the user
is looking at.
If they are looking
at a UI element,
the system adds a highlighting
layer as it is rendered.
This is done by
the rendering engine
outside of the app's process
and only visible
to the person using the device,
so they understand
what they are looking at
without revealing
any information to apps.
And as soon as
a pinch gesture is detected,
the system delivers
a normal tap event
for the highlighted
UI element to your app.
With this system architecture,
the complexity of translating
camera data into input events
is handled
by the operating system.
This means,
no changes are required
to receive inputs
on this new platform.
In addition to the default
system behavior,
UIKit, SwiftUI, and RealityKit
make it easy
to tune these effects
to match your app's design,
with the same
privacy protections
as system-provided UI elements.
You can change the type, shape,
and what elements
the hover effects apply to.
To learn more about
how to adopt,
watch "Meet SwiftUI for
spatial computing" as well as
"Elevate your windowed app
for spatial computing."
This spatial input model
is made possible
by implementing
the privacy pillars.
The system minimizes
the amount of data
each component of the system
needs access to.
All of the processing
takes place on the device.
People have control, since only
intentional interactions
are shared with apps.
And where you look is protected
using process isolation
enforced by the operating
system's kernel.
By making privacy
a core design goal,
it is possible to deliver
both great features
and great privacy.
We hope that learning about
the new privacy changes
across Apple platforms
has helped inspire you
as they make it easier for you
to build trust
through great privacy;
minimize data accessed
by your app
with content-picking APIs
providing seamless user control;
protect children
in your app by adopting
the Sensitive Content Analysis
framework
with on-device processing.
And for protecting
user data in your app,
adopt security protections
such App Sandbox on macOS,
and make sure to encrypt data
in CloudKit.
Thank you for watching
this video.
We can't wait to see
what you build.
♪