[light music]
Welcome to Meet StoreKit for SwiftUI.
I'm Greg, an engineer
on the StoreKit team.
Let's talk about merchandising
in-app purchases.
Merchandising in-app purchase
is all about presenting
your product offerings
and providing a way for customers
to complete the purchase.
Merchandising starts with getting
data about the product you're selling
and getting the status of your customer.
For example, does the customer
already own my non-consumable product?
Are they subscribed to my subscription?
You combine this data to build
an interface
to market the product to customers
and provide interactions
to purchase the product.
This little red rectangle
underrepresents all the hard work
that goes into building your interface.
There are actually many aspects
to building your interface,
requiring skills from a variety
of disciplines.
Then, your customer chooses
to purchase your product.
Your app needs to respond
by using the purchase API
and then updating its interface
as a result of the purchase.
If you've ever added in-app purchase
to an app,
you know getting merchandising right
is critical.
Wouldn't it be nice if we could abstract
all these steps
into a simple, yet powerful, view?
This view could handle
all common functionality
and take parameters
which allow you to configure the bits
that make your app, your app.
Well, I'm excited to introduce
a powerful new set of APIs
from StoreKit
for building merchandising UI.
In Xcode 15, StoreKit now provides
a collection of SwiftUI views,
which help you build
declarative in-app purchase UI.
You just declare what you want
the merchandising experience to be,
and the system puts your declarations
into action behind the scenes.
The StoreView, ProductView,
and SubscriptionStoreView
are new views to get you up and running
merchandising faster than ever.
These views abstract over the data flow
from the App Store
and display system-provided UI
to represent your in-app purchases.
You can even use SwiftUI APIs
you're already familiar with
to customize how these views integrate
with your app.
Just like SwiftUI, these new views are
supported on all platforms,
so merchandising in-app purchase
will be easier than ever
on iPhone, iPad,
Mac, Apple Watch, and Apple TV.
A flock of feathered friends approached me
and asked if I can help them add
in-app purchases
to their new game called Backyard Birds.
With these new views from StoreKit,
of course I said, "No problem at all."
Join me as we deliver
an excellent in-app purchase experience
in Backyard Birds.
Feel free to download the sample project
to work through this with me.
We'll use Xcode Previews
to rapidly iterate on our SwiftUI views.
Because we have so much to cover,
I've already set up
a StoreKit configuration file.
This contains metadata
about our in-app purchases,
which is necessary to use Xcode Previews
with StoreKit.
We have some great sessions
to help you get started in your own app,
such as, "What's new in StoreKit Testing"
and "Introducing StoreKit Testing
in Xcode."
Let's get right into Xcode.
In Backyard Birds, we want to sell
premium bird food
like this nutrition pellet.
After purchasing the food,
we can leave it in our backyard
to attract more hungry bird visitors.
Let's jump into the code to see
how we can leverage StoreKit
to merchandise these products.
To get started, we'll create a view
called BirdFoodShop
to merchandise our bird food.
I already created a file
to implement this view.
To use StoreKit to build our view,
we need to import both StoreKit
and SwiftUI at the top of the file.
Next, I'll declare a query here to get
our bird food data model,
which will help us
build out our store.
I'm adding a StoreView to the app
because it's the quickest way to get
the merchandising view up and running.
We need to provide it a collection
of product identifiers
from our StoreKit configuration file,
which we can get from the birdFood model.
After this declaration, now we have
a functioning merchandising view.
StoreKit loads all the product identifiers
from the App Store
and presents them in UI for us to view.
The display names, descriptions,
and prices
all come directly from the App Store,
which uses what you've set up
in App Store Connect
or your StoreKit configuration file.
StoreKit even handles
more subtle, but important, considerations
like caching the data until it expires
or the system is under memory pressure
and checking whether in-app purchase
is disabled in Screen Time.
Earlier, the bird designers sent
decorative icons
for each bird food product.
We can add these icons to the Store View
just by adding a trailing view builder,
and passing in a SwiftUI view
representing our icons.
The view builder takes a Product value
as a parameter,
which we can use
to determine an icon to use.
I created a helper view that takes
a product ID
and looks up the right icon
from our asset catalog.
Once I place this in here,
you can see the preview updates
to show the icons
for each of our products.
The Store View helps us get up and running
with ease
by turning our product identifiers
and icons
into a functional and well designed store.
A powerful feature of the Store View is,
our products automatically adjust
to different platforms,
so we already have a shop that looks great
on iPad, Mac, and Apple Watch.
Let's change our target in Xcode
to Apple Watch to preview our shop.
Looks great!
I think we're ready to sell some bird food
on Apple Watch as well.
It's common to want to organize
your products
in a way that's unique to your offering.
Our team of bird designers have been hard
at work
creating a composition to showcase
the bird food.
This composition displays
the best value prominently
and organizes the other products
into shelves.
This is different
from the list style layout
we can achieve with StoreView,
but StoreKit has us covered here as well.
For more detailed layouts, we can utilize
the new ProductView.
In fact, the StoreView
we were just looking at
uses the same ProductView
to create its rows.
Let's start by declaring a container
for our new store.
I want to showcase
this box of nutrition pellets
prominently above the other products,
because it's our best value.
To do this, I'll declare a ProductView
by providing the ID
for the nutrition pellet box.
Just like with the StoreView,
we can add a decorative icon
by adding a trailing closure.
I'll reuse our helper view
from before.
Next, let's add a section below
for the other food items.
I'll start by placing a background behind
the best value...
Then a header along with
another helper view I made
to lay out our bird food in shelves.
Inside this shelf helper view,
we can declare a ProductView
for each bird food product,
along with our decorative icon.
There's one last thing we need to tie
this whole shop together.
We really want to display this box
of nutrition pellets
prominently to customers,
but the bird designers think
what we have now could look better.
To appease the birds, we can use
the new productViewStyle API
to set the style for our hero product.
I'll choose the large style
to really make this stand out.
In just a few minutes, we built
a specialized shop just for our bird food
using the new ProductView in StoreKit.
The large ProductView style helps us
display our best value prominently
by just adding one view modifier.
There are three standard styles
to choose from to fit your needs.
Compact helps display more products
in a smaller space,
our bird food shelves automatically use
the Regular style,
and of course, the Large style is great
for prominent presentations.
Since the StoreView is composed
of ProductView instances,
you can use
the same productViewStyle modifier
to change the style of the StoreView.
You can even create custom styles
and use them with ProductView
and StoreView.
Stick around, and I'll show you how
later in the session.
We've built a great way to offer
consumable bird food in-app purchases
using ProductView.
The business birds think we haven't gone
far enough,
and they've tasked me
with offering a subscription
called Backyard Birds Pass
for the most avid birdwatchers.
While we can build subscription UI
using ProductView or StoreView,
the new SubscriptionStoreView
is built specifically for subscriptions.
Let's return to Xcode
and build this together.
To get started,
in our StoreKit configuration,
I've created this "Backyard Birds Pass"
subscription group
which offers three levels of service.
Take note of this group ID.
We'll need this in a moment.
Earlier, I made a new file
for our pass shop,
so let's dive right in
to the SubscriptionStoreView.
The fastest way to get up and running
with the SubscriptionStoreView
is by providing the group ID
from our StoreKit configuration file
or App Store Connect.
I already added the group ID
to our environment,
so we can just declare
an environment property to access it,
and then declare a SubscriptionStoreView
by providing the group ID.
Just like the StoreView
and the ProductView,
the SubscriptionStoreView manages
the data flow for us
and lays out a view
with the different plan options.
It also checks
for existing subscriber status
and whether the customer is eligible
for an introductory offer.
While this automatic look is great,
there are some powerful new APIs
we can use to make this fit
the look and feel of Backyard Birds.
For example, we can replace
the marketing content in the header
with any SwiftUI view.
I built a marketing content view earlier,
so I'll just drop this in here.
We can also add a container background
to the Subscription Store
to make things more visually interesting.
We can use the new SwiftUI containerBackground API.
Notice how I'm choosing to place this
in the full height
of the Subscription Store
and then declaring a view
I created earlier
with a sky gradient and some clouds.
To tie everything together, we can use
some other APIs
for styling the Subscription Store.
By default, the Subscription Store adds
a material layer
between the subscription controls
and a full-height background.
We can use the background style modifier
to make the background
behind the subscription controls clear.
Now, I'll use subscriptionStoreButtonLabel
to choose a multi-line layout
for our subscribe button.
Notice how the subscribe button
now contains both the price
and "Try it Free."
Next, I'll add
subscriptionStorePickerItemBackground
to declare a material effect
for our subscription options.
Here, we can see the sky gradient shine
through the subscription plan options.
Finally, because our subscription
has offer codes,
I'll use the new storeButton modifier
to declare the Redeem Code button
as visible.
With just this one view modifier,
we have a button
for customers to open the offer code
redemption sheet.
Now, our subscription view matches
the feel of the rest of Backyard Birds.
While these new views significantly reduce
the effort required
to add in-app purchase to an app,
there are a couple important pieces
we're missing.
First, we must add logic
to actually unlock the content
after a purchase is made.
Second, we need to check if someone
is already subscribed
and then hide any controls
that present the SubscriptionStoreView.
StoreKit views handle customers who are
already subscribed automatically,
but in many cases, the best experience
is choosing not to present
any merchandising UI
to existing customers.
StoreKit has some brand new APIs
to make implementing
these important capabilities
just as easy and fun as selling
your content.
Before you get started
with these APIs,
you'll want to have already implemented
your business logic,
or at least have some scaffolding
in place.
Ensure you're handling
updated transactions,
cooperating with your server,
tracking consumable entitlements,
and creating a data model that's suitable
for your UI code,
among other things.
I recommend checking out "Meet StoreKit 2"
and "What's new in App Store server APIs"
to learn more about implementing
your business logic.
I already went ahead and implemented
our bird business logic
into an actor called BirdBrain.
You'll see me referencing this soon.
Let's get started
with giving bird watchers
access to the consumable bird food
they purchase.
Handling purchases that come from any
of the StoreKit views is simple.
You just modify a view
with onInAppPurchaseCompletion
and provide a function to call whenever
a purchase completes.
You can modify any view
with this method,
and it will be called
whenever a descendant StoreKit view
finishes a purchase.
Let's add this modifier
to our BirdFoodShop.
The modifier gives us the product
which was purchased
and the result of the purchase,
whether it was successful or not.
Let's implement this to send
any successful results
to the BirdBrain actor for processing.
By adding this modifier, we're now
unlocking the consumable bird food
that people purchase.
Let's give this a try in the simulator.
I'll choose a backyard
and tap the supplies.
Then, I'll purchase
some nutrition pellets.
After the sheet dismisses, you'll notice
we now have five nutrition pellets
in our supplies inventory.
Now, we can place a nutrition pellet
and sit back as our pellet brings
all the hungry birds to the yard.
In addition to onInAppPurchaseCompletion,
there are a few other related
view modifiers
you can use to handle events
from StoreKit views.
You can use onInAppPurchaseStart
to handle when someone triggers
a purchase button,
but before the purchase begins.
This is useful if you want to update
some UI components
while the purchase is running,
like dimming controls.
The function you provide here receives
the product that will be purchased
as a parameter.
When using these modifiers,
it's important to know
that they will handle events
from any descendant ProductView,
StoreView, or SubscriptionStoreView
instances.
If you add multiple modifiers,
all of your actions will run
for each event.
Keep in mind, using these modifiers
is entirely optional.
By default, successful transactions
from StoreKit views
will emit from
the Transaction.updates sequence,
but you have the option
to add onInAppPurchaseCompletion
to handle the result directly.
You can pass nil to any of these modifiers
to revert to the default behavior.
Now, let's talk about handling
Backyard Birds Pass subscriptions.
In addition to the new view APIs,
StoreKit has new view modifiers
for declaring data dependencies
in SwiftUI.
First, I'll cover
the subscriptionStatusTask,
which we can use
to make unlocking our pass a breeze.
In any view that depends
on our subscription,
we can add
the subscriptionStatusTask modifier.
Let's start with the Backyard Grid,
because this is where we show the button
to open the subscription offer sheet.
The subscriptionStatusTask modifier
takes the group ID of the subscription
we depend on.
This is the same group ID
we used earlier
when we declared
the SubscriptionStoreView.
Now, whenever the Backyard Grid appears,
a background task
will load the subscription status
and then call the function we provide
once the task completes.
The best practice for using this API
is to just pass the statuses
to our business logic,
in our case, the BirdBrain actor,
and then have the actor process the data
and return a model type
that is easier to work with
in our UI code.
I made this Pass status enum,
so I'll just make a state property
to assign this to.
Then, we can choose to only show
the subscription offer card
if someone is not currently subscribed.
With these quick additions,
we'll now only show the offer card
to bird watchers
who aren't yet subscribed.
StoreKit will call our function
when the status changes,
so our view will always reflect
the most up to date information.
We can use this same pattern
throughout the app
to unlock Backyard Birds Pass content,
and we can use
the onInAppPurchaseCompletion modifier
to automatically dismiss
the Pass Shop sheet
after a successful subscription.
I already completed this part earlier,
so let's run the app
in the iPhone simulator
and give this whole thing a test.
I'll just tap Check It Out
and press Try it Free.
The payment sheet appears,
and I can tap Subscribe,
then dismiss the alert.
Watch how the offer sheet
automatically dismisses,
and the offer card is hidden too.
That's because
the subscription status task
calls our function again
each time the status changes,
so we can be sure our app's UI
is always up to date.
While we're on the topic,
if your app offers non-consumables
or non-renewing subscriptions,
there's a new API to make
checking entitlements as easy
as the subscriptionStatusTask.
You can use
the currentEntitlementTask modifier
to declare a view as dependent
on the current entitlement
for a product ID,
and the system will asynchronously load
the current entitlement
and call your function
with the current entitlement
whenever it changes.
The functions you provide to both
the subscriptionStatusTask
and currentEntitlementTask
take an entitlement task state
as a parameter.
That way, you can choose
to granularly handle the case
when the entitlement is still loading,
if it fails to load,
and when the entitlement loaded
successfully.
I covered how these new StoreKit views
help streamline in-app purchase
integration in Backyard Birds.
Now, I want to go a little deeper
and show how you can take these views
a step further
with all the new StoreKit APIs
for SwiftUI.
First, we'll look at more options
for setting icons for ProductView
and StoreView.
Then, I'll go into detail
about styling the Product View.
After that, I'll cover how to add buttons
with common functionality
to the StoreView
and SubscriptionStoreView.
Finally, I'll go into the various new APIs
you can use to make
the Subscription Store View
fit your brand's look and feel.
Let's get into decorative icons.
When you provide an icon,
the standard Product View styles
all show a placeholder icon
while the product is loading,
like what you can see on the left.
Sometimes the automatic icon
doesn't exactly fit
what you expect the actual icon to be.
For example, on iPhone,
the automatic placeholder is a square,
but we use circle icons
for Bird Food products.
You can easily improve this appearance
by adding a second trailing closure
to your ProductView
with the icon you want
to use for your placeholder.
In this case, I just provided
a circle for the placeholder.
If you set an App Store promotion image
in App Store Connect,
you can have the ProductView
use that same image
instead of a SwiftUI view.
Just set the prefersPromotionalIcon
parameter to true.
You can still provide a SwiftUI view
as a fallback,
but this view is ignored as long
as the product has a promotional icon.
Check out "What's new in StoreKit 2
and StoreKit Testing in Xcode"
and "What's new in App Store Connect"
to learn how to set up a promotional icon.
Even if you don't want to use
a promotional icon from the App Store,
you can still use the cool in-app purchase
icon treatment
for your icons declared in SwiftUI.
Just add this modifier to the view
you provide for the icon
to get this border added to your view.
That's all about icons
in the Product View.
Keep in mind, there's corresponding API
to do all of the same things
with Store View icons, too.
Now, let's talk about styling
the Product View.
Earlier in the session, I mentioned you
can make custom Product View styles,
and it's finally time
for me to show you how.
The Product View's appearance,
layout behavior, and interactions
are entirely defined by the style it uses.
So, if you can't find a standard style
that fits what you're going for,
you can always create
your own custom Product View style.
The first case we'll look at involves
creating custom styles
composed of the standard styles
so you aren't starting
entirely from scratch.
For example,
what if you want the Product View
to show a progress spinner
instead of the standard placeholder
appearance while loading?
The first step for creating a custom style
is to create a type that conforms
to the ProductViewStyle protocol.
The only requirement for implementing
the protocol
is this makeBody method.
The configuration value passed
to your makeBody method
has all of the properties you need
to declare an excellent Product View.
For example, it has a state enumeration
which covers the different states
of loading the product.
To customize the loading appearance,
we just have to declare a ProgressView
for the loading state.
Then, we can fallback
to the standard ProductView behavior
for any other states
by simply passing the configuration
to a ProductView instance.
You apply custom styles the same way
you do standard styles,
by passing it to
the productViewStyle modifier.
Of course, you don't need to compose
your custom style with a standard style.
You can always define your style
using other views in the makeBody method.
When the task state is success,
you can access the Product value
the view is representing.
This is the same Product value
you're already used to working with
if your app uses StoreKit 2.
You can use all of the properties
of the Product to create your view.
The configuration also allows you
to access the decorative icon.
When you're adding the purchase button,
make sure to use the purchase method
on the configuration value,
not the product value.
Using the method on the configuration
will add default purchase options
to make sure
the payment confirmation sheet
displays in proximity
to your Product View,
and also triggers the reactive modifiers
like onInAppPurchaseCompletion.
Remember: when your custom style is built
from scratch,
the appearance and behavior
of Product Views using this style
will match that of the views you composed
to build the style.
Creating custom styles is a great way
to leverage
all the infrastructure
for the Product View,
such as App Store data flow,
while being free to declare
any appearance and behavior you want.
While loading, the UI we built
for the Bird Food Shop
shows placeholder shapes for each product.
But what if we want an appearance
like this loading spinner on the right?
The solution to this problem
is to lift up state.
Let me explain what I mean here.
This diagram represents the hierarchy
of the BirdFoodShop we built earlier.
The BirdFoodShop
has several ProductView descendants.
When you initialize a ProductView
with a product ID,
each view internally keeps state
of the product
since the loading operation
is asynchronous.
If you want to create an effect
where the parent BirdFoodShop
shows a different appearance
while the products are loading,
you'll need to lift your state up
into the parent BirdFoodShop.
Once the parent BirdFoodShop is managing
the state of the products,
it's free to change its appearance
while the data is loading,
and then create ProductView instances
using the pre-loaded product values
instead of their IDs.
We've only covered creating Product Views
by product ID so far,
but it's important to know
you can pass a Product value
that you've already loaded
to a ProductView.
This causes the Product View
to skip loading
and just lay out
the merchandising view directly.
You might be thinking: that's all cool,
but in order to do that,
now I have to write my own product request
and caching logic.
Well, you'll be happy to know
we're exposing the insides
of the StoreKit views
as a view modifier,
so you can declare any view as dependent
on the metadata for a product ID.
StoreKit will handle loading
the products for you,
caching them, and keeping them up to date.
To do this, you just use
the new storeProductsTask modifier.
Similar to the subscriptionStatusTask
we covered earlier,
you pass a collection of product IDs
for the view to depend on.
Then, you get a state value you can use
to handle the states of the async task.
This should all feel pretty familiar
after we just looked at a custom
ProductViewStyle implementation.
From here, we can show
our loading view on loading….
Use the new ContentUnavailableView
if the products aren't available…
Or just show our BirdFoodShop directly
with the preloaded Product values.
It's that easy.
Speaking of easy, there are
several useful common actions to include
with in-app purchase merchandising UI.
The StoreView and SubscriptionStoreView
make it really easy to add
auxiliary buttons
for these common actions.
When I talk about auxiliary buttons,
I mean buttons that perform actions
which support the main purpose
of the view.
For example, this Cancellation button
and Redeem Code button
are both auxiliary
to subscribing to the pass.
We already looked at adding
the Redeem Code button
using the storeButton modifier
when we first built this sheet.
Let's take a closer look
at this view modifier.
There are a few values you can pass
for each of the two parameters here.
The first parameter enables you
to choose the visibility.
Automatic is the default for all buttons,
which causes StoreKit to choose
whether to make the button visible
depending on the context.
You can also choose to make a button
explicitly visible or hidden.
The next parameter allows you to choose
the button kind
you want to configure the visibility for.
The cancellation button shows
a platform-appropriate button
to dismiss the view.
This button works for both the StoreView
and the SubscriptionStoreView.
The automatic behavior
for the cancellation button
is to show whenever the view is presented.
On the right, the Subscription Store View
is presented as a sheet
so it shows the cancellation button
in the top right automatically.
On the left, the view
isn't presented as a sheet,
so there's no cancellation button.
Of course, you could choose to override
this behavior
and hide the cancellation button
when presented.
Keep in mind, you only want to do this
when you're replacing
the cancellation button
with your own cancellation button.
It's good practice to always accompany
your merchandising UI
with a clear button
to dismiss the presentation.
Just like the cancellation button,
both the Store View
and Subscription Store View
can show a Restore Purchases button.
By default, the Restore Purchases button
is always hidden,
but you can choose to show it
in your merchandising UI
with the storeButton modifier.
The next three button kinds are only
for the SubscriptionStoreView.
We've already talked
about the redeemCode button.
The next button kind is a signIn button.
If your subscription service allows people
to subscribe outside of the App Store,
it's a good idea to show a sign in button
in case an existing subscriber
needs to access their subscription.
An important thing to know
for the sign in button is,
you must declare a sign in action
using the new
subscriptionStoreSignInAction modifier.
If you set a sign in action,
the sign in button will be visible
automatically.
The sign in button simply calls
the function you declare
with subscriptionStoreSignInAction,
so you can use this as a signal
to run your sign in flow.
The final button kind to review
is policies.
You might want to show links
to the terms of service and privacy policy
along with your subscription offer,
and the SubscriptionStoreView
makes this really easy.
Typically the policy buttons are hidden
by default.
If you make them visible
with the storeButton modifier,
they'll display
above the subscribe controls
on iOS and Mac.
Since these buttons display
above your container background,
the default style may not be legible
against your background.
Use subscriptionStorePolicyForegroundStyle
to set a shape style
to use for the policy buttons
that is legible against your background.
Configuring auxiliary buttons
with the storeButton modifier
helps add powerful functionality
to your merchandising UI
with just a few
straightforward declarations.
Earlier in the session, we configured
the style of the Subscription Store View
to match the look and feel
of Backyard Birds.
Now, I want to look
at these style APIs closer.
First, let's look at choosing
a control style.
Automatically, the SubscriptionStoreView
chooses a control style
based on the kind of subscription
you're merchandising.
You can use the new
subscriptionStoreControlStyle modifier
to choose the style of controls to use
for your subscription plans.
For example, you can choose
a button per plan
instead of the automatic picker.
Let's talk about the different styles
of controls.
If you don't specify the style,
the Subscription Store View picks
a control automatically.
On iPhone, this is the picker control
for subscriptions
with multiple plan options.
You can also explicitly choose
the picker control.
On iOS and Mac, there's
a prominent picker control,
which displays the subscription
plan options more prominently
with a shadow and selection ring.
Last, you can choose to show a button
for each subscription plan
instead of the picker control.
On the topic of subscribe buttons,
there's a new API you can use
to customize the button labels.
By default, the SubscriptionStoreView
shows a subscribe button
that contains an action phrase
and the pricing information
as a caption above the button.
You can add
the subscriptionStoreButtonLabel modifier
to change the button label to multiline,
which causes the pricing text
to be contained within the button label,
instead of as a separate caption.
In addition to customizing the layout
of the button label,
you can also customize the content.
For example, you could choose
to show the display name
of the selected subscription
instead of an action phrase.
You can even compose
a button label value
with both the layout and the content
by chaining the components together,
like this.
Since the button controls are composed
of the same subscribe buttons
as the picker controls,
you can use the same modifier
to customize these buttons too.
For example, you can choose to only show
the price in the label.
This is useful when your plans
are all the same service,
but with different price points.
Different subscription plans use
the display name
and the description
you set up in App Store Connect
to build the controls.
To make these controls more interesting,
you can choose to add a decorative view
for each different plan.
To add the decorative view,
just add the subscriptionStoreControlIcon
modifier to the Subscription Store.
The modifier takes a view builder.
It provides the view builder
with both a Product value
and a SubscriptionInfo value.
Using these parameters, you can provide
a different view for each plan.
These icons also work when you use
the button control style
for your subscription plans.
Now, let's look a little closer
at adding background content
to the Subscription Store View.
To recap from earlier,
you can add a container background
to the Subscription Store
by modifying your marketing content
with the containerBackground modifier.
In this case, we're providing a gradient
of our accent color for the background
and choosing to place it
in the Subscription Store.
You can learn more
about the new containerBackground API
in the session "What's new in SwiftUI."
There are a few different
background placements you can use
for the Subscription Store.
If you use
the Subscription Store placement,
it will choose an automatic placement
based on the context.
On iOS and Mac, you can explicitly specify
you want your background to be placed
in the Header of the Subscription Store.
This placement
is behind your marketing content.
There's also a Full Height placement,
which places the background
behind the full height
of the Subscription Store View.
Earlier in the session,
we discussed how to use an API
like the subscription status task
to avoid presenting
our Get Backyard Birds Pass sheet.
However, there is a case when we may want
to show a Subscription Store View
to existing subscribers,
and that's when
we want to encourage subscribers
to upgrade to the premium plan.
When we detect a subscriber is currently
subscribed to a plan
with a lower level of service
than premium,
we can present an upgrade sheet
by passing upgrade
as the visibleRelationships parameter.
This could be any combination
of subscription relationships we want,
and it only has effects
when someone is currently subscribed.
Then, to make the offer more effective,
we can provide a different view
for the marketing content
to explain the benefits
of the premium plan.
You can use the subscriptionStatusTask
to keep track of a subscriber's level
of service,
and then use this information to know
which offering to present to a customer.
That's everything I have to cover today.
When you start adding in-app purchase
to your apps,
declare a StoreView to get
up and running quickly.
If you desire a more customized layout,
give ProductView a try.
For your subscriptions, you can declare
a SubscriptionStoreView
to build compelling offers.
And when you're ready to take things
to the next level,
try out the new view modifiers
and other APIs
to really make this your own.
If you can't get enough StoreKit
and SwiftUI,
check out the sessions;
"What's new in StoreKit 2
and StoreKit Testing in Xcode"
and "What's new in SwiftUI" next.
Thanks for joining me today to learn
about the new StoreKit APIs for SwiftUI.
Happy coding!
[light music]