♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hello. I'm John,
and I'm an engineer
on the RealityKit team.
Today, I'm delighted
to introduce you
to the new RealityKit for
creating spatial experiences.
RealityKit is a framework
for realistically rendering,
animating, and simulating
3D models and effects.
We introduced RealityKit in 2019
and have added a lot
of new features since then.
If you've already
used RealityKit
for building apps
on other devices,
you'll find that
there's a lot in common.
With RealityKit, you can
augment your app's 2D windows
with 3D content, bring 3D
content front and center
in a separate window, or bring
yourself and your environment
into an immersive experience.
RealityKit is a core 3D
framework on Apple platforms.
And especially on xrOS,
it offers a lot of features.
In this presentation,
I'll focus on some key features,
like entities, components,
and RealityView,
which will introduce you
to RealityKit
and show you how to use it.
I'll also mention sessions
that cover other concepts
or go into more detail.
Let's get started.
I'll use the Hello World
experience to explain
the concepts
in this presentation.
But before I get
to those concepts,
let me take you through
the three different modules
that are a part
of this experience.
The first module, Planet Earth,
presents a 3D globe
in its own window
that you can interact
with from any angle.
The second module,
Objects in Orbit,
immerses you in a model
of the Earth, the Moon,
and a satellite,
demonstrating animations,
Spatial Audio,
and custom behaviors,
like the trace
which follows the satellite.
The third module,
the Solar System,
contains a fully immersive
experience,
which you can learn more about
in other sessions.
I'm going to show you
how to build the 3D elements
of this Hello World experience
using SwiftUI, RealityKit,
and Reality Composer Pro.
Let's dive in.
I'll get started by talking
about how you can use RealityKit
together with SwiftUI
to bring your app
into the next dimension.
Next, I'll examine the building
blocks of RealityKit,
entities like the Earth model
and the components
which implement its behaviors.
You'll learn about the features
of RealityView,
which is a new SwiftUI view
for 3D models and effects.
Then I'll explain
how you can handle input
and bring your app to life with
animation and Spatial Audio.
Finally, I'll talk about
unlocking the potential
of RealityKit with custom
components and systems.
Let's begin by exploring
how RealityKit
and SwiftUI work together.
SwiftUI is how you define
your views and windows,
and RealityKit
lets you add 3D elements.
For example, the World app
uses SwiftUI to display
a standard 2D window
with a few buttons.
Tapping the Planet Earth button
on the left
navigates to a detail view,
which shows a 2D illustration
of the Earth.
But what if I want to replace
that 2D image with a 3D globe?
Adding 3D content
to a 2D window is easy
using the model 3D view
in RealityKit.
Let's go over the code.
Here's the SwiftUI view,
which displays that globe image.
I'll change it to display a 3D
globe by importing RealityKit
and changing the image
to a model 3D view,
referencing a USD file
in my project called Globe.
We can customize the loaded
model before displaying it
by adding two pieces of code:
a content closure for the model
that is returned
and a placeholder view builder
to specify a view
that's displayed
while the model is loading.
In the content closure,
I'll add resizable
and scaledToFit modifiers
to make sure that the model fits
into the available space
in my UI.
And because Model 3D
loads its model asynchronously,
there is a placeholder
view builder,
which you can use
to customize the view
that's displayed
during the loading process.
In this case, I'm just using
the built-in ProgressView
to display a spinner.
Finally, I need to add
the globe 3D model as a resource
to the app or Swift package.
And now the model appears
in line in the app
with the same appearance
that it has in Quick Look
or Reality Composer Pro.
Placing 3D content
in a 2D window is great,
but I want my 3D model
to be front and center.
To accomplish that,
I'm going to put the globe
in a separate window.
I'll add a button
to the app's detail view
to open that new window.
And instead of
using a regular window,
which displays its contents
against a 2D background,
I'll use a new window style
which places its contents
in a volume.
This is called
a volumetric window,
and it's great
for viewing 3D content.
Unlike a 2D window,
a volumetric window is meant
to be used from any angle,
so it's ideal for 3D models.
A volumetric window
also keeps a fixed size
that is true to life.
You can scale a model
in a volumetric window
to be one meter across,
and it will always be displayed
at exactly that size.
I think that's a great fit
for the globe in Hello World.
Let's go through the process
of adding a volumetric window.
First, I'll add a window group
to my app.
Window groups act as a template
that an app can use
to open new windows.
I'll give the new window
an identifier to distinguish it
from this app's main window.
Next, I'll add a windowStyle
volumetric modifier
to the window group.
I'll also add
a defaultSize modifier
to give this window
a size in meters.
Finally, I'll add a button
to the detail view.
To make the button open
the window I've just added,
I'll add a property
that gives me access
to the open window action
from the SwiftUI environment.
Then I'll call that action
from my button.
Let's run this app
in the simulator.
When I press
the View Globe button,
a volumetric window appears.
Now I can interact with
the globe from multiple angles,
not just the front.
But sometimes, the key
to unlocking the experience
you want to create is immersion.
In the Objects in Orbit module
of the World app,
you're immersed in an animated
model of the Earth
and its satellites
that demonstrates their orbits.
This uses an immersive space,
a new scene type
which allows your app to place
3D elements anywhere in space.
When you open
an Immersive Space,
your app can go beyond
the bounds of a window
and provide
a magical experience.
Adding an Immersive Space
is similar to adding
a window group.
It's a new scene
in the body of my app.
Here I'm using RealityView,
which will give me more control
over the scene than Model 3D.
I'll go over RealityView
in more detail in a few minutes.
Like before, I'll add a button
to the app's detail view.
I'll get the openImmersiveSpace
action from the environment
and call it with the identifier
of the scene I've defined.
Note that the openImmersiveSpace
action is asynchronous.
It completes once the space
has finished opening.
When I press
the View Orbits button,
an Immersive Space appears.
This is already stunning,
but you can make
it more engaging
by adding interactivity,
animation,
and audio with RealityKit.
Whether you're working with 2D
windows containing 3D content,
or volumetric windows
that emphasize your 3D models,
I encourage you to check
out these SwiftUI sessions
if you haven't already.
The "Meet SwiftUI for spatial
computing" session
is an overview of what's new
with SwiftUI on this platform.
The "Take SwiftUI to the next
dimension" session
demonstrates how to get the most
out of 3D content in a window.
There are also multiple styles
of immersion.
The solar system module
of Hello World
uses a fully immersive space
that hides passthrough
and displays its own backdrop.
The "Go beyond the window
with SwiftUI" session
goes into detail about
all styles of Immersive Spaces.
If you're thinking
about creating
an immersive experience,
I highly recommend this talk.
You've encountered two ways
to use RealityKit
in your SwiftUI views,
the easy-to-use Model 3D
and RealityView.
RealityView is what I'll use
for the rest of this session
because it allows you
to compose your 3D content
using RealityKit entities.
So what is a RealityKit entity?
An entity is a container object.
If you create
an empty entity from code,
it won't do anything.
To make an entity render
or give a behavior,
it must have components.
Each component enables some
specific behavior for an entity.
Here are some examples.
The Earth entity in this app is
implemented with two components:
a model component, which gives
the entity a mesh and materials,
and a transform component,
which places
the entity in 3D space.
The same is true
of the satellite entity.
The model component
renders a mesh
and applies materials to it.
These Earth and satellite models
were created in a digital
content creation tool,
exported to a USDZ file,
and loaded into RealityKit.
These meshes have
a physically-based material
applied to them to give them
their final appearance.
A material uses a set
of textures and shaders
to describe how the surface
of a mesh responds to light.
To learn more about materials,
I recommend watching
Niels' session,
"Explore materials
in Reality Composer Pro."
In addition to a model,
these entities have
a transform component.
The transform component
places an entity in 3D space.
You can control an entity's
position, orientation,
and scale by setting properties
on its transform component,
as well as by setting
the entity's parent.
RealityKit uses the same 3D
coordinate conventions as ARKit
and many other 3D engines.
The origin is at the center
of the RealityView.
The y-axis points upward,
the z-axis points towards you,
and the x-axis
points to your right.
One unit is one meter.
Note that these conventions
are different
from SwiftUI's conventions.
There are functions on
RealityView's content instance
that make it easy
to convert back and forth
between the RealityKit
and SwiftUI coordinate spaces.
Every entity has a transform,
but not every entity
has a model.
Sometimes an entity is assembled
out of multiple child entities,
each with their own set
of components.
This gives you more
programmatic control.
For example, you could play
individual animations
on the transforms
of child entities.
RealityKit contains
a variety of components
depending on what
you want to do.
I'll talk about some
specific components today,
collision, input target,
and hover effect
just to name a few.
I'll also demonstrate how
to create your own components.
Now that we've got a sense
of how entities
and components work,
let's use RealityView
to place those entities
in your app.
RealityView is a SwiftUI view
that contains
any number of entities.
Entities need to be
added to a RealityView
in order to be rendered,
animated, and simulated.
So, how does a RealityView work?
RealityView provides
a content instance
which lets you add entities
to the view.
This is an easy way
to get started
if you have already
loaded an entity
or if you want to create
an entity programmatically.
But this closure
is asynchronous,
so it's simple to load
an entity from a file
and display it in your view.
Here I asynchronously load
an Earth model from a USD file
and add it
to the content instance
once the load has completed.
You can also load
more than one model
and place both of them
in your RealityView.
Instead of being laid out
next to each other,
these models will
coincide in space.
If that's not what you want,
you can change the position of
the entities added to the view.
This example positions
the moon entity
half a meter to the right.
Once you've set up
your RealityView,
you may want to connect state
in your app to properties
stored on
RealityKit components.
RealityView lets you express
the connections
between SwiftUI managed state
and the entities
in a RealityView
with an update closure.
This makes it easy to drive
the behavior of 3D models
with a source of truth
from your app's data model.
This view loads a model
and applies a rotation
controlled by whoever
uses the view.
Note that the code
in the update section only runs
when the values
that it depends on change.
If you're building a UI
with a combination of 2D
and 3D elements,
you'll sometimes need to convert
coordinates between
views and entities.
RealityView provides coordinate
conversion functions
between SwiftUI
view coordinate spaces
and RealityKit entity
coordinate spaces.
The RealityView's
content instance
provides a convert function
that converts points,
bounding boxes, and transforms
from a SwiftUI coordinate space
to an entity's local space
or vice versa.
Here, I get the minimum length
of any of the view's dimensions
and scale the loaded entity
to fit in the available space.
RealityView also provides
a mechanism
for subscribing to events
published by entities
and components.
In this example,
I play an animation
authored in the loaded USD file
after the load completes.
The content instance
has a subscribe to: function,
which adds an event handler.
This example runs some code
when an animation completes.
There are RealityKit
events published
for all kinds of things, from
animation to physics to audio.
You can also attach
SwiftUI views to entities.
The attachments feature
of RealityView makes it easy
to position views in 3D space.
Check out Yujin’s session,
"Enhance your spatial
computing app with RealityKit,"
to learn more.
There's a lot you can do
with RealityView.
But let's get back
to our celestial bodies
and bring them to life.
First, I'll show you how to add
a drag gesture
so that you can reposition
the Earth entity.
And then I'll explain animations
and Spatial Audio.
Here's an example RealityView
containing three entities.
You can add a gesture
to a RealityView,
like any other SwiftUI view,
and it will hit test against
entities in that view.
To receive input,
the entity must have both
an input target component
and a collision component.
When a touch event is handled
by RealityView,
it will ignore any entities
that don't have both collision
and an input target.
Only this last entity
has both components,
so gestures added
to this RealityView
will only react to input
directed at this entity.
To make the Earth
entity draggable,
I'll give it an input target
component
and a collision component,
and add a drag gesture
to the RealityView.
To add the components,
I'll use Reality Composer Pro.
Reality Composer Pro
is a new developer tool
that lets you compose, edit,
and preview 3D content.
I'll just use it to add
a few components to an entity.
To learn more about what you can
do with Reality Composer Pro,
check out Eric's session,
"Meet Reality Composer Pro."
The World app already has
a World Assets package set up
containing the USD files
that this experience uses.
I'll open that package
in Reality Composer Pro.
The Earth model
is in a USDZ archive,
which is self-contained
and not meant to be modified.
Instead of modifying that asset,
I'll create a new USD scene file
and reference
the Earth asset.
USD files can reference other
USDs and modify them in place
without actually changing
the referenced file.
Nondestructive editing like this
is really handy
when you need to make small
changes to a USD file
that someone else is working on.
I'll create a new scene
named DraggableGlobe
and drag in the globe file
to create a reference to it.
Now I can add components to it.
I'll add an input
target component
and also a collision component.
The default shape
for the collision component
is a cube.
I'll change it to a sphere
so it better matches the model.
It's important for
the collision shape to be
a reasonable approximation
of the visual model.
The closer the match,
the more intuitive interactions
with the model will be.
I want to be able to move
the Earth model around,
so I'll add a drag gesture
to the RealityView.
A standard SwiftUI
drag gesture will work,
but I can enable the gesture
to manipulate specific entities
rather than the entire view
by adding a targetedToEntity
modifier on the gesture.
When the gesture's value
changes,
I'll change the entity's
position to match.
There's one
critical detail though.
The gesture's value is in
SwiftUI's coordinate space,
so I have to convert it to
RealityKit's coordinate space
in order to change
the entity's position.
All the pieces are now in place.
So in the Objects in Orbit
module,
I can now pinch and drag
to move the Earth around.
Great, our app
is now interactive.
But I'd like my Earth entity
to indicate
that it's interactive.
There's a RealityKit component
we can use for this,
the HoverEffectComponent.
Hover effects provided
by SwiftUI and RealityKit
are the only way
to make your app react
to where you're looking.
This effect is applied outside
of your app's process
in a privacy-preserving manner.
I'll add a hover effect
component to the Earth entity
when it's added
to the RealityView.
Now, the Earth model lights up
when the pointer is over it
to indicate that I am able
to interact with it.
Next, let's move on
to animations.
RealityKit has a number
of built-in animation types,
such as from-to-by animations,
which animate a property from an
initial value to a final value,
orbit animations that cause
an entity to revolve
around its parent,
and time-sampled animations
that progress frame by frame
through a series of values.
I'll set up an orbit animation
on the Moon.
The Moon will take 30 seconds
to complete a full orbit
and the orbital axis
will be the y-axis.
And I'll make sure
that the orbit starts
from the Moon's
current position.
Once I've defined the properties
of this orbit animation,
I'll generate
an animation resource for it
and play that animation
on the Moon entity.
And now the Moon orbits
the Earth.
To me,
this is the magical moment.
With an animation in place,
the scene feels alive.
But while animation helps bring
your 3D content to life,
Spatial Audio makes your model
feel like it's really there.
There are three types
of audio in RealityKit:
spatial, ambient, and channel.
Let's look at each one of them
in more detail.
RealityKit sounds are spatial
by default,
so audio sources sound
like they actually exist
in your surroundings.
Spatial Audio Component lets you
customize how your objects
emit sound into your space to
make them even more realistic
or more artistic.
Use directivity to emit sounds
in all directions
or project sound
in a specific direction.
Ambient Audio Component
is great for multichannel files,
which capture the sound
of an environment.
No additional reverb
is added to ambient sources.
Each channel of the ambience is
played from a fixed direction.
And finally,
Channel Audio Component
sends the audio files channels
directly to the speakers
without any spatial effects.
This is ideal
for background music
which is not connected
to any visual element.
You can add audio to your scene
in Reality Composer Pro
and interface
with it using RealityKit.
Or you can hook up audio
in code.
Let's take a look.
I'll add a bit of looping audio
to an orbiting satellite.
First, I'll add a Spatial Audio
Component to an empty entity
that will act as
the audio source.
A directivity of 0.75 creates
a tight beam of sound
in a particular direction.
I'll rotate that audio source
entity around its y-axis
so that the audio is projected
in the direction I want.
I'll then load a looping
audio clip from a resource
and play it on the audioSource
entity by calling playAudio.
Let's see this in action.
[DISTANT BEEPING]
Since the Spatial Audio source
is configured
with a tightly
focused directivity,
the audio can be heard
clearly on my side of the Earth,
but it is quieter when the
satellite is on the other side.
That was input, animation,
and audio.
You can build more functionality
in RealityKit by combining
its existing functionality
in different ways.
There are two primary tools
you can use for this purpose,
defining your own components
and defining your own systems.
A component contains the data
controlling one aspect
of a 3D experience.
Components are grouped
into entities.
Without components,
an entity does nothing.
Each component supplies
a single element
of an entity's implementation.
You've learned that
a transform component
positions an entity
and that a model component
renders a 3D model.
In addition to the
predefined components
that RealityKit provides,
you can define
your own components.
Here's an example custom
component
that contains a traceMesh object
that my coworker
Paul has created.
The trace component type
conforms to the component
protocol,
so you can get
and set this component
on any entity at runtime.
You can also adopt
a data-driven workflow
by defining a component
in a Swift package
and conforming it
to the Codable protocol.
Codable components will appear
in the Reality Composer Pro
interface
and can be directly added
to entities at design time.
You can learn more about
custom components in the talk
"Work with Reality Composer
Pro content in Xcode."
I already went through
entities earlier in this talk,
and I just covered components.
Next, let's talk about systems.
Systems contain code that act
on entities and components.
Taken together, entities,
components, and systems, or ECS,
are a tool for modeling
the appearance
and behavior
of your 3D experience.
Systems are a way
to structure the code
that implement
your app's behaviors.
Code in a system
runs at a regular interval,
acting upon your component's
current state.
For example, this
TraceSystem updates a line mesh
that's traced behind
the satellite entity
as it orbits the earth.
Each update, it adds
the entity's current position
to the trace.
Once a system is registered,
it automatically applies
everywhere in your app
that you use RealityKit.
Registering the trace system
in my app's initializer
causes it to update
for all relevant entities.
But what entities are relevant,
and when does the system update?
This system only wants to update
entities with a trace component,
so I create an entity query
that filters to entities
which have a trace component.
In the update function,
the system passes in
the entity query
and also specifies
that it wants to update entities
when rendering.
The rendering condition means
that this system will update
at an appropriate rate
for smooth animations.
Here's the trace system
in action,
adding the entity's position
to the line mesh
in order to produce
a fluid custom animation.
Systems are a really effective
way to implement
a variety of effects
and behaviors.
RealityKit has a lot of features
that make it easy
to build 3D apps.
You can use RealityKit and
RealityView to add 3D elements
to views, windows, and immersive
spaces defined with SwiftUI.
You can load USD files, handle
gestures, and play animation
and Spatial Audio,
all using RealityKit.
RealityKit provides many
predefined components,
but you can also define custom
components and systems
for your app's specific needs.
With that, I've covered
the concepts you need
to get started with RealityKit.
Yujin’s session,
"Enhance Your spatial computing
app with RealityKit"
will take you through
more features of RealityKit,
like portals, particle emitters,
attachments, and more.
And Amanda's session
"Work with Reality Composer Pro
content in Xcode"
takes you through the process
of building an immersive app
using Reality Composer Pro,
RealityKit,
Xcode previews,
and the simulator.
There are a lot of exciting
features in RealityKit
that you can use in your app.
I'm really excited to see
the wonderful experiences
you'll create.
Thanks for watching.
♪