♪ ♪
Will: Hi, welcome to
"What's New in App Pre-orders?"
My name's Will Lo, and I'm a software
engineer on the App Store Connect team.
Offering your app for pre-order
can be a powerful way
to generate excitement
for your upcoming app release.
When you make your app available
for pre-order,
its product page becomes published
on the App Store,
where your app can be purchased
before it's released for download.
On release day,
your customers will be notified
and your app will be automatically
downloaded on their devices.
In this session, I want to talk
about some exciting updates
that we're making in App Store Connect.
This year, we're giving you the ability
to offer your app for pre-order
on a regional basis.
These updates will give you
more flexibility
to choosing where and how you publish
your apps for pre-order.
So for an unreleased app,
you'll be able to choose specific regions
to publish for pre-order,
just as you can today.
But with this new flexibility,
you'll also be able to first release
your app to a few regions,
as a soft launch or limited release,
and then offer your app for pre-order
in any other region you choose.
And as you continue expanding
the reach of your app,
you can use pre-order to further build
excitement in each additional region.
So let's walk through a few examples
using App Store Connect
to set up these pre-orders.
In this first example,
Backyard Birds is a brand new,
unreleased app
that you want to publish as a pre-order
to generate some excitement
around its release.
Let's say that you want to release
Backyard Birds on September 1,
and that you've got your product page
details all set up on App Store Connect.
To set up your first pre-order,
you can head
to the Pricing and Availability page
and click Set Up Availability.
Then, within this dialog,
select Pre-Order
in Specific Countries or Regions.
Here's where you would enter
your expected release date,
September 1.
The expected release date
can be up to 180 days in the future.
Next, you would select
the United States,
where your app will be made available
for pre-order.
And finally,
you'll see this confirmation screen,
showing you the expected release date
and where the app will be available
for pre-order.
And with that, the app is now
properly set up for pre-order
in the United States
with an expected release date
of September 1.
That's when
your customers will be notified,
and your app will be
automatically downloaded to their devices.
Now, let's scroll down a bit
and take a look
at the Availability section,
which now gives you a complete
detailed view of the app's release status
in each country or region.
So whether the app is ready for sale,
published for pre-order,
or otherwise unavailable,
this page will help you understand that.
In this example,
this app is available in multiple regions.
But if your app is somehow unavailable,
you'll see a status label like this one
that tells you exactly
what's happening in each region.
So that's how you would set up
publishing a brand new app for pre-order.
Now, let's re-imagine the scenario
for our example app.
Let's say that Backyard Birds
was a limited release,
published in just Canada.
The initial reaction
has been really great,
and you would like to expand
its availability to the United States,
with a scheduled release date
of March 1 of next year.
Let's walk through how we can
set that up as a pre-order.
First, from within
the Pricing and Availability page,
you can hit Manage
under the App Availability section.
Here, we can see
that it's currently available in Canada.
So to publish your pre-order
in the United States,
you can first hit Set Up Pre-order.
Then, you'll enter your expected
release date, March 1st, 2024.
For an app that's already published
on the App Store,
the expected release date
can be up to 365 days in the future.
Next, select the United States
to publish your pre-order in.
Finally,
you'll see this confirmation screen,
showing you a summary of your changes.
These changes will appear
on the App Store within 24 hours.
Here, you can see your app's
updated pre-order availability.
The Published column shows you
that your pre-order has been published
in the United States today,
while the Scheduled Release Date column
shows you that the app is currently
scheduled to be released on March 1.
Now,
from within the App Availability page,
you can update the pre-orders
that you've already set up as well.
We'll walk through a final example
and update the pre-order
that was published.
If you hit Edit,
you'll first be presented with a dialog
that lets you update
three different settings.
First,
you can update your app's release date.
Since this example app
was already released in Canada,
you can choose any date in the future,
up to 365 days
from when your US pre-order
was originally published.
Next, you can also release
your pre-order immediately.
Your customers will be notified
and your app will be downloaded
to their devices.
Remember, once you release your app,
it can't be made available
for pre-order again
in the regions that you've published in.
Finally,
you can choose to remove your pre-order
from the App Store in that region.
After publishing your app
for pre-order on the App Store,
you may be interested
in marketing your pre-order app or
in tracking the performance
of your pre-orders.
To market your pre-order app,
you can use these localized badges
on your website or
in your marketing materials
to directly link people
to your product page.
Pre-order apps
are discoverable through search as well,
and may be featured on the Today,
Games, or Apps tabs on the App Store.
The performance of your pre-orders
can be tracked from within App Analytics,
where you can find the number of purchased
pre-orders by date and by region.
And, with these new updates,
you'll be able to run custom product pages
and product page optimization tests
for any pre-order app.
The performance of your custom
product pages and optimization tests
can also be tracked
from within App Analytics.
So to wrap up, these updates
will give you more flexibility overall
in choosing where and how
you publish your apps for pre-order.
You can use App Store Connect
to set up and manage these pre-orders.
And finally,
the functionality that I covered
will be supported by
the App Store Connect API as well.
If you're interested in learning more,
please be sure to check out
"What's new in App Store Connect",
from WWDC23,
or the tech talk "Get started
with app discovery and marketing".
And as always,
we welcome any feedback
that you may provide
on Feedback Assistant.
Thanks for watching,
and enjoy the rest of WWDC!
♪ ♪