♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Willem Mattelaer:
Hi, my name is Willem,
and I'm an engineer
working on group activities.
I'll be joined by Mia
to talk about
how you can build great
spatial SharePlay apps.
SharePlay has always been
about being present with others
and doing something together,
whether nearby or far apart.
On this platform,
we can increase
the feeling of being present
while in FaceTime.
In FaceTime on this platform,
all Spatial Personas
will take up a physical space
in your room
instead of being constrained
to a single window.
This increases the feeling
of being together with others.
On top of this,
we introduce shared context.
Shared context
means that everyone
will see everyone else in
the same relative position.
To illustrate this, consider
two different perspectives.
The left side shows
Connor's perspective,
and the right side shows Mia's.
If Connor points to
the Persona of Mia,
Mia will see Connor's
Persona pointing to her.
We extend this
to shared experiences,
including SharePlay,
where the system will
place the window in the same
relative position for everyone.
It uses templates for this.
Templates are used
to determine how participants
and a shared app will be
arranged relative to each other.
This will lead
to spatial consistency.
Apps don't need to handle
displacement themselves
and can rely
on the system for this.
One thing that apps
should worry about
is having visual consistency.
Visual consistency
means that everyone
is seeing the same content
inside the app.
Imagine being in front
of a whiteboard with others.
Everyone will have the same view
of the whiteboard.
And whenever someone
points to something,
the others can see
what they're pointing at.
We want to replicate this
in spatial experiences
with SharePlay.
Bringing it back
to our earlier example,
here the app doesn't
have visual consistency.
If Connor points to
the square in the app,
Mia will see Connor's
Persona point to the circle.
This breaks the illusion
of being together.
However, if the app
had visual consistency,
Mia would clearly
see that Connor
was pointing to the square.
It's the responsibility
of the app
to keep the content
and its placement
in sync for all participants.
This way, it feels like everyone
is looking at the exact same app
as if they were really together.
In the "Design spatial SharePlay
experiences" session,
we go in a lot more detail
on these concepts.
I strongly encourage you
to watch that session
to learn more.
Now that we've gone over
some of the new concepts
that are introduced with
FaceTime on this platform,
let's dive into what a
windowed app should consider
when adopting SharePlay,
and what additional steps
an existing iOS SharePlay app
should take
to elevate their experience
when used in a spatial setting.
Afterwards, Mia will show you
the new APIs
to make incredible immersive
SharePlay experiences.
To support SharePlay
in windowed apps,
we've added the new system
coordinator for group sessions.
System coordinator
is responsible for two things:
receiving system state
for the active SharePlay session,
and letting you provide
additional configurations
during SharePlay.
I'll cover two of these
which are relevant for both
windowed and immersive apps:
the isSpatial flag
and template preferences.
Knowing if a participant
is spatial or not is important
when determining the required
level of visual consistency.
For instance,
here we have Connor's
first-person perspective.
He's in a call with Mia in red,
looking at a document
that I shared with SharePlay.
Mia's perspective of this
scenario is on the right,
where she sees Connor in blue.
When Connor scrolls,
we would want to synchronize
the scroll position.
That way,
Mia will see Connor scroll
and we still have
visual consistency.
We actually do this when panning
in a Freeform document
while in SharePlay.
But if you're not spatial,
you don't have the context
of the other person
interacting with the document.
So if Connor would scroll,
we shouldn't sync that,
and Mia will keep seeing
the document at the same spot.
To observe if the local
participant is spatial,
and adjust what you're syncing
between participants,
you first need to get
the system coordinator
for the group session.
You can know if the local
participant is spatial
by checking if isSpatial is true
on the local participant state.
To observe the state,
you can use the
localParticipantState property,
which returns an async sequence
that will iterate
through updates
of the local participant state.
The system coordinator
also offers apps
a way to provide
a template preference.
Templates are used to determine
how all participants are placed
by the system
relative to the app
to establish
spatial consistency.
We support
three different templates.
Side-by-Side, we'll place
all participants in an arc
facing towards the shared app.
This is the default template
that will be applied
when the app is using
a regular windows scene.
In the Conversational template,
all participants are
placed in a half circle,
with the app placed
in front of that half circle.
This is great for experiences
where the focus
isn't on the content in the app.
For instance,
when playing music in SharePlay.
Lastly, we have
the Surround template.
This places the participants
in a circle,
and the app is put
in the center of the circle.
This template is only available
when the app is using
a volumetric scene.
The distance between
the participants and the app
is based on the size of the app.
If the app is bigger,
it will be placed
further from the people.
And if the app is smaller,
it will get placed closer.
A SharePlay app can provide
a template preference
through the system coordinator.
FaceTime will try
to apply this template
while the group session
is active.
There are three preferences
available for SharePlay apps.
.none, which will follow
the system default behavior,
where it will be Side-by-Side
for vertical apps
and Surround
for volumetric ones.
This is the default preference
that will be used.
There is also .sideBySide
which will try to apply
the Side-by-Side template,
no matter
what kind of app it is.
And finally,
there is .conversational,
which will try to apply
the corresponding template.
To configure
the template preference,
you just need to set it
on the configuration
of the system coordinator
before calling join
on the group session.
Templates are used
to place the app and participant
in an optimal position
for the experience.
But what if your app
has multiple window scenes
and there is more than one
currently foregrounded?
In this example, we have
an app with three scenes.
Seen on the left
is a browse view.
The small scene in the middle
provides an easy way
to navigate through the content.
And the last scene
provides detailed information
about one piece of content.
All of these scenes
can be open at the same time,
so you can easily
navigate the content
while reading about it.
When in SharePlay,
we want the detail scene
to be the shared scene.
But if all of them are open,
the wrong scene
could be used in the template.
To solve that,
we've added scene association.
This is a way for the system
to know which scene of the app
is hosting
the SharePlay activity.
There are two reasons
we need to know this.
First, it allows the Share menu
above a window
to show to the person
which scene is shared.
This is a helpful indicator when
there are multiple windows open
and will help prevent possible
embarrassing situations
where someone was accidentally
interacting with a shared window
without realizing it.
More importantly, however,
it determines which window scene
will be used with the template.
If your app
is a single-scene app,
you don't need
to worry about this.
Since there's only ever
one scene possible,
we will automatically
associate that scene
with the group session.
However, multiscene apps
will need to consider this
when adopting SharePlay.
If not adopted, a random
open scene will be selected,
and it might not be
the right one.
Let's go over how you can
adopt scene association.
We'll start by looking
at what happens
for the person who started
the SharePlay activity.
When the group activity
gets activated,
we'll go through
each of the scenes
and check which scene
can handle this.
We do that by evaluating
the scene activation conditions
against the activity identifier
of the group activity.
Scene activation conditions
consist of two checks,
can and prefers.
Can indicates that the scene
could potentially handle it,
while prefers will help
direct it to a scene
that is more ideally
suited for it.
So we'll start by checking
the scene on the left
to see if it can
or prefers to handle
the activity identifier.
It can but doesn't prefer.
Next, we'll check
the middle scene, which can't.
Finally, we'll check
the last scene,
which both can and prefers.
Since the last scene can
and is the preferred one,
we'll associate it
with the group session.
If no scene could handle
the identifier,
we will launch
a new window scene.
This is great
if your SharePlay experience
requires its own scene
to work in.
If multiple scenes can
handle and none prefer,
then one of those scenes
will be randomly picked.
For the participants that didn't
activate the group activity
and are receiving it,
the same logic will execute
if the app is already running.
If your app is not running,
it will get launched and the
first scene will be associated.
To specify scene activation
conditions for an app
that uses the SwiftUI
app lifecycle,
you can use
handlesExternalEvents.
Just include the activity
identifier of the group activity
in either the preferring
or allowing set of strings.
If your app uses
the UIKit app life cycle,
you can set the activation
conditions on the UI scene
by specifying predicates.
To learn more about
scene activation conditions,
check out this session
from 2019.
Let's consider one more example.
In this case,
it's a document-based app
where each scene represents
a different document.
Now we want to use SharePlay
to collaborate
on the first document.
We'll again use
the group activity identifier
to evaluate each of the scene's
activation conditions.
Unfortunately,
there isn't anything
inherently different
about these scenes,
so they all end up matching
and the wrong scene
gets associated.
In this case, we want
to change the identifier
that is used
to match scenes with.
To accomplish this, we've added
scene association behavior.
This allows an app
to provide an identifier
that will be used
to find the right scene.
Going back to our example,
we could use a unique identifier
of each document
that all participants agree on.
We'll then use that identifier
to find the right scene.
If we evaluate the scenes now,
we can easily configure
the scene activation conditions
so only the first scene
is matched,
and we'll end up with
the right scene association.
You can specify the identifier
that will be used
by setting
the scene association behavior
on the metadata
of your group activity.
Keep in mind that the same
identifier will be used
for all other participants
that join the SharePlay session.
So you want to use something
that everyone will agree on.
We support three types
of scene association behavior.
Default is the behavior
we looked at first,
where the identifier that is
used to associate the scene
will be the group
activity identifier.
As the name indicates,
this is a default behavior
if you don't
explicitly specify one.
Content behavior allows you
to specify a custom identifier.
This is meant for apps
where each of the scenes
will show different content,
and the group activity
is tied to that content.
Finally, we offer
the none behavior.
The none behavior will disable
scene association.
This means that no scene
will be associated,
so the person won't see
the shared banner
above any of the scenes
of your app.
It also means that spatial
consistency is broken.
This should only be used
in specific cases,
such as immersive apps that
don't need an additional scene,
or in cases where the content
that is displayed in the scene
is different
for each participant
in the SharePlay session.
Sometimes you might need
to know what scene
a group session
is associated with.
This might happen if multiple
scenes could potentially
be selected for
scene association.
To get this information,
we exposed a new property
on the group session
called sceneSessionIdentifier.
This property will include the
identifier of the scene session
that was associated
with the group session.
Scene association is crucial
to build great SharePlay
experiences,
so definitely apply it
if you have an app that
supports multiple scenes.
Finally, let's talk about
SharePlay from the Share menu.
When in FaceTime, every window
has a share banner above it.
As we just saw, it will indicate
which scene is shared
while in SharePlay.
But it's also useful
when not in SharePlay.
When a scene is not shared,
it will show different ways
that that scene can be shared.
One option is to simply
share the window.
Everyone else will see
a noninteractive video feed
of the window.
This works out of the box
for all apps.
A SharePlay app can take
this further, however.
By exposing a group activity
that is relevant
to the current content
of the window,
it will get surfaced
in that menu.
This is a great way
to improve the discoverability
of your SharePlay activity
and can also remove the need
to have a dedicated SharePlay
button in your app's UI.
The way an app exposes
the group activity
is done through the same way as
starting SharePlay via AirDrop.
In iOS 17, you can start
SharePlay via AirDrop
by having a SharePlay app open.
To fetch the group activity,
the system goes through
the UI responder chain
of the scene
that is being shown
and tries to find a group
activity that is specified
in the activity items
configuration
of one of the responders.
That way you can just set
the group activity
on the activity items
configuration
of a view controller that is
showing SharePlayable content,
and it will get
picked up automatically.
To configure the Activity Items
configuration,
you start by creating the
activity that can be activated.
Next you'll create
an item provider
and register
the group activity on it.
You then initialize the
UIActivityItemsConfiguration
with the item provider.
Finally, you'll need
to make sure
that the configuration exposes
the right metadata,
since that is what will be
presented in the Share menu.
To do that, you can use
the metadataProvider
on UIActivityItemsConfiguration
and provide
an LPLinkMetadata object
for the LinkPresentationMetadata
key.
The title and image provider
will be used in the Share menu.
All of this will also work
if you use your own class
that conforms to UIActivityItems
Configuration reading.
I just covered what you
will need to consider
when building windowed SharePlay
experiences for this platform.
Mia, can you walk us through
how to build shared experiences
for immersive apps?
Mia Ren: No problem, Willem.
Now let's check out
how SharePlay works
for immersive apps.
On this platform, we can easily
create immersive experiences
using Immersive Space.
Immersive Space
is a special scene
that allows an app
to make its contents
go beyond boundaries
with different immersion styles.
When the app opens
an Immersive Space,
the system backgrounds
all other apps,
and people can be fully focused
in the unbounded world
of this app.
You can check out this session
to learn more
about Immersive Space
and Immersion Styles.
During FaceTime, you can launch
an Immersive Space at any time.
When you are in
a private immersive space,
you are in your own
private world,
and you break shared context
with everyone else.
Because of this, the system
will hide other people for you.
And they will see you
as your contact photo,
which indicates you are not
with them right now.
Everyone can still
communicate by audio.
But come on, we don't want
to be alone in FaceTime.
Let's share the magical moments
in the immersive world.
I have got many great ideas
of immersive experiences
which I would love to share
with my friend.
For example, it could be
a group activity like this,
hanging out in outer space
and exploring our beautiful
planet together.
To accomplish this,
our shared app
needs to configure
a group immersive space
that can be shared
with everyone.
In the configuration of the
system coordinator, you can find
the supportsGroupImmersiveSpace
flag.
By enabling it,
the app tells the system
that Immersive Space in this app
is meant to be shared
and wants to support
immersive group activities.
When people join a group session
that has this flag enabled,
their immersive space will
become a group immersive space.
The system will move
the space origin
to a shared location
defined by the template
to establish a shared coordinate
system for spatial consistency.
People in the group
immersive space
will see each other as Personas.
Now we have got
a group immersive space
with a shared coordinate system
and people in there,
we can place objects
at the same location in it
to get spatial consistency.
In the globe
explore activity example,
we can place a globe
in the center above the origin
and make sure
we apply the same offset
relative to the origin
for everyone.
Everyone will then see the globe
at the same spot.
Next, we will figure out how
to maintain visual consistency.
For instance, if we want
to rotate the globe,
we will need to make sure
that its orientation is synced
between everyone.
To learn more about
how to use group session
and group session messenger
to synchronize state,
check out this
SharePlay session.
We could also add
some UI elements
relative to each person
in a group immersive space.
For example,
we can give every participant
a private control menu
like this.
It's right in front of them.
They can use it to manipulate
the shared globe easily.
To place this control properly,
we have to know
where the local user is
in the group immersive space.
We can utilize the
systemExperienceDisplacement
method
in GeometryReader3D.
This method tells you how the
system has placed space origin
away from the local user.
it returns a Pose3D struct,
which has both translation
and rotation.
In order to get
where the local user is
relative to the space origin,
we can invert this pose.
Then we can use it to offset
and rotate the control,
so it will appear
relative to the local user.
One thing to note
is that the displacement
does not update
if the user moves.
It only provides
a displacement of the space
when it was initially placed.
This offers an easy way to place
content relative to the person
without needing to fully track
where they are.
The surround template is great
for the globe explore activity,
where the app only has
a group immersive space
with a shared content
in the center.
But what if your group activity
has both a shared window
and a group immersive space?
For example,
I want to build a group activity
for studying the solar system
like this,
where people can start
by reading about a planet
on a shared window.
And they can press a button
to take a closer look
at the planet model
in a group immersive space.
I would love people to always
stay side by side in both cases.
Let's check out
what we can do with template.
By default, when your app only
has a group immersive space,
the Surround template
will be applied,
and the space origin
will be placed in the center.
The same layout is applied
when your app
also has a shared
volumetric scene.
But if your app has
a shared vertical window,
the Side-by-Side template
will be chosen by default,
and the space origin is
right below the shared window.
But keep in mind, you can always
change the template preference
to the one that fits
your group activity best.
You can choose
the .conversational template
or the .sideBySide template,
which I think will be
a great one
for our solar exploration
activity.
As we learned before,
the distances in the template
are dynamically adjusted
based on the size
of the shared window.
You may wonder how we can ensure
that the distance is good
when there's only
a group immersive space.
To solve this, we have
a useful knob to tweak templates
called content extent.
It's a modifier
on the template preference,
which works for both immersive
and window-based
group activities.
Apps can set this value
as the distance
from the center of the content
to its farthest edge in points.
When content extent is set,
the active template
will factor in this value
for placing the people
relative to the app.
All right, let's apply what
we learned about template
and configure the group session
for the solar explore activity
we showed before.
First, we should enable
supportsGroupImmersiveSpace
so people can view the object
together while immersive.
Next, let's set the template
preference to .sideBySide
and also add a modifier
for the contentExtent
so people can always
stay side by side
and have a great distance
with the shared content.
Cool.
Let's check out
what this group activity
would look like with people.
Here, I'm with my friend Connor,
and we're browsing planets
on a shared window side by side.
Later, I press a button,
which lets me go into
a group immersive space
to explore Saturn.
While I am amazed by
how beautiful this model is,
I also find Connor
is not with me anymore,
and all I see
is his contact photo.
But actually,
Connor is left behind,
still watching the window.
He needs to press
the button himself
to enter the group
immersive space.
As we learned before,
when people are not in the group
immersive space together,
they would have
no shared context.
So the system
will hide Spatial Personas
and show contact photos.
If we can still see
each other's Persona,
Connor may feel really confused
when I look surprised
at something he doesn't see.
Same situation could happen
if our group immersive spaces
are presenting in different
immersion styles.
For example,
I'm looking around
in a fully immersive
environment,
but Connor remains
in passthrough.
But it would be so nice
if Connor can just follow me
into the same group
immersive space automatically.
And when he's not
with me there,
he could know where I am
and join me easily.
To minimize split contacts in
your immersive group activity,
we have a great tool
you can utilize
in the system coordinator
called Group Immersion Style.
It provides an async sequence
of optional immersion style,
which tells your app
a specific immersion style
of the group immersive space
that other people join,
or nil when they leave
a group immersive space.
For example, when I open
a group immersive space,
Connor's app will receive
the immersion style of it,
and his app can open
a group immersive space
with a matching style.
Then we will be together
in the group immersive space
and have shared context again.
Likewise, when Connor
presses the button
and leaves the group
immersive space,
my app will receive nil
and can dismiss immersive space.
Now with the help
of group immersion style,
everyone can always be together.
Sometimes you
may want to step out
of the immersive experience
temporarily
for something urgent.
You can do it with a single
press on the Digital Crown.
In this case, the system
will not disturb other people
and change their
group immersion style.
When you step out, you will see
a SharePlay banner notice,
which tells you where
the rest of the group is
and also provides you
a button to join back
to the group
immersive space easily.
When you tap on the Join button,
a group immersion style
will be sent to your app
for setting up
the group immersive space.
All right, we have seen
a lot in this session.
Let's recap!
We learned about shared context
and how to use
system coordinator
and scene association
to manage spatial
and visual consistency
in both windowed
and immersive shared apps.
We introduced template
preferences for your app
to place people properly.
And finally, we also showed you
a new way
to start SharePlay
using the Share menu.
Thanks for tuning in.
We can't wait to see
what incredible experiences
you’re going to build
with SharePlay.
♪