♪ ♪
David: Hi. My name is David Findlay.
I'm a machine learning engineer
on the Create ML team.
We've been working
on some great improvements
to the Create ML app and frameworks.
I'm excited to take you
on a tour of what's new.
Training a large-scale model from scratch
can take thousands of hours,
millions of annotated files,
and expert domain knowledge.
Our goal is to give you the tools
to build great apps
that use machine learning
without all of the overhead.
We've gone through the process
of creating state-of-the-art models
that power many features,
like the Search experience
in the Photos app
and Custom Sound Recognition
in Accessibility.
Create ML gives you access
to our latest technology
so you can build your own
custom machine learning experiences,
without the hassle.
I'll start by going through improvements
that we've made to Create ML.
Then I'll introduce a brand-new way
of building machine learning models
to understand scenes with multiple labels.
And lastly,
I'll talk about new Augmentation APIs
that we designed to help you
improve the quality of your model
when you're limited on training data.
Let's get started
with Text Classification improvements.
A text classifier is
a machine learning task
designed to recognize patterns
in natural language text.
To train such a model, all you need to do
is provide it with a table of text
and label pairs.
In this example, I have sports,
entertainment, and nature labels.
You can choose
the transfer-learning algorithm
that uses a pre-trained embedding model
as a feature extractor.
This year,
we designed a new embedding model
and trained it on billions
of labeled text examples.
It's a bidirectional encoder
representations from transformers model,
or BERT for short.
You can find the new option
in the Create ML app
in the model parameters section
of the Settings tab.
The BERT embedding model is multilingual,
which means your training data
can now contain
more than just one language.
On top of supporting
multilingual text classifiers,
BERT can also boost the accuracy
of your monolingual text classifiers.
You can leverage BERT on iOS 17,
iPadOS 17, and macOS Sonoma.
We have a whole video
that covers all of the details.
Make sure to watch
"Explore Natural Language
multilingual models" to find out more.
Next, I want to talk about
how we use transfer-learning
in the image classification task.
The image classifier in Create ML
is designed to help you build models
to answer the question,
what is the best label
to describe the contents of my image?
Similar to the text classifier,
the image classifier leverages
a pre-trained model to extract
relevant information from images.
The latest version of the Apple Neural
Scene Analyzer is now available to you
for building state-of-the-art models
with very little training data.
Image understanding models in the OS
continue to evolve
to give you the best possible experience.
You can find out more
by checking out our article
on the machine learning research website.
In the Create ML app, you'll notice
a new feature extractor option
in the model parameters section
of the Settings tab.
The new feature extractor has
a smaller output embedding size
when compared to our previous version.
On top of general improvements,
this can boost the accuracy
of your classifier,
lead to faster training time,
and reduce the memory needed
to store the extracted features.
Now that I've covered
improvements in Create ML,
I want to talk about the new
multi-label image classifier.
Before I get there, recall that
single-label image classification
is designed to predict the best label
describing the contents of an image.
For example, you might describe
this image as dog or maybe outdoors.
But you need to pick one.
If you're interested in objects,
then you can use
the object detector
to locate objects within a scene.
For example, I've drawn a bounding box
around the dog
and another one around the ball.
Now, this is great,
but I'm also interested
in the scene that the objects are in.
I can't really draw a bounding box
to represent
that the dog is in a park or outdoors.
That's where the new
multi-label image classifier comes in.
It allows you to predict a set of objects,
attributes, or labels for your images.
For example this image contains
a dog, toy, grass, and park.
Let's go build one using Create ML.
As usual, the first thing I'll need to do
is collect some training data.
I decided to have a bit of fun
and build a classifier that detects
multiple succulent plants
in different scenes.
For example,
here I have an image of Haworthia,
Jade, and Aloe in pots on a window sill.
In the next image,
I have a person holding a cactus in a pot.
While collecting training images,
it's also okay to include some images
that only have a single label,
like a photo of just aloe.
You'll need to organize your annotations
in a JSON file.
All you need to do is annotate each file
with a set of annotations.
Now, let me give you a demo
of building a model in the Create ML app.
In the Create ML app, I'll select the new
multi-label image classifier template.
And create a project
named Succulent Classifier.
This takes me to the Settings tab.
To start, I'll drag in my training data,
which gives me a summary
of the number of classes
and training images.
I also have the option
to drag in validation data,
but I'll choose to randomly split
the training data for now.
I'll use the default number of iterations
and also leave out augmentations.
I'm done setting up my model,
so I'll go ahead and click Train.
This model takes only a few minutes
to train on my Mac.
Right away,
the model starts extracting features
using the new feature extractor
that I introduced earlier.
Once that's finished,
the app starts to train a classifier.
During the training process,
the app measures the quality of my model
by computing a mean-average
precision score, or MAP for short.
In general,
I want to maximize the MAP score
because that means my model has
both a higher precision
and a higher recall on average
for all of the labels in my dataset.
My model finished training
and converged early at 74 iterations,
with an MAP score of 97%
on the training set
and 93% on the validation set.
The next step is to evaluate
my model on test data.
I'll drag a folder in from my desktop
and click the Test button.
The test data should contain
the same set of class labels
that I used to train my model.
The app calculated
a few high-level statistics,
like the MAP Score
and which class labels have
the highest and lowest
precision and recall.
Let's focus on the Metrics tab.
The app calculates metrics
for each class label,
like False Positives,
False Negatives, Precision,
Recall, and Confidence Threshold.
When making predictions with my model,
a prediction is correct
if the confidence is above the threshold
for a given class label.
Let's explore the images
that the model predicted
above the confidence threshold for aloe.
Now I'll click on an example.
The model predicted that this image
contains aloe with a 90% confidence,
which is above the aloe
confidence threshold of 40%.
For other labels,
the model predicted a confidence
below their respective thresholds.
In other words,
the model did not predict them.
Next, I want to explore images
that my model did not predict aloe
but are labeled as aloe.
I can do that by selecting
the False Negatives result type.
This image is interesting.
Let's explore further.
Here, the aloe is behind the barrel cactus
and the moon cactus,
so the model has
a hard time predicting aloe.
But the good news is that the model
predicts two other labels correctly.
Next, I'll head over to the Preview tab.
This is where I can preview
my model predictions
on images that I haven't labeled yet.
I have a succulent arrangement
that I planted myself
that I think would be fun to try out.
Nailed it.
My model correctly predicted
my moon cactus,
bunny ears cactus,
and barrel cactus in my kitchen.
I'm pretty happy
with the quality of my model,
but I'll definitely continue experimenting
to understand my model's limitations
as well as adding more succulents
and scenes to my dataset.
For now, let's move on.
From the Output tab,
I can save
the model that I trained to disk.
Let's go through some code that you'll
need to write to create predictions.
The first step is to create a Vision model
from the compiled Core ML model.
Then using the vision framework,
I'll create an image request handler
with a source image
and then perform a request.
Lastly, I can retrieve
the classification observations
and filter them using a precision
and recall value that I'm interested in.
To find out more about how to choose
a precision and recall value
that work for your use case,
make sure to watch the video
from WWDC 2019,
"Understanding Images
in Vision Framework."
Before I move on,
I want to take a moment and mention that,
similar to our image classifier
and multi-label image classifier,
we've enhanced the evaluation tab
with an explore option
for object detection.
Make sure to check it out.
I want to shift your focus
to my last topic,
training machine learning models
on limited data using augmentations.
To get a model that generalizes well,
the images in your training set
should have a variety of characteristics
like different lighting conditions,
orientations, and backgrounds.
But capturing and labeling
training images in different situations
can be time-consuming.
Data augmentation is a technique
that generates new training examples
from your existing ones
by applying transformations.
In the case of images,
the transformations can be
horizontal or vertical flipping,
cropping, or contrast, just to name a few.
In this example,
I start with an image of a succulent
and generate four variations.
And transformations can be combined,
like flipping and increasing the contrast.
Augmentations can boost
the quality of your model,
especially when you have
a small training data set.
You can use them to improve
your model's generalization
because it prevents your model
from learning attributes
like the exact location
of an object in a scene.
However, it's important to consider
that training is usually slower
because feature extraction happens
at each training iteration.
If you haven't already,
make sure to watch our videos
from WWDC 2022,
where we introduced Create ML Components.
We designed the framework to help you
build custom machine learning models
using components
like transformers and estimators.
This year, we added new
Augmentation APIs that you can use
to design your own
custom augmentation pipelines.
If you have experience with SwiftUI,
this may be familiar to you.
The first step is to create an augmenter.
Similar to SwiftUI,
the augmenter uses result builders.
In the body of the augmenter, you can add
transformations to augment your data.
Since the augmenter is generic,
your data can be labeled images,
labeled sounds, or even something else.
The important part is that
the input and output types
of each transformation need to match.
For example, taking an image
and producing an image.
I want to augment my images
by flipping them horizontally
with a 50% probability.
I'll start by adding
ApplyRandomly to the Augmenter.
This applies a transformation
with a given probability.
Then I'll add a horizontal
flipping transformer to its body.
Okay, now that I have my augmenter,
I can use it to create augmentations
by calling the applied method.
When you design augmentations,
it's important to carefully consider
the nature of your data.
It's unlikely that you'll encounter
an upside down succulent.
So it doesn't make sense to apply
a vertical flip augmentation in this case.
Or imagine for a moment that you wanted
to classify traffic signs instead.
When you apply a flip augmentation,
the label may no longer
correctly describe your image.
So remember to consider
the nature of your data
before designing a custom augmentation.
All right, the next step is to add
more transformations to the augmenter.
This time, I'll randomly rotate my images
using the
UniformRandomFloatingPointParameter.
This generates a random angle
each time that I apply the augmentation.
And lastly, I'll randomly crop the images.
Note that each transformation
in the augmenter is applied in sequence.
So first, my image is randomly flipped.
The result is randomly rotated
and then randomly cropped.
I've only scratched the surface
of what you can do with the Augmenter.
Here are some of the components
that we provide to get you started.
But what if you want to go even further?
Let's go through an example of how
you can build custom transformations
and use them to augment your images.
In order to build a robust classifier,
it's important to capture
your training images
in different scenes and environments.
In this example,
I'll create a custom augmentation
that places a succulent
in a random location in a random scene.
I'll start by defining
a RandomImageBackground.
It conforms to a new protocol,
RandomTransformer,
which is similar to a transformer
but takes a random number generator.
Since I want my augmentations
to place succulents randomly
with different background scenes,
I'll create an initializer
that takes background images.
To conform
to the RandomTransformer protocol,
I'll need to implement the applied method.
When applying my augmentation,
the first step is
to randomly select a background.
Then, I'll choose a random location
in the background image
where I'd like to place my input image,
taking care not to crop it.
Next, I'll translate my input image
to the random location.
And finally, I'll place the input image
over the randomly selected background.
I'll add my new custom augmentation
to the end so that the flipping, rotating,
and cropping happen before I place
the succulent in different backgrounds.
And this is my final augmenter.
Using my augmenter, I can generate
some really interesting images
for training a classifier.
That's the next step.
When using augmentations
it makes more sense
to train progressively
using the update method.
With that in mind,
let's go through an example
of training using augmentations.
And I won't hold back:
I'll also incorporate batching,
randomization, and early stopping.
I'll start by creating
an empty image classifier model.
Then I'll create a training loop.
In the training loop, the first step is
to shuffle and augment my training images.
You'll want to shuffle before augmenting
so that on each iteration,
the batches contain different images.
The result of the augmenter
is an async sequence,
which means
that transformations happen lazily.
Using the batches method,
I can group the async sequence
of augmentations into groups.
In this case,
I've used a batch size of 16.
Finally, I'll update my model
with each batch of augmented images.
This is why using the update method
is a good choice
when doing data augmentation.
On each iteration,
you get a new set of images.
Depending on your augmenter,
the update method is unlikely
to encounter the exact same image
more than once.
This encourages the model
to generalize instead of memorize.
I selected 100 iterations,
but ideally you should stop training
when the validation accuracy
stops improving.
In this example, the training accuracy
continues to improve,
but notice that the validation accuracy
starts to decrease after a few iterations.
This means that the model is
memorizing the training data,
making it less generalizable to new data
and performing worse
on validation and test data.
Continuing training
after this is detrimental.
As a final example, I'll add
early stopping to the training loop.
After the update step,
you can compute validation metrics.
I'm using validation accuracy
to stop training early,
which works for classifier models.
But that is really up to you.
You can use validation loss
or even design your own metric
to assess the quality of your model.
Then, I'll break out of the training loop
when the accuracy hasn't improved
for the last five iterations.
And that concludes
my augmented image classifier.
In this video,
I introduced new state-of-the-art models
shipped in the OS
that you can use to build
great machine learning experiences
in your apps.
Then I gave an example
of how you can build models
for understanding scenes using
our new multi-label image classifier.
Finally, I went into detail
about how you can build
your own custom augmentations
to improve your model quality.
And that's a wrap.
It's time for you to enhance your apps
with Create ML.