♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Carnaven Chiu: Hi, I'm Carnaven.
Jay Moon: And I'm Jay.
Carnaven: We're
from Apple's Design team.
We are excited to talk to you
about how you can design
great SharePlay experiences
for spatial computing.
In a SharePlay session,
Spatial Personas
let you feel present with others
in a way technology
has never enabled before.
You can look your friends
in the eye,
express yourself naturally with
movement and body language,
and best of all,
enjoy a shared activity together
using your app.
These shared activities
are a key part
of what makes this an exciting
new computing platform
and people will expect your app
to fully support
the features I'm going
to talk about today.
Shared activities in FaceTime
build on the existing foundation
of SharePlay,
which is already a great way
for groups of people
to enjoy content together
while apart.
This includes simple UI patterns
for understanding
what everyone is doing,
shared control of the content,
and independent control
for how the experience
appears on your own device.
Shared context,
available in SharePlay sessions
with Spatial Personas,
allows for an even more
immersive SharePlay experience.
Picture yourself sitting
in a living room
in front of a TV with friends.
If someone is to your right,
you are to their left.
Everyone is free to move
around the room,
and anyone can control the TV.
It's always clear
who is controlling the TV
because everyone is seeing
the same thing as everyone else.
This is what we mean
by shared context.
Shared context also allows us
to communicate effortlessly.
For example,
you can see Jay
is not paying attention
to the movie.
He's clearly distracted
by his phone.
He can point at things
or use gestures
to better communicate.
He can communicate his emotions,
thoughts, and intentions,
using his facial expressions.
You can even tell
by his body language and actions
whether he's calm and relaxed
or stressed and anxious.
Maintaining a shared context in
FaceTime with Spatial Personas
allows us to communicate
more the way we have become
accustomed to in the real world.
In this presentation,
we're going to cover
how to set up the shared scene
for your activity,
key considerations when starting
SharePlay experiences
with Spatial Personas,
how to pick
the seating arrangement
that suits your shared activity,
interactions in shared context
and the role of UI,
and how to present
shared content
when your app
is in a Full Space.
Setting up a SharePlay activity
with Spatial Personas
starts with understanding
the type of experience
you are trying to recreate.
Each type of experience
requires its own considerations
for content placement
and interactivity.
Enjoying media together
might look different from
collaborating
on a presentation together,
which might be different, again,
from an engaging game that
deepens social connections.
Your app can share
up to one window
and one immersive space
at a time through SharePlay.
Once you choose
the type of content
your shared activity
will be built around,
you need to think about
how to organize and present it
in the most
socially desirable way.
Consider the following
when deciding what form
your experience will take.
If you are presenting
your content in a window,
you can think of your window
as being like a communal device
or tool like a TV, a speaker,
a whiteboard, or a table.
People can interact
with your windowed app
in their surroundings
or even pull up environments
like the Moon.
When creating SharePlay
activities in a Full Space,
you can create
a more immersive experience,
but people won't be able to
interact with their other apps
at the same time.
You can think
of these experiences
like a dedicated room --
this degree of control and focus
is useful for content like games
and media experiences.
And keep in mind,
on this platform,
people can easily have
many windows open.
In SharePlay, every window
is marked clearly by the system
with "shared" or "not shared."
Putting your activity
in a window
is a great way to support
multitasking and collaboration
and doesn't require people
to leave their surroundings.
Using a windowed shared
activity enables workflows
like dragging and dropping items
into your activity.
You could even have more than
one window from your own app,
enabling for example,
dragging and dropping songs
from a private music library
to a public player window.
Next, let's talk about
how someone
would join your shared activity.
As on other platforms,
you can include entry points
to SharePlay within your UI.
For example,
in the TV app,
any Play button can be used
to start a shared activity.
The platform makes it easy to
start or stop a shared activity
from the top of any window.
People can share any window
with no additional effort
from your app,
similar to macOS.
But for richer, more volumetric
visuals or group interactivity,
you will want
to adopt SharePlay.
When possible,
don't launch any extra windows
unrelated
to the shared activity.
If your app requires an account,
consider making shared
activities work without them.
Minimize the amount of setup
involved in joining.
If your shared activity
does need additional steps
to get started,
start the activity
for people who have
the right permissions
and present a placeholder window
to those who don't.
This signals what the rest
of the group is doing.
The window should allow the
person to open anything needed
to resolve any issues.
As soon as the person has met
the minimal requirements
to participate,
close any extra windows
and reveal the activity
to the participant,
exactly where the placeholder
was the whole time.
When someone begins
a shared activity in FaceTime,
everyone already on the call
automatically joins,
which adjusts where
everyone is seated
and makes your app
visible for everyone.
Where your app is positioned,
where people sit around it,
and where a new person shows up
when they join
are all defined by one of three
seating arrangements
that the platform offers
and your app can choose from.
We call these
Spatial Persona Templates.
For scenarios where
it's important for everyone
to have a good view
of your app's content,
choose a side-by-side template
where people sit
shoulder to shoulder.
For an activity that resembles
a tabletop experience,
choose the Surround template,
where your app's content
is placed in the middle
of a circle of people.
People can converse over your
app while looking at its content
from their own unique
perspective.
And for scenarios
where your app is ambient
or doing something
in the background
and conversation
is front and center,
choose a Conversational
template.
Not everyone gets a good angle
of your app's content,
so make sure
if you choose this,
your activity doesn't
rely on everyone
getting to interact with it.
Your app can create
a SharePlay experience
that supports up to four other
Spatial Personas.
Your app is responsible
for scaling what it presents
to any number of participants
ranging from two to five.
For example, if you choose
a Surround template,
you should design your content
around the fact
that there might be up to five
seats around the table.
And of course,
life isn't just about work
or content consumption.
You can just hang out
in a relaxing place
with friends and family
and enjoy quality time together.
You should also choose
the surround template
when there's nothing to present
in the middle of the group.
Next, my colleague Jay
will take you through
how your content and
user interface should adapt
when you bring people
into a SharePlay experience.
Jay: Thanks, Carnaven.
Conveniently for you,
the platform
takes on the responsibility
of making your app,
your participants,
and their spaces
share a common coordinate system
and frame of reference
that we call "shared context."
This means
you don't need to manage
the synchronization
of the size, position,
and orientation of your scenes.
While we maintain the illusion
that everyone is looking
at the same app,
your app is actually running
separately on multiple devices,
and each instance
could display audio,
visuals, and UI differently.
Your app manages
the interactions, feedback,
and choice of content
displayed on each device
to make everyone feel like
they're looking
at the same thing.
Your app needs to synchronize
everyone's view of content,
showing animations and any
state changes in lockstep.
This is key to making
gestures like pointing
make sense to everyone
on the call.
It's possible that your
shared activity might work
both as a window and as
a more immersive experience.
You should encourage everyone
to be in the same mode
by having everyone follow
the first person to transition.
Spatial Audio
is a great tool for adding
more shared spatial context
to your app.
When everyone
is in the same environment,
everyone shares
the same audio context
so the group can hear
the gentle lapping of a lake
coming from the same direction.
A shared music player window
will sound as if it's a speaker
positioned in the space
with you.
In your app, you, too, can make
sound come from your app window
or as part of a more
immersive soundstage
that everyone
can navigate together.
Once you've established
shared context,
we can actually
get away with less UI.
If you're used to SharePlay
on iOS,
you might be familiar
with how the system communicates
when someone has done something
that affects
everyone's experience.
We do this to simulate
a sense of presence while apart
and to understand
why something might have changed
without your intervention.
Remember that we can perceive
more of each other's actions
naturally in FaceTime
on this platform,
especially when they involve
large physical motion,
and we have the ability
to verbally resolve
small moments of confusion.
You can lean on in-person
communication
to close any knowledge gaps,
so you don't need much UI,
if any, to communicate
why something has changed.
SharePlay activities
feel most like their real-life
counterparts when people
feel free to interact with
everything they see.
Avoid the temptation to create
complicated permissions systems
or turn-taking mechanisms
if they aren't a natural
part of your experience.
Consider instead being very
permissive with interactions,
and impose a consistent
and predictable way
to resolve conflicts.
You can lean on the group
settling on norms
that arise from bumping up
against these rules.
While it's important to share
as much context
across devices as possible,
look for opportunities
for software
to improve
on the physical limitations
of real-world
social experiences,
especially when it comes
to comfort and accessibility.
For example, some people have
different volume preferences,
or different abilities
to parse language.
So in TV, I can set
my own volume level
without affecting
someone else's.
And people who have trouble
hearing dialogue
can still enjoy a show
at the same time
as someone who'd rather not
see subtitles.
Throughout these
personalizations,
the same content will still be
played back at the same time,
so no one is missing context.
Collaborative work can take on
a different form on this device.
By necessity, we're all used
to sitting at different devices
even when we're working
on the same thing.
We look at our own view
of content
and edit one area of a document
while a coworker edits another,
often leaving notes along
the way to call out changes.
On this platform,
collaboration experiences
can be more lively
with a shared view
that everyone works on.
This also allows you
to guide the group's attention
with gestures.
In real life,
we can use different tools
at the same time.
So while people may be
looking at what feels like
the same app window,
it's important to allow people
to be in different
editing modes.
This means the tool
each person has active
should also be personalized,
so just because
you're marking in red
doesn't mean someone else
is stuck doing the same.
As always,
keep the main viewport --
the shared context --
the same for all participants.
If individuals want
to separately dive in
on another part of the document,
you could always
allow each person
to open a personal window,
as if they brought
their own iPad to the meeting.
Opening multiple windows
can allow individuals
to focus on their own edits
while still keeping
the shared context
open for everyone else.
Finally, we'll discuss
when it's appropriate
for a participant
to leave a shared context
and enter a Full Space
on their own.
There's a ton of content
designed for this medium
where there's only
one ideal viewing position.
In these cases,
it may be appropriate
to separate people
into different contexts.
For example,
the magical spatial captures
you can photograph in Head Set
can be shared as a window
side by side with everyone
else's Spatial Personas.
But to get the full effect
of the capture,
you can enter a Full Space.
This Full Space view
is best seen head-on,
so we don't allow
side-by-side viewing
and hide other people's
Spatial Personas.
Think of these moments
as if each person
has temporarily
entered their own room.
Similarly, panoramas,
180-, and 360-degree videos
are designed to curve around
a single point of view,
so Spatial Personas
should also not be visible
when you enter this mode.
You should make sure
context remains shared
by continuing to synchronize
everyone's position
in the video.
Another good reason
to leave a shared context
is for individual safety.
Someone may want to step out
of an immersive experience
temporarily.
People can always
press the Digital Crown
to return to passthrough.
When this happens,
find a way to continue
representing the shared context
in a window
and make it easy
for the participant
to rejoin shared context
once they're done.
When done right, even when
someone has to dip out,
they should never feel lost
about where the rest
of the group is.
In summary, design how your
activity begins for everyone.
While the system provides
a stable coordinate system
for all participants,
your app is also responsible
for sharing as much context
as possible.
Depending on how complex
your app interactions are,
personalized control
can be necessary
for comfort and accessibility.
In-person nonverbal cues
can take the place
of state-change notifications
in your UI.
And designing a great
shared spatial experience
often comes down to knowing
when and how to diverge
from shared context.
Apps on this platform
really shine
when they can be enjoyed
with others.
We encourage you
to build your app
with these social experiences
in mind.
Carnaven: Thanks for watching.
[CLAP]
♪