[light music]
Hi, I'm Kartik,
from Car Experience Engineering,
and welcome to "Optimize CarPlay
for vehicle systems."
Today, we're thrilled to share
how your vehicle can deliver
the best CarPlay experience to drivers.
If you're an automaker or developer
of vehicle systems,
this is the session for you.
CarPlay is the smarter, safer way
to use your iPhone in the car.
A large part of what makes
a great CarPlay experience
is how effectively you integrate CarPlay
in your vehicle.
Today's session consists
of 5 topics to help you achieve this.
Visual integration is all about making
CarPlay look and feel natural
in your system.
Then we'll cover
CarPlay infrastructure advancements
in connectivity, audio,
and video encoding,
which all serve as the backbone
of a great CarPlay experience.
And in our final topic,
we'll go over EV routing in CarPlay.
Last year, we gave a sneak peek
of the next generation of CarPlay.
The infrastructure advancements
we're introducing today
will help prepare your system
for the next generation of CarPlay.
Let's get started
with visual integration features.
Modern vehicles feature
large main displays
with an increasing variety of shapes
and layouts.
Some displays are wide,
while others are tall.
Some displays are non-rectangular,
and some show it all,
by featuring a mix of CarPlay UI
and built-in vehicle UI.
CarPlay is designed to integrate well
into all these variations
of main displays.
Let's see how you can tailor CarPlay
to make it feel at home in your vehicle.
In a previous WWDC video, we introduced
the CarPlay view area.
Today, we're building upon this concept.
The view area defines the boundaries
where CarPlay draws its UI.
CarPlay looks great in full screen.
However, your built-in vehicle UI
may have additional layouts
where CarPlay appears alongside widgets
or other elements.
In this case, support
dynamic screen resizing
so people can seamlessly switch
between layouts.
If your system displays
a widget next to CarPlay,
CarPlay automatically insets itself
to create more visual spacing
with your built-in UI.
You don't need to inset the view area;
simply give it as much space as possible,
and CarPlay will create
the right amount of padding.
What if your display is non-rectangular?
In this case, define the view area
as the smallest rectangle enclosing
your display.
Also, define a safe area
as the largest rectangle
within your display.
CarPlay draws interactive content
inside the safe area
to ensure all important UI is visible.
Outside the safe area,
the pixels are black.
Now you have the option to enable CarPlay
to draw UI outside the safe area.
CarPlay will draw its background
to the edge of your display,
giving the driver a visually appealing
and immersive experience.
Keep in mind that this safe area flag is
only available for the main display.
Let's turn our attention
to the CarPlay status bar.
The CarPlay status bar is permanently
displayed in CarPlay's UI,
providing the driver with convenience
at all times.
The status bar is intelligently positioned
based on your display's resolution
and aspect ratio.
It can appear vertically,
on the driver side,
or horizontally,
along the bottom edge of CarPlay's UI.
In some cases, it may make sense
to override the status bar's position
for a better fit with your system's
built-in UI.
This can be done
with the view area flag.
For example, you may want to align
the status bar
with other permanent controls
in your system's UI.
The status bar also features
some slick rounded corners.
We love how rounded corners look
on CarPlay,
and corner clipping masks help
with their visual appeal.
Let's start with some context.
By default, the background
of CarPlay's rounded corners
appear in black.
This looks great
when CarPlay is full screen.
Here's a system where CarPlay is drawn in
a window.
If you look at the corners
of CarPlay's UI,
you can see the black background
showing behind CarPlay's rounded corners.
These small black triangles now appear
which may not blend well
with your system's wallpaper.
By supporting corner clipping masks,
your system can magically make
these black triangles disappear.
The way this works is,
iPhone provides
a corner blending mask
containing transparency information.
Your vehicle system applies this mask
to each corner of CarPlay's UI
to remove the black triangles.
Then you can draw your background
all the way up
to CarPlay's rounded corners.
This makes CarPlay truly blend
into the built-in system
and create great visual appeal.
Take note that corner clipping masks
cannot be used
when CarPlay draws outside the safe area.
It's time to shift our focus
onto the next feature, UI focus transfer.
Some systems support a rotary knob
or touchpad as an input device.
As the driver interacts with CarPlay
using this input device,
CarPlay UI shows a focus highlight
on the selected element.
Your system may show
its own focus highlight
as the driver scrolls
through the built-in UI.
CarPlay supports focus transfer,
allowing the driver to seamlessly move
between UI elements
in CarPlay and your system.
The driver can simply nudge the knob
to transfer focus.
Our APIs ensure
that only one focus highlight
is shown at a time
by arbitrating focus
between CarPlay and your system.
Support focus transfer if your system
presents CarPlay
in a windowed configuration
and supports a knob or touchpad.
Let's walk through how focus is
coordinated using the CarPlay protocol.
When CarPlay starts,
the built-in system determines
if focus should be given to CarPlay.
Here, you can see focus belongs
to the system.
When the driver directs
focus towards CarPlay,
the system dismisses focus
and provides heading
and position information to CarPlay.
CarPlay uses this information
to present its focus highlight
on the most intuitive UI element.
When the driver directs focus
back to the built-in UI,
CarPlay offers focus to the system.
If the system acquires focus,
CarPlay dismisses its focus
and the system presents
its own focus highlight.
Adopt UI focus transfer
to create continuity
between CarPlay and your built-in UI.
Let's talk
about CarPlay appearance mode.
CarPlay UI can appear in either light
or dark themes.
This brings the familiar
light and dark UI experience
which people love on iPhone.
Synchronize CarPlay's appearance
with your built-in UI appearance.
People will appreciate seeing CarPlay
and your system in harmony.
CarPlay's appearance can change based
on vehicle state, user settings,
and time of day.
For example, if your system
shifts to a dark theme at night,
your system simply informs CarPlay
to change appearance based on time of day.
And if your system activates night mode,
CarPlay will automatically shift
into a dark appearance.
There is also a separate appearance mode
control for Map UI.
Let's walk through a few examples
to illustrate how all this works.
In this example, the built-in UI is using
a dark theme on the main display.
The system informs CarPlay to use
a dark appearance mode
to create a consistent look.
If your system shows CarPlay navigation UI
on the instrument cluster,
specify the appearance for each display.
In this case, both the main display
and instrument cluster
are in a dark UI theme.
If your system shows
different appearance modes per display,
inform CarPlay to match.
And lastly, CarPlay's map UI has
a separate appearance setting.
Keep your eyes on the instrument cluster
as we shift into a light map appearance.
Be sure to synchronize
CarPlay's map UI appearance
with your built-in system's
map appearance.
Now that we've covered synchronizing
UI appearance with your system,
let's look into what kinds of content
iPhone can power
across your system's displays.
We'll be covering three common kinds
of displays in modern vehicle systems:
the main display,
the instrument cluster display,
and a head up display.
Let's review the iPhone content available
today for each of these displays.
On the main display,
show the CarPlay video stream.
In addition, your system’s built-in UI
can be powered with iAP2 metadata
like route guidance, phone call,
and now-playing information.
If your system presents a map widget,
populate the widget
with a CarPlay navigation UI stream
while CarPlay navigation is active.
This UI stream can be configured
to present ETA information,
speed limit signs, and a compass.
On the instrument cluster, you can show
CarPlay navigation UI streams.
If your system has controls to change
the map zoom level
on the instrument cluster,
add CarPlay map zoom support.
And implement your built-in UI
with iAP2 metadata
as you would on the main display.
On the head up display, use iAP2 metadata
so people can view information
like turn-by-turn directions
in their line of sight as they're driving.
Let's look under the hood
at infrastructure features
to create a reliable and performant
CarPlay system.
Ultimately, these changes will also set
your system up
for the next generation of CarPlay.
Our first topic is all about connectivity
between iPhone and your vehicle system.
The wireless connection experience begins
when a driver pairs for the first time.
Make the first-time-pairing experience
easy for drivers
by supporting out-of-band pairing.
Out-of-band pairing allows people
to pair their device for wireless CarPlay
by simply plugging their iPhone
into the car.
It's convenient and requires
less interaction.
People expect all wireless CarPlay systems
to support out-of-band pairing over USB.
If your system supports digital car keys,
we've got something new for you.
Starting with iOS 17,
iPhone supports pairing for CarPlay
over a car key connection.
This makes pairing even easier for people,
as car key and CarPlay pairing experiences
combine into a unified flow.
After adding a car key on iPhone,
people are prompted to pair
for wireless CarPlay.
If accepted, pairing occurs
over the car key connection,
and CarPlay connects wirelessly.
After performing a one-time pairing,
your vehicle automatically connects
with iPhone
every time the driver enters the car.
Bonjour is used for your vehicle
and iPhone
to establish an IP connection
and start the CarPlay session.
We've introduced
a simplified connection flow
which is the preferred way
to connect CarPlay.
By using the existing iAP2 connection
to perform IP address
and port information exchange,
Bonjour is no longer needed,
and the implementation is simpler
and faster.
This also adds support
for WPA3-only networks.
The simplified connection flow can connect
with devices running iOS 14 or newer.
If your system is designed to connect
with earlier iOS versions,
continue to support
the Bonjour connection flow.
For those of you who support car keys,
we're back with another feature.
Your system can instantly connect
to wireless CarPlay
as soon as the driver enters the vehicle
with a digital car key.
Using iAP2 messages, your system can map
a digital car key pairing
to a CarPlay device.
The next time a driver approaches
the vehicle
and a car key connection is created,
your system prepares its CarPlay stack.
By checking for a corresponding
CarPlay pairing with that car key,
you can start CarPlay even earlier.
To the driver, CarPlay appears instantly.
We are so stoked for you to make use
of this in your next system.
And let's not forget, we all agree
on how important a robust connection is
to create a reliable CarPlay experience.
To maintain a robust CarPlay connection
in your system,
design for handling wireless interference,
as interference may impact
Wi-Fi performance.
The first step is to detect interferers
on the wireless channel.
Once interferers have been detected,
steer clear of the interference
by using channel switch announcements.
If your system supports
multiple wireless radios,
you can use BSS transition management
to direct iPhone
onto another access point.
Keep in mind that people
best experience wireless CarPlay
when operating on the 5 GHz band.
And finally, to create
a smoother experience
during intermittent disconnects,
your system should suppress
short link disconnects
on CarPlay TCP sockets.
Do not close these sockets
due solely to a data link layer
disconnection.
After connecting to your system,
CarPlay can start playing audio
through the vehicle's speakers.
Let's go over some audio features
that are available to your system.
Audio apps are now adopting
AirPlay enhanced audio buffering
to provide a greater playback experience
on iPhone.
People would love to experience
the same audio improvements
in your vehicle as well.
Now, you can add support
for enhanced buffering to your system,
and your vehicles will automatically take
advantage of these benefits.
Enhanced buffering
is the preferred platform
for streaming audio like music
to your car's speakers.
The audio is provided
as an additional stream
to the vehicle system,
called main buffered audio.
The CarPlay communication plugin contains
an up to 2 minute audio buffer,
where audio from iPhone is streamed
in faster than real-time speeds.
This makes for improved responsiveness,
and audio content can continue playback
through an intermittent disconnection.
You may want check out
"Tune Up Your AirPlay Audio Experience"
for more details on what's available
to audio app developers.
People expect audio mixing in CarPlay
to work as it does on iPhone.
Ensure your system can mix
various audio output streams
to create a consistent audio experience.
Main audio, main buffered audio,
alternate audio, and auxiliary audio
can be active and mixed simultaneously.
Enhanced Siri brings
the familiar Siri experience on iPhone
to CarPlay.
People are accustomed to saying "Siri"
in order to activate Siri,
and they expect it to work in CarPlay
as well.
Ensure your system supports Enhanced Siri.
Enhanced Siri leverages
the vehicle's microphone
to reliably detect when the driver
is activating Siri by voice.
Also, audio apps and radio are mixed
into the background of Siri audio.
People love the resulting
uninterrupted audio experience.
And lastly, it enables the driver
to instantly activate Siri
upon pressing the push to talk button.
See "Advances in CarPlay Systems"
for a detailed look at how Enhanced Siri
can work in your system.
Let's move on to video encoding.
Historically, CarPlay UI streams
have used H.264 encoding.
CarPlay now supports HEVC encoding
for all UI streams.
HEVC is more efficient and enables CarPlay
to support higher-resolution displays.
Your system should continue to support
H.264 for backwards compatibility.
All of these connectivity, audio,
and video encoding features
will make the experience so much better
for drivers.
For that reason, they are required
for systems supporting
the next generation of CarPlay.
We have just enough range
to cover our final topic: EV routing.
Apple Maps can help you plan trips
that include stops for charging
your electric vehicle.
When you get driving directions, Maps
analyzes the route and other factors,
and identifies charging stations
along the way.
This year, in addition to support
for offline maps,
EV routing has some great updates.
Users can now tell Maps
which charging network they prefer
and see real-time charging station
availability on the map.
To support EV routing,
Apple Maps needs to know
about some characteristics
of your electric vehicle
to tailor the EV routing experience.
In addition, you will need to support
interfaces to communicate
your vehicle's state of charge.
If you have an automaker app,
support SiriKit intents so people can use
EV routing
when inside or outside the vehicle.
In addition, you should support
iAP2 messages
for real-time state of charge
when driving.
We've made it through all the ways
you can enrich the CarPlay experience
in your vehicle system.
Soon, you may want your next vehicle
to support the next generation of CarPlay:
the ultimate iPhone experience
for the car.
It brings a fully integrated, immersive
iPhone experience to your vehicle.
The next generation of CarPlay
builds on CarPlay
and fully utilizes
the infrastructure changes
we covered in this video.
Prepare your vehicle
for the next generation of CarPlay
by supporting these features
in CarPlay today.
The features we discussed today
are available
in the latest CarPlay specification
and communication plugin.
For more information
on developing CarPlay systems,
visit developer.apple.com/carplay.
We're excited for you to make the most
of what CarPlay offers
in your next vehicle system.
Thank you so much for joining us today,
and keep riding on with CarPlay.
[light music]