♪ ♪
Cody: Hi, and welcome to
"The SwiftUI cookbook for focus."
I'm Cody, and today I'll be discussing
some of the things that you can do with
focus APIs in SwiftUI
to cook up a really great user experience.
In this video,
I'll serve up a three-course meal
from a fixed menu of tasty API details
paired with a series of
fine code examples.
As an appetizer, I'll spend some time
reviewing the very basics of focus:
what is it, and what job does it do?
For the first course, whet your palate
with a look at the ingredients
that make the focus experience.
With those ingredients laid out,
I can really start cooking.
For the main course, I'll dig in to some
recipes for controlling focus appearance,
observing focus movement,
and responding to keyboard input
with custom controls.
So, what is focus?
Focus is a tool for deciding
how to respond when someone
presses a key on a keyboard,
swipes on an Apple TV Remote,
or turns the Digital Crown on their watch.
These input methods have
one important detail in common.
On their own,
they don't provide enough information
to identify which on-screen control
their input is intended for.
Compare this with things like mice,
and trackpads, and touch screens.
When you use a mouse or trackpad,
the on-screen cursor associates
your clicks with screen coordinates
that the system uses to find
the target of the interaction.
Focus provides the extra information
that the system needs
to direct input without a pointer cursor.
When a view has focus, the system will use
it as a starting point for responding to
input from keyboards, Apple TV remotes,
and Apple Watch Digital Crowns.
Focus isn't just an implementation detail.
It's equally important to
the people using your app,
which is why the focused view
is presented with special emphasis.
macOS automatically adds
a border around the focused view
to show that it will receive
keyboard input.
watchOS draws a green border
around controls
to signal that the control's value can be
changed by rotating the Digital Crown.
And on tvOS, the focused view
receives a hover effect
that lifts it above
the plane of other controls.
Emphasizing the focus view
helps people in a couple of ways.
They can anticipate where
their input will go
when they type on a keyboard
or swipe on the remote.
And in a complex or detailed layout,
it reminds people at a glance
which part of the app
they're interacting with.
Focus behaves a lot like
a special kind of cursor.
Instead of tracking a point on screen
like a mouse cursor does,
it tracks which part of your UI
is the target for focus input.
For this reason, I like to think of focus
as a cursor for the user's attention.
Now that you know a little about what
focus is and how it appears in your app,
I can lay out the first course,
a look at the basic ingredients that
go into every app's focus experience:
focusable views,  focus state,
focused values, and focus sections.
The main ingredient to consider
when cooking with focus
is the focused view itself.
This is the view the system uses as
its starting point
when responding to focus input.
Different controls are focusable
under different circumstances,
and for different reasons.
Compare text fields and buttons
on macOS and iPadOS.
Text fields are always focusable,
whether you tap on them
or you press the Tab key to move focus
from a previous control.
This kind of control supports focus
for editing,
because its role is to capture
continuous focus input.
Buttons are different.
Their job is to handle clicks and taps.
macOS and iPadOS don't give focus
to buttons when you tap them,
and the only way to reach them with
the Tab key is to turn on
keyboard navigation system-wide.
If you aren't familiar with this setting,
you can find it in the Keyboard settings
pane of macOS System Settings.
It's the switch labeled
"Keyboard navigation".
After flipping that switch, I can press
the Tab key to focus on buttons,
and press the Space bar to activate them.
Buttons support focus for activation.
These controls don't require focus
to do their job,
but they'll take focus
if the system allows it,
in order to support focus-driven
alternatives to clicking and tapping.
In iOS 17 and macOS Sonoma,
there are new APIs for custom controls to
participate in the focus system.
When you apply
the "focusable" view modifier,
you can now fine-tune
the resulting behavior
by specifying the kinds of
focus interactions your control supports.
For controls that use focus
to update state over time,
specify edit interactions.
For controls that use focus as an
alternative to direct pointer activation,
specify activate interactions.
If you don't provide any arguments at all,
the system gives the control focus
for all interactions.
Prior to macOS Sonoma,
the focusable modifier only supported
activation semantics.
If you're already using the focusable
modifier in your macOS code,
verify that the new behavior suits
your use case.
You may need to update your code
by adding an "interactions" argument.
The next ingredient relates to the state
of the focus system from moment to moment.
This ingredient is aptly named
"FocusState".
The system keeps track of
which view has focus,
and the app can use that information
in its logic
to determine how to handle input
and how to style views.
To observe the state of the system,
you create bindings that associate values
that you provide
with focus being on a particular view.
Views can read these bindings to
get notified when focus changes,
such as a view becoming focused,
or when focus is dismissed.
Focus state properties with Boolean values
will tell you if a single view is focused,
as shown here.
For more complex cases,
you can also use custom data types.
Later, I'll discuss an example of this,
and show how focus state can be changed
programmatically.
Next up, the Focused Values API.
The Focused Values API solves the problem
of how to build data dependencies
that link remote parts of
your user interface.
Use this API to update your app's commands
based on what's happening
in the active scene.
Focused values enable data flow
between these different elements.
I'll define a custom one and use it to
build my main menu content.
Creating and using focused values is
similar to creating and using
custom environment keys and objects.
You define a new key using
the "FocusedValueKey" protocol,
and then extend "FocusedValues"
with a computed property
that uses the new key to
get and set values.
The data you use comes from
your scene's views,
and can be a value, a binding,
or an observable object.
In any case, you use a family of
view modifiers to associate the data
with focus being in that part of
the view hierarchy.
As with environment values,
you access your focused values by
declaring a dynamic property.
In this example,
my focused value is a binding,
so I use the "@FocusedBinding"
property wrapper
and provide it with my custom key path.
"@FocusedBinding" looks at
the focused view and its ancestors
to see if there's currently a binding
associated with the key.
The property wrapper automatically
unwraps the binding
so I can work with
the bound value directly.
The only other thing I need to do is
use my new property in the view's body.
Over time, as focus moves
between different controls
and different windows become active,
the system will update the view to reflect
the values it finds in the new context.
The last ingredient is
the Focus sections API.
Focus sections give you a way to influence
how focus moves when someone
swipes on an Apple TV Remote
or presses the Tab key on a keyboard.
By default,
focus starts on the top-most control
that's closest to
the leading edge of the screen.
From there, pressing Tab moves focus from
one control to the next,
following the layout order
of the current locale.
When you reach the last control on
the screen,
pressing Tab again will restart
the sequence.
Focus movement with an Apple TV remote is
directional.
You can swipe up, down, left, and right
to move focus between controls.
Directional movement only works
between adjacent targets.
In this example, I can swipe right
from the Creme Brûlée button
to one of the other desserts.
But if I want to add creme brûlée fixings
to my grocery list, I can't swipe down.
That button isn't directly beneath
the creme brûlée button,
so my gesture fails.
To make these focus targets line up,
I'll mark the bottom button's container
as a focus section.
Focus sections become targets for
movement gestures,
but they don't become focusable.
Instead, they guide focus towards
the nearest focusable content.
To be effective, the focus sections have
to take up more space than their contents.
In this case, I'll add spacers
before and after the button
to make the stack grow
to fit the width of the screen.
With the larger focus target in place,
I can now swipe down from anywhere
to reach the bottom button.
I can taste that creme brûlée already!
I'll take you through
some recipes that combine
the staple ingredients I just described
to polish the look and feel
of custom controls
and remove friction from common tasks.
Recently, I've been using a cookbook app
made by my fellow chef Curt.
You may recognize it from
his WWDC22 video.
The recipes in this section are based on
some new features I've been working on
that will benefit from some attention to
focus behavior.
For instance,
I've added an in-app grocery list
to help me remember what to get
on my next trip to the grocery store.
This first recipe shows how
a dash of programmatic focus movement
can make editing my grocery list
a delightful experience.
When the grocery list sheet appears,
it always has an empty item at its end.
Tapping on the empty item brings up
the keyboard
so I can describe what I need to buy.
Adding groceries is a frequent task,
so I'd like to save myself a tap
by putting focus on the empty item
automatically whenever the list appears.
Earlier, I showed how to use
the Focus State API
to observe and update
which view has focus.
I'll use the same API here.
The previous example used a flag
to signal whether a single view had focus.
In the case of my grocery list, there are
any number of text fields to observe.
FocusState's value can be
any Hashable type for cases like this.
Each ingredient I add on this screen
has a unique ID,
and I can keep track of focus
by storing the ID associated
with the focused text field.
I'll use the "focused(_:equals:)" modifier
to make the link between each text field
and its ingredient.
I need to provide this modifier with
two arguments:
a binding to my "focusedItem" property
and the ingredient ID that
the binding should be updated
with, when focus is in that text field.
I can now run the app and verify that
the "focusedItem" property is updated
with different ID values
when I tap around the grocery list.
With my focus state binding in place,
I have what I need to programmatically
move focus to the text field
when the grocery list first appears
on screen.
I do this by adding
the "defaultFocus(_:_:)" view modifier
to my list,
which is now also available in iOS 17.
When the system is evaluating focus
for the first time on this screen,
it will try to update my binding with
the ID of the last grocery list item.
With these changes, adding to my grocery
list is now a two-step process.
Tap the toolbar button to present
the sheet,
and then start typing.
There is no step three.
As my shopping list grows,
I notice that tapping the Add button in
the toolbar creates a new empty list item,
but focus remains where it was.
I have to tap the empty item
to give it focus.
This is another case where I want
the app to move focus programmatically
so that I can start typing as soon as
the new item appears.
The difference is that now I want to be
in control of the timing of the change.
Happily, I can use the same focus state
binding that I created
for setting default focus.
In my GroceryListView,
I have an "addEmptyItem" method
that adds a new item in my model.
And since I've already associated
the new item's TextField
with the "currentItemID" property,
I just need to update the property with
the new ID
as part of my toolbar button action.
Voilà!
Now when I want to start
or update my grocery list,
I don't have to tap anything
to put focus where it needs to be,
I can just start typing.
Next up, let's use some more of
the ingredients
to improve the focus interactions for
a custom control that I've created.
At this point,
I've cataloged a lot of recipes.
As I try each one out, I want to remember
which ones come out well
and which might need some re-thinking,
or at least a little more salt.
To help with this, I've built
a custom picker control with emoji
to capture the highs and lows of
my culinary journey.
I can rate each recipe
by tapping on an emoji,
but as someone who lives
the keyboard navigation lifestyle,
I'd really like to be able to focus on the
control with the Tab key
and use the arrow keys
to change the selection.
Let's make that happen.
Here's the basic structure of
my emoji picker:
The first thing I need to do is make
the control focusable.
I start out by adding the "focusable"
modifier with no arguments.
This makes my control focusable
when I press the Tab key,
but I notice some additional behavior
that I don't see with other buttons
and similar controls.
My control, for example,
gets focus on click,
whereas buttons
and segmented controls don't.
Those controls require "Keyboard
navigation" in order to be focused.
Mine should, too.
To get that behavior,
I'll specify my control
as being focusable for activation.
Controls that are focusable for activation
don't get focus on click,
and they need "Keyboard navigation"
turned on
to receive focus with the keyboard.
The next thing I notice is that
the focus ring that macOS draws around
my control is rectangular.
For a more polished look,
I want the focus ring to follow the path
of the capsule-shaped background.
Focus rings always follow
the content shape of a view,
which is a rectangle by default
in my case.
I'll use the "contentShape" modifier
and pass in the same Capsule shape that
I'm using to visually clip the view.
Now that my control is focusable, the next
step is to have it handle key presses.
I want to be able to use
the left and right arrow key
to change the chosen rating.
Using the "onMoveCommand" modifier,
I can provide an action to perform
in response to
a platform-appropriate move command,
like when arrow keys are pressed
on a Mac keyboard,
or the directional edges are tapped
on an Apple TV remote.
The system calls the action with
the direction of movement,
so I'll move the rating selection
left or right based on that.
Control content should flip horizontally
for folks using
a right-to-left language
like Arabic and Hebrew.
Make sure your move command action uses
the Environment's "layoutDirection"
to account for this.
One of the neat things about implementing
focus behavior is that
I can take the same control and get
a great result in my Apple Watch app.
To handle focus input on watchOS,
I use the "digitalCrownRotation" modifier
instead of the "onMoveCommand" modifier.
And I'll use the isFocused
environment value
to draw the familiar green border
around the control when it has focus.
With just these few modifiers,
I was able to take a simple control
and add support for keyboards
and the Digital Crown.
The last recipe is for
a focusable grid view
that I've been building to showcase the
pictures I've been taking
of my finished results.
I'm building this as a lazy grid,
and I've already implemented
some selection behavior.
So clicking on an image selects it
and double-clicking goes to
the recipe's detail view.
Now I need to consider how
it should handle focus interactions.
Specifically, I want the grid to be
focusable when I press the Tab key.
When focused, I want the arrow keys
to update the selection,
and I want the Return key to take me
to the selected recipe's details.
I'll use several of the ingredients
I talked about before,
plus a few extra ones
to help me handle key presses
and customize how the grid appears
when it has focus.
As in previous examples, the first step is
to make the grid focusable.
In this case,
I don't need to specify any interactions.
By default, the grid will take focus when
I click on it
and when I use the keyboard to tab to it,
whether or not
"Keyboard navigation" is enabled.
This is exactly what I want.
Now that I've made the grid focusable,
the system automatically
draws a focus ring around it.
For containers of selectable content,
the effect is redundant.
The colored border I add around
the selected recipe already communicates
whether the grid has focus.
I can use
the "focusEffectDisabled" modifier
to turn off the automatic focus ring.
Use "SelectionShapeStyle" for borders and
other indicators that a view is selected.
It automatically adapts to
my chosen accent color,
and it turns gray when
none of its ancestor views have focus,
like when focus moves from
the grid to the sidebar.
The next thing I want to do is hook up
a main menu command
for marking the selected recipe as
a favorite.
I'll use the Focused Values API for this
and I'll pass in a binding to my selection
for my menu commands to update as needed.
To support arrow key selection,
I'll use the onMoveCommand modifier.
And when the system calls,
I'll use the movement direction
to update my grid's selected recipe.
Lastly, I want a way to act on
the selection
and navigate to it when
the Return key is pressed.
I can do this with
the "onKeyPress" modifier,
which is new in macOS Sonoma and iOS 17.
This modifier takes a set of keys or
characters and an action to perform
when any of those keys are pressed on
a connected hardware keyboard.
Return "ignored" if the action
didn't handle the press
and dispatch should continue up
the view hierarchy.
And for a bonus feature, I'll also use
"onKeyPress" to implement Type Selection,
so I can quickly scroll to
and select a recipe
by typing the first letter of its name.
Now that I've built a great keyboard
experience for my grid on macOS,
let's turn to the grid on tvOS.
On tvOS, each cell in the grid
is focusable,
so that as focus is moved in
different directions with the remote,
the cell in that direction becomes focus
and visually lifts above the others.
The system uses the "lift" hover effect by
default with Buttons and NavigationLinks.
And this effect is appropriate for
views with text
or those combining text and images.
However, these recipe photos would benefit
from a different effect.
New in tvOS 17, I can apply the highlight
hover effect to my focusable views.
This effect adds a perspective shift
and specular shine to the focused item
as I swipe the remote,
and it looks great with artwork and
photos, like my recipe thumbnails.
And as a cherry on top for my tvOS app,
I'll add focus sections.
The grid is next to a list of buttons,
and I'll often need to navigate between
these two groupings.
When using the app,
I notice a familiar problem.
When focus is on one of
the lower rows in the grid,
I can't swipe left to move
the category buttons,
because the focus targets
aren't adjacent to one another.
I'll place the category list in
a focus section that spans
the full height of the layout.
Now as I swipe left from the Creme Brûlée,
focus moves to the categories,
just as I would expect.
And the grid is complete.
Bellisimo!
I covered a lot of ground in this video.
It's time to gather up
your focus ingredients
and see what you can make.
Test your macOS and iPadOS apps
with keyboard navigation enabled.
Place default focus where it will be
most useful.
Organize your controls in focus sections
to help guide movement through
irregular layouts.
Thank you, and bon appétit!