♪ ♪
Jacob: Hi, I'm Jacob.
The UIs we build
continue to grow more dynamic,
with change and motion everywhere.
People love this.
It makes an interface feel more alive,
makes it easier
to understand what's happening,
and it just brings a sense of enjoyment
to interacting with a UI.
And there's a lot that comes together
to make these dynamic interactions.
There are transitions,
where we move from one scene to another.
And there are gestures, where we're
directly interacting with the device.
And finally, there are animations,
where an on screen object moves,
grows, or changes visual properties.
These all work together
and help to make a fluid, interactive UI.
Today, we're going to dive deep
into building great animations.
Differences between animations
can be subtle,
but when an animation is just right,
your users can feel it.
So I want to share with you how
to make the animations in your app
feel elegant and natural.
And we're going to do that
focusing on just one tool
that's powerful, versatile,
and even fun:
springs!
We'll start by discussing why springs
are a good fit for animations.
Then we'll go into some of the details
of how springs work.
And finally, we'll talk about
how to use springs in our apps.
So why are springs useful for animations?
To answer that, we need to step back
and discuss what makes a great animation.
Let's examine a context
where we have a few animations:
a simple toggle.
Let's focus in on this toggle.
We use animations for several reasons,
but one of the most important is that
they give us a better sense of continuity.
If an object starts in one place,
and then suddenly appears somewhere else,
it feels jarring,
and can sometimes be confusing.
It feels much more natural
if we see the object move
from one place to the next.
But it's not just about the position.
If an object's velocity suddenly changes,
that also feels unnatural.
For example here, the knob in the toggle
is starting and ending
with a jump in velocity,
and it doesn't feel right.
So one goal we have
is to make our animations
have continuous position and velocity.
Let's look at a few animation types
and see how they do with that requirement.
And while our toggle is a useful example
of a complete animation,
I want to focus in
on just the motion of the knob,
so it's easier to see what's happening
in just a single animation.
Let's start by looking at Ease in and out.
This is a type of Bezier curve animation,
which means that its motion is defined
by a combination
of a curve and a duration.
Looking at the motion of this object,
it doesn't feel like
there are any sudden jumps.
To make sure this is the case,
we can also examine a chart
of the motion in this animation.
We're going to look
at several of these charts,
so let's discuss what it's showing.
The horizontal axis represents time,
the bottom line shows the initial position
of the animation,
and the top line
shows the target position.
And as we play the animation on repeat,
we'll repeatedly progress
through this curve.
Now let's start the animation again.
Notice how the curve in the chart
doesn't have any jumps,
that means that its position
is continuous.
And if we update our chart
to show the velocity as well,
we can confirm that the velocity
doesn't have any jumps either--
so the velocity is continuous as well.
If we look at the motion
of a linear animation instead,
there's a sharp corner
and a jump in velocity
as the animation starts and ends.
Linear animations can be useful
as a specialized tool in some places,
like a repeating spinning indicator,
but otherwise you should be cautious
about using them,
especially for movement,
where it has this non-physical behavior
that generally feels out of place.
Next, let's check the continuity
of a spring animation.
Just like we want, this has continuous
position and velocity as well.
So far, ease in and out and
spring animations are our best options,
but we've only been looking at cases
where the animations start
from a resting position.
Let's examine what happens if we use
a gesture together with an animation.
Let's take our movable knob
over to an iPad,
where we'll drag it with our finger.
We can drop it on either
of these two positions.
But we could also end the gesture
somewhere in between
and throw our knob towards one side.
With an ease in and out animation,
it does animate to the end,
but its motion jerks to a halt
as the gesture ends.
This type of animation
is just a prespecified curve,
so there's no way
to represent an initial velocity.
This gets even worse
if we also allow our knob
to be dragged to any position
in 2 dimensions.
Let's try this again,
but with a spring animation.
A spring can start
with any initial velocity,
so we get a natural feeling
where our animation picks up
right where the gesture ends.
And this also works great
for two dimensional drags.
SwiftUI will now automatically
track velocities
any time a gesture is changing properties,
so you can get this behavior
without any extra work.
So springs are the only type of animation
that maintains continuity
both for static cases
and cases with an initial velocity.
The next benefit of springs we can examine
is the shape of their motion.
When you hear the motion of a spring,
you might be thinking
of something like this.
But a spring animation
doesn't only mean a bouncy animation.
It's true that springs can have bounce,
and that can be a great tool,
but that's not the main reason
we use springs.
Later on,
we'll look at when it makes sense
to use a spring with bounce,
but springs with no bounce are great too!
These types of non-bouncy springs
are used in animations all over iOS.
So if it's not just about bounce,
what is so good
about the motion of a spring?
Let's look again
at our simple spring animation,
and pay attention
to how the animation ends.
It very slowly and gradually
comes to rest.
There's no single point
when the object is abruptly done.
This feels much more like
what we'd expect to see
if this was an object
that was moving and stopping.
And there's a reason this version
feels more natural to us.
A spring animation is based on the
behavior of an object attached to a spring
in the physical world,
so it feels more natural
and believable to our eyes
when we see it move.
Now you may have heard that different
properties animating with springs
can finish at different times,
which is true.
If you're used to timing curve animations,
this may feel strange.
Don't we want all animations
to start and stop at the same time?
The answer is no!
We want our animations
to feel like the motion of objects
in the physical world that we're used to.
And generally,
these start and stop at their own time
as they're slowed down by friction,
so these times
usually don't line up perfectly.
In fact, it's sometimes useful to go even
further for multi-property animations.
Here's an animation
of an app launching on iOS.
At first glance, it may seem
like just a single uniform animation,
but if we slow down the animation,
you can see how different springs,
different start times,
and different end times come together
to form an incredible
and naturally feeling animation.
So now that we know why springs
are such a great tool for animations,
let's examine springs more closely
to understand how they work
and how best to use them.
When we use a spring animation,
we're modeling it with the motion
of an object attached to a spring.
If we go back to physics,
this motion is defined by 3 properties:
the object's mass,
the spring's stiffness,
and the damping of the system,
which is a measure of how much friction
is applied to the object
by its surroundings.
Then we use the initial position
of the animation
as the initial position of the object,
and the target position of the animation
to define the resting position
of the spring,
where the object will get pulled towards.
Then we can release the object
to start the animation.
The properties we use
to define the spring system
determine the type of motion that occurs,
and changing them
changes the resulting animation.
So when creating a spring animation,
you could use these same properties
of mass, stiffness, and damping
to configure what kind of spring to use.
But while these are a natural way
to model a physical system,
they're not very intuitive
for defining a spring animation.
There isn't a real object with mass
or a spring with stiffness here,
and making up these values
to change the curve is not easy to do.
So we've been refining a new way
to configure springs
that's easier to understand
and to work with.
It uses just 2 parameters:
duration and bounce.
These do what you'd expect,
increasing the duration
makes the animation take longer.
And increasing the bounce
adds bounce to the animation.
And we're adopting these universally
across Apple's design
and engineering efforts.
So all of our frameworks
that support springs will use them.
As you play with these spring parameters,
you can see different types of shapes
in the curves.
When bounce is greater than 0,
we get a bouncy spring
that overshoots its target.
When bounce is 0,
we get this smooth curve
with a long tail
gradually going towards its target.
And there's one other type of spring too.
This one isn't as common,
but with a negative bounce value,
you can get a spring that also has a long
tail gradually approaching its target,
but that's a little flatter than
what you get with a bounce of 0.
In the physics of springs,
these are called underdamped,
critically damped, and overdamped springs.
But I like to think of them
as bouncy, smooth, and flattened.
And as you may have noticed,
these bounce values are percents,
so bouncy springs have bounce values
up to 100%
and flattened springs have bounce values
between 0 and -100%
Now I want to dig into these springs
a bit more.
Springs can sometimes seem
a little intimidating,
and their motion
can seem hard to understand.
But if we break down what's happening,
it's actually just several simple things
combining together.
For me, being able to understand
the math that's behind these curves
helps make springs feel more approachable,
so I want to share that with you as well.
But if math just makes your head spin,
don't worry,
it's completely optional.
We implement all of this math for you.
So let's start with a bouncy curve.
You may notice
that the overshooting of this spring
oscillates like a more complicated
kind of sine or cosine wave.
And if we take the bounce of this spring
up to its maximum value of 100%,
you can see that it's now
exactly the behavior of a cosine wave,
just oscillating back and forth.
The physical interpretation of this
is that it's a spring
that has no friction acting on it,
so it oscillates forever
without slowing down,
and never actually reaches
its target position.
As you'd expect,
the math for this is pretty simple:
it's just a cosine curve,
and the time is divided by the duration.
So for this bounce value,
the duration corresponds exactly
to the period of the curve.
As we decrease bounce,
that's physically equivalent
to adding friction
or damping to the spring,
which slows it down as it goes.
And we still have those oscillations.
In fact, the cosine curve from before
is still there,
which is more clear
if we draw it overlaid on top.
This is the same equation as before,
just with different constants
and shifted horizontally a bit.
So this explains
the bounciness in the curve,
but clearly
we need something else as well.
In the original curve,
the size of the oscillations
is getting smaller,
or decaying, over time.
And that's the piece that's missing.
This additional curve
is an exponential decay curve.
And it's the last piece of our motion,
the part that gives us
the gradual feeling of coming to rest.
So what seemed like a complicated curve
is just the product
of these two components,
which is called a damped cosine
or sine wave.
That's pretty satisfying,
but if you look closely at the chart,
there's one thing that might seem
a little strange:
why does our cosine curve
now have this dip at the beginning?
This is related to something
we discussed earlier:
preserving velocity.
Remember that for this base case,
we need to preserve a velocity of 0
at the beginning.
So the velocity of the product of our two
component curves should be flat around 0.
But notice that our decay curve
starts with an upward-pointing slope.
If we started off the cosine curve flat,
then our initial velocity
would point upwards too.
So our cosine curve has to start off
pointing downwards
to cancel out with the decay
and give us our flat start.
And this is how springs
are able to match any initial velocity
by using different shifts and scales
in our cosine curve
to give us the right start.
This initial velocity can come from
the velocity of a gesture
as it ends and hands off to an animation,
as we discussed earlier.
And there's another place
where this initial velocity can come from.
Let's examine it on an iPad.
Here, we can tap to move our knob,
and show a fainter image of the knob
at its target position.
We'll also use a slower spring so it's
easier to keep track of what's happening.
Sometimes, while an animation
hasn't yet finished,
a new animation begins
that changes to a new target value.
When that happens, a spring animation
uses the velocity it had
when it was retargeted
as the initial velocity
towards its new destination
and this same velocity preservation
makes these kind of interruptions
feel smooth and natural.
So that's how velocity preservation
and bouncy springs work.
Now if we decrease our bounce,
the oscillations get farther
and farther apart,
until when bounce gets all the way to 0,
the oscillations are completely gone
and we just have a straight line
going down and away
that's getting multiplied by our decay.
So these equations are even simpler.
We just need the basic equation of a line,
and then we multiply that
by the same exponential,
giving us our resulting curve.
Flattened curves,
which are springs with negative bounce,
work very similarly,
but using two exponential functions
added together instead of a line.
This type of spring is less common,
but the fact that it's represented
by just exponential decay
makes it useful
for modeling decaying velocity,
like what happens in a scroll view.
One thing you might wonder
when using springs for animations is:
How long does it take until
a spring animation actually finishes?
As we've seen,
that question is a bit subtle.
The exponential decay of the spring
means that technically
it keeps moving forever,
just with smaller and smaller movement.
Of course, we don't want our spring
animation to keep going forever,
so we do need to choose a time
to remove it,
when it no longer contributes
any noticeable change to the UI.
That amount of time until a spring
animation is finished enough to remove
is called the settling duration.
This settling duration is different
from the duration parameter
for configuring a spring.
The settling duration depends
on many different factors,
so can be a bit unpredictable,
but the duration parameter
is a perceptual duration
that is chosen to be predictable
and not move around,
even as the other parameters
of a spring change.
Because of its unpredictable nature,
you shouldn't wait for the settling
duration for user-facing changes.
If you want to make a UI change
when a spring is mostly done,
you can use the new
completion handler support in SwiftUI,
which uses a perceptual duration
instead of a settling duration.
Now that we know
all about how springs work,
let's discuss using them in our code.
Because springs are such
a great tool for animations,
we now use them
as the default animation in SwiftUI,
so all you need to do is call
withAnimation to start with a spring.
We've also made it easier
to explicitly use springs for animations.
We've built in a few spring presets
based on spring values
that are used in iOS.
If you're not sure
what spring parameters to use,
these are a great way
to get something that feels good.
You can use these in code
by directly using the preset
when you need an animation.
But an important part of using
a spring animation is tuning it
for the exact context you need,
so these presets can also be used
as tunable starting points.
You can take a preset and specify
that its duration should be different,
Or give it a little more or less bounce
by specifying a relative amount
of extra bounce to add.
These presets are a great way to get
started introducing springs into your app.
But if you want to go further,
you can also make a completely
custom spring with the .spring animation.
This lets you fully specify the duration
and the bounce of the spring.
And these bounce values have
a range from -1.0 to 1.0.
You can also use these same parameters
to create spring animations
in UIKit and Core Animation.
There's another new spring tool you can
use if you want to go even further.
We've added a Spring model type to SwiftUI
that lets you create a representation
of a spring, including its parameters.
This lets you programmatically
convert parameters
between the different ways
to specify them.
You can also create a spring model
with a set of parameters, like mass,
stiffness, and damping,
and then use it
as a spring animation directly.
But if you really want to do
a conversion yourself,
here are the three equations to convert
from bounce and duration values to mass,
stiffness, and damping.
In addition to converting parameters,
you can use spring models to build
your own advanced spring behaviors.
You can call methods on the spring
to get the built in spring evaluation math
for yourself.
For example, you can call value
to get the position of the spring.
You just pass in a target,
which is what the spring
is moving towards,
and the time you want to evaluate it at.
You can also use the same inputs
on a velocity method
to evaluate the spring's velocity over
time.
This lets you easily use springs
in your own code,
which can be useful for simulations,
or to get values for charts,
like the ones in this session.
You can even use this
to build your own custom animations.
Just call into the spring model,
and you can modify the inputs or outputs
to apply customization
to a spring animation.
Check out Explore SwiftUI animation
to learn the details
of making a custom animation.
One last thing I want to discuss
is how to choose parameters
to use for your springs.
To choose a value that works great
for your animation,
it's generally best to start
by finding a duration value
that gives a pacing that you like.
Once you've decided that, you can start
adjusting the amount of bounce
to choose what kind of character and
feeling you want this animation to have.
You'll find that different bounce values
feel qualitatively different.
A bounce of 0 feels like
a smooth, gradual change.
A small bounce, like around 15%,
doesn't feel very bouncy yet,
but the long tail
feels a little more brisk.
And for larger bounce values like 30%,
you do start to feel
some noticeable bounciness.
If you go even further, you can get
a pretty extreme amount of bounciness.
But you should be cautious
about using values higher than around 0.4,
since they may feel too exaggerated
for a UI element.
So which bounce value
should you actually use?
When you're not sure,
use a spring with bounce 0,
which is also what you get
if you don't specify the bounce.
This gives you a great general
purpose spring that's the most versatile.
Then if you want your animation
to feel a little more playful,
you can start to add some bounce.
Bounce can also make sense when you want
an animation to feel more physical,
like if it's going to be used
at the end of a gesture.
And one thing you should keep in mind
is consistency.
Think about what kind of character
your app has.
Is it serious or playful?
Should it feel relaxed or fast-paced?
That can help you choose
spring values that feel consistent
with the feeling of the UI around them.
So that's a quick tour
of using springs for animations.
Remember that a spring doesn't need
to bounce to make a great animation.
There's also a new set of spring presets
that are great starting points,
but you can use duration and bounce
to customize when you need to go further.
And most importantly,
after seeing all the unique advantages
that springs have,
I hope you're excited
to use spring animations
to make your app feel fluid
and a joy to use.
Thank you.
♪ ♪