♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hello, my name is Yujin,
and I'm an engineer
on the RealityKit team.
Today, I'm going to show you
new features in RealityKit
that you can use to enhance
your spatial computing apps.
Since the time we released
RealityKit in 2019,
We've seen apps
use its rich feature set
to create some
amazing experiences.
Now spatial computing adds even
more features to RealityKit,
like portals, particle emitters,
RealityView attachments,
and many more.
In the session titled
"Build spatial experiences
with RealityKit,"
we learned about the basic
building blocks of RealityKit:
entities, which are
container objects;
components, which define
specific behavior on entities;
and systems, which act on
both entities and components
to add functionality.
We covered
the RealityView API,
which acts as a bridge between
SwiftUI and RealityKit.
We also showed you how to add
interaction, animations,
and Spatial Audio
to your RealityKit scene.
If you haven't
watched it already,
I highly recommend
that you check out that session.
In this session, we will cover
new features in RealityKit
that will help make your app
even more engaging
and immersive.
First, we will learn how
to embed SwiftUI views
into our RealityKit content
using attachments
in RealityView.
Next, we will look at
how to add video playback
within our RealityKit scene.
Then we will learn
how to use portals
to open a window
to an alternate world.
We'll go through how to use
the Particle Emitters API
to enhance your scene
with visual effects.
Finally, we'll learn how to use
anchors in RealityKit
to attach 3D content
to real-world locations,
such as a wall.
Let's get started
with RealityView attachments.
Attachments are a useful way
to embed SwiftUI content
into your RealityKit scene.
In this example app,
I've used attachments
to put text labels
beneath the models
of the earth and moon.
I've also attached a view
that explains how the moon
affects tides on our ocean.
Let's see how to make this
in code.
Inside of my app,
I'm using a RealityView
to render my earth model.
A RealityView is a view that
lets us add RealityKit entities.
Entities need to be added
to a RealityView
in order to be rendered,
animated, and simulated.
Here we simply
load an entity for the earth
and add it
to the RealityView's content.
Let's now change our RealityView
to use attachments.
Attachments are views that can
be placed at specific locations
relative to your
RealityKit content.
There are two parts
to setting up attachments.
First, there's the added
parameter
in the make closure
of our RealityView.
Second, there's an attachments
view builder
that is added
to our RealityView.
Let's cover the attachments
view builder first.
Here you can provide
SwiftUI views
that you want to add
to your RealityKit content.
In this example, I've added
a text view to label the Earth.
We'll also add a tag modifier
to the view
so that we can later identify it
when our view gets delivered
to the make closure
as an entity.
This tag can be
any hashable value.
Here I've used the string
earth_label.
In the make closure
of our RealityView,
the attachments
parameter contains our views
that are now represented
as entities.
To get our view in entity form,
we call entity(for:)
on our attachments
and pass in the same tag
that we provided in the view
builder, earth_label.
The result that we get
is a view attachment entity,
which we can add
to our RealityKit content,
just like any other entity.
To make the label appear
beneath the earth,
we'll add the attachment
as a child of our earth entity
and position it slightly below.
We can now repeat this process
for all the other attachments
we want to add
using a different tag for each.
Let's take a look in Xcode.
In my sample app, I'll add three
attachments to my RealityView.
First, I'll add a label
below the earth.
I'll also do the same
for the moon.
Finally, I'll add
a short paragraph
explaining the role of
the moon's orbit on the tides.
I've styled this using
a glassBackgroundEffect
in SwiftUI.
In the make closure
of the RealityView,
I'll add the corresponding
entities to my content.
First, I'll add
the earthAttachment
below the earth.
I'll do the same for the moon.
Finally, I'll place
the tides explainer
to the left
of my container entity.
I'll build and run my app,
and we'll see the attachments
that I've created
displayed next to my models.
Let's recap the data flow
for attachments.
Attachments start off in
the attachments view builder
in our RealityView.
Here, we can provide
SwiftUI views
that we want to add
to our RealityKit scene.
In the make closure
of our RealityView,
we get the attachments back
as entities,
which we can then
add to our scene.
We can also update the entities
inside of the update closure.
This closure is called
when there are changes
to our SwiftUI view state.
You can use this to respond
to dynamically changing content
in your RealityView.
For a more detailed usage
of attachments,
check out the session
"Work with Reality Composer Pro
content in Xcode."
RealityView attachments
are a useful way
of adding text content in
other UI elements to a scene.
Additionally, we can also
add a video to our app
to make it more engaging.
To do this, let's use
VideoPlayerComponent.
Video player component is a new
component type in RealityKit
that is used for embedding video
content inside of a 3D scene.
As a reminder, components
define specific behavior
that you can attach to entities.
To play a video using
VideoPlayerComponent,
we'll first load a video file
from our resources bundle.
Then we'll use that to create
an AVPlayer instance.
With it, we can now create
a VideoPlayerComponent.
When you attach
a VideoPlayerComponent
to an entity,
a rectangular mesh
that matches the aspect ratio
of the video
is automatically
generated for you.
This behavior is analogous
to existing video player APIs,
such as VideoPlayer
in SwiftUI
and AVPlayerLayer
in Core Animation.
However, since RealityKit
is a 3D framework,
your video will be represented
as an entity with a mesh
so that you can move
and position it in 3D space.
All video formats that are
supported by AV Foundation
will work with
VideoPlayerComponent,
including 2D video formats
and 3D video using MV-HEVC.
Finally, VideoPlayerComponent
will automatically
display captions that are
provided through the AVPlayer.
To learn more about how to
create your own video content,
including 3D videos,
check out the session entitled
"Deliver video content
for spatial experiences."
To add video
to my RealityKit scene,
we'll first create
an AVPlayerItem
using the URL
to my video asset.
We'll then create an AVPlayer.
On the entity, we'll add
a VideoPlayerComponent
initialized with the AVPlayer
that we just created.
VideoPlayerComponent will
automatically generate a mesh
that is sized based on
the aspect ratio of my video.
Because RealityKit works
in real-world units,
by default, the video
will be one meter in height.
To make the video
a different size,
we can scale the entity.
In my case, I'd like the video
to be 40 centimeters tall,
so we'll multiply the
entity scale by 0.4.
Finally, we're ready
to play the video.
We'll set the current item
to our AVPlayerItem,
and then call play
on the AVPlayer.
Let's rebuild and run our app
with this code.
I've added a Learn More button
to our app,
which will add the video entity
to our scene.
On button click,
I'll fade in the video
using an opacity component
and a fromToByAnimation.
For our video content,
I've prepared a short clip
that explains the role of
the Moon's gravitational force
on the Earth's rising tides.
Let's take a look.
>> The moon orbits our planet.
Its gravitational pull exerts
a powerful force on our oceans,
causing it to bulge
ever so slightly
towards the lunar sphere. <
VideoPlayerComponent respects
the systemwide preferences
for captions.
Let's turn them on
in the Settings app
under the Accessibility section.
>> And so it is, that twice
a day, in a never-ending cycle,
the tides rise and fall, driven
by this unceasing interplay
of earth and moon. <
VideoPlayerComponent also
supports passthrough tinting.
When this feature is enabled,
your passthrough content
is adjusted to match colors
in the video.
This is the same treatment that
is used when watching movies
and TV shows inside
of the TV app on this platform.
To use passthrough tinting,
you can set
the isPassthroughTintingEnabled
property to true.
You can also subscribe to
VideoPlayerEvents to be notified
when properties on
a VideoPlayerComponent change,
such as the content type,
viewing mode, and video size.
To subscribe to events, you can
call the subscribe function
on your RealityViews content
and specify the event type
and entity.
You can respond to events inside
of the event handler closure.
VideoPlayerComponent is a great
addition to our 3D scene.
So far, our app features a model
of the earth and moon,
but I'd like to present it
against a backdrop
of outer space.
I think it would be pretty
cool if we can make ourselves
a magic window in the room
that reveals the moon's orbit
in outer space.
We can do this using
a portal to render our scene.
A portal creates an opening
to a different world
that is visible
through a mesh surface.
Entities inside of this world
use separate lighting
and are masked
by the portal's geometry.
This example demonstrates
three distinct features
in RealityKit.
First, a portal is used to
render the scene in outer space.
Then a particle effect is used
to decorate the rim
of the portal.
Finally, anchoring is used
to place the portal
on the wall of our room.
Let's start with portals.
To make a portal,
we must first create a world.
To do this,
we add an entity in our scene
that has a World component.
This component marks
its entity tree
as belonging
to a different world.
Entities in a world
are only visible
through a portal surface.
To add content to our world,
we can attach entities
as children of the world entity.
Here, we'll add models
for the sky, earth, and moon,
as well as an ImageBasedLight
to define the lighting
inside of the world.
All descendants of the world
entity will appear
only inside of this world.
Next, we'll make a portal.
To do this, we add an entity
with a model component.
The model component
contains two properties,
a mesh and a material.
For the mesh,
we'll generate a circular plane
to act as the surface
of the portal.
For the material, we'll assign
a new portal material
in order to make the mesh
appear as a portal.
To connect the portal
with our world,
we'll add a portal component
to the entity
and set its target property
to the world entity.
This allows the portal
to act as a mask
to reveal the content
inside of our world.
Let's see how this looks
in code.
In our RealityView,
I've added calls
to two functions
that will implement
makeWorld and makePortal.
In our makeWorld function,
we'll create a world entity
and populate it
with the portal's contents.
In the makePortal function,
we'll create a portal
and link it to the world
that we just created.
Finally, we'll add
both of these entities
to our RealityView's content.
Let's dive into
each of these functions.
Inside of the makeWorld
function,
we create an entity
and attach a WorldComponent.
Next, we load
an EnvironmentResource
to use as our ImageBasedLight.
We'll apply this to the world
using the ImageBasedLight
component
and ImageBasedLight
ReceiverComponent.
To learn more about image-based
lighting in RealityKit,
check out the session
"Explore rendering
for spatial computing."
Next, we'll populate the world
with our contents.
I'll load models for the earth,
moon, and sky,
and add them
to the world as children.
Because these entities
are children of the world,
they will only be visible
through the portal.
Let's move on to
the makePortal function.
To make a portal,
we first need a mesh.
We'll create one by making a
model component for the entity.
To make our portal circular,
we'll generate a plane
with equal dimensions
and a corner radius
that is half the size.
I'll also create
a PortalMaterial
to use as a material
for the ModelComponent.
Finally, we'll also attach
a portal component
that is initialized
with the world entity
that we created earlier.
This links the portal
with the world
so that we can see the world's
contents through the mesh.
Next, let's decorate
the rim of the portal
with a particle effect.
To do this, we can use
the ParticleEmitterComponent
provided in RealityKit.
Particle emitters
can be used to represent
many different visual effects
in RealityKit,
such as sparks, snow,
and impact effects.
Particle emitters can be created
either via Reality Composer Pro
or at runtime using RealityKit
through
the ParticleEmitterComponent
Here, I've prepared
a particle asset
using Reality Composer Pro.
We can use this to decorate the
portal that we created earlier.
Let's load this into our scene
and modify
the particle properties
at runtime using RealityKit.
To update the particles
over time,
I've created a custom system
called
ParticleTransitionSystem.
Here, we'll use an EntityQuery
to find entities that have
a ParticleEmitterComponent.
Inside of the system update,
we'll perform our query
and iterate
over the resulting entities.
On each entity, we'll call
the function updateParticles,
which we will implement next.
To learn more about
custom systems in RealityKit,
check out the session
"Build spatial experiences
with RealityKit."
Inside of our
updateParticles function,
we'll first get the
ParticleEmitterComponent
from the entity.
The ParticleEmitterComponent
contains many properties
that control various aspects
of particle look and behavior.
Here, we'll set the lifeSpan
and vortexStrength properties
based on the entity's scale,
so that as the entity
grows in size,
the particles start spinning
faster around the portal.
Finally, let's apply our changes
by assigning the component
back to the entity.
And we are set.
To learn about all
the different properties
on particle emitters,
check out the session
"Meet Reality Composer Pro."
We're almost done adding
the final touch to our app.
To finish, let's attach our
portal to the wall in our room.
To do this, we can use anchors
in RealityKit.
Anchors can be used to place
content on walls, floors,
or locations relative
to your head or hand.
Anchors in RealityKit
support two tracking modes,
.continuous and .once.
When using the
continuous tracking mode,
the anchor entity moves along
with the anchor over time,
such as when your head moves.
When using
the once tracking mode,
the anchor entity will not move
after being positioned once.
To listen to when an entity
becomes anchored,
you can subscribe to the
AnchoredStateChanged event
in RealityKit.
Note that while you can use
anchors to parent entities
to place 3D content,
explicit transforms
of the anchors themselves
are not visible to the app
to preserve user privacy.
To get access to anchor
transforms,
you will need to use ARKit.
For more information on this,
check out the session,
"Meet ARKit
for spatial computing."
To use anchors in our app,
we first need to modify our app
to use an immersive space.
An immersive space
is a special type of container
that allows your app to render
content outside of the window.
To do this,
we can add an ImmersiveSpace
to our SwiftUI scene.
We'll also add
an .immersionStyle modifier
and set it to mixed.
Inside of the ImmersiveSpace,
we can use a RealityView
to place content
that will be anchored.
To learn more about Immersive
Spaces, check out the session
"Go beyond the window
with SwiftUI."
Inside of our RealityView,
we can use an anchor entity
as a container for our portal.
We initialize an anchor entity
with a specification
of the type of surface
that we would like
to anchor our content on.
In our case, we are looking
for a vertical wall
with a minimum size
of one meter by one meter.
When an anchor is found
that matches the specification,
RealityKit will automatically
attach our content to the wall.
And we are finally done.
When we run our app,
we get a portal
that is attached to the wall.
From portals and particles
to anchors and attachments,
RealityKit provides
many features
that let you build
immersive experiences.
Let's summarize everything that
we went over in this session.
Attachments in RealityView
let you embed SwiftUI content
inside of your entity hierarchy
so that you can
place UI elements
alongside 3D elements.
VideoPlayerComponent, portals,
and particle effects let you add
dynamic elements to enhance
your scene in RealityKit.
Finally, anchors let you
attach 3D content
to real-world surfaces
such as your floor or wall.
The session "Build spatial
experiences with RealityKit"
goes over key concepts
like entities, components,
and RealityView.
The session "Work with Reality
Composer Pro content in Xcode"
takes you through the process
of building an immersive app
using Reality Composer Pro
together with RealityKit.
I can't wait to see
all the things you'll create
using these new features
in RealityKit.
Thank you for watching.
♪