♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Howdy, I'm Chris.
I'm an engineer
on the AVFoundation team,
and I'd like to welcome you
to our session.
In this talk, we're going
to look at how to prepare
and deliver streaming content
for spatial experiences.
We'll start with a brief review
of the current steps
in producing, preparing,
and delivering 2D media
using HTTP Live Streaming.
also known as HLS.
With 2D content preparation
and delivery covered,
we'll turn
to 3D video content --
what's supported and updates
to the steps just described.
Considering
the content pipeline,
we'll start with media encoding
of video, audio, and captions.
Then, those media resources
need to be packaged,
ready for HLS delivery.
This is how 2D content
is delivered today.
The goal of delivering
3D content
is to build upon current
2D processes.
HLS adds new support for
fragmented MP4 timed metadata
that allows
an important adaptation.
Please note
the HTTP Live Streaming page
on the Apple Developer website,
which provides links
to documentation, tools,
example streams,
developer forums,
and other resources.
This is where more details
covered in this talk
will be made available
over time.
Our goal is that delivering
2D audiovisual content
to this platform should be the
same as all our other platforms.
This is achieved by building
upon Apple Media technology
such as HTTP Live Streaming,
AVFoundation, Core Media,
and standards-based formats
such as the ISO-based
media file format,
often thought of as MPEG-4.
This is done all
while supporting
a new spatial
experiences paradigm.
For a deep dive into how
to best support playback
of audiovisual media,
see the session
"Create a great spatial
experience for video playback."
For video,
encode the source video.
Edit it to the right length
and color correct it
for the bitrate tiers
that matter to you.
Here you'll make choices
of how you configure
and use video encoders
such as HEVC,
short for High Efficiency
Video Coding.
While support for existing
2D audiovisual media
you deliver to other Apple
platforms is fully supported,
take note of these
playback capabilities.
This platform supports playback
of up to 4K resolution,
allowing your highest-quality
video to be experienced.
The display's refresh rate
is 90 Hertz,
And for 24-frames-per-second
video,
a special 96-hertz mode
may be used automatically.
There's support for standard
and high dynamic range.
For your video's
corresponding audio,
identify and produce the number
of source audio streams
you need.
The number depends upon
the set of spoken languages
you are targeting
and the roles of that audio.
One role might
be main dialogue,
another, audio descriptions.
Encode these sources
for delivery with HLS in mind.
You may want to deliver
Spatial Audio,
along with a fallback
stereo audio track.
This ensures a great experience
for those devices
supporting Spatial Audio and
reliable playback everywhere.
The HLS Developer page
has links to documentation
on preparing audio.
And then there are captions.
Here, captions includes both
subtitles and closed captions
to cover different
languages and roles.
The term "subtitles"
is used for transcriptions
of spoken text
providing translations
in different languages
for viewers
that may not speak the language
or for establishing
the settings time and place.
Closed captions is like
subtitles but is intended
when the audio can't
be heard by the viewer.
Close captions provide
a transcription
of not only the dialogue
but also of sound effects
and other relevant audio cues.
There might also be subtitles
for the Deaf
and hard of hearing, SDH,
serving the same purpose.
Akin to video
and audio encoding,
you should produce
caption files and formats
supported by HLS,
most commonly WebVTT.
With source video, audio,
and captions in hand,
next comes packaging.
Packaging is a process that
transforms the source media
into various types of segments
for reliable delivery.
This can be done
with Apple's HLS tools
available at the earlier
HLS streaming page.
Some content providers might use
their own production tools,
hardware, or workflows.
Others might be vendors
delivering those services
and tools to the first group.
The goal of packaging is to
produce a set of media segments,
the media playlists
that drive their use,
and a multivariant playlist
that ties them all together.
Two kinds of HLS media segments
are most typically used today.
Fragmented MP4 media segments
are produced by starting
with an already encoded movie
file of video or audio
and generating
a number of resources.
These resources are known
as media segments.
It is these segments
that are retrieved
by client devices
during playback.
Subtitle files also
require segmenting.
This is done with
a subtitle-segmenting tool
to generate media segments.
A source WebVTT file may
be split into any number
of WebVTT files for
the target segment duration.
Finally, the collection
of HLS resources
is hosted on a web server
for HTTP delivery.
This might be to one server
that serves clients directly
or to an origin server used
with a content delivery network,
or a CDN.
Either way,
it is these resources
that are delivered
to client devices for playback.
Now that we've reviewed
the 2D production
and delivery pipeline,
let's turn to 3D content
and the differences
taking advantage
of new spatial capabilities.
We will again look
at source encoding,
packaging, and delivery,
focusing on differences
between 2D content
and 3D stereoscopic content.
So, we're talking
about 3D video.
Let's deconstruct this term.
First, it's video,
so a sequence of frames
in a movie track
or a network stream.
The "3D" in "3D video"
is used interchangeably
with stereoscopic,
which provides an image
for the left eye,
and another very similar image
from a slightly different
perspective for the right eye.
These differences between
the left and right images,
called parallax,
causes you to perceive
three-dimensional depth
in the video when presented.
While there are choices in how
3D video frames might be carried
there are some guiding
principles that seem useful.
By using a single video track
for all stereo frames,
traditional production with
2D video tracks is preserved.
Both the left and right
images or views,
for any display time is
in a single compressed frame.
If you have a frame
in your hands,
you have both views
or the stereo pair.
It should be efficient,
ideally, it's supported
by Apple silicon,
and to the greatest
degree possible,
it should be decodable
by non-3D-aware playback,
allowing the video to be
auditioned in 2D workflows.
To deliver stereo frames,
we introduce the use
of multiview HEVC,
also called "MV-HEVC."
It's an extension of HEVC.
The "MV" is multiview.
Carrying more than one view
in each frame,
each frame has a pair
of compressed
left and right images.
Because MV-HEVC
is HEVC at its heart,
Apple silicon supports it.
In MV-HEVC stores
the base HEVC 2D view
in each compressed frame.
Encoding determines
a difference, or delta,
between the left
and right images.
This technique,
known as 2D Plus Delta,
means that 2D decoders
can find and use
the base 2D view,
for example the left eye.
But 3D decoders can calculate
the other view
to present both views
to the corresponding eyes.
Efficiency is achieved
because the differences
between base 2D images
uses standard HEVC techniques,
and just the differences between
the left and right eye views
are described
in the stereo frames.
The video format description,
or the visual sample entry
in MPEG-4,
indicates the coding type,
the codec,
the dimensions of each view,
and other details necessary
to decode the video frames.
A new extension
to the video format description
is introduced.
Termed the
Video Extended Usage box,
it serves as a lightweight,
easily discoverable signal
that the video is stereoscopic,
and which stereo eye
views are present.
For HLS delivery, this will be
both left and right.
A specification describing
this new VEXU box
is available with the SDK.
Its structure will evolve,
and that will be described
in the specification.
Like 2D content,
3D video uses HEVC,
except this time,
the variation called MV-HEVC.
This is required to carry
the stereoscopic views.
Like with 2D production,
local movies with MV-HEVC
can be used and should behave
like other 2D video.
Having both a left
and a right image
presented to
the corresponding eye
produces a perception
of stereoscopic depth,
providing a sense
of relative depth.
An object in the video scene
might be perceived nearer
or farther than another
due to the differing amounts
of parallax.
Three primary zones
of stereoscopic depth
can be defined.
They are the screen plane
with no parallax cues;
negative parallax,
which will cause objects
to be perceived in front
of the screen plane;
and positive parallax,
which will cause objects
to be perceived
behind the screen plane.
If an element like a caption
is rendered with no parallax
in the same area of the frame
as negative parallax cues,
then a depth conflict
will be created
and cause discomfort
when viewing.
Question.
Given stereoscopic parallax and
potential for depth conflict,
how involved is producing
captions for 3D video?
Can we support the following?
Playback works
for horizontal captions,
playback works
across languages,
including for vertical captions,
and playback works
when accessibility settings
is used to adjust the user's
preferred caption sizing.
Well, the answer is yes.
With stereoscopic video using
the approach I'll next describe,
captions should just work as is,
while also allowing
the same 2D caption assets
to be shared between
2D and 3D experiences.
This is possible by including
the new timed metadata
I mentioned earlier.
With stereoscopic video,
avoiding depth conflict
and visual elements overlaying
the video is important.
Instead of requiring
new caption formats
or changes to existing formats,
we offer a way to characterize
each video frame's parallax.
This can vary across the frame
with some areas
apparently closer and some
farther from the viewer.
We call this a parallax contour,
and it is recorded as metadata
in a metadata track
that is synchronized
with a video track's frames.
If we tile the 3D video
and indicate the depth parallax
for each tile,
we can use that to ensure
that captions never interfere
with elements
in the stereo video.
During playback,
the parallax of the caption
will be automatically adjusted
to avoid depth conflict.
Each metadata item with such
a parallax video contour
describes a 2D tiling
of the associated video
with the minimum parallax
value associated with each tile.
Each video frame's presentation
should be associated
with a metadata item describing
the video frame's contour.
We recommend a 10 by 10 tiling
as a good balance
between storage and resolution
to characterize
different areas of parallax
in the video.
Considering how this parallax
metadata is produced,
start with left and right views
for each frame.
This can be done in production
with two synchronized
video tracks
and doesn't require MV-HEVC.
Then, perform parallax
or disparity analysis to create
parallax information suitable
for describing the tiling.
For each stereo frame,
this is then packaged
in a metadata payload
for the next step.
A specification describing
the format of this metadata
is available with the SDK.
This parallax information is
packaged in metadata samples
and written into a timed
metadata track.
The metadata track
will be associated
with the corresponding video
it describes.
The metadata and video track
should be multiplexed
with the video so that
HLS packaging will produce
video segments with both the
video and the parallax metadata.
Captions you might
already produce for 2D
can be reused with 3D.
This means the processes
used today
or the vendor
you might work with
can continue to work in 2D
with your 3D production.
Also, this means
your 3D content is agnostic
to the choice of languages,
horizontal and vertical layout,
or potential use of
accessibility subtitle
preferences by users.
By adding the described
parallax metadata,
the platform adapts dynamically
to the parallax metadata
you build.
As for audio use with 3D video,
you can use the same audio use
for 2D delivery.
As the platform
supports head tracking,
consider using
a Spatial Audio format.
To share the same audio
between 2D and 3D experiences,
the video should
match timingwise,
having the same edits.
If they differ, you will need
to separate audio tracks
between the 2D and 3D assets.
Turning to packaging of 3D,
updated HLS tools
take care of the details,
with 3D assets
making the process nearly
identical to that with 2D.
Most production systems,
which do not use Apple's tools,
will be able to use the new
specs that are being released
to build equivalent
functionality.
If you're building your own
playlists or inspecting them,
take note of a few changes.
REQ-VIDEO-LAYOUT is a new tag
for video streams
to indicate video
is stereoscopic.
The attribute value indicates
if the video is stereo or not.
Note that if your asset
is loaded as 3D,
it won't switch to 2D
or vice versa.
2D Video is unchanged
and can be mixed with 3D video
in the same playlist.
REQ-VIDEO-LAYOUT requires
a new version of the HLS spec,
so the version is updated to 12.
This is documented with the SDK.
Here's an example
multivariant playlist
with the change of
the version number to 12,
and using REQ-VIDEO-LAYOUT
for the 3D video stream.
For the best
navigation experience,
you should include
a 2D iFrame stream
to the multivariant playlist
to support thumbnail scrubbing.
Finally, HLS delivery works
the same with 3D assets.
Delivering 3D assets
is largely the same
as delivering 2D assets,
but there are some things
you can do to optimize
the experience.
Prepare your source assets,
noting to use MV-HEVC
for 3D video,
and including the new parallax
contour metadata.
Audio and caption production
can be the same.
Use updated packaging to produce
the relevant segments
and playlists.
Hosting remains the same.
Before closing,
I want to emphasize
that visual comfort is a key
content-design goal
for 3D experiences.
3D content should be
comfortable to watch
for sufficiently long durations.
Some 3D content characteristics
that could potentially
cause comfort issues
include extreme parallax,
both negative and positive,
high motion in the content
causing focusing difficulties;
as well as depth conflicts
resulting from something
termed "window violations."
Screen size may affect
viewing comfort,
depending on how much
of the screen
is in the viewer's
horizontal field of view.
Note that the user can affect
the screen size
by positioning it
nearer or farther.
So in our journey, we've
looked at 2D and 3D delivery
with HTTP Live Streaming.
For video, I introduced MV-HEVC.
For audio, we noted
that the same audio streams
can be used across 2D and 3D.
For captions, the same streams
can likewise be used
across 2D and 3D.
Finally, a new
timed metadata format
is introduced to characterize
the 3D videos' parallax,
allowing the same captions
to be used.
To wrap up, we've made it
as easy as possible
to bring your existing 2D
content to a spatial experience.
With some small modifications
to your current 2D pipeline,
you can support 3D content
using MV-HEVC.
You can even continue to use
all your existing captions
from 2D assets.
But if you provide
timed metadata,
those captions can be
unobscured
and provide a comfortable
viewing experience.
Watch our companion session
for considerations
in implementing
playback of video.
We look forward to the great new
content you'll be delivering.
Thanks for joining us today.
♪