♪ ♪
Jeff: Howdy, I’m Jeff.
I’m an engineer on the MapKit team
and I’m excited to introduce you
to MapKit for SwiftUI.
With our greatly expanded SwiftUI API,
it’s easier than ever
to integrate Maps into your apps
across all platforms.
We think you’re going to love
using MapKit for SwiftUI
to create powerful mapping experiences
for your users.
To show you how easy it is,
I’ll build a fully functional trip planner
from scratch.
I’ll walk you through every step and we’ll
be done before the end of this session.
My family is heading back home
to New England this weekend,
and we’ll spend Saturday
exploring the beautiful city of Boston.
We’ll walk through the city
in the morning and see the sights,
we’ll have lunch
in the historic North End,
and probably grab a cannoli for dessert.
The weather is looking perfect, too,
so we’ll head out to the beach
in the afternoon
and feel the sand between our toes.
It’s gonna be a lot of fun.
I’ll build an app to help us plan the day.
I’ll use annotations
to mark places on the map.
I’ll enable selection so that
I can tap on each marker
to learn more about that place.
I’ll integrate Look Around to explore
some places we might want to visit.
I’ll add an overlay that shows
a driving route to the beach.
I’ll use the map to display
different locations and regions.
I’ll add another dimension to the map
by enabling realistic elevation.
I’ll show you how to display satellite
and flyover imagery as well.
I’ll add some controls to the map,
including a user location button,
so that I can figure out where I am.
We have a lot to cover.
Let’s get right into it!
I’ll start with a brand-new
SwiftUI project.
I’ll be using MapKit.
And I’ll add a Map.
Nice!
I have an interactive map
with just one line of code!
My family will start the day
by driving into the city
and parking so we can walk around.
I’ve heard it said
that there’s a particular place
you should "pahk" your "cah"
near Boston,
but I like the parking garage
right underneath the Common.
Boston Common is a beautiful park
right in the middle of everything,
and it’ll make a fantastic starting point
for our walking tour.
The first thing I’ll do is
add some content to the map
to mark the parking garage.
I’ll mark the spot right above the ramps
that vehicles use to access the garage,
near the elevator we’ll ride up
to start walking.
You’ll learn about using Marker
and Annotation to display content
at a specific coordinate on the map.
So, let’s park the car and start walking!
I’ll use a MapContentBuilder closure
to add a marker to the map.
Cool!
If you’re familiar with SwiftUI,
adding a Marker to the map
feels a lot like adding a View to a List.
Check out how the map has
automatically framed our content
by zooming in to show the Marker.
So what’s a Marker?
Are there other types of content
that I can present
using the content builder?
Markers are used to display content
at a specific coordinate on the map.
The balloon shape
might look familiar to you.
You’ll find Markers used in the Maps app
and across the platform,
including in a wide variety of apps
you can find on the App Store.
Like Marker, Annotation is used to
display content at a specific coordinate.
Instead of Marker’s balloon,
Annotation displays a SwiftUI View.
The content builder can be used
to present overlay content as well.
You’ll learn more about these a bit later.
For now, all you really need to know
is that you can use
the content builder closure
to add all kinds of content to the map.
I want to display a custom SwiftUI view
for the parking spot,
so I’ll use an Annotation to mark it.
Here, I’m using ZStack to compose
some shapes and an image.
This SwiftUI view
will be displayed on the map
centered right on the parking coordinate.
If you’d like your view to be positioned
above the coordinate instead,
you can use Annotation’s anchor parameter.
Specifying an anchor value of “bottom”
will position the bottom of your view
right on the annotation’s coordinate.
All right!
The app marks where
we’ll start our walking tour.
I’ve used a MapContentBuilder
to display annotation content on the map.
Next, I’d like this app to convey a sense
of place as I’m looking at the map.
I’ll use mapStyle to achieve that
by enabling realistic terrain elevation.
You’ll learn how to use mapStyle
to display satellite
or flyover imagery as well.
You can set a style
using the mapStyle modifier.
This is the standard map style.
By default, it offers a flat presentation
much like a physical paper map.
[no audio]
It looks like there’s a bridge
across the lagoon,
so you can walk
from one side to the other.
This flat map really leaves something
to the imagination, though.
I’ll enable realistic elevated terrain
to give the map another dimension
to work with.
[no audio]
Enabling realistic elevation
really brings the map to life.
Looking at the lagoon now,
I can imagine taking a ride
on one of the swan boats
that cruise around in the summer
and picture the boat
passing under the bridge.
Using the imagery map style
is another great way
to offer your users a sense of place.
The imagery map style displays a map
rendered using satellite
or flyover imagery.
The Hybrid map style combines imagery
with roads and labels.
To recap, I’ve enabled realistic elevation
using the standard mapStyle
and I’ve shown you how to use
some other map styles as well.
Next, I’d like the app to help us search
for the places we want to visit.
Our kids will be with us
walking around Boston,
and I want our morning
to be fun for them, too.
The grown-ups
can appreciate seeing some history
while the kids can appreciate swings
and slides and monkey bars!
I’ll add a button
to search for playgrounds,
and a button to search for beaches, too.
The app will add a Marker
for each search result.
You’ll learn
a little bit more about Markers
and you’ll also learn how
to show your own UI above the map
without getting in the way
of the search results.
Earlier today,
I made a little BeantownButtons View.
Tapping a button calls a search function
with a simple query,
either playground or beach.
The search function uses
MKLocalSearch to find places
near the Boston Common parking garage,
and writes the results using a binding.
Back in the app’s main ContentView,
I’ll add State to keep track
of the search results.
When the BeantownButtons UI
performs a search,
it will write the results back
to this state using a binding.
[no audio]
I’ll add the buttons above the map
at the bottom of the screen.
Using safeAreaInset will make
sure the app’s UI doesn’t obscure
any of the content I’m adding
or any system-provided controls
that can appear on the map, such
as the Apple Maps logo and Legal link.
Next, I’ll use the content builder
to add search result Markers.
I'm using ForEach to add a marker
for each search result.
I’ll try these buttons out.
Let’s find some playgrounds.
Look!
Playgrounds!
The map has automatically framed them
by zooming out
so that all of them are visible.
How ‘bout some beaches?
The search results are MKMapItems,
which is the type MapKit APIs
like MKLocalSearch use
to represent places.
Here,
I’m using Marker’s map item initializer.
Markers created this way use
the map item’s name for their title
and use information from the map item
to show an icon and tint color
that represent the place.
Most of these search results show
as light blue beach umbrella markers.
When you’re working with map items,
Marker’s automatic content
and style support is very convenient.
Even if you aren’t using map items,
though,
you still have control over
the Marker’s presentation.
By default, Marker shows a map pin icon
in its balloon, like you see here.
You can provide your own icon
using an Image asset or a system image.
You can also show up to three letters
of text using monogram.
You can change the Marker’s color
using the tint modifier.
To recap, I’ve used safeAreaInset
to display some buttons above the map
while making sure they don’t
obscure the search result markers.
Next, I’m going to put the app in control
of what’s displayed by the map.
I’ve been adding content to the map.
Each time I have, the map has
automatically framed my content for me.
I’ll show you how to enable
this convenient behavior when you need it.
I’ll also show you how to display
something else entirely,
like the Boston area’s
North Shore coastline.
Right now, we’re looking at beaches.
If I pan away
and search for playgrounds...
the map no longer
automatically displays the results
near our Boston Common parking spot.
To display the search results after
the user has interacted with the map,
I’ll need to re-set
the Map’s camera position state
so that the map will frame the markers...
so, I’ll add state to track the position.
I’ll use the default automatic position
that frames the content
we’ve added to the map.
And I’ll pass the binding
to Map’s initializer.
[no audio]
I’ll use an onChange modifier to find out
when the search results are updated.
When they are,
I’ll simply set the camera position back
to automatic to make sure they’re visible.
Let’s give it a try.
I’ll search for beaches,
see the results...
and then pan away before
searching for playgrounds.
Cool!
Now when I perform a search,
the results are all displayed
even if I had panned
all the way to Rhode Island.
There’s another thing I’d like to do
using this position state.
After a fun morning in Boston,
my family will be driving North
to spend the afternoon at the beach.
I’d like the app to make it easy
to see the North shore coastline
so we can get a feel
for where we’ll be going.
I’ll use the position state to do that.
I’ll add coordinate regions for the city
and for the North Shore.
I’ll switch over
to the BeantownButtons UI
and I’ll add a binding
for our position state.
I’ll add a couple of buttons, each setting
the camera position to a region.
When I press the City button,
the Map will show Boston.
When I press the Waves button,
the map will show
the north shore coastline.
I’ll switch back to ContentView and pass
a position binding to the buttons UI.
[no audio]
Let’s give it a try!
When I tapped the “waves” button,
the map’s position was updated
to show the north shore coastline region.
When I tap the “city” button,
it’s updated to show Boston.
Behind the scenes, what the Map shows
is ultimately controlled by a MapCamera.
The camera looks at a coordinate
on the ground from a certain distance
and the orientation of the camera
determines what is visible in the map.
The app I’m building has not had
to create or configure the camera itself.
Instead, it simply specifies what
should be in view using MapCameraPosition.
MapKit takes care of the camera for me.
The app uses an automatic camera position
to frame content, such as search results.
It uses a region position to show Boston
and the North Shore.
You can specify a camera position
to frame other things, as well.
Rect position is used to show an area,
just like how we’ve used region.
It simply uses a map rect to represent
that area, instead of a coordinate region.
Let’s take a closer look at item, camera,
and user location camera positions.
Using MKMapItem,
you can show a particular place.
This works for all kinds of map items.
If your map item represents Cape Cod Bay,
MapKit will automatically zoom out
so that it fits.
If you’re trying to show a certain park
in the North End,
the camera will zoom in
to show the surroundings
and deliver a sense of place.
You can also simply supply a MapCamera,
configured exactly the way you want it.
Using a MapCamera with a pitch angle is
a great way to deliver a 3D perspective.
Or, perhaps you’d like the camera
to follow the user’s location
as they’re walking
along the Charles River.
You can supply a fallback position
that will be used
when the user’s location is not known,
such as when location authorization
has not been granted
or while the device is trying
to get a location fix.
If you provide a binding
to your camera position state,
MapKit will update it
when the camera position changes.
Here is a user location camera position.
The followsUserLocation property is true.
If the user pans away, the camera is
no longer following the user’s location.
When the user interacts with the map,
the camera position state
is positionedByUser.
If the app sets the camera position
state back to userLocation,
the camera follows the user’s location.
When your app sets the camera position
state, it is not positionedByUser.
The user can position the camera
by interacting with the map
no matter which type of camera position
you specify.
All right! The app is now in control
of what’s in view on the map.
I’ve used the automatic camera position
to ensure the search results are visible
even after the user
has interacted with the map.
I’ve used the region camera position
to display Boston and the North Shore.
Next up, instead of only
searching near Boston Common,
I’d like to pan the map to an area
I’m interested in visiting
and search there instead.
I’ll show you how to get the visible
region when the camera changes.
I’ll add state to track the region
that’s visible in the map.
I’ll add an onMapCameraChange modifier,
where I’ll grab the visible region
from the update context
and stash it in my own state.
By default, the closure supplied
to onMapCameraChange
will be called when the user
has finished interacting with the map.
To have the closure called while
the user is interacting with the map,
you can request continuous updates
by passing a frequency parameter.
In addition to the region property
that I’m using here,
the context also has a property
for the visible map rect
and one for the map camera itself.
Depending on my needs,
I could use those as well.
I’ll update BeantownButtons
so that it will search within the region
that’s visible to the user.
I’ll add the visibleRegion
to the buttons.
And I’ll use it in the search request.
In ContentView, I’ll pass
the visibleRegion to the buttons UI.
Let’s search for North Shore beaches!
There’s the North Shore.
Show me some beaches!
Sweet!
How about Rhode Island?
Cool! Now I can search for beaches
in Rhode Island, too!
I’ve enabled this using onMapCameraChange,
which informs us when there’s
been a change in what’s visible.
Next, I’d like the app
to make it a little easier
to pick which beach we’ll be going to.
There sure are a lot to choose from.
To get started, I’ll add support
for selecting a search result.
Right now, if I tap on a search
result marker, nothing will happen.
There is no selection state,
so the markers are not selectable.
[no audio]
To enable selection, I’ll just
add a selection binding to our Map.
Now let’s see what happens
when I tap on a result.
The balloon animates
to show that it’s selected!
I’m using MKMapItem as the selection type,
so each marker that represents
a map item is now selectable.
The Parking Spot annotation
doesn’t represent a map item,
so it is not selectable.
If you want to support selection
for Markers and Annotations
that don’t necessarily have the same type
of identity, you can simply tag them.
This works the same way it does when
managing selection with Picker and List.
Here, the selectedTag state is an Int.
Each marker is tagged with an Int,
so the binding enables selection
for both of them.
When using tag to enable selection,
you can use any type conforming
to hashable for your selection state.
To recap, I’ve added
an MKMapItem selection binding to Map,
enabling selection
for the search result markers.
Next, the app should display
some additional information
about the selected search result.
I’ll add a look around preview
to offer a sneak peek at the beach,
and I’ll add the name of the beach
and the drive time as well.
Earlier today, when I was
writing the BeantownButtons View,
I also wrote a little
ItemInfoView that shows...
a title, the estimated travel time,
and a Look Around Preview.
The Look Around Preview will show me
what the selected beach looks like.
The Preview displays a Look Around Scene.
You can get the scene for a given map item
using MKLookAroundSceneRequest.
The scene will be fetched
when the view is displayed,
and again any time
the selected search result changes.
Finally, there’s a property that formats
an MKRoute’s expected travel time
for display, using
DateComponentsFormatter.
I’ll switch back to ContentView
and add this ItemInfoView.
First things first:
I’ll get a route from the parking garage
to the selected search result.
I’ll add state to keep track of a route...
and I’ll add a function
that uses MKDirections to get one...
and set the state.
I’ll add another onChange modifier
to call the function
when the selection changes.
[no audio]
The app will show our item info view
when it has a selected search result.
While I’m at it, I’ll hide
the Marker titles for the search results
to clean up the appearance
of the map just a bit.
The ItemInfoView will display the name
of the selected place instead.
Okay!
Let’s see what we got.
Ya know, I heard there was
a playground near this one…
It looks pretty nice.
I wonder what’s over this way?
[no audio]
Nice!
A beach with a playground, right there?
For our family,
that’s gonna be pretty tough to beat.
It’s about half an hour
from Boston Common.
Seems like a great spot.
To recap, I’ve added a look around preview
that will be displayed
when a marker is selected.
Along with the estimated travel time
from MKRoute,
this will really help us pick a beach.
Next, since we already have a route
to show the travel time,
we should totally use it
to display the driving route
from Boston Common
to the selected search result.
I’ll add a MapPolyline overlay
to show the route,
and I’ll show you some other types
of overlay content you can add as well.
When a route is available,
I’ll add a MapPolyline,
and stroke it with blue.
Let’s see it on the map.
[no audio]
Looks like a pretty nice drive!
It was pretty easy to use MapPolyline
with MKRoute.
You can also use MapPolyline
to show your own location data.
You can use StrokeStyle to deliver
some pretty fancy stuff,
such as dashes and a gradient.
If you’re looking to highlight an area,
you’ll want to use MapPolygon
or MapCircle.
Here are two polygons
that mark a couple of parks.
Here are two circles
marking the same parks.
You’ll notice that an overlay level
is specified for each circle.
The pink circle is using
the default overlay level of above roads,
which puts the map’s labels
above the circle.
The cyan circle is using above labels.
The app is really taking shape.
I’ve added a MapPolyline
to show the driving route to the beach,
and I’ve shown you a couple of other
overlay types that you can use as well.
Next up, I want the app to make
it really easy to figure out where I am.
When we get to Boston and
start walking around, it’s possible,
maybe even likely,
that we’ll get just a little bit lost.
I’ll add UserAnnotation as content
to show where I am,
and I’ll add a MapUserLocationButton
to find myself.
You’ll learn about several other types
of map controls
that are available to use as well.
So when I’m trying to find myself,
I usually start by looking
for the little blue dot on the map.
I’ve added UserAnnotation
to my map content,
so now my location appears on the map.
Where am I?
[no audio]
There I am!
It looks like I’m really quite far away
from those playgrounds and beaches
we’ve been checking out.
I sure had to zoom out and pan a lot
to get over to Apple Park.
MapUserLocationButton
will sure make that easier.
Now, I can tap the button
to display my location.
The map camera will follow me
as I move around.
I’ve also added a MapCompass
and a MapScaleView.
The default mapControls configuration
shows a compass when the map is rotated,
and a scale indicator while
the user is zooming in or out.
I want these default controls
in this app too,
so I’ve specified them in addition
to the user location button.
I’ve added all of these
using the mapControls modifier,
so the map will automatically display them
in their default locations.
This includes map controls
on all platforms,
including the MapZoomStepper and
MapPitchSlider that you’ll find on macOS.
If you’d prefer
to position these controls yourself,
you can present them in your own UI.
The Map controls are simply views,
so instead of using
the mapControls modifier,
you can just add them
as you would any other view.
When you do this,
you will need to use the mapScope modifier
to associate your controls
with a particular Map scope.
We’re almost
at the end of our presentation,
so let’s summarize
what we've learned today.
MapKit for SwiftUI
is an incredibly powerful,
easy-to-use API
to integrate Maps into your app.
It allows you to use Markers,
Annotations, and Overlays
to show your content on a map.
Map Camera and Map Controls
allow you to tailor the map to your needs.
Finally, MapStyle and Look Around
give your users a real sense of place.
These are just some of the features
of MapKit for SwiftUI,
so make sure to check out
the Developer Documentation to learn more.
And of course, because this is SwiftUI,
your map will look great on all platforms!
A few final thoughts as we wrap up.
We’ve extended our Apple Maps Server APIs
to support Autocomplete and Directions.
To learn more
about how to use our Server APIs,
check out last year’s dub-dub session
“Meet Apple Maps Server APIs.”
As always,
we’d love to hear your feedback!
Please use the Feedback Assistant
to let us hear your thoughts.
Last, but not least,
I encourage you to check out
the new features in SwiftUI this year.
Animation plans are a great way
to add animations to your map!
Check them out in the session below.
That’s it!
Thanks so much for watching!
I’ll see ya at the beach!
♪ ♪