♪ ♪
Alla: Hello, my name is Alla Shashkina,
and I am an engineer
in the Internationalization team.
I am here to help you with language.
Today we'll unlock the power
of grammatical agreement.
Language in software
impacts our daily interaction with it.
The words in your app matter.
Handling language in software can be hard,
especially when
you don't speak that language.
In 2021, we introduced new APIs
in Foundation that help your apps
with grammatical agreement.
Today, I'd like to introduce new features
in Foundation that will unlock
a different level
of user experience for your apps
through natural language
that is grammatically more correct,
better sounding, and more inclusive.
So let's dive in.
We'll start with a very short recap
of why we think
handling grammatical agreement
is important.
We'll walk you
through different examples in languages
that we've added support for since 2021.
We'll talk about new APIs
in grammatical agreement space
and introduce dependency agreement.
We went one step further
and asked ourselves,
how can we help you
make the language in your app
not just more grammatically correct,
but also more inclusive?
Grammar should not be something you should
worry about when you build your app.
We believe well-designed APIs
can help ease the linguistic complexity
and help you scale.
Rich and grammatically correct words
in your UI
make the user experience flawless
and enjoyable.
Different languages present
their own set of challenges.
All of this linguistic complexity
is what we take into consideration
when we design new APIs.
Our goal is to pack all that into simple,
easy-to-use interfaces.
Let's briefly review
how grammatical agreement enhances
user experience throughout the system
in different languages.
New APIs introduced in 2021
let you specify a range of words
that need to change
based on users' preferred term of address,
as well other words
within the inflectable range.
If a user selects
a feminine term of address,
iPhone will greet her
in a feminine setting in Spanish
when she's setting up
her phone for the first time.
Last year,
three more languages joined Spanish.
French speaking users enjoy
a more personalized experience
when they choose
to select their term of address.
The software throughout the system
will change the words to reflect that,
just like this example in the Notes app.
Personalized strings are pervasive
across the system experience.
Setting up your phone,
working with Shared Notes,
or managing your Calendar,
the language is adapting
to match your settings,
just like here,
in Italian or Brazilian Portuguese.
This year, we've added support
for grammatical agreement
to two new locales:
European Portuguese and German.
Now let's talk about what's new
in grammatical agreement
in Foundation this year.
Languages are complex,
but good APIs are not.
Very often, words in the UI need to change
their form based on another word.
To help you visualize it,
let me walk you through an example
from our food ordering app.
This is Spanish.
In Spanish, adjectives need
to agree with the nouns they describe.
Here, the food size "pequeño"
needs to agree
with the food it describes, "ensalada."
This is a very common use case
in other languages as well,
where word agreement happens
between certain parts of speech.
And since these words
are separated in the UI,
handling this kind
of agreement is not easy.
We created a new API that fixes this type
of dependency agreements easily.
The fix is very simple
and requires very few code changes.
Here, we want a string containing
the food size, "pequeño,"
to agree with the food name, "ensalada."
This year, we are introducing
a new property to LocalizationOptions,
concepts, which allows us to specify
objects that affect grammatical agreement,
but are not formatted
into the strings like arguments are.
We use a localizedPhrase concept
for a string value we want to agree with,
in this case, "ensalada."
Lastly, we need to annotate the word
that needs inflection
with agreeWithConcept.
A value of 1 here means that we
are asking for grammatical agreement
with the first object
in the concepts array.
Note that we use 1-based indexing.
The agreeWithConcept attribute
is also new this year,
but you can use it
even if your app runs on older devices.
When that is the case,
we will simply ignore the attribute.
Now that we've introduced these changes,
let's take a look at our UI.
Observe that the word "pequeño"
has changed to "pequeña."
This is the correct form to use
when describing "ensalada" in Spanish.
Now let's look at other places
where we need linguistic enhancements.
Here in the sentence "Our salad contains
lettuce, cheese, tomatoes and ham,"
the Spanish words "nuestro"
and "hecho" both need to agree
with the noun "ensalada."
Luckily, we only need
to facilitate grammatical agreement
within the string,
so we don't need any code changes.
First, let's make "nuestro" agree
with the food by annotating it
with the inflect attribute.
When we use the inflect attribute
on a block that has an argument,
it will try to make every word
grammatically agree with the argument.
However, there is one more
word we need to inflect, "hecho."
We try to keep inflect blocks as short
as possible to help with ambiguity,
so we cannot annotate "hecho"
with inflect: true.
This year, we are introducing another
new attribute called agreeWithArgument.
Unlike agreeWithConcept,
where you need
to make changes to the code base
by passing the value of the food name,
the agreeWithArgument attribute
does not require any code changes
and is an easy way
to facilitate agreement
not possible with the inflect attribute.
We can use agreeWithArgument
to indicate that "hecho" should agree
with an argument
that is elsewhere in the string.
Here, a value of 1 means
that we want the word to agree
with the first argument in the string.
With these changes made,
let's take a look at the UI again.
Now both words are formatted
to grammatically agree with "ensalada,"
and we use fully correct Spanish
in our localization.
Next, let's look at a similar
but yet different example.
This is French.
In French, demonstrative adjectives need
to agree with the nouns they describe.
Notice that the sizes,
as well as the button with the quantity,
are already fixed for Spanish
as we applied agreeWithConcept
and inflect attributes.
Let's fix this demonstrative case
in French.
The fix is really easy.
Wrap both the adjective and the argument
with an inflect: true block
and let the Engine do its magic.
Et voila, grammatically correct food
just tastes better.
To recap, dependency agreement
makes it possible to change words
based on other words they depend on.
Use agreeWithConcept attribute
when you want a word to agree
with another word or phrase that does not
exist within the same sentence.
Use agreeWithArgument attribute for
situations where you want a word to agree
with another word or phrase,
and both of them are in the same string.
Now let's talk about new APIs
for Inclusive language.
Let's take a look at our Caffé app again.
Let's say,
we've picked a small sandwich
and a small juice for our lunch
and put in an order.
Since we're really hungry, we want
to check the status of our delivery.
It looks like Tony is delivering
our order soon.
When localizing user interface, it's good
practice to use gender-neutral language .
At the same time,
using gendered language
in the UI feels more personal
and sounds more natural.
Let's try to personalize this string
for Tony,
who uses he and him pronouns.
First, we need to change
the model for the delivery person
to include
their preferred term of address.
To represent that,
we add a new property
of type TermOfAddress,
which is new this year.
Then, we can set the term of address
to any of masculine, feminine, or neutral.
Since we want to refer to Tony using
he and him pronouns, we choose masculine.
Next, we need to annotate the strings
where pronouns need to change.
To do that, we use the new
referentConcept attribute.
A value of 1 indicates
that the referent of the pronoun
should be the first concept
in the LocalizationOptions.
You can apply referentConcept
to any third-person personal pronoun,
and the engine will figure out
what to replace it with.
Now let's pass a termsOfAddress inflection
concept when inflecting the string.
We assign this to the concepts
property of LocalizationOptions,
just like we did earlier
for grammatical agreement.
Let's see how
this changes our UI in English.
Notice how "their" and "they" have
been replaced by "his" and "he."
You can use the same localized string
to refer to other people too.
Use a feminine term of address
when you want to refer
to someone using she and her pronouns.
And use a neutral term
of address when you want to refer
to someone using they and them pronouns.
You can also further personalize pronouns
by using localized term of address.
In a localized term of address,
you have to specify
the language it applies to,
in this case, English.
And list all pronoun forms
that you wish to use
using the new Morphology.Pronoun type.
In English,
we have to list five pronouns.
Each Pronoun consists of the pronoun form
in the target language,
and a Morphology
describing when it should be used.
Please refer to our documentation
for detailed instructions
on constructing pronouns.
Using this API is a great way to enhance
the personalization of your app.
We use this technique
to tailor the language used
in localized strings in iOS.
Now let me show how all these new features
are working live in a demo.
I hope everyone is hungry for some
delicious food from our Caffè app now.
Let me launch it in Spanish.
Let's see what's on the menu.
Let's order a pizza this time.
Here is the same grammar issue
we just discussed.
In Spanish, determiners and adjectives
need to agree with nouns.
To make two words agree with each other,
we can use inflect: true attributes.
So let's apply this easy fix
to the words "nuestro" and "pizza."
First, let's locate this string
in our String Catalog.
To make "nuestro" agree
with the argument "pizza,"
we enclose both of them
in an inflect: true block.
Next, let's also fix the adjective
"hecho" that needs to agree
with "pizza" in the same sentence.
We want to use
agreeWithArgument attribute here.
We generally try
to keep the inflect: true block
as short as possible
to help with ambiguity.
Because "hecho"
is distant from the inflect block,
we need to use
"agreeWithArgument" attribute this time.
The value of 1 here indicates
that we want "hecho" to agree
with the first argument in the string,
in this case, "pizza."
Let's run our app again.
Now this looks like a great
localization experience in Spanish.
Now let's see how we can use
the new agreeWithConcept attribute
to fix up the food sizes here.
Since pizza is feminine, the adjective
that describes it should be "pequeña."
We have already defined
the localizedNames for the food sizes.
To fix the agreement,
we want to convert localizedNames
into a method that agrees
with the specific food item.
Next, we want to pass the food name
when formatting the SIZE_BUTTON.
Here, we will define the new property
to LocalizationOptions, concept.
Concepts are objects
that affect grammatical inflection
but are not interpolated
into strings the way that arguments are.
Here, we use the localizedPhrase concept
to insert the string that we want
to grammatically agree with.
And we should remember to use options,
which is defined
when initializing the string.
Next, we want to modify
our Spanish string catalog.
We want to annotate this
with the new attribute agreeWithConcept.
Here the value of 1 indicates
that we want this argument to agree
with the first concept
we passed to the LocalizationOptions.
Lastly, let's update the FoodSizeView,
where the user selects the size
of the pizza they want,
with the new method.
Now let's run our app again
and finally order the pizza.
Amazing, our food sizes are
correctly agreeing with the pizza here.
Let's try sandwich,
which is masculine in Spanish.
This looks great.
Now let's launch our app in English,
and finally put an order for a pizza.
I will opt for a huge one this time.
And let's make it two. Why not?
Looks like Tony is going
to deliver our order soon.
The gender neutral language here is great,
but we happen to know that Tony
set his pronouns to be he/him/his.
This is something we could easily fix.
To do that, let's extend the model
for the delivery person
to include preferredTermsofAddress.
And let's extend our instance
of Tony and indicate that he prefers
to use masculine pronouns.
Next, we want to change the string itself.
Here, we want to substitute "they"
with the pronoun depending
on the termsOfAddress
of the delivery person.
To do this, we use
the new referentConcept attribute.
Here the value of 1 means
that the referent of the pronoun "they"
has to be the first concept
which passed in LocalizationOptions.
We can apply this to any third person
personal pronoun in this sentence.
Next, we want to pass the termsOfAddress
as a concept in LocalizationOptions.
Let's initialize LocalizationOptions
for deliveryMessage.
Here, we can
also use termsOfAddress concept
to provide termsOfAddress
that we can use for grammatical agreement.
And lastly,
let's use the new LocalizationOptions
when we initialize the string.
Now let's try running our app again.
Okay, huge pizzas, two.
Let's make it three.
Now that we've applied the agreement,
this looks so much more personal.
There are a lot of great new features
in Foundation this year,
and they are ready
for you to try in your apps today.
Inflect: true supports
even more languages this year.
Our new dependency agreement APIs
will help you agree words
within same string,
or even completely out of context.
Finally, the new termsOfAddress inflection
concept and referentConcept attributes
in Markdown will help
make your language be more personalized.
Please refer to our documentation
for language-level support.
I hope you'll love these new features.
We're looking forward to seeing them
beautify the language in your apps soon.
Thank you.
Oh, and my pizza has arrived.
Thank you, Tony.
♪ ♪