♪ ♪
Pulkit: Hi, I am Pulkit,
and I am an engineer on the Core ML team.
I am excited to share several updates
that have been made to Core ML Tools.
These updates help you optimize
the size and performance
of your machine learning models.
With the capabilities of models
improving significantly,
more and more features are
being driven by machine learning.
As a result, the number of models
deployed in a single app is increasing.
Along with that, each model
in the app is also getting bigger,
putting an upward pressure
on the size of an app.
So, it's critical
to keep model size in check.
There are several benefits
of reducing model size.
You can ship more models in the same
memory budget if each model is smaller.
It can also enable you to ship bigger,
more capable models.
It can also help
make the model run faster.
This is because a smaller model
means less data
to move between the memory
and the processor.
So, it seems like reducing a model's size
is a great idea.
What makes a model large?
Let me walk through an example
to help you understand.
ResNet50 is a popular
image classification model.
Its first layer is a convolution layer
with about 9,000 parameters.
And it has 53 convolution layers
in total with varying sizes.
At the end, it has a linear layer
with about 2.1 million parameters.
This all adds up to 25 million parameters
If I save the model
using Float16 precision,
it uses 2 bytes per weight,
and I get a model of size 50 megabytes.
A 50-megabyte model is large,
but when you get to some newer models
like Stable Diffusion,
you end up with even larger models.
Now, let's talk about some paths
to getting a smaller model.
One way is to design
a more efficient model architecture
that can achieve good performance
with fewer and smaller weights.
Another way is to compress
the weights of your existing model.
This path of model compression
is what I will focus on.
I'll start by describing three
useful techniques for model compression.
Next, I'll demonstrate two workflows
that integrate
these model compression techniques.
I'll then illustrate
how the latest Core ML Tools helps you
in applying these techniques
and workflows to your models.
And lastly, Srijan will discuss
the impact of model compression
on runtime performance.
Let's start
with the compression techniques.
There are a couple of ways
to compress model weights.
The first way is to pack them
more efficiently
using a sparse matrix representation.
This can be achieved
by using a technique called pruning.
Another way is to reduce
the precision used to store the weights.
This can be achieved either
by quantization or by palettization.
Both of these strategies are lossy,
and the compressed models are
typically slightly less accurate
compared to their
uncompressed counterparts.
Let's now take a deeper look
at each of these techniques.
Weight pruning helps you
efficiently pack your model weights
with a sparse representation.
Sparsifying or pruning a weight matrix
means setting
some of the weight values to 0.
I start with a weight matrix.
To prune it, I can set
the smallest magnitude weights to 0.
Now, I only need to store
the non-zero values.
I end up saving about 2 bytes of storage
for every zero introduced.
Of course, I will also need to store
the locations of zeros,
to reconstruct the dense matrix later.
Model size goes down linearly
with the level of sparsity introduced.
A 50% sparse model means
50% of its weights are zero,
and for a ResNet50 model,
it has a size of about 28 megabytes,
which is approximately half
the Float16 size.
The second weight compression technique
is quantization,
which uses 8-bit precision
to store the weights.
To perform quantization,
you take the weight values
and scale, shift, and round them
such that they lie in the INT8 range.
In this example, the scale is 2.35,
which maps the smallest value to -127,
and the bias is 0.
Depending on the model,
a non-zero bias can also be used,
which sometimes helps
in reducing quantization error.
The scale and bias can later be used
to de-quantize the weights
to bring them back
to their original range.
To reduce the weight precision
below 8 bits,
you can use a technique
called weight clustering or palettization.
In this technique,
weights with similar values
are grouped together and represented
using the value of the cluster centroid
they belong to.
These centroids are stored
in a look up table.
And the original weight matrix
is converted to an index table,
where each element points
to the corresponding cluster center.
In this example,
since I have four clusters,
I am able to represent each weight
using 2 bits,
achieving 8x compression over Float16.
The number of unique cluster centers
that can be used to represent the weights
is equal to 2 to the power of n,
where n is the precision
used for palettization.
So 4-bit palettization means
you can have 16 clusters.
While quantization reduces
your model size by half,
palettization can help you make it
up to 8 times smaller.
To summarize, there are three different
techniques for weight compression.
Each of them uses a different way
to represent the weights.
They offer varying levels of compression,
which can be controlled
by their respective parameters,
like the amount of sparsity for pruning
and the number of bits for palettization.
Now, I will illustrate
how you can integrate these techniques
in your model development workflow.
Let's first start with the workflow
for Core ML model conversion.
You may start by training a model with
your favorite python training framework
and then use Core ML Tools
to convert that model to Core ML.
This workflow can be extended
one step further
to become a post-training
compression workflow.
To do that, you add a compression step
which operates on the already trained
and converted model weights
in order to reduce the overall size.
Note that this workflow
can start at any point.
For example,
you may start with a pre-trained model
with no need for training data
or an already converted Core ML model.
When applying this workflow,
you will have an option
to choose the amount
of compression applied.
The more compression you apply,
the smaller your resulting model will be,
but as one may expect,
there are some tradeoffs.
Specifically, you will be starting
with an uncompressed model
that achieves a certain accuracy.
As you apply some compression,
your model size will reduce,
but it may also impact your accuracy.
As you apply more compression,
this impact may become more prominent
and the accuracy loss
may become unacceptable.
This trend and the acceptable tradeoff
will be different for each use case
and it is model- and dataset-dependent.
To see this tradeoff in practice,
let's look at a model
that segments objects in an image.
For my image,
the model returns probability
of each pixel belonging to the sofa.
The baseline Float16 model
segments the object very well.
For a 10% pruned model, the output is
very similar to the base model.
Artifacts start appearing at 30% sparsity
and increase with higher levels.
Once I get to 40% pruning,
the model completely breaks down,
and the probability map
becomes unrecognizable.
Similarly, 8-bit quantization
and 6-bit palettization
preserve the base model's output.
At 4-bit palettization,
you start seeing some artifacts,
and at 2-bit palettization, the model
fails to segment the object altogether.
To overcome this degradation
in model performance
at higher compression rates,
you can use a different workflow.
This workflow is called
training time compression.
Here, you fine-tune your model
on some data
while compressing the weights.
Compression is introduced gradually
and in a differentiable manner
to allow the weights to readjust
to the new constraints imposed on them.
Once your model achieves
a satisfactory accuracy,
you can convert it and get
a compressed Core ML model.
Note that you may either incorporate
training time compression
in your existing model training workflow
or start with a pre-trained model.
Training time compression improves
the tradeoff between model accuracy
and the amount of compression,
allowing you to maintain
the same model performance
at higher compression rates.
Let's look at the same
image segmentation model again.
For training time pruning,
the model output is unaltered
up to 40% sparsity.
This is where
the post-training accuracy broke down.
In fact, now even at 50% and 75% sparsity,
the model achieves a similar
probability map as the base model.
It's at 90% sparsity
that you start observing
a significant degradation
in model accuracy.
Similarly, training time quantization
and palettization
also preserve the baseline model's output,
even up to 2 bits of compression
in this case.
To recap, you can apply weight compression
either during model conversion
or during model training.
The latter provides
better accuracy tradeoff
at the cost of longer training time.
Because the second workflow applies
compression during training,
we also need to use
differentiable operations
to implement the compression algorithms.
Let's now explore how these
compression workflows can be executed
with Core ML Tools.
Post-training model compression APIs
have been available in Core ML Tools 6
for pruning, palettization,
and quantization
under the compression utils submodule.
However, there were no APIs
for training time compression.
With Core ML Tools 7,
new APIs have been added
to provide capabilities
for training time compression as well.
And we have consolidated the older APIs
and the new ones under a single module
called coremltools.optimize.
The post-training compression APIs
have been migrated
under coremltools.optimize.coreml,
and the new training time APIs
are available
under coremltools.optimize.torch.
The latter work with PyTorch models.
Let's first take a closer look
at the post-training APIs.
In the post-training compression workflow,
the input is a Core ML model.
It can be updated by the three methods
available in the optimize.coreml module,
which apply each of the three compression
techniques that I have described.
To use these methods,
you start by creating
an OptimizationConfig object,
describing how you want
to compress the model.
Here, I am doing magnitude pruning
with 75% target sparsity.
Once the config is defined,
you can use the prune_weights method
to prune the model.
It's a simple, one-step process
to get a compressed model.
You can use similar APIs for palettizing
and quantizing the weights
using configs
specific to those techniques.
Let's consider the training time
compression workflow now.
In this case, as I described earlier,
you need a trainable model and data.
More specifically,
to compress the model with Core ML Tools,
you start with a PyTorch model,
likely with pre-trained weights.
Then use one of the available APIs
in the optimize.torch module to update it
and get a new PyTorch model
with compression layers inserted in it.
And then fine-tune it, using the data
and the original PyTorch training code.
This is the step where weights will
get adjusted to allow for compression.
And you can do this step
on your MacBook locally,
using the MPS PyTorch backend.
Once the model gets trained
to regain accuracy,
convert it to get a Core ML model.
Let's explore this further
through a code example.
I am starting
with the PyTorch code required
to fine-tune the model I want to compress.
You can easily leverage Core ML Tools
to add training time pruning
by adding just a few lines of code.
You first create
a MagnitudePrunerConfig object
describing how you want
to prune the model.
Here, I am setting
the target sparsity to 75%.
You can also write the config
in a yaml file
and load it using the from_yaml method.
Then, you create a pruner object
with the model you want to compress
and the config you just created.
Next, you call prepare
to insert pruning layers in the model.
While fine-tuning the model,
you call step API
to update the pruner's internal state.
At the end of the training,
you call finalize
to fold the pruning masks
into the weights.
This model can then be converted
to Core ML using the conversion APIs.
The same workflow can be used for
quantization and palettization as well.
Now, Srijan will walk you through a demo
showing how you can use
Core ML Tools APIs
to palettize an object detection model.
Srijan: Thank you, Pulkit.
My name is Srijan, and I will be
walking you through a demo
of the Core ML Tools optimize API.
I will be using an SSD model
with a ResNet18 backbone
to detect people in images.
Let's first import
some basic model and training utilities.
I am going to start
with getting an instance
of the SSD ResNet18 model
I just talked about.
To simplify things,
I will just call the pre-written
get_ssd_model utility for that.
Now that the model is loaded,
let's train it for a few epochs.
Since it's an object detection model,
the goal of training would be
to reduce the SSD loss
of the detection task.
For conciseness, the train_epoch utility
encapsulates the code
required to train the model for an epoch,
like calling the forward
through different batches,
calculating the loss,
and performing gradient descent.
During training,
the SSD loss seems to be coming down.
I will now convert the model
into a Core ML model.
To do that, I will first trace the model
and then call the coremltools.convert API.
Let's call an imported utility
to check out the size of the model.
The size of the model is 23.6 megabytes.
Now, I will run predictions
on the Core ML model.
I have chosen an image of myself
from my London trip
as well as another image
to test the detections.
The confidence threshold for the model
to detect an object is set to 30%
so it would only plot boxes
for which it is at least 30% confident
of the object being present.
That detection seems spot on.
I am now curious to see
if I can reduce the size of this model.
I am going to try out
post-training palettization first.
For that, I'll import some config classes
and methods
from coremltools.optimize.coreml.
I am now going to palettize
the weights of the model with 6 bits.
For that,
I'll create an OpPalettizerConfig object,
specifying mode as kmeans and nbits as 6.
This will specify parameters
at an op level,
and I can palettize each op differently.
However, right now, I'm gonna apply
the same 6-bit mode to all the ops.
I'll do that by defining
OptimizationConfig
and pass this op_config
as a global parameter to it.
The optimization config is then passed
to the palettize_weights method
along with the converted model
to get a palettized model.
Let's see
what the size got reduced to now.
The size of the model has gone down
to around 9 megabytes,
but did it affect the performance
on test images?
Let's find out.
Wow, the detection still works well.
I am really excited to push my luck
to trying out
2-bit post-training palettization now.
Doing that is as simple
as just changing nbits from 6 to 2
in the OpPalettizerConfig
and running
the palettize_weights API again.
Let's use the utilities to see the size
and performance of this Core ML model.
As expected, the model's size has reduced
and has come down to around 3 megabytes.
The performance, however, is suboptimal
as the model isn't able to detect people
in both the images.
No boxes show up in the prediction,
as none of the boxes
predicted by the model
have confidence probability
above the 30% threshold.
Let's try out
2-bit training time palettization
to see if that performs better.
I will start by importing
DKMPalettizerConfig
and DKMPalettizer
from coremltools.optimize.torch
to do that.
DKM is an algorithm
to learn weight clusters
by performing an attention-based
differentiable kmeans operation on them.
Now it's time to define
the palettization config.
Just need to simply specify n_bits as 2
in the global_config,
and all supported modules
would be 2-bit palettized.
And here, I'll create a palettizer object
from the model and the config.
Calling the prepare API now would insert
palettization-friendly modules
into the model.
Time to fine-tune the model
for a few epochs.
Now that the model has been fine-tuned,
I will call the finalize API
which would restore the palettized weights
as weights of the model,
thus completing the process.
The next step is to check out
the size of the model.
For that, I will convert
the torch model into a Core ML model.
Let's start by tracing the model
using torch.jit.trace.
I will now call the convert API,
and this time, I will use
an additional flag called PassPipeline
and set its value
to DEFAULT_PALETTIZATION.
This will indicate to the converter
to use a palettized representation
for the converted weights.
Let's see the size of the model
and its performance on test images.
I can see that the model
I training-time palettized
is around 3 megabytes as well,
which comes down to 8x compression,
but unlike
the post-training palettized model,
this model is performing the detection
on test images correctly.
Since this was a demo, I just tested
model performance on two sample images.
In a real-world scenario,
I would use a metric
like mean average precision
and evaluate on a validation data set.
Let's recap.
I started with a trained model
and converted it
to get a 23.6-megabyte model
with Float16 weights.
Then, I used the palettize_weights API
to quickly get a smaller model
with 6-bit weights,
which did perform well on my data.
However, when I pushed it further
to 2 bits,
it showed a clear drop in performance.
Post this, I updated the torch model
with the optimize.torch APIs
and used
the differentiable kmeans algorithm
to fine-tune for a few epochs.
With that, I was able to get good accuracy
with the 2-bit compression option.
While the demo employed a specific model
and optimization algorithm combination,
this workflow will generalize
to your use case
and will help you
in figuring out the tradeoff
between the amount of compression
you desire
and the time and data required
to retrain the model.
This brings us to our last topic,
performance.
I would like to briefly touch
upon the improvements
that have been made to the Core ML runtime
to execute such models more efficiently
when deployed in your app.
Let's look at a few key differences
between the runtime in iOS 16 and iOS 17.
While in iOS 16, there was support
for weight-only compressed models,
in iOS 17,
8-bit activation quantized models
can also be executed.
In iOS 16, a weight compressed model runs
at the same speed as the corresponding
model with float weights,
while in iOS 17,
the Core ML runtime has been updated,
and now compressed models run faster
in certain scenarios.
Similar runtime improvements are available
in newer versions
of macOS, tvOS, and watchOS as well.
But how are these improvements achieved?
In models,
where only the weights are compressed,
since the activations are
in floating point precision,
before an operation such as a convolution
or a matrix multiplication can happen,
the weight values need to be decompressed
to match the precision of the other input.
This step of decompression takes place
ahead of time
in the iOS 16 runtime.
Hence, in this case,
the model is converted
to a fully float precision model
in memory prior to execution.
Hence, no change is observed
in inference latency.
However, in iOS 17,
in certain scenarios,
the weights are decompressed
just in time,
just before the operation is executed.
This has the advantage of loading
smaller bit weights from the memory
at the cost of doing decompression
in every inference call.
For certain compute units,
such as the Neural Engine,
and certain types of models
that are memory bound,
this could lead to inference gains.
To illustrate these runtime benefits,
I selected and profiled a few models
and plotted the relative amount
by which their inference is sped up
compared to their Float16 variant.
As expected, the amount of speedup
is model- and hardware-dependent.
These are the range of speedups
for 4-bit palettized models
on iPhone 14 Pro Max.
The improvements vary between 5% to 30%.
For sparse models too, there are
varying improvements based on model type,
with some models running 75% faster
than their Float16 variants.
The question now arises:
what is the strategy
to get the best latency performance?
That would be to start with a float model
and use the optimize.coreml APIs
to explore various representations
of the model.
This would be quick,
as it doesn't require
retraining the model.
Then, profile it
on the device of your interest.
For this, Core ML performance reports
in Xcode will give you
a lot of visibility into inference,
including where operations run.
Then, shortlist
based on which configurations
give you the best gains.
After this,
you can focus on evaluating accuracy
and trying to improve, which may require
applying some training time compression
with torch and Core ML Tools
before finalizing your model.
To summarize, it is important
to reduce the size of the models,
and now you can do that
more easily than ever
with the new Core ML Tools APIs
and achieve lower memory footprint
and inference speedups.
To check out more options
and benchmarking data,
do visit our documentation.
I would also highly recommend
tuning in to the "Improve Core ML
integration with async prediction" video
which talks about improvements
made to the Core ML framework
that I did not cover in the slides today.
Thank you, and happy compressing.