♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Israel Pastrana Vicente:
Hello and welcome
to "Design for Spatial Input."
My name is Israel,
and I'm here with Eugene.
We are designers
on the Apple Design team.
Eugene Krivoruchko:
Today, we'll talk about
designing interactions
for eyes and hands.
We'll cover what's special
about these new input methods,
and how to make the best use
of them on our platform.
Israel: Let's take a quick look
at all the available
input modalities.
With spatial input,
you can simply look at a button
and tap your fingers together
to select it,
keeping your arm
relaxed on your lap.
Our system is designed
to interact with UI
comfortably at a distance.
In some cases, you can also
interact with elements directly.
For example,
typing on a virtual keyboard
using your fingertips.
Holding your hands in the air
can cause fatigue,
but we will see that some tasks
are better suited
to interact directly.
Now, eyes and hands
are the new spatial inputs,
but you can also use
other familiar inputs
like voice to search
without needing to type.
Or keyboard and trackpad,
which are great
for getting things done.
Lastly, you can also
connect a game controller
to play your favorite games.
We are going to focus
on the most new
and exciting spatial inputs:
eyes and hands.
Using your eyes and hands
to interact
is distinct in a few ways.
First, it's personal.
Your eye movements and hand
gestures are unique to you.
An array of cameras inside
and outside the device
capture all the details
of your natural movements
in a privacy-respectful way.
Next, it's comfortable.
You can keep your hands
resting beside you
because the device sees
a wide area around you.
Lastly, it makes spatial
interactions precise.
The device filters all the data
and translates it
into accurate interactions
that you can use in your apps.
So spatial input,
it's a personal input
that feels incredibly
comfortable while providing you
great precision
to control your interactions.
Today, we'll be going over
how to use your eyes and hands
to interact naturally
with your apps.
Let's start with eyes.
Eyes are the primary
targeting mechanism
for spatial experiences.
All the interfaces in the system
react to where you look.
And we can effortlessly target
any element
just by looking at them,
no matter how far away they are.
Now, I'll talk about
how to make apps
that are comfortable
to interact with;
how to make them easy
to target with your eyes;
how to make interfaces
that respond to where you look
while respecting privacy;
and finally, how eye intent
simplifies our layouts
and offers unique
assistive options.
In order to build apps that are
comfortable for the eyes,
we need to consider how your
content shows up in the device.
Here's the first thing
to consider.
Even though you have an infinite
canvas for your apps,
you only see the content
inside the field of view.
Within the field of view,
it's most comfortable
to look in the center,
and it's less comfortable
to look at the edges.
So, design apps that fit
inside the field of view,
minimizing neck
and body movement.
Try to keep the main content
of the app in the center
of the field of view, the most
comfortable area for your eyes.
Looking at the edges
of the field of view
can be tiring for your eyes,
so use these areas
for content that
you don't need all the time,
like secondary actions,
which remain accessible
and don't interfere
with the main content.
Always try to maximize eye
and neck comfort in your apps
by placing the content
inside the field of view.
Now, we should also
consider depth
when thinking about eye comfort.
Depth is a unique feature
of spatial experiences.
Placing your content
near or far away
creates different feelings
in your projects.
But our eyes focus on
one distance at a time,
and changing
the focus depth frequently
can create eye strain.
Look to keep interactive content
at the same depth
to make it feel effortless
to switch between UI.
For example,
presenting a modal view
pushes the main view
in the z-axis,
and the modal is placed
at the original distance.
By maintaining
the same Z position,
your eyes don't need
to adapt to the new distance.
Now, you can use
subtle changes in depth
to communicate hierarchy,
like in this example,
with a tab bar on the left
and a segmented control
at the bottom.
This way, you're using
depth meaningfully,
while avoiding eye discomfort.
Now that we've seen
how to make an app comfortable,
we also need to make it
easy to use with your eyes.
Eyes are very precise,
but there are certain qualities
that help our eyes target
successfully on UI elements.
Our eyes naturally focus on
shapes that guide our attention
to the middle of an object.
To help our eyes,
use round shapes
like circles, pills,
and rounded rectangles.
Avoid using shapes
with sharp edges.
When you use sharp edges,
your eyes tend to focus
on the outside,
decreasing eye precision.
Also, keep the shapes flat
and avoid thick outlines
or effects that call attention
to the edges.
And lastly, make sure to center
the text and the glyphs
in your elements
using generous padding.
So, always make sure
that your UI is designed
to guide the eyes
to the center of the element.
Now that our attention is
in the middle of our elements,
let's look at the right size
for your controls.
The minimum area that your
element needs for eye target
is 60 points.
But the element
can be smaller than 60 points.
You can achieve
the minimum target area
combining size and spacing.
Use generous spacing between
elements in your layouts.
This will help you target
quickly and accurately
with your eyes.
Again, it's very important to
respect the minimum target area
of 60 points,
combining size and spacing
to make your UI look great
and easy to use with your eyes.
Out of the box,
standard components
have sizes that are
easy to target.
Use these components
as much as you can.
And if you use your own,
make sure to follow
our guidelines on sizing.
To learn more about
points and layout,
check out the session "Design
for spatial user interfaces."
Now that we've learned about
how important the target area is
for your eyes,
we have to make sure that
we maintain this target area
in any position in a space.
For that, we need to understand
how to scale your UI.
Let's look at two different
scale mechanisms.
The system provides
dynamic scale for app windows.
You can see how the window
scales larger as it moves away,
and smaller as it moves close.
Dynamic scale makes your UI
fill the same field of view
and preserve the size
of the target areas,
no matter
where the window is positioned.
If you use fixed scale instead,
your UI becomes smaller
as it moves away.
Fixed scale changes
the size of the interface
and makes your app
difficult to use with your eyes.
Let's look at this side by side.
Dynamic scale keeps your UI
and the target areas
at the same size,
while fixed scale
changes the size and makes
the target areas too small.
When you create custom UI,
use dynamic scale to ensure
that your eyes can always target
all the controls.
Besides scale,
orientation also affects
the usability of your app.
If the interface is at an angle,
it's difficult to read
and hard to use.
That's why system windows are
always oriented to face people.
But if you create custom windows
in your app,
always make sure to keep your UI
facing the viewer.
As we've just seen,
correct scale and orientation
of windows and UI
are fundamental
to ensure accuracy
with your eyes.
To learn more about how windows
on this platform behave,
check out the session
"Principles of spatial design."
Eyes are a very novel input.
and it's really important
to make your interfaces
respond to your eyes.
When interactive
elements highlight,
you understand that your eyes
are driving the interaction.
Let's see what happens when
you look at a group of buttons.
See how they highlight
as you look at each one.
All interactive elements
should be highlighted,
and we do this
with a hover effect.
But because your eyes
move quickly,
the effect needs to be subtle
and work on top of any content,
like when looking at
your favorite photos,
reinforcing intention
without being prominent.
Thanks to the hover effect,
all the system-provided controls
highlight when you look at them.
If you create custom elements
for your apps,
use hover effects
to add eye feedback
and make your elements
feel responsive.
Now, eye intention
is very sensitive information.
Privacy is our top priority
when dealing with eye data.
The hover effect happens
out of your app's process,
so you will only
get the information
of which element is focused
when there is an interaction
on the element
triggered by a gesture.
Hovering on an element
with your eyes
is a signal for intention.
When you look at something
for a long time,
we know that you are
interested in it.
It is a great opportunity
to show you
more information about it.
For example,
buttons can have tooltips
that reveal as you look at them.
Also, tab bars expand
when you focus on them,
showing a label for each tab.
Lastly, focusing on
the microphone glyph
inside a system-provided
search field
will trigger Speak to Search,
revealing this layer
and allowing you
to perform a search
using just eyes and voice.
All these system elements
give extra information
when you need it,
while keeping a clean UI
when not in focus.
Take advantage of them
when creating your apps.
They are also built with privacy
in mind to ensure
that no focus information
is being sent to the app.
Eye intent also provides
great opportunities
for assistive technology.
For example, using
the Dwell Control feature,
you can select content
just with your eyes.
In this example, focusing on
a button for a short time
will show the Dwell Control UI
and will select the button
without needing to perform
a tap gesture with your hand.
So, what did we just learn
about designing
interactions for eyes?
We learned about how to make
your apps comfortable
for your eyes by placing content
in front of the viewer,
inside the field of view,
and using depth responsibly.
Then we looked at how to design
interfaces that are easy to use
and how to guide your eyes
to the center of the elements.
We also reinforced
how important it is
to respect the minimum
target area of 60 points
in your controls.
How we should always
communicate interactivity
and reinforce targeting
by adding hover effects
to your elements.
And lastly, how we can
take advantage of UI elements
that reveal extra information
on eye intent.
I think this was great,
and there's even more.
We've seen that eyes are a
fantastic target mechanism,
and they become
much more powerful
when you combine them
with hands.
Now, I'll hand it over
to Eugene to talk about it.
Eugene: Thanks, Israel.
Let's talk about hands.
Combined with eyes
for targeting,
hand gestures
are the primary way
to interact across the system.
Pinching your fingers together
is an equivalent
of pressing on the screen
of your phone.
The system supports
other familiar gestures.
For example, you can
pinch and drag to scroll,
and perform two-handed
gestures like zoom and rotate.
Notice how in all these cases,
UI feedback continues
the motion of the hand,
which really helps it feel
connected to the gesture.
The gestures work the same way
across the system
and follow the logic similar
to the Multi-Touch gestures.
This means that people can
really focus on the experience,
instead of having to think about
how to perform the interaction.
This is why you should
lean on these familiar patterns
when designing your experience,
and make sure
to respond to gestures
in a way that matches
people's expectations.
In some cases,
part of your experience
might be a unique behavior
that can't easily be expressed
with standard gestures.
In this case, you may
want to define a custom one.
Here are some tips on how
to make a successful
custom gesture.
First, make sure that
the gesture is easy to explain
and perform so that people
can learn how to use it quickly.
It is also important
to avoid gesture conflicts.
Your custom gesture needs to be
distinctly different
from the standard system set
or common hand movements
people might use
in the conversation.
This has to be a gesture that
people can consistently repeat
without strain or fatigue,
and that has a low rate
of false activations.
Be mindful of people who
are using assistive technologies
to interact across the system
and consider how your gesture
will work in those cases.
To learn more
about accessibility,
check out the session "Create
accessible spatial experiences."
Gestures can also mean
different things
to different people,
so make sure your custom gesture
doesn't send messages
you didn't intend.
All of this may be
a tricky balance to hit,
so it's always worth
considering a fallback
in the form of a UI affordance.
One of the most exciting
aspects of our input model
is the opportunity to use eyes
as a signal of intent.
Using eye direction
combined with hand gestures,
we can create precise
and satisfying interactions
that are not possible
on other platforms.
Let's look at the zoom gesture
again to see what I mean.
At the start of the gesture,
the origin point of the zoom
is determined by where
within the image
your eyes are focused
at that moment.
This results in that particular
area to be magnified
and centered as you zoom in.
As a result, you can
navigate the image easily
just by looking around and
performing this simple gesture.
This feels really magical
and 100 percent expected
at the same time.
The point you are looking at
naturally indicates
the intent of that interaction.
Another example of this behavior
is pointer movement in Markup.
To draw, you control
the brush cursor with your hand,
similar to a mouse pointer,
but then if you look
to the other side
of the canvas and tap,
the cursor jumps there landing
right where you're looking.
This creates a sense of accuracy
and helps to cover
the large canvas quickly.
These are examples
of interactions
that use eye direction
to make simple behaviors
more precise and satisfying.
Eyes are used not only
to target elements,
but to implicitly provide
a more granular location
for that interaction.
This is a really powerful aspect
of our input model
that allows us
to respond to interaction
in a much more intelligent way.
Now let's talk about
direct touch.
Across the system, we support
being able to reach out
and use your fingertips
to interact.
For example, you can bring
Safari close to you
and scroll the page directly.
You can also use
both your hands
to type on the virtual keyboard
and even
have more spatial experiences,
manipulating 3D content
within your arm's reach.
Interactions at a distance
stay comfortable for a long time
because it's easy to target
controls with your eyes,
and your hands can stay rested
while performing
minimal gestures.
When designing
for direct interaction,
we have to keep in mind
that holding hands in the air
will cause fatigue
after a while.
Still, certain apps will benefit
from placing content
within arm's reach
for direct touch,
like experiences
that invite up close inspection
or object manipulation;
or any interactive mechanic
that builds on top
of the muscle memory
from real-world experiences;
and generally,
whenever physical activity
is at the center
of the experience.
Lack of tactile response
is another thing to consider
when designing
for direct interaction.
Every time we touch something
in the physical world,
our hands receive
lots of multisensory feedback,
which is essential
to our perception.
None of this is happening
when we reach out
and touch virtual content.
And to make
that interaction work,
we need to compensate for
the missing sensory information
with other types of feedback.
Let's look at how we approached
this challenge
with keyboard buttons.
The buttons are actually
raised above the platter
to invite pushing them directly.
While the finger
is above the keyboard,
buttons display a hover state
and a highlight
that gets brighter as you
approach the button surface.
It provides a proximity cue
and helps guide
the finger to target.
At the moment of contact,
the state change
is quick and responsive,
and is accompanied
by matching
spatial sound effect.
[DIGITAL KEYSTROKES]
These additional layers
of feedback are really important
to compensate
for missing tactile information,
and to make direct interactions
feel reliable and satisfying.
Audio plays a special role
in connecting input
with virtual content
across the system.
To learn more about it,
check out the session called
"Explore immersive
sound design."
To recap,
here are the takeaways
for designing
interactions with hands.
Use gesture language
consistent with the system
so people can focus
on the content
instead of the interaction.
Be careful to only introduce
custom gestures
when the desired behavior
can't be achieved
with the standard set.
Look for ways
to improve your interaction
using eyes
as a signal of intent.
Only use direct interaction
when it's at the core
of your experience.
And if you do,
provide extensive feedback
to compensate for missing
sensory information.
Today, we have talked about
some of the design principles
for spatial interactions
with eyes and hands.
We talked a lot about
comfort and ergonomics.
With so many ways
for how software can look,
behave, and react
to input on this platform,
there is more responsibility
on designers and developers
to make sure these experiences
are comfortable and accessible.
By running your app on device,
people welcome your work
into their space and give it
their full attention.
Software is no longer contained
within a screen.
Instead, it's allowed to occupy
a more significant portion
of people's
physical surroundings
and react to their
natural body movements.
Using hands to interact
with virtual content
is also something very new
for most people.
That's why it's so important
to guide them
by providing clear feedback
and to rely on
familiar interaction patterns
where possible.
As we know from designing
for other platforms,
great input experience
is the one
that you don't
have to think about.
Software response becomes
a natural continuation
of your body movement
and perfectly matches
the interaction intent.
Our ability to use eyes
as the foundation
of the input model
opens up opportunities
to respond to interaction
with magical precision.
We think it's really powerful,
and we hope you will use it
to create delightful
and novel interactions
for the spatial medium.
Please make sure to check out
the sessions
that we have referenced
throughout the talk.
Thanks for watching!
Israel: Adios!
♪