♪ ♪
Becca:
Hi, I'm Becca from the Swift team.
Today we'll be talking about Swift macros,
an exciting new feature
that lets you customize
the Swift language for your needs.
We'll start by talking
about what macros are for.
Then, we'll talk about some
of the principles we kept in mind
when we designed Swift macros.
And then we'll
cover how Swift macros work
and the specific ways they can interact
with the other code in your project.
After that,
we'll talk about how to implement macros
and finish by discussing how
to make sure your macros work correctly.
So let's get started by talking
about why Swift supports macros.
Swift loves to let users
write expressive code and APIs.
That's why it provides features like
derived conformances and result builders,
which help users to avoid
writing repetitive boilerplate.
These features all work
basically the same way.
For example, when you conform to Codable
without providing implementations
for its members,
Swift automatically expands
the conformance into a set of members
that it inserts into the program.
I've shown the expansion
for the conformance in the gray box.
Creating this code for you lets you
use Codable without having to know
exactly how it works
and makes it so you don't have to decide
if adding Codable support
is worth writing a screenful of code.
Swift has many features
that work in this way.
You write some simple syntax,
and the compiler expands it into a more
complicated piece of code automatically.
But what if the existing features
can't do what you want?
Well, you could add
a feature to the Swift compiler,
since it's open source.
But that literally involves me,
personally,
getting on a video conference
and discussing your feature
with other Swift project leaders,
so it's not exactly a process that scales.
That's why we're introducing macros.
They let you add
your own language features to Swift,
eliminating tedium and boilerplate,
in a way you can distribute
in a Swift package
without modifying the compiler.
Some of you haven't used macros
in other languages.
But if you have,
you may have mixed feelings about them.
That's partly because a lot
of Swift developers are familiar
with Objective-C or other languages
that use the C preprocessor,
and they know about the limitations
and pitfalls of C macros.
But Swift macros are very different
in ways that avoid many of those issues.
We designed them with four goals in mind.
The first goal is that it should be
pretty obvious when you're using a macro.
There are two kinds of macros:
Freestanding macros stand in place
of something else in your code.
They always start with a pound (#) sign.
And attached macros are used as attributes
on declarations in your code.
They always start with an at (@) sign.
Swift already uses the pound (#) and at (@) signs
to indicate special compiler behavior.
Macros just make that extensible.
And if you don't see #’s or @’s,
you can be confident
that there aren't any macros involved.
The second goal is that both
the code passed into a macro
and the code sent back out of it should
be complete and checked for mistakes.
You can't pass "1 +” to a macro
because arguments have
to be complete expressions.
Nor can you pass an argument
with the wrong type
because macro arguments
and results are type-checked,
just like function arguments.
And a macro's implementation
can validate its inputs and emit
compiler warnings or errors
if something's wrong,
so it's easier to be certain
that you're using a macro correctly.
The third goal is that macro expansions
should be incorporated
into the program
in predictable, additive ways.
A macro can only add
to the visible code in your program.
It can't remove it or change it.
So even if you have no idea
what "someUnknownMacro" does,
you can still be sure
that it doesn't delete the call
to "finishDoingThingy"
or move it into a new function.
That makes it a lot easier
to read code that uses macros.
And the final goal is that macros
should not be impenetrable magic.
Macros just add more code to your program,
and that's something
you can see right in Xcode.
You can right-click on a macro's use site
and ask to see what it expands into.
You can set breakpoints in the expansion
or step into it with the debugger.
When the code inside a macro
expansion doesn't compile,
you'll see both where the error
is in the expansion,
and where that expansion goes
in your source code.
And all of these tools work
even if the macro is provided
by a closed-source library.
Macro authors can even write
unit tests for their macros
to make sure they work as expected;
something we highly encourage they do.
We think these goals make
Swift macros easy for developers
to understand and maintain.
So now that we understand
what Swift macros are trying to achieve,
let's talk about how they do it.
Before we get lost in the details,
let's just get the basic concept down.
When Swift sees you
call a macro in your code,
like the "stringify" macro
from the Xcode macro package template,
it extracts that use from the code
and sends it to a special compiler plug-in
that contains the implementation
for that macro.
The plug-in runs as a separate process
in a secure sandbox,
and it contains custom Swift code
written by the macro's author.
It processes the macro use
and returns an "expansion,"
a new fragment
of code created by the macro.
The Swift compiler then adds
that expansion to your program
and compiles your code
and the expansion together.
So when you run the program,
it works just as though you wrote
the expansion yourself
instead of calling the macro.
Now, there's an important point
I glossed over here.
How did Swift know
that the "stringify" macro exists?
And the answer is,
it comes from a macro declaration.
A macro declaration
provides the API for a macro.
You can write the declaration
right in your own module,
or you can import it
from a library or framework.
It specifies the macro's name
and signature,
the number of parameters it takes,
their labels and types,
and the type of the result
if the macro has one,
just like a function declaration.
And it also has one or more attributes
that specify the macro's roles.
It's impossible to write a macro
without thinking about what its roles are.
So let's talk about what a role is
and how you can use different roles
to write different kinds of macros.
A role is a set of rules for a macro.
It governs where
and how you apply the macro,
what kind of code it expands into,
and where that expansion
is inserted into your code.
Ultimately,
it's macro roles that are responsible
for achieving our goal of inserting
expansions in predictable, additive ways.
There are two roles
that create freestanding macros:
Expression and declaration.
And there are five roles
that create attached macros:
Peer, accessor, member attribute,
member, and conformance.
Let's take a look at these roles
and when you might use them.
We'll start with
the "freestanding expression" role.
If the term "expression"
doesn't ring a bell,
an expression is what we call a unit of
code that executes and produces a result.
In this "let" statement, the arithmetic
after the equal sign is an expression.
But expressions have
a recursive structure--
they're often made up
of smaller expressions.
So "x + width"
alone is also an expression.
And so is just the word "width."
A "freestanding expression" macro then is
a macro that expands into an expression.
How would you use one?
Imagine you need
to force-unwrap an optional.
Swift provides a force-unwrap operator,
but some teams feel
that it's a little too easy
to throw in a force-unwrap
without thinking about its safety,
so their style guides tell developers
to write something more complex
that indicates
why the value should never be nil.
But most of these alternatives,
such as using a "guard let"
and then calling "preconditionFailure"
in the "else" branch,
are a little too much ceremony.
Let's design a macro that strikes
a better balance between these extremes.
We want this macro
to compute and return a value,
so we make it
a "freestanding(expression)” macro.
We give it the name "unwrap"
and a generic type
where the value passed in is optional,
but the value returned is non-optional.
And we also pass in a string
that's part of the message printed
if the unwrap fails.
So we end up with a macro
that we call just like a function,
but it expands into an expression
that contains a "guard let"
wrapped in a closure.
The error message
even includes the variable name,
something that would be impossible
with a normal function.
Now that we've seen
the freestanding expression role,
let's look
at the freestanding declaration role.
It expands into one or more declarations,
like functions, variables, or types.
What could you use it for?
Imagine you're writing
some kind of statistical analysis
that needs a 2D array type.
You want all of the rows in the array
to have the same number of columns,
so you don't want an array-of-arrays.
Instead, you want to store the elements
in a flat, one-dimensional array,
and then compute a one-dimensional index
from the two-dimensional indices
passed in by the developer.
To do that,
you might write a type like this one.
The "makeIndex" function takes
the two integers needed for a 2D index,
and then does a little arithmetic
to turn them into a 1D index.
But then you find that,
in another part of the program,
you need a three-dimensional array.
It's almost exactly the same
as the 2D array.
There's just a few more indices,
and the calculation
is a little more complex.
And then you need a 4D array
and then a 5D array,
and soon you're swimming
in array types that are almost identical,
but not quite close enough
to use generics, or protocol extensions,
or subclasses,
or any of the other features
Swift offers for this kind of thing.
Fortunately,
each of these structs is a declaration,
so we can use
a declaration macro to create them.
So let's declare
a freestanding declaration macro
with the name "makeArrayND,"
since it's going to create
an N-dimensional array type.
We'll pass the number
of dimensions as an Int parameter,
and we won't declare a result type
because this macro
will add a declaration to our program,
not compute a result
that's used by other code.
Now we can call the macro
four times with two,
three, four, and five dimensions,
and each of those calls will expand
into an entire
multi-dimensional array type
with the right number of arguments
and the right calculation for that size.
So far, we've only looked
at freestanding macros.
Now let's move
on to roles for attached macros.
Attached macros are, as the name suggests,
attached to a specific declaration.
That means
they have more information to work from.
Freestanding macros are only given
the arguments they're passed,
but attached macros can also access
the declaration they're attached to.
They often inspect
that declaration and pull out names,
types,
and other information from inside them.
We'll start with the attached peer role.
A peer macro can be attached
to any declaration,
not only variables,
and functions, and types,
but even things
like import and operator declarations,
and can insert
new declarations alongside it.
So if you use it on a method or property,
you'll end up creating members
of the type,
but if you use it
on a top-level function or type,
you'll end up creating
new top-level declarations.
That makes them incredibly flexible.
Here's one way you might use them.
Suppose you're writing a library
that uses Swift concurrency,
but you know that some of your clients are
still using older concurrency techniques,
so you want to give them versions
of your APIs that use completion handlers.
It's not difficult to write these methods.
You just remove the "async" keyword,
add a completion handler parameter,
move the result type
into the parameter list,
and call the async version
in a detached task.
But you're doing this a lot,
and you don't want
to have to write it by hand.
That's a great job
for an attached peer macro.
We'll declare one called
"AddCompletionHandler" and give it
a parameter for the completion
handler's argument label,
and then attach that macro
to the async version of the method.
The macro will create
a completion handler-based signature
equivalent to the original,
write the method body,
and even attach a documentation comment
with extra text
for the completion handler.
Pretty cool.
Next,
let's look at the attached accessor role.
These can be attached
to variables and subscripts,
and they can install accessors
into them, like "get,"
"set," "willSet," or "didSet".
So how might that be useful?
Suppose you have a bunch of types
that basically wrap around dictionaries
and let you access their contents
with properties.
So for instance,
this "Person" struct lets you access
the "name," "height,"
and "birth_date" fields,
but if there's other information in
the dictionary besides those three fields,
it'll just be preserved
and ignored by your program.
These three properties need
computed getters and setters,
but writing them by hand is tedious,
and we can't use property wrappers
because property wrappers can't access
other stored properties
on the type they're used with.
So let's write an attached accessor macro
that can help with this.
We'll call it "DictionaryStorage."
We'll give it a "key" parameter
because the dictionary spells "birth_date"
with an underscore,
but you can also just leave the key out,
and it'll default to nil,
which will make the macro
use the property's name as the key.
So now, instead of writing
that big accessor block,
you can just put “@DictionaryStorage"
before each property,
and the macro will generate
the accessors for you.
That's a nice improvement,
but there's still some boilerplate here:
The identical
"DictionaryStorage" attributes.
They're less boilerplate,
but they're still boilerplate.
Some built-in attributes
let you deal with this kind of situation
by applying them
to the entire type or extension.
The "attached member attribute" role
can make your macros behave like that too.
The macro gets attached
to a type or extension,
and it can add attributes to the members
of whatever it's attached to.
Let's see how it's done.
We're going to do something
a little different here.
Rather than declaring a new macro,
we'll add another role attribute
to the "DictionaryStorage" macro,
alongside the "attached accessor"
role it already has.
This is a really useful technique
for creating macros.
You're allowed to compose any combination
of roles except the two freestanding roles
because there are places where
Swift wouldn't know which one to use.
Swift will expand all of the roles
that make sense wherever you applied them,
but at least one
of the roles has to work there.
So if you attach
"DictionaryStorage" to a type,
Swift will expand
the "member attribute" role.
If you attach it to a property,
Swift will expand the "accessor" role.
But if you attach it to a function,
you'll get a compilation error
because "DictionaryStorage"
doesn't have any roles
that could attach to a function.
With this second role added
to "DictionaryStorage,"
instead of attaching it separately
to every property,
you can just attach it to the whole type.
The macro will have logic
to skip certain members,
like the initializer,
the "dictionary" property,
and properties like "birth_date"
that already have
a "DictionaryStorage" attribute.
But it'll add a "DictionaryStorage"
attribute to any other stored property,
and then those attributes will expand
into the accessors we already saw.
That's a nice improvement, but there's
still more boilerplate we could eliminate:
The initializer and stored property.
These are required
by the "DictionaryRepresentable" protocol,
and the property is used by the accessors,
but they're exactly the same in any type
that uses DictionaryStorage.
Let's make the DictionaryStorage macro
add them automatically,
so we don't have to write them by hand.
We can do that using
the "attached member" role.
Like member attribute macros,
you can apply these macros
to types and extensions,
but instead of adding attributes
to existing members,
they add totally new members.
So you can add methods,
properties, initializers, and so on.
You can even add stored properties
to classes and structs, or cases to enums.
Once again,
we'll add a new "attached member" role
to the DictionaryStorage macro,
composing it with the other two.
This new role will add an initializer
and a property called "dictionary."
You might be wondering,
when two different macros get applied
to the same code,
which one gets expanded first?
Then answer is, it doesn't really matter.
Each one will see
the original version of the declaration
without expansions provided by the others.
So you don't need to worry about ordering.
You'll see the same thing no matter
when the compiler expands your macro.
With the attached member role added,
we don't even have
to write those two members anymore.
Simply using DictionaryStorage on the type
will automatically add them for us.
And then the other role will add
the DictionaryStorage attributes
on the properties, and those attributes
will expand into accessors, and so on.
But there's still one last bit
of boilerplate to eliminate:
The conformance
to the DictionaryRepresentable protocol.
The "attached conformance" role
is perfect for this.
It can add a conformance
to a type or extension.
We'll add
one last "attached conformance" role
to the "DictionaryStorage" macro,
composing it with the other three.
This new role will add a conformance
to "DictionaryRepresentation."
So now we don't have to write
the conformance manually.
The DictionaryStorage attribute
we already added for the accessors
and generated members will now
automatically add the conformance too,
along with all the other stuff
it was already doing.
It's been a long time
since we saw our starting point,
so just to remind you,
we took a big, unruly type
full of repetitive code
and moved most
of that code into several roles
of a super-powerful macro
so that what's left
concisely specifies only what's special
about this particular type.
Imagine if you had 10 or 20 types
that could use DictionaryStorage.
How much easier would it be
to work with all of them?
We've spent a bunch of time now
talking about declarations and roles,
but so far, the code they expand into
has just seemed to magically appear.
Let's fill in that gap now and talk
about how you implement your macro.
When I've showed you
macro declarations so far,
I've left out something very important:
the implementation.
It's after an equal sign,
and it's always another macro.
Sometimes it's another macro
you've written,
just with the parameters rearranged
or with extra parameters
specified as literals.
But usually,
you'll use an external macro.
An external macro is one
that's implemented by a compiler plug-in.
You might remember that I talked
about compiler plug-ins earlier.
I said that when the compiler
sees a macro being used,
it starts a plug-in in a separate process
and asks it to expand the macro.
"#externalMacro" is what
defines that relationship.
It specifies the plug-in
the compiler should launch
and the name of a type inside that plug-in.
So when Swift expands this macro,
it will launch a plug-in
called "MyLibMacros"
and ask a type
called "StringifyMacro" to expand it.
So the macro declaration goes in your
normal library alongside your other APIs,
but the macro implementation goes
in a separate compiler plug-in module.
And "#externalMacro" creates
the link between the declaration
and the type implementing it.
What does
a macro implementation look like?
Well, let's take a look at how
DictionaryStorage might be implemented.
If you recall, our "DictionaryStorage"
macro had an "attached member" role
that added a stored property
and an initializer to the type.
Here's a simple implementation
of that role.
We'll walk through it one step
at a time and learn how it works.
Right at the top, we start
by importing a library called SwiftSyntax.
SwiftSyntax is a package maintained
by the Swift project that helps you parse,
inspect, manipulate,
and generate Swift source code.
Swift contributors keep SwiftSyntax
up to date as the language evolves,
so it supports every feature
the Swift compiler does.
SwiftSyntax represents source code
as a special tree structure.
For example,
the "Person" struct in this code sample
is represented as an instance
of a type called "StructDeclSyntax."
But that instance has properties,
and each of those properties
represents some portion
of the struct declaration.
The list of attributes is
in the "attributes" property.
The actual keyword "struct"
is in the "structKeyword" property.
The struct's name
is in the "identifier" property.
And the body with the curly braces
and the struct's members
is in the "memberBlock" property.
There are also properties like "modifiers"
that represent things
that some struct declarations have.
But this one doesn't.
These are nil.
Some of the syntax nodes
in these properties are called "tokens."
These represent a specific piece
of text in the source file,
like a name, or a keyword,
or a bit of punctuation,
and they just contain that text
and any surrounding trivia,
like spaces and comments.
If you drill deep enough
into the syntax tree,
you'll find a token node that covers
every byte of the source file.
But some of those nodes,
like the "AttributeListSyntax" node
in the "attributes" property
and the "MemberDeclBlockSyntax" node
in the "memberBlock" property,
are not tokens.
These have child nodes
in their own properties.
For example, if we look inside
the "memberBlock" property,
we'll find a token
for the opening curly brace,
a "MemberDeclListSyntax" node
for the list of members,
and a token for the closing curly brace.
And if you keep exploring the contents
of that "MemberDeclListSyntax" node,
you'll eventually find a node for each
of the properties, and so on.
Working with SwiftSyntax
is a huge topic all its own,
so rather than make
this video twice as long,
I'm going to refer you
to two other resources.
One is the companion
"Write Swift Macros" session,
which includes practical tips
for figuring out how a particular piece
of source code is represented
as a syntax tree.
The other is the SwiftSyntax
package's documentation.
You can find it online,
or if you use Xcode's
Build Documentation command
in your macro package,
SwiftSyntax docs will appear
in the Developer Documentation window.
In addition
to the main SwiftSyntax library,
we also import two other modules.
One is "SwiftSyntaxMacros",
which provides protocols and types
necessary for writing macros.
The other is called
"SwiftSyntaxBuilder".
This library provides convenience APIs
for constructing syntax trees
to represent newly-generated code.
You can write a macro without using it,
but it's incredibly handy,
and we highly recommend
you take advantage of it.
Now that we've imported these libraries,
we'll start actually writing
the "DictionaryStorageMacro" type
that our plug-in is supposed to provide.
Notice that it conforms
to a protocol called "MemberMacro."
Each role has a corresponding protocol,
and the implementation has
to conform to the protocol
for each role the macro provides.
The "DictionaryStorage" macro
has four of these roles,
so the "DictionaryStorageMacro" type
will need to conform
to the four corresponding protocols.
But to keep things simple,
we're just worrying
about the "MemberMacro" conformance
for now.
Moving on to the body of this type,
we see a method called
"expansion of, providingMembersOf, in."
This method is required
by the MemberMacro protocol,
and it's what the Swift compiler calls
to expand the member role
when the macro is used.
We're not using the arguments yet,
but we'll talk about them later.
For now, notice that it's a static method.
All of the expansion methods are static,
so Swift doesn't actually create
an instance
of the DictionaryStorageMacro type.
It just uses it
as a container for the methods.
Each of the expansion methods
returns SwiftSyntax nodes
that are inserted into the source code.
A member macro expands
into a list of declarations to add
as members to the type,
so the expansion method
for a member macro returns an array
of "DeclSyntax" nodes.
If we look inside the body,
we see that array being created.
It has the initializer and the stored
property we want this macro to add.
Now, the "var dictionary" bit here
looks like it's an ordinary string,
but it's actually not.
This string literal is being written
where a DeclSyntax is expected,
so Swift actually treats it
as a fragment of source code
and asks the Swift parser
to turn it into a DeclSyntax node.
This is one of those conveniences
that the SwiftSyntaxBuilder
library provides.
It's a good thing we imported it earlier.
So with that and with conformances
to the protocols
for the other three roles,
we'll have a working implementation
of our DictionaryStorage macro.
But although this macro
will now work when you use it correctly,
what happens if you use it wrong?
For instance, what if you try to apply it
to an enum instead of to a struct?
Well, the "attached member" role will try
to add a stored "dictionary" property.
But an enum can't have stored properties,
so Swift will produce an error:
"Enums must not contain
stored properties."
It's great that Swift will stop
this code from compiling,
but the error message
is a little confusing, isn't it?
It's not really clear
why the DictionaryStorage macro tried
to create a stored property
or what you should have done differently.
I said earlier that one
of Swift's goals was to allow macros
to detect mistakes
in their inputs and emit custom errors.
So let's modify our macro's implementation
to produce a much clearer
error message for this:
“@DictionaryStorage
can only be applied to a struct."
That will give developers
a better idea of what they did wrong.
The key to doing this
will be the parameters
to the expansion method,
which we've ignored so far.
The exact arguments are slightly different
for different roles,
DeclGroupSyntax is a protocol
that the nodes for structs, enums,
classes, actors, protocols,
and extensions all conform to.
So this parameter gives us
the declaration that the developer
attached the attribute to.
And the final parameter
is called "context" and is of a type
that conforms
to "MacroExpansionContext".
The context object is used
when the macro implementation wants
to communicate with the compiler.
It can do a few different things,
including emitting errors and warnings.
We'll use all three
of these parameters to emit our error.
Let's see how it's done.
First, we need to detect the problem.
We'll do that by checking the type
of the "declaration" parameter.
Each kind of declaration
has a different type,
so if it's a struct,
its type will be "StructDeclSyntax",
if it's an enum,
it'll be "EnumDeclSyntax", and so on.
So we'll write a guard-else that calls
the "declaration" parameter's "is" method
and passes "StructDeclSyntax".
If the declaration isn't a struct,
we'll end up in the "else" block.
For now, we'll return an empty array,
so the macro doesn't add any code
to the project, but what we really want
to do is emit an error.
Now, the easy way to do it is
to just throw an ordinary Swift error,
This is a bit of compiler jargon.
Just as a doctor looking at an X-ray
of your broken leg diagnoses a fracture,
a compiler or macro
looking at a syntax tree
of your broken code
diagnoses an error or warning.
So we call the instance
representing the error a “Diagnostic."
A diagnostic contains
at least two pieces of information.
The first is the syntax node
that the error occurred at,
so the compiler knows
which line to mark as incorrect.
Here, we want to point
to the DictionaryStorage attribute
the user wrote,
which, happily, is provided
by the "attribute" parameter
the method was passed.
The second is the actual message
you want the compiler to produce.
You provide this by creating a custom type
and then passing an instance of it.
Let's take a quick look at it.
The "MyLibDiagnostic" type defines all of
the diagnostics this module can produce.
We've chosen to use an enum
and provide a case for each diagnostic,
but you could use another kind
of type if you wanted.
This type works sort of like
a throwable Swift error.
It conforms
to the "DiagnosticMessage" protocol,
and it has a bunch of properties that
provide information about the diagnostic.
One of the most important
is the "severity" property.
It specifies whether the diagnostic
is an error or a warning.
Then there's the "message" property,
which produces the actual error message,
and the "diagnosticID" property.
You should use
the plug-in's module name for the domain
and some kind of unique string for the ID.
I've chosen
to use string raw values for this enum,
but that's just a convenience.
So with the message in hand,
you can create the diagnostic.
Then you tell the context to diagnose it,
and you're done.
That's a pretty basic diagnostic,
but if you want,
you can get a lot fancier with them.
For example,
you can add Fix-Its to a diagnostic
you still need
to actually create the expansion.
SwiftSyntax gives you several
different tools to do that.
Syntax nodes are immutable,
but they have lots of APIs
that either create new nodes or return
modified versions of existing nodes.
The SwiftSyntaxBuilder library
adds SwiftUI-style syntax builders
where some of the child nodes
are specified by a trailing closure.
For example, the multidimensional
array macro can use a syntax builder
to generate whatever number of parameters
is appropriate for the type it's creating.
And the string literal feature we used
to make the DictionaryStorage property
and initializer
also supports interpolations.
All of these features are useful
in different situations,
and you'll probably find yourself
combining several
in particularly complicated macros.
But the string literal feature
is especially good
at producing syntax trees
for large amounts of code,
and there's a bit to learn
about its interpolation features.
So let's look at how you might use those
to generate some code.
Earlier, we talked
about the "unwrap" macro.
It takes an optional value
and a message string
and expands into a "guard let"
wrapped in a closure.
The general shape of this code
is always going to be the same,
but a lot of the contents are customized
for the specific use site.
Let's focus in on the "guard let"
statement and see how
we could write a function
to generate just that statement.
To start, we'll just take
that exact code sample we just saw
and put it in a helper method
called "makeGuardStatement"
that returns a Statement Syntax node.
Then we'll slowly add interpolations
to replace all the stuff
An ordinary interpolation like this
can add a syntax node to the code,
but it can't add a plain String.
That's a safety feature to keep you
from inserting invalid code by accident.
The guard-let condition is similar,
except that it's just a variable name,
so it's a token, not an expression.
No matter, we add a TokenSyntax
parameter and interpolate it in,
just as we interpolated the expression.
There's a trickier case when you add
the expression being unwrapped
to the error message.
One of the features
of our macro is that when it fails,
it prints out the code
you were trying to unwrap.
That means we need
to create a string literal
that contains a stringified version
of a syntax node.
Let's start by pulling the prefix
out of the Statement Syntax literal
and into a variable
that's just a plain string.
We'll interpolate that string in,
but we'll use a special interpolation
that starts with "literal:".
When you do this,
SwiftSyntax will add the contents
of the string as a string literal.
This also works for making literals
from other kinds of information
computed by the macro,
numbers, Booleans, arrays, dictionaries,
and even optionals.
Now that we're building up
the string in a variable,
we can change it to have
the right code in the message.
Just add a parameter
for the original expression,
and interpolate
its "description" property into the string.
You don't need
to do anything special to escape it.
The "literal:" interpolation
will automatically detect
if the string contains special characters
and add escapes
or switch to a raw literal
to make sure the code is valid.
So the "literal:" interpolation
makes it super easy to do the right thing.
The last thing to deal with
are the file and line numbers.
These are a little tricky
because the compiler
and then we'll use
its "location of" method.
This returns an object that can
produce syntax nodes for the location
of whatever node you provide.
It will return nil if the node
is one that your macro created,
rather than one
that the compiler passed in to you,
but we know that "originalWrapped" is one
of the arguments that the user wrote,
so its location will never be nil,
and we can safely force-unwrap the result.
Now all you have to do
is interpolate the syntax nodes
for the file and line number,
and you're done.
We're now generating
the right "guard" statement.
So far, we've discussed how
to make macros work at all.
But let's move on and talk
about how to make them work well.
And we'll start
by talking about name collisions.
When we looked
at the "unwrap" macro before,
we looked at an example where
we unwrapped a simple variable name.
But if we try to unwrap
a more complicated expression,
the macro has to expand differently.
It generates code
which captures the expression's result
into a variable called "wrappedValue,"
and then unwraps that.
But what happens if you try
to use a variable called "wrappedValue"
in the message?
When the compiler goes looking
for "wrappedValue",
it'll end up finding the closer one,
so it'll use that
instead of the one you actually meant.
You could try to fix this by picking
a name that you think your users
probably won't use by accident,
but wouldn't it be better
to make this impossible?
That's what the "makeUniqueName" method
on the Macro Expansion Context does.
It returns a variable name
that's guaranteed to not be used
in user code
or in any other macro expansion,
so you can be sure that the message string
won't accidentally refer to it.
Some of you might be wondering,
why doesn't Swift
automatically stop that from happening?
Think of the DictionaryStorage macro,
which uses
a "dictionary" property on the type.
If "dictionary" inside a macro
meant something different
from "dictionary" outside,
it'd be pretty hard to make that work.
And sometimes, you even want
to introduce a whole new name
that non-macro code can access.
Peer macros, member macros,
and declaration macros basically exist
entirely to do this.
But when they do,
they need to declare the names
they're adding,
so the compiler knows about them.
And they do
that inside their role attribute.
You might not have noticed it before,
but we've actually seen
these declarations all along.
The "member" role
on the DictionaryStorage macro
had a "names:" parameter
that specified
the names "dictionary" and "init".
And in fact,
most of the macros we've looked at
in this session have at least one role
with a "names" argument.
There are five name specifiers
you can use:
"Overloaded" means
that the macro adds declarations
with the exact same base name
as whatever the macro is attached to.
"Prefixed" means that the macro adds
declarations with the same base name,
except with the specified prefix added.
"Suffixed" is the same thing,
except with a suffix instead of a prefix.
"Named" means
that the macro adds declarations
with a specific, fixed base name.
And "arbitrary" means
that the macro adds declarations
with some other name that can't be
described using any of these rules.
It's really common to use "arbitrary."
For example,
our multidimensional array macro
declares a type
with a name that's computed
from one of its parameters,
so it needs to specify "arbitrary."