♪ ♪
Jared: Hello, and welcome
to "What's new in Background Assets."
My name is Jared,
and I'm a software engineer here at Apple.
I'm really looking forward
to sharing with you
everything that's new this year
with Background Assets.
Now, our team has changed a few things
over the last year.
However, I'd encourage you to check out
my prior session
where Background Assets was introduced.
There's a lot of detailed information
in there
that this new session builds upon.
In this session, I'll start by giving you
an overview of Background Assets
and why you should adopt it into your app.
Then, I'll discuss what's new
this year in Background Assets,
which includes an entirely new feature
that our team has been
really excited to share with you.
I'll then walk you through a sample
implementation of Background Assets
that you can even download yourself,
and I'll show you how adopting
this technology can significantly improve
the user experience of your app.
I'll then give you some guidance
on debugging your app extension
and simulating its entry points.
Okay! Let's go over a quick recap
of Background Assets.
One of the primary goals behind
Background Assets is to prevent waiting.
The last thing a user wants to experience
is to launch your app
and have to wait
for a large download to complete.
Background Assets solves this problem
through a combination
of its framework
and an associated app extension.
This new technology was introduced
in iOS 16.1
alongside the initial release
of macOS Ventura.
It supports the ability to download
additional content for your app
using your CDN provider
or a server you manage.
For instance, this content may be fetched
during an initial app install,
when the app updates,
or periodically in the background
when the user isn't using your app.
Through the paired app extension,
you are able to write code
that runs when the app is not
actively being used by the user.
This technology is currently supported
on macOS, iOS, and iPadOS,
so it's already available
on your favorite platforms.
One of best parts
about using Background Assets
is that the extension has
the ability to run
before the user has launched your app.
This provides a way
to start fetching assets
the moment your app is installed
through the App Store.
The extension may also be launched by
the system periodically in the background.
This is to ensure that any new
or updated assets are present
when your app is launched by the user.
The extension is also used to service
downloads when the app is not running.
For instance,
when a file finishes downloading,
the extension will be launched
so that it can move the file
to its final destination.
Something to keep in mind is that
the extension's runtime is limited.
This is to ensure that the user's device
is optimized for power and performance.
I'll go into more details
about this shortly.
It's also important to know
that the app extension you develop
to use with Background Assets is
placed into a specialized sandbox.
This is to ensure that the extension
is only being used
to manage content via Background Assets.
If you find that a capability or API
is not available within the sandbox,
please reach out to us
through Feedback Assistant.
I mentioned earlier
that your app extension is invoked
during three system events:
app install, app update,
and periodically in the background.
Let's take a look
at how this lifecycle is managed.
The lifecycle of your extension
begins when the App Store installs
or updates your app on the device.
The Background Assets system service
is then notified
and prevents the app from launching.
The system then inspects your app bundle
and reads its Info.plist
for the BAManifestURL key.
The system will begin downloading
the manifest referenced by that key
and report progress of the download
back to the App Store.
Once your manifest has been downloaded,
the system then wakes your extension
by issuing a content request
for the given install or update event.
The content request includes a path
to the downloaded manifest.
Your extension should use the manifest
to determine the URLs,
file sizes, and what assets
to schedule for download.
Then once your extension has determined
what assets need to be downloaded,
it will return those downloads
as a set of BADownloads.
The system then pauses your app extension,
or sometimes terminates it,
to save power and performance
on the device.
The downloads will then begin
and your extension will be notified
shortly after their completion.
The periodic content request is
nearly identical to the app install event,
with the only key difference being
that your device determines
when the event will occur.
The device makes this decision based on
how the user has been using their device.
Key factors such as Low Power Mode,
Background App Refresh,
or how frequently your app has
been launched are all considered.
Now, let's dive a little deeper
and look at the factors
that contribute to when
your extension runs periodically.
We care a lot about a device's
overall performance and power usage,
which is why Background Assets
has limitations
placed on the extension's runtime.
This includes an enforcement
on your extension's memory usage.
If your extension exceeds
a few megabytes of memory,
it may be terminated by the system.
So you may want to consider memory mapping
any large files
that your extension needs to read,
as memory-mapped data
backed by the device's storage
does not count against this limitation.
When an app is initially installed,
it is provided with a default allotment
of a few minutes of runtime per day.
While this may not sound like much,
with a properly designed extension,
this can go a long way.
The runtime also changes
based on app usage.
If an app hasn't been launched
in some time,
the system may start throttling
launches of the extension.
For instance, a rarely used app may see
its runtime more heavily restricted,
whereas a commonly used app
may be given additional runtime.
The BADownloaderExtension protocol
defines functions that are used
as entry points into your app extension.
The runtime starts being counted
when a function is invoked by the system
and stops being counted
when that function exits scope.
Once your function exits scope
or your extension's runtime
has been exhausted,
the system may suspend
or terminate the extension.
I'll provide an example in a moment.
However, there is one exception
to function scope controlling
the runtime of your extension.
If an asynchronous
exclusive control API is invoked,
your extension will be kept running
up until the point
that its completion handler
is invoked and returned.
There are a couple of ways
that the extension's runtime
may be controlled by the user.
For instance,
if the device is in Low Power Mode
or has Background App Refresh disabled,
whether that's globally
or for your specific app,
then your extension will never run.
Previously, I mentioned
how extension runtime is determined
based on function scope.
Let's have a look at an example
to better understand how that works.
This code represents
the extension's interface
that services your background downloads.
The BADownloaderExtension protocol
defines the functions
that the system will invoke
into your extension.
Now let's add one of the required
functions to conform to this protocol.
The "downloads for request" function
is one of the primary entry points
into the extension.
Its BAContentRequest defines
if it's being invoked
during an app install, app update,
or as a part of a periodic check
in the background.
The manifestURL argument
provides a path to a local file
that was downloaded
before the extension was invoked.
The manifest file is commonly used
to compare what is currently downloaded
versus what downloads might be available
on the server.
The function definition's
return type requires
a set of download objects
that conform to the BADownload type.
This means that answering
this function's request
requires you to synchronously return
any content needing to be downloaded
before the function exits scope.
However, in this contrived example,
let's say that you invoke
a function called parseManifest.
This function reads
the downloaded manifest
and then returns the BADownload objects
needing to be downloaded.
However, let's say that the parseManifest
function is poorly implemented
and takes 30 minutes to parse
and construct the downloads.
This will end up exceeding
the extension's runtime significantly,
and the extension will be terminated.
It's important to remember
that the extension's runtime is calculated
from the moment the "downloads
for request" function is called,
up until the point
it exits scope and returns.
Let's take a look
at another problematic example.
Whenever any of the BADownloaderExtension
protocol functions exit scope,
the extension may become suspended
and then terminated.
You'll notice that the protocol does not
define any of its functions as mutating,
and there's a good reason for this.
When your extension is terminated,
any instance variables
or in-memory state will not be saved.
If your extension needs to maintain
any state,
you should serialize that state to disk.
Next, let's talk about the API you'll use
from both the extension and app
to manage downloads.
The download manager
within the framework is the primary way
to communicate with
the Background Assets system service.
The manager is a singleton object
that can be used throughout your app.
Using the manager, you can schedule
downloads of your assets
in the background and promote
already scheduled downloads
to the foreground.
From the download manager,
you can also manage downloads
that are currently in-flight,
which I mentioned earlier could have been
scheduled by the extension
before your app was ever launched.
There's also a synchronization mechanism
that you may use
to ensure that both your app
and its associated extension
are not performing similar operations
at the same time.
The last thing I'd like to bring up
about the download manager
is that it has a delegate
for receiving callbacks about downloads,
similar to
the BADownloaderExtension protocol.
If you register a delegate
on BADownloadManager,
then it will receive those callbacks
instead of your extension.
This is useful
as it provides your app a way
to manage its downloads
while it is running.
Now that you've had a quick refresher
about how to manage downloads,
let's talk about
how you should manage those files
once they're already on the user's device.
Any files you download with
Background Assets are marked purgeable,
which means that the system may
remove them under critical circumstances.
Think a system security update
or if a user needs to capture a video
of their child's first step.
However, if you modify
or expand a downloaded asset,
then those files are not tracked
by the system
and therefore are not purgeable.
You should think carefully
about how you modify assets
or extract data out of them.
If you incorrectly manage
your downloaded assets,
you could increase the size
of a user's backup of their device
or prevent a critical security update
from being downloaded.
Therefore, you should try to store
your downloaded assets
in your caches directory.
That way, the system knows
that it can purge them
when it is critical to do so.
Now that you have a full recap
of how all of this works,
let's take a look at what's new this year
with Background Assets.
Earlier this year,
we introduced essential downloads,
which provides a way to fetch content
while your app is installing or updating.
This means that your downloads
are completely integrated
into the iOS Home Screen,
macOS Launchpad, and the App Store.
To the end user,
the download of your assets appear to them
as if the app is currently still being
downloaded from the App Store.
This also means that while
your essential downloads are in-flight,
your app cannot be launched by the user.
All the user can do is
cancel or pause installation.
Since pauses are supported,
your server should support HTTP ranges
so that resumes are possible.
Since essential downloads occur
during app install,
they take priority
over any non-essential downloads.
Let's take a look.
It all begins when your app is requested
from the App Store or TestFlight.
If the app's Info.plist
contains essential asset keys,
then progress is set up on the device
and we go through this flow.
Once your app has been
downloaded and installed,
the system wakes your extension
by issuing a request for content,
which includes whether the request is
for an app install,
app update, or for a periodic fetch.
During this time,
an authentication challenge may be sent
in order for the manifest
to be downloaded.
Your extension will then vend back
a combination of essential
and non-essential downloads.
As a side note,
it's important that your extension
vends the downloads back quickly,
as your app's download progress
will appear frozen to the user
until this function returns.
The moment
the extension provides the downloads,
any downloads that were marked
as essential will immediately begin.
Your extension may also receive
an additional authentication challenge
during this time.
Once all of your essential downloads
have finished,
the system will terminate your extension
and the app will become launchable
by the user.
The extension will then receive
a batch of successful
and potentially failed downloads.
If there are any failed downloads
you can re-enqueue them
as nonessential using BADownloadManager.
As your extension is receiving
completion messages
for essential downloads,
the system will immediately start
downloading the nonessential assets.
The nonessential downloads
will then be sent to the extension
as they finish downloading.
Now let's take a look
at how essential downloads integrate
into the App Store installation progress
on the iOS Home Screen.
A percentage of the progress indicator
is broken down
into the time it takes
to download your base app,
plus the amount of time to do the install,
followed by the amount of time necessary
to download your essential assets.
The new BAEssentialDownloadAllowance key
defined in your app's Info.plist
is used to set up
the initial overall progress indicator.
Then once contentForRequest
is invoked into your extension
and your extension returns downloads,
the file size of each essential download
is added together
to determine how much
is actually being downloaded.
If the amount that you schedule
for download is significantly less
than the essential download allowance,
then the progress indicator may move
rather quickly.
You should aim to get
your essential download allowance
close to what is actually being downloaded
to ensure smooth progress for the user.
It's important to keep in mind
that everything we've discussed
can be disabled by the user.
In the App Store settings pane,
there is a section
for disabling in-app content.
While this doesn't disable
Background Assets in its entirety,
it does prevent essential assets
from downloading
and the ability for the extension to run
before the app has been launched
by the user.
So it's important to think
of essential assets as just that:
essential but not a requirement
for your app to launch.
Therefore, its important
for your app to handle flows
where essential assets are not
already on the device
when your app is launched.
The ability to use essential assets
was actually introduced
earlier in the spring as part of iOS 16.4
and macOS Ventura 13.3.
The new APIs are quite minimal
and should be easily added
into your existing extension.
The first API that was created
to support essential downloads
was actually a new initializer
on BAURLDownload.
There are two new arguments we've added
specifically to support this feature.
The essential argument,
as its name implies,
specifies if the download should be
marked as essential,
where essential means contributing
to the app's overall download
and installation progress.
The file size argument is the size
of the assets that will be downloaded.
The file size must be accurate
when creating essential downloads.
The system needs this information
so that the app install progress
on the user's device
is displayed properly.
If the file
that Background Assets downloads
does not match the file size
provided here,
then the download will fail
if the download is marked as essential.
If your extension does not know
the size of the file,
then the file size should be included
in the BAManifestURL
that is provided to the extension
before the extension is launched.
Another API that was introduced
provides an easy one-liner
for creating a nonessential
representation of a download.
Since essential downloads
can only be enqueued
in the contentForRequest function,
this API can be useful in many cases.
For example, let's say fetching
an essential download failed,
perhaps because of a networking issue
or the file was
simply temporarily unavailable.
Well, in the background download
failed function
within your extension,
you can easily create
a nonessential representation
of that download and re-enqueue it.
The download will then begin
in the background
and your extension or app
will be notified when it is completed.
Now let's take a look
at some of the required keys
that need to be present
in your app's Info.plist.
In last year's session,
I went over each of these keys in detail.
If you'd like a more in-depth explanation,
I'd encourage you to check out that talk.
It's important to keep in mind
that these keys are required
not only to use
the Background Assets framework,
but are also necessary in order
to submit your app to the App Store.
There are two new keys this year
that are required
to support essential assets:
BAEssentialDownloadAllowance
and BAEssentialMaxInstallSize.
The essential download allowance
is represented in bytes
and defines an upper bound
on how large the sum
of all of your essential assets
will take to download.
It's important to try to get this number
as close as possible
to the size of the essential assets
you enqueue
so that download progress is smooth
for the user when they install your app.
The other new key,
BAEssentialMaxInstallSize,
represents the maximum size of those
assets extracted onto the user's device.
This number appears on the App Store
as a way to tell users
how much storage your app will use after
the essential assets have been installed.
That pretty much sums up the new APIs
we've added for essential assets.
As you just saw,
adding essential assets support
to your existing app can be done
with minimal code changes.
It's really just that easy.
Now for the fun part.
Let's take a look at how you can extend
an existing app
that uses URLSession
into using Background Assets.
The app I'll be showing you today
downloads WWDC Sessions,
just like this one, and stores them
on your device for offline viewing.
Currently, the app has to be launched
before the videos will download.
By adopting Background Assets,
we can eliminate this wait time
by having the videos already downloaded
before the app is launched.
Let's have a look.
Here's the app
we'll be building upon today.
You'll notice
that the moment it is launched,
sessions immediately begin downloading.
The way this app currently works
is that a manifest downloads
from a server,
which contains a list of WWDC sessions.
After the manifest is fetched,
the sessions start downloading
and then become viewable once tapped.
Let's take a look at what's necessary
to adopt Background Assets
into this project.
Before you begin to use
the Background Assets API,
the first thing to add are the initial
Info.plist keys that I discussed earlier.
These key are required to be present
in your app bundle's Info.plist file.
The next thing you'll need to do is add
a background download extension
and embed it into your app.
You'll want to make sure
that your extension's bundle identifier
is prefixed
with your app's bundle identifier.
You'll also want to ensure
that both your app and its extension
are in a common app group,
as the app group is how your extension
shares downloaded assets with your app.
The last thing you'll want to ensure
is that both your app
and its extension
are signed with your team identifier.
With those steps out of the way,
you can begin to adopt Background Assets.
Here in front of you is the Xcode project
for the app you just saw.
I've already went
and created the download extension
and embedded it into the app.
I've also added
the required Info.plist keys.
With all of that out of the way,
let's begin by navigating
to the SessionManager.
The SessionManager in this project
currently uses URLSession
to fetch the latest downloads.
URLSession is a fantastic API.
We'll continue to use it within the app
to fetch the manifest.
However, we'll migrate
to using Background Assets
to fetch the actual sessions.
This is so that the app can take advantage
of promoting any assets
scheduled in the background
by the extension we're about to create
to the foreground
when the app is launched.
To begin, we'll starting by importing
the Background Assets framework module.
I'll then scroll down and remove
the variables associated with URLSession
as they are no longer needed.
Now I'll navigate
to the "start download" method.
As you can see, the existing code
was tracking sessions to download
by the URLSession download task.
This won't be necessary anymore,
so let's remove it.
Here's where things begin
to get interesting.
When you work with Background Assets,
its important to think about
your extension and app
possibly running at the same time.
To coordinate this
in a near effortless way,
you'll need to use withExclusiveControl
to guarantee
that any work that needs mutual exclusion
with the other process can do so.
Let's add that in now.
As you can tell,
this API is asynchronous and escaping.
Any work scheduled inside the closure
is guaranteed to run
independently from the extension
if the extension also uses this API.
We'll implement the extension in a moment,
but for now, let's focus on the app.
Since we know we're running
in a mutually exclusive context,
let's ask the download manager if there
are currently any downloads in-flight.
There's no reason
to reschedule a download
if the extension has already scheduled it.
However, one thing we can do is,
if we find an existing download,
we can promote it to the foreground.
Promoting a download to the foreground
can significantly decrease
the time it takes
for a download to finish.
Since the user is currently using the app,
it's a great opportunity
to fetch the download
as quickly as possible.
The user might want to view it.
If the download does not already exist,
we'll create it.
Then, regardless of if
we just created the download
or if the extension did, we'll go ahead
and start it in the foreground.
Promoting a download
from the background to the foreground
does not cause the download to restart,
it is simply resumed
from where it left off in that transition.
The next thing on the list is to implement
the BADownloadManagerDelegate,
but before I do that,
I'll delete the old URLSessionDelegate.
Now that the old delegate is gone,
let's create
the Background Assets delegate.
Since the session manager is
now conforming to the delegate,
it's important that it's wired up
to actually receive those messages.
So I'll go up to the initializer
and wire that up now.
Since BADownloadManager connects
directly to the system scheduler,
it's a singleton object.
Having this delegate
attached to the download manager
will cause your app to receive messages
over the extension
if your app is currently running.
Now let's head back to the functions
we need to implement.
For this app,
there are three specific functions
on the delegate protocol
that we'll be implementing.
The first is for progress handling.
Let's implement that now.
Before we start
blindly updating progress in the UI,
we'll make sure that the download
we're receiving progress messages for
is something that the manifest
is currently tracking.
If a download is being tracked,
we'll call updateDownloadProgress,
which is a helper function within the app
that sends the progress
directly over to SwiftUI.
Next, I'll implement what happens
when a download finishes.
It starts pretty much the same way,
which is to make sure
it's handling only downloads
that are expected.
Then replaceItemAt is used to move
the object from the temporary location
that Background Assets has given us
to its final location.
It's important to use
move operations here,
as the system will track
and purge the file
if the device becomes low on space.
So you should make sure
that your app always checks
to see if any files are missing
and refetches it if it so needs to.
The last thing that happens here is,
a Task is spawned
against the MainActor,
the state is marked as downloaded,
and the app begins fetching
the session's thumbnail.
Now, I'd like to say
that all downloads will succeed.
However, the unfortunate truth is
that they can fail,
whether that's because the server
no longer has that resource
or there's a network issue.
Background Assets does retry and wait
for network connectivity problems,
but after a certain point in time,
you have to know
that the file is not on its way.
Another thing to keep in mind is
that downloads that are promoted
to the foreground will fail
almost instantly
if there is a network connectivity issue.
There's not much our app needs to do
when a download fails.
It could present UI or reschedule it,
but for this example,
let's log that there was a problem.
Since the delegate
is now fully implemented,
let's relaunch the app
and see how it looks.
Well, to no surprise, it looks identical,
and that's what
we really wanted to see here.
Adding Background Assets in place
of URLSession is quite effortless.
The next thing I'll show you is
how to implement the app extension
for handling background downloading.
Adding this app extension is how
you can leverage Background Assets
to fetch your content
before your app is installed or updated
and is what provides the support
for enqueuing essential assets.
In essence,
the extension is what is responsible
for scheduling downloads
while your app is not running.
Let's have a look.
Here we are
in the background download handler,
which receives messages
within your extension
related to Background Assets.
From the extension,
the first thing I'll do is create a logger
so that we can see from Console.app
when our extension is running.
Next, I'll implement
the contentForRequest function
that's part
of the BADownloaderExtension protocol.
The first thing this extension will do
is parse the manifest
that was predownloaded
before the extension was launched.
If the manifest that was downloaded
is somehow invalid,
the extension will be configured
to enqueue no downloads.
Once the extension knows
that the manifest is valid,
it is atomically saved into the app group.
This is so that the app and the extension
have the latest version of the manifest
locally that they can reference later.
Since this save is done atomically,
using withExclusiveControl
is not necessary.
The extension will then create
a mutable set of download objects
that the extension will return
to the system to be scheduled.
As discussed earlier,
essential downloads are only supported
during app installation or app update.
I'll then iterate through the manifest
for all sessions that are remote,
which in this context means
that they aren't downloaded.
A BAURLDownload object is then created
for every download
that needs to be scheduled.
The download is given a unique identifier,
a URLRequest,
an annotation for if the download
should be fetched as essential,
its file size, the app group
the asset will be downloaded into,
and a relative priority
to control which downloads
the scheduler should start first.
One important thing to keep in mind
is that any downloads marked as essential
must have an accurate file size,
or the download will marked as a failure.
This is to support smooth progress
on the iOS Home Screen,
macOS Launchpad, and the App Store.
Now that we have support
for enqueuing downloads,
let's take a look
at handling successful downloads.
The extension processes downloads
if the app is not running
or if the app doesn't have a delegate
assigned to BADownloadManager.
The first thing I'll implement
in the download finished handler
will be asynchronously acquiring
exclusive control.
Since acquiring exclusive control
is asynchronous,
we need to hang on to the temporary file
the extension just vended us.
As you can see,
I'm accomplishing this by moving the file
into a temporary location
that will outlive this function's scope.
I'll also add a Swift defer
to ensure that the ephemeral file
that the extension downloads
is always cleaned up.
Although the system will
delete the file for you,
it's best practice to manage it yourself.
I'll then load the manifest
from the app group
and verify its validity.
The extension will then check
to make sure the downloaded identifier
being processed matches a session
that is expected in the manifest.
Then the extension will move that file
from its ephemeral location
to its final destination
inside the app group.
A LocalSession is then constructed
to quickly validate
that the session is downloaded
into its appropriate location.
The last thing to handle
are failed downloads.
An important thing
that is commonly forgotten
is that if a BAManifestURL
fails to download,
the extension is actually notified
about it.
Its type inherits from BAURLDownload.
However, that's not
its exact internal type.
Therefore, the extension filters
to ensure its only dealing
with BAURLDownload objects.
Since essential assets download
in the foreground,
they only wait a few seconds
for network connectivity
since those downloads impact
app installation progress.
Therefore,
it can be a good idea to re-enqueue
essential downloads as nonessential
if they happen to fail.
One way you can easily convert
an essential download
into being nonessential is to use
the new removingEssential() function.
That function returns
a nonessential copy.
You then vend that copy
to BADownloadManager's
scheduleDownload function.
The system will then fetch the download
at an opportune time.
Now that our app and its extension
have fully adopted Background Assets,
let's add some UI that indicates
that a specific session was downloaded
as essential.
Remember, essential means
that app installation and app update
prohibit app launch
until the assets are fully downloaded.
However, since the app being blocked
from launching only occurs
during an install from the App Store
or TestFlight,
having an indicator present
is a good way to visibly recognize this.
This indicator will be implemented
in SwiftUI within the VideoSelector view.
If the session is marked as essential
in the manifest,
a green circle is drawn
in the navigation view.
And that's all there is to it.
Now that you've seen just how easy it is
to implement Background Assets,
let's take a look
at debugging the extension
and simulating its entry points.
As I discussed earlier,
the extension launches
during an app install, app update,
or periodically in the background.
Since app installation is controlled
by the App Store
and periodic events are controlled
by the device,
you'll need a way to force your extension
to launch in order to debug it.
Fortunately, our team has created
a tool that ships with Xcode,
which can be used to launch the extension
and simulate its entry points.
The tool is accessible from Terminal
and can be launched
by entering xcrun backgroundassets-debug.
There is also help information
and a man page that goes along with it.
When using backgroundassets-debug,
you pass in a simulate argument
that provides the ability to trigger
different types of BAContentRequests.
When any of these simulation messages
are sent to the device,
your extension's runtime is reset
to help ease your debugging.
backgroundassets-debug
provides numerous features,
including support for multiple devices.
As long as the device is paired
with your Mac,
it can be used to simulate your extension.
These commands may be sent
over Bluetooth or Wi-Fi
so that your device doesn't have to be
tethered to your Mac via USB.
Lastly, Developer Mode must be
turned on in order for the device
to honor simulation events
triggered by backgroundassets-debug.
This can be easily enabled
from the Privacy & Security section
within your device's Settings app.
Now let's take a look at using
the backgroundassets-debug tool
with the demo app we just built.
Here we are in Terminal.
Since Xcode is installed on this Mac,
I'll go ahead and list
the connected devices.
You'll see that there is currently
only one connected device,
and that happens to be my iPhone.
You'll want to copy the device's UUID
that you are choosing to simulate against.
In the arguments provided,
you see that the device's UUID is present
along with the app's bundle identifier.
I'll be invoking the tool
using the simulate argument
mixed with the app-install argument.
This will cause the app extension to wake
as if it's being awoken
during an initial app-install event.
Now that I've pressed enter,
the tool tells you
that the app-install event
has been sent to the device.
Let's launch the app
and see what it looks like.
As you can see, all of the session videos
have been enqueued for download.
Some of them, as I'm speaking,
have already finished downloading.
And that's Background Assets in action.
If you're like me,
you've probably already started thinking
about the many potential ways
to reduce waiting in your apps.
Now that I showed you
how to debug your app extension,
let's take a look
at some important things to remember.
Essential assets download with the app
and contribute
to app installation progress.
Therefore, these types of assets
are only schedulable
during a BAContentRequest install
or update event within the extension.
If any essential downloads
that were enqueued by the extension fail,
the app will
eventually still become launchable.
You must ensure that you re-enqueue
your essential downloads as nonessential
either within the extension
or on first app launch
if you require those assets.
Any downloads not marked as essential
are downloaded
after the app is installed or updated
and receive background download priority.
It's also important to remember
that the extension is limited
by its memory usage.
So make sure to debug your extension
to ensure that the code you write
is well below the memory threshold.
If your extension uses excessive memory,
you will notice that it will crash
with a memory exception while debugging.
If the extension crashes
during an app install
or app update content request,
then the app will become
immediately launchable.
And finally,
remember to make your app a good citizen
by managing the assets
it downloads appropriately.
One way to manage those assets
is by placing them
into your app's caches directory.
So that's what we have this year
for Background Assets.
If there's anything
you should take away from this session,
it's to eliminate waiting in your apps.
One way you can eliminate waiting
is by adopting Background Assets
and using
the new essential assets feature.
Make sure to utilize TestFlight before
submitting the app to the App Store.
By using TestFlight,
you'll be able to see what it looks like
when your essential assets download
with your app.
If at any point you find yourself
with questions,
please check out
the developer documentation
and feel free to reach out
on the Apple Developer Forums.
I'd also like to encourage you
to utilize Feedback Assistant.
Our team is constantly improving
Background Assets,
and we're looking forward
to having you adopt it into your app.
Oh, and if you haven't already,
I'd recommend checking out
my prior session where
Background Assets was introduced.
There's a lot
of additional information in there.
And with that,
thanks for joining me today.
On behalf of everyone at Apple,
thanks for watching.