♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Omid Khalili: Hello!
My name is Omid.
Oliver and I are engineers
on the ARKit team
and we are thrilled
to review the concepts --
some familiar and some new --
that you'll need know about
when bringing your iOS AR app
to our new platform.
ARKit was introduced
on iOS in 2017
and with it, we introduced
three key concepts
to building augmented reality
applications.
With world tracking,
ARKit is able to track your
device's position in the world
with six degrees of freedom.
This allows anchoring
virtual content
with a position and orientation
to the real world.
Scene understanding
provides insight
about the real world around you.
Using the provided geometry
and semantic knowledge,
your content can be
intelligently placed
and realistically interact
with surroundings.
Finally, rendering engines can
correctly register and composite
your virtual content
over captured images
utilizing camera transforms
and intrinsics
provided by ARKit.
Initially, we started
with a SceneKit view
to use ARKit's
camera transforms
and render 3D content on iOS.
We then introduced
RealityKit,
laying out the foundation
for an engine
capable of highly realistic
physically-based rendering
and accurate object simulation
with your surroundings.
To enable spatial computing,
ARKit and RealityKit
have matured
and are deeply integrated
into the operating system.
For example, ARKit's tracking
and Scene Understanding
are now running
as system services,
backing everything
from window placement
to spatial audio.
The system takes on
responsibilities
that used to belong
to applications.
Camera pass-through and matting
of the user's hands
are now built-in,
so your application gets these
capabilities for free.
Another built-in capability
is that ARKit world maps
are continuously persisted
by a system service,
so your application
doesn't need to do it anymore.
We believe that
this will free you up
to focus on building the best
application and content possible
for this platform.
Here is an example demonstrating
these capabilities,
along with new ones
introduced with this platform.
For example, ARKit now provides
hand tracking to your app,
which allows people to reach out
and directly interact
with virtual content
that can then interact
with their surroundings.
In order to take advantage
of all the new capabilities
and immersive experiences
this new platform offers,
you'll need to update your iOS
ARKit-based experience.
This is a great opportunity
to reimagine your app
and AR experience
for spatial computing.
As a part of this transition,
you'll be using familiar
concepts
that we've introduced
with ARKit and RealityKit.
We're going to cover how these
concepts have carried over,
how they've evolved,
and how you can
take advantage of them.
Let's get started!
First, we'll explore some new
ways you can present your app
for spatial computing,
and introduce new content tools
available to you.
Next, we will talk
about Reality Kit,
which is the engine to use
to render
and interact
with your content.
We'll see how RealityView
lets your app
leverage spatial computing
similar to ARView on iOS.
Then, we'll talk about
the different ways
your app can bring content
into people's surroundings.
Raycasting is something
many iOS applications use
to place content.
We'll show an example
of how to combine ARKit data
and RealityKit
to enable raycasting
for spatial computing.
And finally, we'll review
the updates to ARKit
and see the new ways to utilize
familiar concepts from iOS.
Lets get into preparing
to migrate your experience
for spatial computing.
Spatial computing allows you
to take your iOS AR experience
and expand it
beyond the window.
This platform offers new ways
to present your application
that you'll want to consider
as you bring your
iOS experience over.
Here is an example from
our Hello World sample app.
You can now display UI,
including windows
and three-dimensional content,
anywhere around you.
By default,
applications on this platform
launch into the Shared Space.
The Shared Space is where
apps exist side by side,
much like multiple apps
on a Mac desktop.
Inside a Shared Space, your app
can open one or more windows
to display content.
Additionally,
your app can create
a three-dimensional volume.
For example, now you can show
a list of available board games
in one window,
the rules in another,
and open the selected game
in its own volume.
The game can be played while
keeping a Safari window open
to read up
on winning strategies.
The content you add
to the window and volume
stays contained
within its bounds
to allow sharing the space
with other applications.
In some cases, you may want
your app to have more control
over the level of immersion
in your experience --
maybe to play a game
that interacts with your room.
For this, your app can open
a dedicated Full Space
in which only
your app's windows,
volumes,
and 3D objects appear.
Once in a Full Space,
your application has access
to more features.
Using RealityKit's
anchor entities,
you can target and attach
objects to the surroundings
like tables, floors,
and even parts of your hands
like the palm or wrist.
Anchor entities work without
requiring user permission.
ARKit data is something else
your app can only access
in a Full Space.
With permission,
ARKit will provide data
about the real-world surfaces,
scene geometry,
and skeletal hand tracking,
expanding your app's
ability for realistic physics
and natural interactions.
Windows, volumes, and spaces
are all SwiftUI scene types.
There's so much more
for you to learn about these.
For starters, you can go
to the session mentioned here.
Next, let's review the main
steps needed to prepare
your content for bringing it
to spatial computing.
Memorable AR experiences on iOS
begin with great 3D content;
the same is true for spatial
experiences on this platform.
And when it comes
to 3D content,
it's great to rely
on an open standard like
Universal Scene Description,
or USD for short.
USD is production proven,
and scales from creators
making single assets
to large studios working on
AAA games and films.
Apple was an early
adopter of USD,
adding it to our platforms
in 2017
and growing support since.
Today, USD is at the heart
of 3D content
for spatial computing.
With USD assets ready,
you can bring them into
our new developer tool,
Reality Composer Pro,
to compose, edit, and preview
your 3D content.
If you're using CustomMaterials
for your 3D content on iOS,
then you will need to rebuild
them using its shader graph.
You also have the ability to
edit your RealityKit components
directly through the UI.
And finally, you can import your
Reality Composer Pro project
directly into Xcode,
allowing you to easily
bundle all of your USD assets,
materials, and custom components
into your Xcode project.
We have some great sessions
to help you learn more
about Reality Composer Pro
and how to build your own custom
materials for spatial computing.
Now that we've seen
the different ways
to present your application,
let's learn more about
the features RealityView offers
as you bring
your experience over.
We just saw
how spatial computing
allows apps to display content
in your space.
One of the key differences
coming from iOS
is how different elements
can be presented side by side.
Notice how your 3D content
and 2D elements can appear
and work along side each other.
Coming from iOS,
you're going to use
familiar frameworks
to create each of these.
You'll use SwiftUI
to build the best 2D UI
and get system gestures events
like the ones on iOS.
And you'll use RealityKit
to render your 3D content
for spatial experiences.
The way to interface with both
of these at the same time
is through RealityView -
a new SwiftUI view
that we're introducing
to cater to the unique needs
of spatial computing.
RealityView truly bridges
SwiftUI and RealityKit,
allowing you to combine
2D and 3D elements
and create a memorable
spatial experience.
You'll be using the RealityView
to hold all the entities
you wish to display
and interact with.
You can get gesture events
and connect them
to the entities in your view
to control them.
And with access to ARKit's
scene understanding,
you can enable
realistic simulations
with people's surroundings
and even their hands
using RealityKit's
collision components.
Before we look
at how using RealityKit
carries over from iOS,
let's do a quick refresher
on how to work with RealityKit's
Entity Component System.
In the Reality Kit
Entity Component System,
each entity is a container
for 3D content.
Different components
are added to an entity
to define its look
and behavior.
This can include
a model component
for how it should render;
a collision component,
for how it can collide
with other entities;
and many more.
You can use
RealityComposer Pro
to prepare RealityKit components
like collision components
and get them added
to your entities.
Systems contain code
to act on entities
that have the required
components.
For example, the system
required for gesture support
only operates on entities
that have a CollisionComponent
and InputTargetComponent.
A lot of the concepts
used by RealityView
for spatial computing carry over
from those of ARView on iOS.
Lets see how these two stack up.
Both views are event-aware
containers
to hold the entities
you wish to display in your app.
You can add Gesture Support
to your views
to enable selection
and interaction with entities.
With SwiftUI
for spatial computing,
you can reach out to select
or drag your entities.
Both ARView and RealityView
provide a collection
of your entities.
ARView uses a Scene for this.
RealityView has a Content
to add your entities to.
You can add AnchorEntities
to them,
allowing you to anchor
your content to the real world.
On both platforms,
you create an entity
to load your content model
and an AnchorEntity to place it.
One main difference
between the platforms
is in the behavior
of anchor entities.
ARView on iOS
uses an ARSession
and your app must receive
permission
to run scene understanding
algorithms
necessary for anchor entities
to work.
RealityView is using
System Services
to enable anchorEntities.
This means
that spatial experiences
can anchor content
to your surroundings
without requiring permissions.
Apps using this approach
do not receive
the underlying scene
understanding data
or transforms.
Not having transform data
for your app to place content
has some implications that
Oliver will talk about later
in his section.
As we've seen, there are
many familiar concepts
that carry over
coming from iOS,
but there are also
new capabilities
that RealityKit provides
for spatial computing.
We've only scratched
the surface of what's possible
with RealityKit
on this new platform,
and you may want
to check out the session below
to follow up on more.
Now over to Oliver, who will
talk more about RealityView
and how to bring in
your content from iOS.
Oliver Dunkley: Thanks, Omid!
Let's continue by exploring
the different ways
you can bring in
your existing content
to spatial computing.
Lets start in the Shared Space.
We can add 3D content
to a window or volume,
and use system gestures
to interact with it.
To display your assets,
you just add them directly
to RealityView's Content.
You do this
by creating an entity
to hold your model component
and position it
by setting the transform
component.
You can also set up
gesture support
to modify
the transform component.
Note that all entities
added to the view's content
exist in the same space
relative to the space's origin
and can therefore
interact with one another.
In the Shared Space,
content cannot be anchored
to your surroundings.
Let's consider our options
if we transition our app
to a Full Space.
One of the key differences
coming from the Shared Space
is that apps can now
additionally anchor content
to people's surroundings.
Anchoring your content here
can happen in two ways.
Lets first look at using
RealityKit's AnchorEntity
to place content without
requiring permissions
to use ARKit data
in your app.
RealityKit's AnchorEntities
allow you to specify a target
for the system to find
and automatically
anchor your content to.
So for example, in order
to place a 3D model
on a table surface
in front of you,
you can use
a RealityKit AnchorEntity
with a target set to table.
Different from iOS,
AnchorEntities can be used
without having to prompt
for user permissions.
People's privacy is preserved
by not sharing
the underlying transforms
of the AnchorEntity
with your application.
Note: this implies children
of different anchor entities
are not aware of one another.
New to anchorEntities,
you can target hands,
which opens up
a whole new realm
of interesting interaction
opportunities.
For example, you could anchor
content to a person's palm
and have it follow their hands
as they move them.
This is all done by the system,
without telling your app where
the persons hands actually are.
AnchorEntitys provide a quick,
privacy-friendly way
for your app
to anchor content
to people's surroundings.
Coming back
to a Full Space,
we can also leverage ARKit
to incorporate
system-level knowledge
of the people's surroundings.
This enables you to build
your own custom placement logic.
Let's take a look
at how this works.
Similar to iOS, your application
receives anchoring updates
for scene understanding data.
You can integrate this anchor
data into your app logic
to achieve all sorts
of amazing experiences.
For example, you could
use the bounds of a plane
to center and distribute
your content onto.
Or, you could use planes
and their classifications
to find the corner of a room
by looking for the intersection
of two walls and a floor.
Once you've decided
where to place your content,
you add a world anchor
for ARKit to track
and use it to update your
entity's transform component.
This not only
allows your content
to remain anchored
to the real world,
as the underlying world map
is updated,
but it also opens the door
to anchor persistence,
which we will explore shortly.
All the entities added
to your space
can interact with one another as
well as with the surroundings.
This all works because
scene understanding anchors
are delivered with transforms
relative to the space's origin.
User Permission is required
to use ARKit capabilities.
You just saw how integrating
ARKit data into your app logic
can enable
more advanced features.
So far we have talked about
letting your app place content.
Let's explore how we can
let people guide placement.
On iOS, you can use raycasting
to translate 2D input
to a 3D position.
But with this new platform,
we don't need
this 2D-3D bridge anymore,
as we can use hands
to naturally interact
with experiences directly.
Raycasting remains powerful;
it lets people reach out
beyond arms length.
There are various ways
to set up raycasting.
Fundamentally, you need
to setup RealityKit's
collision components
to raycast against.
Collision components
can also be created
from ARKit's mesh anchors
to raycast against
people's surroundings.
Let's explore two examples
of how to raycast
for spatial computing:
first, using system gestures,
and the second
using hands data.
After obtaining a position,
we can place
an ARKit worldAnchor
to keep our content anchored.
Let's consider
the following example.
Imagine our app revolves around
placing inspirational 3D assets
for modelers.
Maybe in this particular
scenario,
a person wants to use our app
to place a virtual ship
on their workbench
for some modeling project.
Here is our workbench
we want to place our ship on.
We'll start with
an empty RealityView.
ARKit's scene understanding
provides mesh anchors
that we'll use
to represent the surroundings.
They provide geometry and
semantic information we can use.
Remember that meshes
for scene reconstruction data
are delivered
as a series of chunks.
We'll create an entity
to represent this mesh chunk,
and we'll correctly place
this entity in a full space
using the mesh anchor's
transform.
Our entity then needs
a collision component
to hit test against.
We'll use RealityKit's
ShapeResources method
to generate a collision shape
from the meshAnchor
for our entity.
We'll then add
our correctly placed entity
which supports hit testing.
We'll build an entity
and collision component
for each mesh chunk we receive
to represent
all the surroundings.
As scene reconstruction
is refined,
we may get updates to meshes
or have chunks removed.
We should be ready
to update our entities
on these changes as well.
We now have
a collection of entities
representing the surroundings.
All these entities
have collision components
and can support
a raycast test.
Let's first explore raycasting
using system gestures,
and then continue the example
using hands data.
We can raycast and get
a position to place our ship
using system gestures.
Gestures can only
interact with entities
that have both Collision
and InputTarget components,
so we add one
to each of our mesh entities.
By adding a SpatialTapGesture
to the RealityView,
people can raycast by
looking at entities and tapping.
This resulting event
holds a position in world space
representing the place
people looked at when tapping.
Instead of
using system gestures,
we could also have
used ARKit's hand anchors
to build a ray.
Lets take a step back
and explore this option.
To know where people point,
we first need a representation
of the person's hand.
ARkit's new hand anchors
gives us everything we need.
We can use finger joint
information to build the origin
and direction of the ray
for our query.
Now that we have the origin
and direction of our ray,
we can do a raycast against
the entities in our scene.
The resulting CollisionCastHit
provides the entity
that was hit,
along with its position
and a surface normal.
Once we identify a position in
the world to place our content,
we'll add a world anchor
for ARKit to continuously
track this position for us.
ARKit will update
this world anchor's transform
as the world map is refined.
We can create a new entity
to load our ship's model,
and set its transform
using the world anchor update,
positioning it
where the user wanted.
Finally, we can add the entity
to our content
to render it
over the workbench.
Whenever ARKit updates
the world anchor we added,
we update the transform
component of our ship entity,
making sure it stays anchored
to the real world.
And that's it!
We used our hands to point to
a location in our surroundings
and placed content there.
Raycasting is not only useful
for placing content,
but also for
interacting with it.
Let's see what it takes
to raycast against
our virtual ship.
RealityKit collision components
are very powerful.
We can let the ship entity
participate in collisions
by simply adding an appropriate
collision component to it,
which Reality Composer Pro
can help us with.
After enabling the ship's
collision component
and building a new ray from
the latest hand joint positions,
we can do another raycast
and tell if the user is pointing
at the ship or the table.
The previous examples
demonstrated
the power and versatility of
combining RealityKit's features
with ARKit's
scene understanding
to build truly compelling
experiences.
Lets see how using ARkit has
changed for spatial computing.
Fundamentally,
just as on iOS,
ARKit still works
by running a session
to receive anchor updates.
How you configure
and run your session,
receive anchors updates,
and persist world anchors
has changed
on this new platform.
Let's take a look!
On iOS, ARKit provides different
configurations to chose from.
Each configuration
bundles capabilities
necessary for your experience.
Here, for example,
we selected
ARWorldTrackingConfiguration,
and will enable
sceneReconstruction for meshes
and planeDetection
for planes.
We can then
create our ARSession
and run it with
the selected configuration.
On this new platform, ARKit
now exposes a data provider
for each scene understanding
capability.
Hand tracking is a new
capability offered by ARKit
and gets its own provider
as well.
Each data provider's initializer
takes the parameters
needed to configure
that provider instance.
Now instead of choosing
from a catalogue
of preset configurations,
you get an à la carte selection
of the providers you need
for your application.
Here for example, we choose
a SceneReconstructionProvider
to receive mesh anchors
and a PlaneDetectionProvider
to receive plane anchors.
We create the providers
and initialize
the mesh classification
and plane types
we wish to receive.
Then we create
an ARKitSession
and run it with
the instantiated providers.
Now that we have seen
how configuring your session
has been simplified,
let's go and understand
which way
these new data providers
change the way your app
actually receives ARKit data.
On iOS,
a single delegate
receives anchor
and frame updates.
Anchors are aggregated
and delivered with ARFrames
to keep camera frames
and anchors in sync.
Applications are responsible
for displaying
the camera pixel buffer,
and using camera transforms
to register and render
tracked virtual content.
Mesh and plane anchors
are delivered as base anchors,
and it is up to you
to disambiguate them
to figure out which is which.
On our new platform,
it is the data providers
that deliver anchor updates.
Here are the providers
we previously configured.
Once you run an ARKitSession,
each provider
will immediately begin
asynchronously
publishing anchor updates.
The SceneReconstructionProvider
gives meshAnchors,
and the planeDetectionProvider
gives us PlaneAnchors.
No disambiguation
is necessary!
Anchor updates come
as soon as they're available,
and are decoupled from updates
of other data providers.
It is important to note that
ARFrames are no longer provided.
Spatial computing applications
do not need frame or camera data
to display content,
since this is now done
automatically by the system.
Without having to package
anchor updates with an ARFrame,
ARKit can now deliver them
immediately,
reducing latency,
allowing your application
to quickly react to updates
in the person's surroundings.
Next, let's talk about
worldAnchor persistence.
You will love these changes!
In our raycasting examples,
we used world anchors to place
and anchor virtual content
to real-world positions.
Your app can persist
these anchors,
enabling it to automatically
receive them again,
when the device returns
to the same surroundings.
Let's first quickly recap
how persistence worked on iOS.
On iOS, it is the application's
responsibility
to handle world map
and anchor persistence.
This included requesting
and saving ARKit's world map
with your added anchor,
adding logic to reload
the correct world map
at the right time, then waiting
for relocalization to finish
before receiving previously
persisted anchors
and continuing
the application experience.
On this new platform,
the system continuously persists
the world map
in the background,
seamlessly loading,
unloading,
creating, and relocalizing
to existing maps
as people move around.
Your application does not
have to handle maps anymore,
the system now
does it for you!
You simply focus
on using world anchors
to persist locations
of virtual content.
When placing content,
you'll be using the new
WorldTrackingProvider
to add WorldAnchors
to the world map.
The system will automatically
save these for you.
The WorldTrackingProvider
will update the tracking status
and transforms
of these world anchors.
You can use
the WorldAnchor identifier
to load or unload the
corresponding virtual content.
We just highlighted a few
updates to the ARKit principles
that you knew from iOS,
but there is so much more
to explore!
For a deeper dive,
with code examples,
we recommend you watch
"Meet ARKit for
spatial computing."
Let's conclude this session!
In this session, we provided
a high-level understanding
of how ARKit
and RealityKit concepts
have evolved from iOS,
the changes
you need to consider,
and which sessions
to watch for more details.
This platform
takes on many tasks
your iOS app had to handle,
allowing you to really focus
on building beautiful
content and experiences
using frameworks and concepts
you're already familiar with.
We are thrilled to see how you
leverage spatial computing
and all of its amazing
capabilities to evolve your app!
Thank you for watching!
♪