♪ ♪
Denis: Hi, my name is Denis Vieriu,
and I'm a software engineer in the GPU,
Graphics,
and Display Software group at Apple.
Today I will present to you
all the new features and enhancements
introduced to machine learning
this year in Metal.
I'll first recap the existing
machine learning backends.
The Metal machine learning APIs
are exposed
through Metal Performance Shaders
framework.
MPS is a collection of high-performance
GPU primitives for various fields,
like image processing,
linear algebra, and machine learning.
MPSGraph is
a general purpose compute graph,
which sits on top of the MPS framework
and extends support
to multi-dimensional tensors.
machine learning inference frameworks,
like CoreML,
build on top of the MPSGraph backend.
MPSGraph also supports
training frameworks,
like TensorFlow and PyTorch.
To learn more about MPSGraph
and ML Frameworks, please refer
to the previous Metal WWDC talks
listed here.
This session focuses on the updates
and enhancements added to PyTorch
and TensorFlow Metal backends,
the new GPU acceleration for JAX,
and the features added this year
to MPSGraph for ML Inference.
PyTorch and TensorFlow
Metal acceleration enable you to use
the highly efficient kernels from MPS
to get the best performance on your Mac.
PyTorch Metal acceleration
has been available since version 1.12
through the MPS backend.
This was introduced last year
into the PyTorch ecosystem,
and since then,
multiple improvements have been made
for optimizing memory usage
and view tensors.
This year, PyTorch 2.0 MPS Backend
made a great leap forward
and has been qualified for the Beta Stage.
But these were not all the improvements.
Latest PyTorch builds contain lots
of new updates,
such as MPS operation profiling,
custom kernel,
and Automatic Mixed precision support.
Before covering
all the nightly build features,
I'll start with what is new
in PyTorch 2.0.
There is support
for the top 60 most used Torch operators,
including ops such as grid sampler,
triangular solve, topk, and many more.
The testing coverage has greatly improved.
This includes tests
for most of the Torch operators,
gradient testing,
and ModuleInfo based testing.
Since release,
the network coverage has expanded
as multiple popular models adopted MPS
as their official backend on macOS.
This includes foundation models,
such as WhisperAI,
object detection models such as YOLO,
stable diffusion models, and many more.
Let's check one of these models
in action using latest PyTorch 2.0.
For this example, I am using YoloV5,
an object detection network
running on an M2 Max.
On the left side,
I have the network running
and generating live images using
the PyTorch MPS backend,
while on the right,
I have the exact same model,
but running on the CPU.
The left side, using the MPS backend,
is running at noticeably higher framerate.
And furthermore,
the developers not only adopted
the PyTorch MPS backend
in their external networks,
but also have contributed code
for multiple new operators,
including histogram,
group_norm, signbit, and more.
Next, I'll cover the new features
available in the latest PyTorch builds,
starting with profiling support
for MPS operations.
PyTorch nightly builds
have profiling support
that uses OS signposts
to show the exact running time
for operation executions,
copies between CPU and GPU,
and fallbacks to the CPU
caused by unsupported operators.
You will be able to visualize the
profiling data in a very familiar tool,
Metal System Trace,
which is part of Instruments.
To learn more about profiling
ML applications using Metal System Trace,
I recommend you watch
the session from last year,
"Accelerate machine learning with Metal."
Using the profiler
is a very simple process.
Call the start method on the MPS
profiler package to enable tracing,
and, at the end of your script,
use the stop method to end profiling.
Now I will walk through the profiler
to debug an example.
This sample network uses
a Sequential model composed
of linear transformations
and Softshrink activation functions
with a total of seven layers in the model.
The current performance
of this model is not satisfying.
In this case, the profiler can be used
to find the bottleneck.
In the Metal System Trace, first,
make sure to enable the os_signpost.
This will allow you to capture
the PyTorch operator information.
Next, check that the device
and the right executable are set,
in this case, the Python binary.
Then click on the record button.
Instruments is now recording
the PyTorch execution.
I'll let it run for couple of seconds
to make sure I capture enough data.
Then I click Stop.
In the os_signpost tab,
disclose the PyTorch Intervals timeline.
This timeline displays
the execution time of an operator,
alongside PyTorch Metadata,
such as string identifiers,
data types, and copy lengths.
Zooming into the timeline reveals
PyTorch operators used by this example.
The pattern from this trace
can be easily identified
to the custom Sequential model
made of seven layers.
From the trace,
it's clear that the bottleneck
is in the Softshrink fallback to the CPU.
This process is very inefficient.
The model incurs the overhead
from the CPU execution
of the Softshrink operator
and the additional copies,
while the GPU is starved.
Most of the gaps
in the GPU timeline are coming
from the Softshrink activation
function falling back to CPU.
In order to fix this, I'll write a custom
kernel to improve the performance.
There are four steps
to write a custom operation.
First, implement the operation
in Objective-C and Metal.
Next, create the Python bindings
for your Objective-C code
and compile your extension.
Finally, once your extension is built,
import the operation into
your training script and begin using it.
I'll start
with the operation implementation.
Start by importing
the Torch extension header.
This includes all the necessary
PyTorch bits to write C++ extensions.
Then define the compute function
and use the get_command_buffer
MPS backend API to get a reference
to the MPSStream Command Buffer.
Similarly, use the get_dispatch_queue API
to get a reference to the serial queue.
Next, create an encoder using the command
buffer and define the custom GPU kernel.
You encode the kernel
inside the dispatch queue
to ensure that submissions
from multiple threads are serialized.
After all the work is encoded,
use the synchronize API to wait
until the current command buffer
is done running,
so you can observe serialized submissions.
Or if you don't need serialization,
use the commit API.
Next, bind your custom functions.
You can use PYBIND11
to bind the Objective-C functions
into Python in a very simple manner.
For this extension, the necessary
binding code spans only two lines.
After binding, compile your extension.
First import torch.utils.cpp_extension.
This provides a load function which you
can use to compile your extension.
Next, pass the name
of your extension to build,
then a list of relative or absolute paths
to the source code files.
Optionally, you can list additional
compiler flags to forward to the build.
The load function will compile
the source files into a shared library,
which will be subsequently loaded into
the current Python process as a module.
Finally, import the operator
into your script to begin using it.
Start by importing the compiled library
and change the previous Sequential model
to use the custom Softshrink kernel.
Let's run the same model again
and check the result.
With the newly added custom operator,
the model runs much more efficiently.
All the copies and intermediate tensors
created by the fallback
to the CPU are gone,
and the Sequential model runs much faster.
Now let's explore more ways
your network can be further improved.
PyTorch MPS backend now supports
automatic mixed precision,
which allows you
to train faster using less memory
and without loss in quality.
To understand mixed precision,
I will first review
the supported data types.
Mixed precision training
is a mode that allows training
deep learning models with a mix
of single precision floating point
and half precision floating point.
Starting with macOS Sonoma,
MPSGraph adds support
for a new data type, bfloat16.
bfloat16 is a 16-bit floating point format
for deep learning.
It is comprised of 1 sign bit,
8 exponent bits,
and 7 mantissa bits.
This is different from the standard
IEEE 16-bit floating point format,
which was not designed
with deep learning applications in mind.
Automatic Mixed Precision will be enabled
for both float16 and bfloat16.
Automatic mixed precision
chooses the right precision per layer
by measuring the performance
of the network in default precision,
then it runs again,
with mixed precision settings
to optimize the performance
without impacting the accuracy.
Some layers of the neural networks
can be executed at lower precision,
such as convolutional or linear layers.
Other layers such as reductions will
often require a higher precision level.
Adding Automatic Mixed Precision support
to your network is a very easy process.
First, add autocast.
Both float16 and bfloat16 are supported.
Autocast serves as a context manager
that allows a region of the script
to run in mixed precision.
In this region, MPS ops run
in a data type chosen by autocast
to improve performance
while maintaining accuracy.
The MPS backend has also
been significantly optimized.
With PyTorch 2.0 and macOS Sonoma,
the MPS backend is up to five times faster
compared to our previous release.
That's it for PyTorch.
Now let's move on to TensorFlow.
The TensorFlow Metal backend has
matured to a stable 1.0 release version.
In this release,
a grappler remapping optimizer pass
has been added to the plugin.
The Metal plugin
also gets mixed precision support,
and the installation process
is now simpler than before.
The performance of the TensorFlow Metal
backend has been improved
through addition of automatic fusion
of recognized computation patterns.
These computations
include fused convolutions
and matrix multiplications,
optimizer operations, and RNN cells.
This optimization happens automatically
through the grappler pass
when the computation graph is created.
Here I have an example
of a common computation
of a two-dimensional
convolution operation.
The convolution is often followed
by an addition function,
a common pattern
in convolutional neural networks.
By identifying this pattern,
the grappler pass
can remap the computation.
This allows you to use a more optimized
kernel to achieve the same output,
leading to better performance.
Like in PyTorch, TensorFlow
also gets mixed precision support.
TensorFlow allows setting
mixed precision globally.
This enables all network layers
to be automatically created
with the requested data type policy,
so enabling this change
in your standard workflow requires
minimal changes to existing code.
Global policy can be set
to use either Float16 or BFloat16.
In addition to improvements
in performance,
the user experience in enabling the Metal
acceleration has been streamlined.
From now on,
simply following the usual path
of installing the TensorFlow wheel
and the TensorFlow-Metal plugin
through a package manager
will enable the Metal acceleration.
For those who want to stay on the bleeding
edge of TensorFlow development,
the Metal acceleration support
is now also available
on the nightly releases of TensorFlow.
Now let's talk about the new
GPU acceleration for JAX.
This year,
JAX GPU acceleration will be supported
through the Metal backend,
similar to PyTorch and TensorFlow.
JAX is a Python library
for high-performance numerical computing
and machine learning research.
It is based on the popular NumPy framework
for working with large arrays,
with three key extensions
for machine learning research.
First, it supports automatic
differentiation using the grad function.
It can differentiate through
a large subset of Python's features,
and it can even take
high order derivatives.
JAX also supports fast
and efficient vectorization.
Given a function apply_matrix,
you could loop over a batch dimension
in Python,
but it may run at sub-optimal performance.
In this case, vmap can be used
to add batching support automatically.
And further,
JAX lets you just-in-time compile
your function into optimized kernels
using an API called jit.
In the same case,
jit is used to transform the function
on top of vmap to make it run faster.
On a MacBook Pro with M2 Max,
JAX Metal acceleration provides
amazing speedups,
with an average of ten times faster
than the CPU across these networks.
For more details on environment setup
and installation of JAX,
please refer to the Metal Developer
Resources web page.
Let's switch gears
and move to ML inference.
I will start by introducing
a new serialization format
for MPSGraph that you use
to optimize your load times.
This new serialization format
can be generated
from your existing serialized networks
from other frameworks.
Finally, I will show you how
to optimize the memory footprint
of your network by leveraging
8-bit integer quantization.
Let's begin.
An MPSGraph can be created using
the high level APIs with full flexibility,
layer by layer.
Please refer to the video
on building customized ML models
with Metal Performance Shaders Graph
for details.
After defining and compiling
your custom graph,
it will then execute through
the MPSGraphExecutable to get results.
Normally, this process works great.
However,
in complex graphs with many layers,
this initial compilation can lead
to high application launch times.
MPSGraph has a new serialization format
called MPSGraphPackage,
to address exactly this problem.
This new serialization format
allows you to create
the MPSGraphExecutable ahead of time.
Once created,
the optimized MPSGraphExecutable
can be loaded directly
from a MPSGraphPackage file.
Creating a MPSGraphPackage is very simple.
All you need to do is
to create a serialization descriptor
and pass it to the serialize function
of the MPSGraphExecutable
you want to serialize.
You'll also need
to pass a path to store it.
After creating the package,
this is how
you load the graph into your app.
You need a compilation descriptor
and the path to your stored package.
Then use them to initialize
the MPSGraphExecutable.
If you've been already using MPSGraph,
you can easily adopt
the new serialization format
using the APIs we have presented.
But if you're coming
from other frameworks,
you can now easily migrate
to MPSGraphPackage
using the new MPSGraphTool.
For users of CoreML,
you can pass your ML Programs
tp the MPSGraphTool, which will create
a MPSGraphPackage for you.
The same goes for ONNX,
where you can use your ONNX file
as the input.
This new tool lets you quickly include
your existing models
to your MPSGraph application
without the need
to encode the inference model manually.
Here's how you use the command line tool.
You give the MPSGraphTool a flag
to declare the input model type,
in this case, CoreML Package.
You also provide it with the path
to your output destination
and the name of your output model.
Additionally,
you define the target platform
and minimum OS version.
After conversion,
the produced MPSGraphPackages
can be loaded to your app
and executed directly.
Next, lets discuss how
you can improve the efficiency
of your computations using
the 8-bit integer quantizations.
It's common to use floating point formats
to do training and inference,
such as 16-bit floating point format.
However, at inference, these models
may take a longer time to predict results.
Instead, it's better in many cases
to use reduced precision
or 8-bit integer numbers.
This will help you
in saving memory bandwith
and reduce the memory footprint
of your model.
For 8-bit integer formats,
there are two types of quantization:
symmetric and asymmetric.
MPSGraph now supports APIs
for both of them.
Compared to the symmetric quantization,
the asymmetric one lets you specify
a quantization bias,
denoted by zeroPoint here.
Now let's delve into using quantized
computations through an example,
starting with activation and weights
in an Int8 format as the inputs.
These inputs are dequantized
to floating point format
using the dequantizeTensor op in MPSGraph.
Now the floating point inputs can be fed
into a convolution operation.
The resulting floating point tensor
can then be quantized back to Int8
using the quantizeTensor op.
MPSGraph will automatically fuse all
of these kernels into a single operation,
therefore saving memory bandwidth
and potentially improving performance.
And this is how you can use
the quantization support in MPSGraph.
In addition to the previous new features,
MPSGraph supports
even more machine learning operators.
Starting this year, complex types
are supported for most graph operations.
You can use complex numbers
either with single precision
or half precision floating point formats.
Building on the complex data type,
MPSGraph adds operators for computing
Fast Fourier Transformations.
You can apply complex to complex,
complex to real,
and real to complex transformations
up to four dimensions.
These are very common in audio,
video, and image processing applications.
Furthermore, using MPSGraph,
you can now perform
three-dimensional convolutions,
grid sampling, Sort and ArgSort,
and cumulative operations,
including sums,
products, minima, and maxima.
And this concludes the discussion
about the new features in MPSGraph.
Let's review what was presented
today in this session.
I went over the improvements
in accelerating popular ML frameworks
like PyTorch and TensorFlow
through Metal.
Now you can also take advantage of
the new Metal accelerated JAX framework.
We also discussed how to seamlessly
integrate your existing models
from other frameworks to MPSGraph
using the new serialization tools.
And this concludes our talk.
We can't wait to see
the amazing content that you will create
using all of these features.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪