♪ ♪
Ricky: Hello, I'm Ricky, and welcome
to "What's new in StoreKit 2
and StoreKit Testing in Xcode."
In this session,
I'll talk about the new features
we're bringing to StoreKit this year,
as well as the enhancements
to the testing experience in Xcode.
StoreKit 2 was first introduced
at WWDC in 2021,
with new and more flexible APIs
using Swift.
This year, I am excited to show you
the new features
that make StoreKit 2 even better.
First, I will review
the new StoreKit framework features,
then, I'll share some updates
for building SwiftUI apps using StoreKit,
and finally, I will cover
what's new in StoreKit Testing in Xcode.
I am excited to introduce a new Swift API
for managing promoted in-app purchases,
available starting in iOS 16.4.
Promoted in-app purchases is
a feature that allows you
to merchandise your products
on your App Store product page,
each with a dedicated promotional image.
Promoting your in-app purchases
is a great way
to increase your product's visibility,
and you can easily set up
promoted purchases in App Store Connect.
To learn more about configuring
promoted in-app purchases,
check out
"What's new in App Store Connect."
Since promoted in-app purchases
are listed on the App Store,
when a customer buys a promoted product,
their interaction starts here
by tapping the purchase button.
Then, the App Store sends
the purchase data to your app
where you can listen for this information
and prompt them to complete the purchase.
To listen for promoted purchases,
use the Swift async sequence
which receives a new purchase intent
every time a customer initiates
the purchase for a promoted product
in the App Store.
First, create a listener
to receive purchase intents
using PurchaseIntent.intents.
Every time
the sequence receives a new object,
it contains the StoreKit Product
associated with the purchase.
You can prompt your customers
to purchase these products as usual
by calling purchase(),
which displays the familiar payment sheet
and allows them
to complete the interaction there.
If your app isn't ready
to complete a purchase,
you can also save the intent locally
and defer it.
You can always process it later.
Another feature
of promoting in-app purchases
is being able to customize
how your products are displayed locally
on the current device.
For example,
if a customer buys one of these products,
you can hide it, so the App Store doesn't
show it again when they browse or search.
You can also change the product order,
or the subset of products featured,
based on a current state in your app,
for example, a level advancement
in a game.
To cover all of these cases,
I am excited to show you
some new Swift APIs that you can use
to customize the order
and the visibility
of your promoted in-app purchases.
Let's see a quick demonstration.
After importing StoreKit,
you can check the current promotion order
with Product.PromotionInfo.currentOrder.
This returns a sequence
of PromotionInfo objects,
in the order that is currently set.
If this list is empty,
it means there are no local overrides
set for this device,
and the products people see
in the App Store are in the same order
that you configured in App Store Connect.
Each object in this sequence
contains information
regarding a promoted product in your app.
To set a custom order of promotions,
you can use the
Product.PromotionInfo.updateProductOrder
API
and pass a list of product identifiers
in the order you want them to appear
in the App Store for this device.
You can also hide and show products
without having to set a whole new order.
This can be done by changing
the visibility property
associated with promoted in-app purchases.
The visibility state can be
visible, hidden, or default,
which follows the settings
you configure in App Store Connect
and applies to all devices that don't have
a local override set by your app.
Let's see how we can change this in code.
The visibility value can be changed
in a couple of different ways.
Your app can call
the Product.PromotionInfo.
updateProductVisibility API
and change the value for a single product
by passing both the new visibility state
and the identifier
of that in-app purchase.
Alternatively,
you can also change the visibility value
by setting a member property
on each PromotionInfo object.
Then, to save the changes, call update()
on that same object you just modified.
And that is everything you need
to start using promoted in-app purchases
with StoreKit 2.
Now, I would like to show you
some of the enhancements we made
to the core data model in StoreKit 2.
These models are useful
for managing your in-app purchases
and related information,
for example, the purchase date
and the subscription status.
Let's dive into the new fields
we're adding to the Transaction
and RenewalInfo data models, which bring
great improvements many of you requested.
The first new field is storefront,
and it appears
in the Transaction model
along with storefrontCountryCode.
The next new field is called reason.
It tells you whether a customer initiated
a purchase,
or if the transaction is
an automatic subscription renewal.
In the RenewalInfo model
under Product.SubscriptionInfo,
there is a new member
called nextRenewalDate.
This tells you when this
subscription renewal will be processed.
All of these new fields are available
for apps you build with Xcode 15,
and although initially released
with iOS 17,
most of them also work retroactively
with prior versions of iOS as well
when you are using StoreKit 2.
Next, I'd like to talk
about StoreKit Messages
and the great new feature we just added.
We introduced the Message API
last year at WWDC 2022
as a way for the App Store to notify
your customers of important information.
Messages have a Reason value
that tells you the purpose of the message.
Your app can choose
whether to defer or suppress messages.
For example,
you may want to defer a message
if displaying it would interrupt
your customers during an interaction flow.
Otherwise, StoreKit displays
any active messages automatically
when your app launches.
This year, we added a new message reason
called billingIssue.
This message is available
starting in iOS 16.4.
The App Store sends this message
when a subscription fails to renew
because of a billing problem.
StoreKit displays a Billing Problem sheet,
and customers can resolve the issue
without leaving your app.
This new property is already enabled
in sandbox to give you time to test it.
Please check back on the Apple Developer
website later this year
for updates on when this will be enabled
for all customers.
When the App Store fails
to renew a subscription,
the subscription goes
into a Billing Retry state.
To learn about how to test
this feature in sandbox,
please refer to the WWDC session
on testing in-app purchases.
Now, let's review
some security related updates.
In order to keep StoreKit up-to-date
with modern security practices,
we're migrating
our receipt signing certificate
from using SHA-1 to SHA-256
for the "original StoreKit" receipt.
Modern versions of cryptographic
libraries, like OpenSSL,
already support SHA-256, but if your app
performs on-device receipt validation,
it is important you verify that it handles
the new certificate properly.
The new SHA-256 signing certificate
will be used to sign receipts in sandbox
starting on June 20th,
and you will be able to test
on devices running iOS 16.6
and macOS 13.5 or later.
After August 14th,
the new certificate will be used
to sign receipts for all new apps
and app updates
submitted to the App Store.
For more details on this timeline,
you can check the Apple Developer website.
If your app uses StoreKit 2,
you don't need to do anything.
StoreKit 2's Signed Transaction,
Renewal Info,
and App Transaction
already use SHA-256 today.
And if you use App Store server APIs
to do receipt validation,
you also don't need to make any changes,
since we handle
the new format automatically.
Next, I am excited to show you
a whole new set of features for StoreKit
that make it very easy and quick
to merchandise in-app purchases
in your app, using SwiftUI.
There are new APIs to create
SwiftUI views for single in-app purchases,
whole stores of products, and even some
custom ones specific to subscriptions.
These function like normal SwiftUI views
and require minimal code to implement,
allowing you to get up and running
with your app as quick as possible.
Let's take a look at these new views.
With this product view, you can represent
a single in-app purchase,
complete with its localized title,
description,
and even the optional promotional image.
You can create it by passing
product identifier to ProductView.
And there is no need to load
the StoreKit product either.
You can just use the productID string.
StoreKit and SwiftUI will
take care of the rest.
There is also a new view to display
a whole collection of products,
like a store right in your app.
Instead of passing
a single product identifier,
you can use a collection of productIDs
in combination with StoreView
to create a list
of products to merchandise,
which you can then further customize
using SwiftUI components.
The StoreView is a great way
to get your app or game started
and support in-app purchases,
since it requires
only a few lines of code to set up,
like shown here.
Last but not least,
there is also a new view
to merchandise subscriptions with
all of their available levels of service.
Use SubscriptionStoreView
to quickly create a custom page
for a subscription group, like this one.
All you need is the subscriptionGroupID,
which you can normally find
in App Store Connect,
but it's now also available
in the StoreKit configuration,
right in Xcode.
There are many possible customizations
that can be easily added
to any of these new view types.
For example,
check out how changing a few lines of code
to create a custom background
can significantly alter
the look of this SubscriptionStoreView.
To go along with these new
subscription changes, we’re also adding
an additional manage subscription sheet
to provide a new experience
to how people can interact and choose
their subscription in a StoreKit app.
Let's take a look at it.
Here, you can see the familiar flow
to manage subscriptions,
which shows the customer a sheet
with their current active tiers
and provides the option
to tap into each one
to see a list of the other ones available
in that subscription group.
To make this process faster
and provide more customization,
there is now another view
that allows you to skip a step
and jump right into the subscription group
you would like to show.
You can pick the relevant
subscription group in your app's context,
if you have more than one, for example,
and show what other levels of service
are available
for your customers to choose.
This sheet can be used
with the same API as the regular one:
.manageSubscriptionsSheet.
This time, additionally pass
the subscriptionGroupID parameter.
There is so much more to show you
on the topic of creating SwiftUI apps
with StoreKit,
with lots of other views and customization
you can apply to make it fit
your app's aesthetic.
If you would like to learn more,
Greg will tell you about it
in "Meet StoreKit for SwiftUI."
After looking at the new features
for in-app purchases in StoreKit,
let's see how we can test them
using the new tools in StoreKit Testing
in Xcode, starting with Xcode 15.
With StoreKit Testing in Xcode
you can ensure your app using StoreKit
provides a great experience
from the time you start building it,
even before you set anything up
in App Store Connect.
This allows you to test, manage,
edit, and even create actions
related to StoreKit
while testing on your Mac,
and it is supported on both
the simulators and devices.
Starting off with the transaction manager,
there is new functionality
for debugging and testing your apps.
It now organizes all of your testing apps.
In the navigator, you can see
all the current connected devices
and simulators that have
your current StoreKit apps installed
using a StoreKit configuration
for testing.
This allows you to test
on multiple devices at the same time
much more easily and quickly,
and you are not required
to run your app
to see a history of purchases.
Let's jump in
and see what that looks like.
I have both an iPhone connected to my Mac
and a simulator running.
And I'm using the new
in-development game, Backyard Birds.
When you open Xcode, no matter if you have
a project opened or not,
you can go to Debug, StoreKit,
Manage Transactions,
and be presented
with the transaction manager view
you’re already familiar with.
In the navigator, you can see all
the current devices connected to your Mac.
In my case, this is the physical iPhone
and the simulator.
Notice how they both have
a few apps showing in this list,
including Backyard Birds.
These are all apps using
StoreKit Testing in Xcode
that you can inspect
outside of a debug session.
Clicking on an app
on either of these devices,
you can see a list
of StoreKit transactions for that app,
and with the details sidebar
we showed you last year,
you can inspect each one individually.
This also works if I open
the Xcode project for Backyard Birds
and run it on the simulator, for example.
In this case, I can also see
which app is actively being debugged
because it will have
this small indicator next to the app name.
This is not all that's new
with the transaction manager.
I am excited to show you that you now have
the ability to make in-app purchases
for your app
right from your Mac using Xcode.
Plus, when creating a new purchase,
you can also customize
various purchase parameters,
such as the quantity
for a consumable product,
or you can pick offer codes
for your subscriptions.
Let's see how this works in practice
using Backyard Birds.
You first need to select
the app you want to test.
Then, click the plus button
on the left of the filter bar
to create a new purchase.
The pop-up I am presented with lists
all of the available in-app purchases
for this app.
These are the same products we configured
in the StoreKit configuration.
I am going to purchase a consumable first,
so I can select
Nutrition Pellet and click Next.
Now, I have the opportunity
to configure this new purchase,
but the default options are also valid
if I wanted to skip ahead.
I am satisfied with these settings,
so let's click Done to complete
the purchase using these parameters.
Although the app is not running
in the simulator,
StoreKit received and processed
the new purchase.
If I look at the transaction list,
there is now a new item at the top.
Clicking on it, I can inspect the details
for this new transaction.
Subscriptions are different, however,
so let's make another purchase.
I am going to again click on
the plus button to create a new purchase,
and this time, I will search
for the name of a subscription
in this app,
then, pick the one I am looking for,
and click next.
The options to configure the purchase
have now changed,
because this is a different type
of in-app purchase.
Some are the same, like the purchase date,
but there's also some new ones,
so let's go over what they do.
The default properties are
also valid here, by the way.
I have the option to pick an offer code
for this subscription,
if it has any set up
in the StoreKit configuration.
Customers have to type in
offer codes and promotions,
but to make testing easier,
we provide a list of available offers
for this productID.
I would like to change
the purchase date in this case
and set it to exactly one year ago,
as if I had first subscribed
to this service
during last year's WWDC.
Next, I can choose if this subscription
should renew automatically
or only remain subscribed
for exactly one subscription period,
which, in the case of this product,
would be one month.
I would like to keep
automatic renewals enabled
so I can test how my app handles
active subscriptions
before I even start using it.
Let's click Done to complete the purchase
and look at the results
by filtering the transaction list.
As expected, I have one renewal
for each month since last year.
These are all currently marked
as unfinished,
because the app wasn’t running
and didn’t get a chance to receive them,
so I am going to run it in the simulator
and see that I now have access
to the Backyard Birds Pass.
The new features in the transaction
manager work with all devices
and platforms that already support
StoreKit Testing in Xcode,
beginning with iOS 17 and macOS 14.
And they are also supported
on other platforms,
including iPadOS, watchOS, and tvOS.
If you are running an older version
of the operating system,
nothing changes for you:
the transaction manager is
still compatible
with all the same features as before
when using an active debug session.
Next, I would like to introduce
a new feature
in the StoreKit configuration
that allows for more in-depth testing
of how your StoreKit app behaves
in different scenarios.
To demonstrate this,
I am going to open the Xcode project
for Backyard Birds
and go to the StoreKit configuration.
There is now a new item
above the configured in-app purchases
called Configuration Settings.
This is a new menu we added
to provide configurable options
for your app's test environment,
some that you might already be
familiar with,
and some new ones starting with Xcode 15.
This first and the second sections
cover all the existing options,
like the default storefront
and the locale your app should use
for pricing and availability,
and others such as the speed
of subscription renewals
or the ability to force ask to buy,
for example.
In prior versions of Xcode,
you can find these in the Editor menu
when your StoreKit configuration
is opened,
and they are still there
and can be used interchangeably.
While we are talking
about StoreKit Testing options,
there are new subscription renewal rates
we added this year in iOS 16.4.
These are designed to change
the subscription expiration
on a per-renewal basis,
helping you generate
consistent renewals quicker
than the subscription's actual duration.
This is really helpful
for quick and reliable testing
of the long-term state
of your subscription.
You can find these new configurable rates
in both the Editor menu
and in the StoreKit configuration settings
in Xcode 15.
The third section
in the StoreKit configuration settings
covers options you can use
to simulate StoreKit errors in your app,
which was a highly requested feature
by many of you.
It expands
on the Fail Transactions submenu
that used to be in the Editor menu,
and it brings support
for more StoreKit APIs and error types.
Each option represents a StoreKit 2 API
your app might be using
and allows you to pick an error
that API should throw
every time when it's called by your app.
Numerous APIs are supported
by this feature.
You can test product loading issues,
purchase failures,
receipt and transaction
verification problems,
refund requests, and so many more.
Let's see what this looks like
in practice.
I have the Xcode project
for Backyard Birds opened on the left
and the app running
in the simulator on the right.
In the StoreKit configuration, I can
enable purchase errors using the checkbox
next to the Purchase API name
and choose the error it should throw.
I would like to test
how the app handles purchases
when the customer changes storefronts,
so I will pick Product Unavailable.
This file automatically saves on edit,
and it also syncs to your device
when the app is running,
so you can test the change immediately
without needing to re-run your app.
Let's try to purchase a product
and see what happens.
[pings]
As expected, it fails.
It tells me I cannot purchase this product
and I should contact the developer
for more information.
Let's now disable purchase errors
and try this again to ensure
it completes successfully this time.
[pings]
With these steps,
I have now effectively tested
that this app's code can handle
these kinds of errors
when making a purchase,
if they should ever occur.
This method can be applied
to any of the APIs and error options
in the StoreKit configuration settings
to cover multiple scenarios
and ensure your app is robust.
These errors are all part of StoreKit,
and you might have encountered them
already.
Each one of them represents
a clear case of a failure in your app.
And that is all the new features
for StoreKit Testing in Xcode.
Today, I showed how to inspect
and manage transactions
on multiple devices
outside of a debug session,
how to purchase products
from the transaction manager
to test how your app handles
existing purchases,
and how to simulate StoreKit errors
to cover many possible failure scenarios.
All of these new features in Xcode
are also available in code
using the StoreKit Test framework
to write unit tests for your app,
so you can write automation
that performs all the same tasks.
Let's have a look at the new APIs
to create off-device purchases
and set simulated errors
in an XCTest session.
To create new in-app purchases,
there is a new Swift API in StoreKitTest
that works the same way
as the StoreKit purchase(_:) API,
with the same purchase options as well.
To support the new purchase features,
like changing the purchase date,
we also added new purchase options
only for testing.
Let's look at an example.
After setting up an SKTestSession,
I am making an off-device purchase
for a subscription
and overriding the purchase date
to a year ago from today.
This is the same purchase I made
in the transaction manager,
and it behaves exactly the same way,
allowing you to create
repeatable results
and automate the testing for your app.
There are also some new APIs
in StoreKitTest
for simulating StoreKit errors
in an SKTestSession,
and they work the same way
as the simulated errors
in the StoreKit configuration settings.
After creating your test session,
you can call setSimulatedError
with the error type you would like to test
and the StoreKit API
it should be simulated for.
In this example, I am choosing to simulate
a network error for the loadProducts API.
Any time I call the loadProducts API
in this test,
it will always throw the same error.
To disable the simulated failure,
use the same setter API
and pass nil in place of the error type.
Lastly, there are also APIs
for the new subscription renewal rates.
These can be accessed the same way
as the existing ones,
via a member in SKTestSession
called timeRate.
In this example test
to make a subscription purchase,
I added an extra line of code
to set a faster renewal rate
and generate multiple renewals quickly.
A lot of new StoreKit and StoreKit Testing
in Xcode features were covered today.
In StoreKit, there are new APIs
to support promoting in-app purchases,
the data model for Transaction
and RenewalInfo got some enhancements
to give you more valuable information
on hand,
and there is a new message type
you can listen for
to handle billing issues.
The new StoreKit views in SwiftUI
are a wonderful tool
to quickly build apps
that support product merchandising,
and they don't require any extra code
to work across all devices.
And finally, you can validate
all the StoreKit features in your app
using great tools
provided with StoreKit Testing in Xcode.
StoreKit 2 is packed
with many great features
that allow you to build awesome apps
and grow your business.
We have added many tools
that take full advantage of Swift,
and with new APIs that are simple
but powerful,
you have the opportunity to focus more
on the experience you're building
for your customers.
Any app that want to merchandise
products and subscriptions
can now be built using StoreKit 2.
If you aren't using StoreKit 2 yet,
give it a try, and if you are,
let us know what you think
of the new features I showed you today.
Use the new in-app purchase
merchandising views
in your existing app
to further customize the experience,
or create a new one
using exclusively these new APIs.
And with StoreKit Testing in Xcode,
you can put your code to the test
and ensure everything works well
and as expected
to provide your customers with the best
experience under all conditions.
For more information
about other StoreKit features,
check out these sessions linked below.
We look forward to seeing what you create
using StoreKit 2.
Thank you for watching.