♪ ♪
Cyrus: Hello and welcome
to the "Explore advances
in declarative device management" session.
My name is Cyrus Daboo,
and I am an engineer
on the device management client team.
I am here to describe
to you the exciting new features
of declarative device management.
Declarative device management
is the new device management solution
for all your Apple devices.
It provides an autonomous
and proactive management capability
that allows devices to apply management
logic without prompting from the server,
and supports
asynchronous status reporting,
avoiding the need
for servers to poll devices.
Also, it is built into MDM
to allow an easy transition
and integration with existing products.
At WWDC22, we said,
"The focus of future protocol features
will be declarative device management."
And we are following up
on that for this release with,
"The focus of new protocol features
is declarative device management."
This release has
new and compelling features
that are only available
via declarative device management.
These include features
that provide more parity with MDM
and help with transitioning from MDM.
First introduced at WWDC21
and enhanced with more
foundational capabilities at WWDC22,
declarative device management
has generated a lot of excitement
amongst MDM developers
and enterprise administrators.
Several MDM developers have already
implemented and shipped MDM servers
with declarative
device management support.
With the new features in this release,
even more will want to do so
to provide their customers
with an enhanced management feature set.
Please review the sessions from WWDC21
and WWDC22 for an in-depth look at what
declarative device management is
and how to adopt it in your products.
A quick update on platform support.
MDM and declarative device management
are now available for watchOS.
Full details can be found in the session
"Meet device management for Apple Watch."
Declarative device management
is a collaboration
between many different teams within Apple,
aiming to provide robust
and secure solutions
for MDM developers
and enterprise administrators.
Our focus is always on providing
a seamless user experience
that protects the privacy and security
of users and their devices,
while giving administrators the tools
needed to protect enterprise data
and to enforce compliance with policies.
It is also a collaboration with MDM
developers and enterprise administrators.
Your feedback has helped us
prioritize the features
we are delivering in this release.
With the foundational elements
of declarative device management
now in place, our focus has moved
to implementing core management features.
Let’s examine what those are.
First, is a new way
to enforce software updates.
Second, is managing apps.
Third, is securing devices
by locking down system services
and monitoring background tasks.
That is followed by installing
certificate and identity credentials
for use on a device.
And finally,
a new behavior to make transitioning
profiles from MDM
to declarative device management easier.
In partnership
with our software update team,
we are bringing a new managed
software update experience to macOS,
iOS, and iPadOS devices
built on declarative device management.
I.T. administrators need
to ensure their users’ devices
have the latest system
software updates installed
to guarantee required features
and fixes are in place.
Administrators need
to enforce software updates,
as well as defer them
for a short period of time
to allow the new OS release to be tested
to ensure it is compatible
with organization apps and services.
They also need to verify
that devices have been properly updated
when commanded to do so.
For large fleets of devices,
this can be a time consuming task.
Today, administrators can use
MDM commands to install updates
on supervised devices.
They can receive feedback
on the state of an update
when the server polls the device.
Administrators can also defer
minor and major updates via profiles,
preventing supervised devices
from offering software updates
to users
during a specified period of time.
But based on your feedback,
we want to improve
the overall managed
software update experience
for both administrators and users.
Declarative device management
is the mechanism to provide administrators
more control over the update process
and give users
a more informative experience,
while also ensuring
updates happen in a timely fashion.
Here’s how.
Configurations can be used
to define software update behavior.
The device can proactively
carry out those instructions,
while keeping the user informed
of the update process
and giving them the opportunity
to do the update themselves
ahead of any deadline.
Predicates can be used
to power sophisticated logic to control
the ordering of software updates
as devices get upgraded
to seed and GM builds
or as rapid security responses
become available.
And asynchronous status reporting
keeps the administrator up to date
with the software update flow
so that issues
can be quickly resolved if they arise.
Let’s examine how this is implemented.
A configuration has been added
to manage an enforced software update
of a supervised device by a specific time.
There is also a set of new status items
that report on the software update flow
on the device,
including details of the installation
state and any failure reasons.
Let’s study some examples.
This example configuration
enforces a software update
for a specific OS version
and build at a specific time.
The TargetOSVersion key indicates the OS
version that the device should update to.
The optional TargetBuildVersion key allows
targeting specific seed builds if needed.
TargetBuildVersion will take precedence
over TargetOSVersion if both are set.
If no update is found
for the specified version,
the device will search for the default
update vended by Software Update servers.
The TargetLocalDateTime key
specifies a local date and time
at which the update will be forced.
Here is an example status report
for softwareupdate status items.
The install-reasons status item
is an array of reasons
describing why an install happened.
This includes showing whether the update
was initiated by a declaration,
the system, or the user,
or any combination of those.
The pending-version status item
indicates which software update version
the system is trying to install.
The install-state status item
identifies what state
the system is currently in
with respect to the update.
The failure-reason status item
specifies the count of any errors
and the reason and timestamp
for the latest error.
Let’s examine what this looks like
from the user’s perspective.
Users will be able to clearly identify
what update is being enforced and by when.
They can easily choose to update
ahead of the deadline or schedule it
for that night.
If a user chooses "Update Tonight,"
the update will be downloaded
and prepared,
and then queued to update that night
when the device has enough charge
and is sufficiently inactive.
If the user
doesn’t immediately trigger the update,
then Software Update will post
an Updates Available notification
every day until the deadline.
On macOS, the user has the option
to choose "Install" or "Try Tonight"
when the notification appears.
24 hours before the deadline,
this notification appears hourly
and ignores Do Not Disturb.
One hour before the deadline,
the notification appears every 30 minutes,
and then every 10 minutes.
Let’s say the user had their device
turned off because they were on vacation,
and as a result, the deadline was missed.
When the user restarts the device,
Software Update will post a notification
telling them an update is past due,
and the update will be tried
within the next hour.
A similar experience happens
on iOS and iPadOS.
Here, an administrator
is enforcing an update to iOS 17.0,
as shown in the highlighted section
at the bottom.
The user can easily choose
Update Now or Update Tonight,
ensuring the update installs
ahead of the deadline, just like macOS.
And like macOS,
reminder notifications will be sent
on an increasing cadence if they choose
not to trigger the update themselves.
And the same past due behavior will occur.
Software update declarations and MDM
commands and profiles can co-exist.
However,
software updates enforced by declarations
will always take precedence
over MDM commands and profiles.
The software update configuration
and status items are available on macOS,
iOS, and iPadOS.
Now let’s turn our attention
to another important aspect
of managing devices:
Apps.
Administrators are required
to manage the licensing,
installation, updating,
and removal of apps on managed devices.
This includes providing support
if problems arise
and re-provisioning devices
as they are assigned to different users
with varying roles in the organization.
MDM developers provide a variety of tools
to help administrators manage apps,
making use
of the MDM app-related commands
and using Apple server APIs to look up
app metadata and manage licensing.
The imperative,
polling nature of MDM means
administrators often struggle
to respond in a timely fashion
when problems arise,
or when users change roles,
or devices need
to be cycled between users.
Also, users have
their devices react slowly
when they first set them up
or make changes.
Declarative device management
can provide administrators with a new,
more efficient experience
when it comes to managing apps,
and also provide users with a more
responsive and reliable experience.
Here’s how.
Configurations can be used
to specify an app that can be available
on a device when needed.
They can be sent
to the device ahead of time
so that they are already present
when device conditions dictate their use.
Predicates can be used to power logic
to control which sets of apps
are available to which users,
based on device status
or management properties
set by the server.
So administrators can quickly switch
between sets of apps as needed.
An app can be shown to a user
without it having to be installed,
so that the user
can choose when to install it,
without the need for server intervention.
This also avoids the need
for intrusive user consent prompts.
And asynchronous status reporting keeps
the administrator up to date with changes
to managed apps so that issues
can be quickly resolved if they arise.
Let’s examine how this is implemented.
A configuration has been added
to manage the installation,
update, and removal of an individual app.
There is also a new status item
that reports on the list of managed apps.
Apps can come from the App Store
or be enterprise apps
specified by a manifest, similar to MDM.
On macOS, packages are supported,
but they must contain only a single app.
Also,
app installs can be marked as optional
to be triggered by the user.
Let’s study some examples.
This example managed app configuration
will install the Pages app
from the app store.
The install behavior
indicates the app is required.
That causes the app to be
immediately installed and managed
when the configuration is activated.
The app will also
not be removable by the user.
Alternatively, the install behavior
can be set to “Optional.”
When the configuration is activated,
the app is made available
for the user
to download when they want it.
The user will also be able
to remove the app whenever they want.
Other attributes to control management
are present in the configuration,
such as per-app VPN.
This example shows a status item
for the Pages app
that has finished installing.
The Identifier key is the unique
identifier for the status object
and is set to the app’s bundle identifier.
The declaration-identifier key
is the identifier
of the configuration
that is managing the app.
The status updates asynchronously
as changes are occurring on the device,
so polling is not needed.
Now let’s turn our attention
to the user experience.
Many MDM developers provide an app
that gives users options
for controlling the management experience.
Often, a list of apps is present
to give users the choice
of what to install and when.
Users can tap on an app
to trigger its installation.
To implement this,
a private protocol is needed
between the app and the MDM server
to convey the list of apps,
and then send actions
from the user back to the server.
The server has to then send
an MDM command to trigger the install.
All this back-and-forth
introduces additional latency
into the user experience.
We want to improve this by making
optional app installs simple and fast,
while remaining secure.
A new managed app
distribution framework is available
for third party management app use.
An entitlement will be required to use it,
and that can be applied for
as part
of the App Store submission process.
The framework contains a SwiftUI view
extension that exposes each managed app
as a SwiftUI view that can then
be placed in a customizable layout.
Users can view details of an app
and tap to install.
This improves the user experience
by removing the roundtrip latency
to the MDM server, allowing the app
to be immediately installed,
and also by providing
better feedback on progress.
Let’s examine what this might look like
in an app that you could build.
This slide shows
an MDM management app on iOS,
using the new view service
to show a list of apps to the user.
One app is currently installed.
One is downloading, showing live progress.
And another is optional
and waiting to be installed.
The style of the app view
is customizable and,
in this case,
uses a standard list style.
On macOS,
a more expansive layout can be used,
such as the grid layout shown here,
using a different style of app view.
The app using the view service
can sort and group the set of apps
in whatever way is appropriate.
If you already have a management app
that shows an app list,
this view service can be used
as an alternative
and provide users
with a better experience.
If you are planning
on providing a management app,
this view service will give you
a head start to implementing it.
Note that if you intend
to use the optional install behavior
of the new managed app configuration,
then you must provide
your own management app for users.
The management apps
configuration and status item,
public framework and view extension,
will be available for macOS,
iOS, and iPadOS.
Additionally,
as part of our goal to improve
the experience of managing apps,
I am pleased to announce
a new "Apps and Books for Organizations"
server API,
available for immediate use.
This replaces the existing
contentMetadataLookup server API.
The new API provides new
customization and versioning features,
in addition
to better performance and uptime.
Please visit the developer.apple.com site
for full details of using the new API.
Now let’s examine how declarative device
management can be used to help enforce
and verify security compliance for macOS
system services and background tasks.
Administrators are often required
to ensure the devices
they support behave
in a consistent and secure manner.
Ensuring consistency means
that it is easier
to support a large fleet of devices,
given that they are
all configured in the same way.
Ensuring compliance means that devices are
known to have a base level of security,
providing assurances
that organization data is secure.
And when changes need
to be made across all devices
or when new devices
are added to the inventory,
this needs to be done
in a quick and efficient way.
One part of this requirement
involves configuring and monitoring
system or third party services
installed on a device.
macOS ships with many system services
that are controlled
via system configuration files.
For example,
sshd is configured via the files
in the directory /etc/ssh.
Many of these system services must be
securely configured by the administrator
to guarantee the consistency and
compliance required by the organization.
Thus, it is important to ensure
users cannot deliberately
or inadvertently change
these system configurations.
However, this is hard to achieve,
as users often have the ability
to modify the system configuration files
or override the system service
to use a custom configuration file.
Declarative device management
is ideally positioned to provide a secure
and reliable mechanism to support
the configuration of system services
protected by System Integrity Protection
and provide a means
to monitor background tasks
to help guarantee device consistency
and security compliance.
Here’s how.
Declarative device management
configurations can be used to specify sets
of tamper-resistant system configuration
files for different system services.
Status can be used to monitor
background tasks as they come and go.
And predicates can power
sophisticated compliance rules
triggered off device state,
in a purely autonomous manner if needed.
Let’s examine how this is implemented.
A declarative device management
configuration has been added
to support managing system
service configuration files.
The configuration references a data asset
that provides a ZIP archive.
When the configuration is activated,
the archive is downloaded and expanded
into a tamper resistant,
service-specific location.
This location
can be programmatically found
by calling a function in a new library
so that any system service can
adopt managed service configuration files.
Built-in system services will be modified
to look for the managed
service configuration files
and always use those ahead of any default
or overridden system configuration.
Third party services can also adopt
managed service configuration files
in the same manner.
We encourage you to contact developers
of any third party services you use
and have them adopt the new feature.
Let’s examine how this works.
This example configuration will install
managed service configuration files
for the sshd service.
It includes a reference to a data asset.
Here is the example data asset.
The asset type is a new type
and is used for conveying arbitrary data.
Also new is a way for assets
to indicate what type of authentication
is used when retrieving the asset data.
This allows greater flexibility
in where assets are hosted
and how authentication and authorization
is achieved to securely access the data.
The data URL
in the asset points to a location
where a ZIP archive file
can be downloaded
when the referencing configuration
is activated.
The archive is expanded
into a tamper-resistant,
service-specific location,
where the sshd process can access it
and use it
as its managed service configuration.
The first built-in services
to adopt this feature are:
sshd, sudo, PAM,
CUPS, Apache httpd,
and finally, bash and zee shells
In addition to locking down
system service configuration,
this release also adds a new status item
that reports the list
of installed background tasks.
This allows administrators
to quickly verify
that required tasks are running
and that unwanted tasks are not running.
Let’s examine what this looks like.
This example shows a status array item
for a background task.
The details include:
The unique identifier of the task.
The uid of the user account
running the task.
Its state.
The type of task, which is either daemon,
agent, login item, app, or user item.
Also available are any launchd details,
such as label and program arguments,
as well as a checksum hash of the launchd
properties used to load the service.
Additionally,
this release adds a status item
to report on the FileVault enabled state
of the macOS boot volume.
It returns a boolean value to indicate
whether FileVault is enabled or not,
and it is easy to use
in an activation predicate,
so that security sensitive configurations
can be installed
only when it is safe to do so.
With this combination
of managed service configuration files,
background task,
and FileVault status reporting,
administrators now have a powerful way
to ensure consistency and compliance
across all macOS devices
in the organization.
Now lets discuss
security certificates and identities
in declarative device management.
Administrators need to ensure
secure access to organization resources
hosted on internal and external networks.
Often this requires adding certificates
and identities to devices
to ensure transport layer security
or authenticated access to app services.
Different app services may use
the same certificate or identity,
and it is important to be able
to manage such relationships.
Certificates also have a finite lifetime,
so there needs
to be a reliable way to refresh them.
Also, it is desirable to replace password
authentication with secure technology,
such as passkeys, which are faster,
easier to use, and phishing resistant.
It is thus critical for MDM developers
to provide a reliable and efficient way
for administrators
to manage certificates and identities.
MDM already includes profile payloads
that can be used to create certificates
and identities in the keychain on devices.
It also supports provisioning identities
via the ACME and SCEP protocols
and supports retrieving certificates
via a certificate list command.
But there are some limitations
on what MDM can do.
MDM certificate
or identity payloads can be referenced
by one or more other payloads
within the same profile.
However, references to certificates
or identities in other profiles
are not allowed.
This means profiles either have to
become larger to accommodate all payloads
referencing the same item
or certificates and identities
have to be duplicated
across multiple profiles,
which means more work
to keep them up to date.
Also, when a certificate
or identity does need to be refreshed,
all the other payloads in the profile
will be updated in the system,
which can be disruptive
to the user experience.
Declarative device management
can provide a more efficient mechanism
for managing certificates and identities
by utilizing the full power
of its declaration data model.
Here’s how.
Certificates and identities
can be defined as asset declarations,
and configurations
can reference those assets.
Multiple configurations can reference
the same certificate or identity,
and multiple certificates
or identities can be referenced
by the same configuration.
And only the asset needs
to be updated when the certificate
or identity needs to be refreshed.
This combination
of assets and configurations
resolves many of the limitations
of MDM profile payloads.
In addition,
status for certificates and identities
can also be reported,
including providing quick feedback
when ACME and SCEP identities
are provisioned
without the need for polling.
Let’s examine how all this is implemented.
A set of assets has been added
to provide certificate or identity data.
Certificates use either
the PEM or DER data formats.
Identities use the PKCS #12 format,
or can be provisioned
via the ACME or SCEP protocols.
This includes use of hardware
bound keys where available.
A new status item is also available
to report on each certificate
or identity installed via assets.
Let’s study some examples.
This example asset
will install a certificate.
The reference details provide a URL
that delivers the actual certificate data
to the device.
Another example shows an asset to
provision an identity via an ACME server.
In this case,
the reference details provide a URL
that delivers a JSON document
containing the properties needed
for the ACME protocol exchange.
Here is an example of the ACME
properties JSON document.
The directory URL specifies
the URL of the ACME server.
There are a set of properties that define
what type of key is generated
and a set of properties
for the generated certificate.
Now, lets look at the status.
This example shows
a status array item with two certificates.
Each item includes the declaration
identifier of the associated assets,
as well
as the DER encoded certificate data
and an indicator
of whether the certificate
corresponds to an identity.
Now that we have assets
for certificates and identities,
we can make use of them in some new
and existing configurations.
First, we have two new configurations
that can be used
to install
stand-alone certificates and identities.
Both reference a credential asset
to provide the actual certificate
or identity data.
The certificate configuration installs
a single certificate into the keychain.
If the certificate is self-signed
and is a certificate authority,
then it will also be added
to the trust store.
The identity configuration installs
a single identity into the keychain.
These configurations are available
on all platforms.
Next, we have a configuration
for deploying enterprise passkeys.
WWDC22 introduced passkeys
as a solution for eliminating the use
of passwords on websites and in apps.
In this release, our focus has turned
to making passkeys easy
to deploy in the enterprise
by ensuring that only authorized devices
and users can provision them.
To support this, there is a new enterprise
passkey attestation configuration
that can be used
to securely generate a passkey for a user
on a device when they visit any site
specified by the configuration.
The configuration
references an identity asset.
The identity is then used to perform
a standard WebAuthn attestation
of a generated passkey.
The WebAuthn relying party
can then verify this attestation
and allow access to the relevant sites.
Thus, administrators can restrict
certain passkeys to only managed devices.
This feature is available
for macOS, iOS, and iPadOS.
Details of how the MDM server
and relying party work together
to implement this flow can be found
in the session "Deploy passkeys at work."
Finally, the Mail and Exchange
account configurations
have been updated
to support S/MIME to bring feature parity
with their MDM profile
payload equivalents.
The configurations can now reference
identity assets that can be used
for S/MIME signing and encryption.
This is available for iOS and iPadOS.
For our final item,
let's discuss a new behavior
that makes it easy for you to transition
from MDM profiles to configurations.
Declarative device management
is built into MDM and can be used
in parallel with MDM to add
new management capabilities,
allowing you to transition your products
over time.
Implementing declarative device management
in MDM is as simple as sending
the MDM DeclarativeManagement
command to the device,
and syncing over a set of declarations
that get activated on the device.
Then the server listens
to incoming status reports.
To make this transition easy,
a legacy profile configuration was created
to allow existing MDM profiles
to be sent as a configuration,
enabling profiles to take
full advantage of the autonomous
and proactive behavior
of declarative device management.
Doing that involves first removing
the existing MDM profile,
then sending
and activating a configuration
that installs that same profile.
This can be a disruptive process,
causing things like accounts to have
to refresh all their data,
or leaving a management gap
in which restrictions are missing
from the device for a short while.
MDM developers have asked
for an easier way to transition
from using MDM profiles
to the legacy profile configurations.
And now this is possible.
Here’s how.
Declarative device management
now supports taking over management
of already installed MDM profiles
without the need to remove them.
To use this, all a server has to do
is send and activate a configuration
that contains the same profile
as one already installed by MDM.
The declarative device management system
will then take over management
of that profile
without reinstalling or updating it.
At that point, declarative
device management owns the profile.
MDM will not be able
to make changes to it.
There is no disruption to the device state
the profile is managing.
And there is no management gap.
This makes it much easier to transition
from MDM to declarative device management.
This new behavior
is available on all platforms.
That concludes the last of our agenda
items covering the exciting new features
we are bringing you for this release
of declarative device management.
Now let’s wrap up.
With the foundational elements in place,
this release has focused on building out
key management features using the power
of declarative device management.
Many of these features
are the results of requests received
via your feedback,
and we thank you for that.
As declarative device management
continues to advance,
we welcome more feedback
to help us prioritize the features
that are important to you.
With new management features being added
only to declarative device management,
it is now critical for you
to build support into your products
if you have not already done so.
If you already have support,
the new features in this release
will give you even more opportunity
to make great products
your customers will love.
Information about other new
management features in this release
can be found in the session
"What’s new in managing Apple devices."
The schema for new configurations,
assets, and status items
is available
in our open source schema repository,
which you can find linked
in the session reference details.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪