♪ ♪
Tu: Hi, my name is Tu Nguyen,
and I'm an engineer on the Workout team.
I'm here today with my colleague Abhiraj,
and we'll walk you through how
to build custom workouts for Apple Watch.
In watchOS 9, we introduced
new workout types in the Workout app
for users to create and customize
their ideal workout experience:
Goal based workouts where users can
perform a workout with a singular goal,
such as distance, energy, or time.
Pacer workouts that puts the focus
on pace or speed front and center.
Swim-bike-run workouts
for triathletes to seamlessly transition
between swim, bike, and run activities.
And custom workouts,
structured steps with a combination
of custom goals and alerts.
So in iOS 17 and watchOS 10,
we're bringing all of these workout types
into a new framework called WorkoutKit.
WorkoutKit is a brand-new Swift framework.
It allows you to create and customize
all of the different workout types
that a user can create in the Workout app
within your own apps.
It is also the bridge
to help you bring these workouts
into the Workout app for users to perform.
WorkoutKit provides preview UI
and the ability
to sync scheduled workouts.
We're bringing these four workout types
to WorkoutKit,
and today we're going to be focusing
on custom workouts.
In this session, we'll be
going over building a custom workout,
previewing for export,
and how to schedule workouts.
Let's first jump
into building a custom workout.
Custom workouts are a great way for users
to focus their workout
in a structured manner.
They contain a series of distinct steps
that guides the user
through their workout.
When looking at a custom workout,
there are three distinct stages.
First, we have a step
at the beginning of the workout.
This is the warmup step.
Next, we have an ordered collection
of repeatable blocks,
which contain
their own combination of steps.
These blocks represent
the majority of the workout.
And finally,
a step at the end of the workout
that we refer to as the cooldown step.
Now, whether it's a warmup, cooldown,
or step within a repeatable block,
every step contains
two important attributes.
First, every step contains a single goal.
Goals define the progression
of steps within a custom workout.
When a goal is complete,
the custom workout
moves on to the next step.
A step within a custom workout can have
a time or distance goal, if applicable.
You can also set an open goal,
which requires the user
to manually progress through the step.
And secondly,
every step can contain a single alert.
Alerts inform the user
of a particular metric
that indicates their current performance.
For example, the user may want
to be alerted when their heartrate
is elevated past a certain threshold.
And we're bringing support for pace,
cadence, power, and heartrate alerts.
Now that we know what makes up a step,
let's take a closer look at blocks.
Blocks contain steps distinguished
as work steps or recovery steps.
The steps within a block
contain their own goal and alert,
as you saw before,
and you can have any number of steps
in any order within your block.
Blocks can also be repeatable.
You can specify the number of iterations
that you want your block to be repeated.
Now let's see how this translates
into the in-workout experience
on Apple Watch.
First, we see that the user's current step
is a work step within the block.
Since this step has a distance goal,
we see the current goal progress
with 0.2 miles remaining.
This step also has an alert
for current power,
which we display at the bottom.
If you don't happen
to specify an alert for this step,
we'll display
the user's current heartrate.
And finally, we also give a preview
that the next step is a recovery step
with a time based goal.
With steps and blocks, you are able
to construct a complete custom workout.
Again, at the very beginning,
we have a warmup step,
then a series of repeatable blocks
containing work and recovery steps,
where we spend the majority
of our time in the workout,
and finally, a cooldown step at the end.
Now I'll hand it over
to my colleague Abhiraj
to show you how to build
your own custom workout with WorkoutKit.
Abhiraj: Hi I'm Abhiraj.
I'm an engineer on the Workout team.
As Tu mentioned,
with WorkoutKit you can create workouts
for goal, pacer, swim-bike-run,
and custom workouts.
Let's take an example
of a custom outdoor cycling workout.
We will have four steps for this workout:
Warmup,
two repeating blocks of work and recovery,
and cooldown to end the workout.
For our warmup step,
we'll use an open goal.
For our first block,
we'll have a work step
with a distance goal and pace alert
and a recovery step
with a distance goal and heart rate alert.
This block will have four iterations.
For our second block, we'll have a work
step with a time goal and power alert
and a recovery step
with a time goal and heart rate alert.
Finally, our cooldown step
will have a time-based goal
Let's see how
we can represent this in code.
Let's start with our warmup step.
First, we import WorkoutKit.
As we mentioned before, our warmup step
has an open goal with no alert.
So in this case, we'll create it
with the default initializer.
Let's move on
to the first block of this workout.
In this first block, we'll have two steps.
The first step is a work step
with a distance goal and pace alert.
We'll need to import HealthKit here
since we're leveraging
HKQuantity and HKUnit
to represent our goals and alerts.
We'll now set up
a 2-mile goal using WorkoutGoal.
We also add a pace alert to this step,
aiming for a pace of 10 miles per hour.
Let's first create HKQuantity
of pace value with 10 miles per hour.
We'll use WorkoutAlert
for creating this alert.
To create WorkoutAlert,
we'll need WorkoutAlertTargetType,
in this case,
target with 10 miles per hour,
and a WorkoutAlertType,
in this case, current pace.
And now we can create
our pace WorkoutAlert.
Now, to create our work step,
we'll use BlockStep of type work
with twoMileGoal and paceAlert.
The 2nd step
of this block is a recovery step.
We'll create a 1/2 mile goal for recovery
with a heart rate zone 1 alert.
Then we can create
our recovery BlockStep of type rest.
Now, we can create our block with the work
and recovery steps we just defined.
To do this, we use IntervalBlock with
an array of steps and iterations set to 4.
And with that,
our first block is complete.
Now lets move on to our second block.
In this block, we also have two steps.
The first step is a work step
with a time goal and power alert.
We set up a two-minute goal.
For this work block,
lets create power range alert
with a range of 250 to 275 watts.
We create our WorkoutTargetType
of type range
and create WorkoutAlert.
Finally, creating BlockStep using
the goal and alert that we just created.
The second step
of this block is a recovery step.
We create a 30 second goal
with a heart rate zone 1 alert.
Then we can create our recovery step.
Now we can create our second block
with the work and recovery steps
we just defined with iterations set to 2.
Finally,
let's move on to our cooldown step.
We wanted our cooldown step
to have a time-based goal,
so let's create that here.
We create WorkoutGoal of type time
and use that to create CooldownStep
with goal set to fiveMinuteGoal.
Now let's put it all together.
Using everything we've built so far,
warmup step, block1, block2,
and cooldown step, we can create
our custom workout composition.
We set the activity type to cycling
and location to be outdoor.
LocationType parameter
of CustomWorkoutComposition's initializer
is optional,
and by default, it's set to outdoor.
Lets combine all this and create
our custom workout named "My Workout."
You might also
be wondering why initializer
of CustomWorkoutComposition
is preceded by a try.
That's because we're
validating the composition.
Let's discuss the importance
of validating workout compositions.
Validations ensure
a coherent workout structure
and prevents any issues
during workout runtime.
For instance,
distance goals should not be used
for non-distance based
workout compositions.
Similarly,
pace alerts should not be applied
to workouts that do not support pace,
such as elliptical.
To help with this,
we have a series of validations
that are performed
when certain properties are set,
example, workout activity type,
or when running through certain API.
We have also created WorkoutComposition
wrapper to perform additional operations.
For example, we have also created APIs
to import and export workout composition
to a file which can be shared
across devices.
Use dataRepresentation
to export in JSON or binary.
We recommend exporting
your compositions in binary format
for its much smaller size.
And now I'll hand it over back to Tu
to talk about how you
can preview compositions.
Tu: Thanks a lot, Abhiraj.
It's great to see
how we can leverage these APIs
to build fully custom workouts.
Now let's take a look at what we can do
once we have workout compositions.
With a workout composition,
there are a few different things
you can do with them in WorkoutKit.
First, as Abhiraj mentioned earlier,
you can export the composition to a file
with a .workout extension
for sharing and distribution.
Remember that validation automatically
happens when calling certain API,
and exporting a composition
is one such example.
We also have API
for you to present a preview
of the contents
of your composition to the user.
Now, this has different behavior
on iOS and watchOS.
On iOS, when you call the preview API
on your composition,
an out of process UI
will be presented on top of your app
and display the entire contents
of your workout composition.
In this example,
we have a custom workout composition.
The title is prominently displayed
at the top,
the list of steps and blocks,
including the goals and alerts,
and an option for users
to save the workout
directly into the Workout app
on their Apple Watch.
Now, if we turn to watchOS,
calling the preview API
will launch the Workout app
with the contents
of the workout composition.
From here, the user is able to immediately
start the workout or save it for later.
Again, I'll hand it off to Abhiraj to show
you these preview options with WorkoutKit.
Abhiraj: Now that we have a great workout,
let's get it saved by the user.
As we discussed earlier,
we can use WorkoutComposition
to perform additional operations
on the workout, such as validations.
With the WorkoutComposition,
we can present a preview to the user.
The preview API is optimized for iOS
and watchOS to provide a convenient way
for users to preview,
save, or start workouts.
So lets take the cycling workout
that we created earlier
and wrap it in a WorkoutComposition.
You can use any workout type
that Tu mentioned earlier
with a WorkoutComposition.
Now lets present the preview
using the presentPreview function
on workoutComposition.
We use a task block here
because this API is designed
to work with Swift's
modern concurrency features.
As mentioned before,
presentPreview will display
the workout preview differently
depending on the platform it's running on.
Let's see how this works.
On iOS, the function presents
a remote view on top of your app.
It shows the workout
and an option for the user to save it
directly to the Workout app
on the Apple Watch.
The "Add to Watch" button will update
the Workout app with new workout.
The preview function
behaves differently on Apple Watch.
Rather than presenting a sheet
over your app,
calling the preview function
on watchOS will launch the Workout app
with a preview of the workout.
And now I'll hand it back to Tu
to talk about scheduling workouts.
Tu: Thanks, Abhiraj.
Those preview options are really helpful
to get a single workout composition
in front of the user
for a quick interaction.
But what if you have a collection
of workouts for the user to perform
over a period of time?
For example, let's say you have some
cycling scheduled for your user today,
and later in the week, hiking,
a few days after that, golfing,
maybe some scheduled rest,
before some more cycling.
You could use
the composition and preview APIs
to save workouts
directly into the Workout app,
but now the user is responsible
for managing all of these workouts
and remembering
when they need to complete them.
It's not very scalable.
To simplify this whole process,
as part of WorkoutKit,
your app can schedule workouts
directly into the Workout app.
Let's see what that looks like.
When you schedule workouts,
your app will have a dedicated space
at the top of the Workout app.
This dedicated space will be styled
with your app's icon and name
and a preview
of the next workout for the day.
Tapping here will immediately start
the displayed scheduled workout.
Tapping the ellipsis
will show more details,
including upcoming scheduled workouts
that you synced over.
Scheduling workouts
requires the user's permission,
and syncing is handled locally.
The user is able to see workouts
scheduled in the next seven days
and the previous seven days.
You can sync up to 15 workouts at a time,
and you can query for scheduled workouts
that the user has completed from your app.
When querying scheduled workouts,
they only contain
the composition you created,
the scheduled date, and whether or not
the workout was completed by the user.
They do not contain any health data.
So if you want actual health statistics
from a completed workout,
refer to the HealthKit APIs.
And as part of WorkoutKit,
we're providing an extension on HKWorkout
to retrieve a workout composition,
if it's available.
Now I'll hand it over to Abhiraj
to show you how
to schedule workouts using WorkoutKit.
Abhiraj: Thanks, Tu.
For apps
to schedule workouts for the user,
we are providing a set of APIs
to support syncing workout compositions
to Apple Watch
for use within the Workout app.
Let's actually build an app that takes
advantage of the WorkoutKit APIs.
We'll need to associate scheduled dates
with workout compositions,
and then sync them.
Let me show you how to do it.
I've started building an app
that has placeholders
to interact with WorkoutKit APIs.
Let's see how I can leverage WorkoutKit
to make this functional.
Before we can start syncing workouts
to the Workout app,
we need to get permission from the user.
You can call authorizationState
on WorkoutPlan
to check your app's current permissions.
Since we haven't requested
permission yet,
we can request authorization from the user
by calling requestAuthorization
on WorkoutPlan.
I'm going to tap
the "Request Authorization" button.
When calling requestAuthorization(),
a user is prompted
with an alert to opt into syncing.
Users can also change this setting
in Workout settings from the Watch app
on iOS and the Settings app on watchOS.
Now that we have authorized our app,
we'll get our current workout plan
from the Workout app on Apple Watch.
You can query WorkoutPlan
using WorkoutPlan.current.
WorkoutPlan is our interface to store
and modify scheduled workouts
from our app.
I'm going to tap
the "Get Workout Plan" button.
As we have not scheduled any workouts yet,
the plan has no scheduled workouts.
Next, let's create
and schedule some workouts.
I'm thinking I want to go for golf today
and cycling later this week.
So lets create that schedule
with some new workout compositions.
ScheduledWorkoutComposition object
contains a workout composition,
scheduled date, and a completion state.
I have assigned today
for the golfing scheduledDate
and cycling scheduledDate
for the day after tomorrow.
Let's see how that looks in my app.
As you can see,
I have a golf workout scheduled for today
and a cycling workout coming up
in a couple of days.
Now that we have created our schedule,
let's sync it to the Workout app.
Using the current workout plan,
we'll append these new scheduled workouts
to the scheduledCompositions array.
Finally, to add these workouts
to the Workout app,
we call workoutPlan.save().
Let's see how this works in action.
Great.
Now these workouts are synced.
As Tu mentioned,
when you schedule a workout,
your app will have a dedicated space
at the top of the Workout app.
Let's dig in to see what it looks like.
Let's open the Workout app.
As you can see,
my app's icon and name is present.
Since I have
a golf workout scheduled today,
tapping here will start the workout.
I can tap the ellipsis
to see my upcoming schedule.
On the first screen, I see all
of my workouts scheduled for today.
If l tap "View More,"
I'll be able to see workouts
that are scheduled for the next
seven days and the previous seven days.
Here I see both today's golf workout
and my upcoming cycling workout
that I synced earlier.
Now you have an understanding
of how scheduled workouts are presented
and how your app can have
a dedicated space inside the Workout app.
As you know,
I've got a round of golf planned today.
My tee time is soon.
So if you don't mind, I'll be right back.
I'm back.
I had a great round of golf
and shot 72 on the back nine.
When the user completes
a scheduled workout in the Workout app,
the completion state will be updated.
You can query WorkoutPlan
using WorkoutPlan.current
to determine
which workouts were completed.
If a workout was marked
as completed in your app,
you should update the completion state
to make sure the user has
the most recent information everywhere.
Let's get back to our code.
In our sample app, we can check
if scheduledComposition is completed.
If it is, we are marking it as complete.
Let's see this in action.
It's a great practice
to keep your app in sync with Workout app.
Now you have a basic understanding of how
to implement the Workout schedule APIs,
from requesting authorization
to syncing compositions to Workout app.
With that, I will hand it back to Tu.
Tu: Thanks, Abhiraj, and nice
to see you improving your golf game.
So let's wrap up
with some best practices to keep in mind
as you're adopting WorkoutKit
in your apps.
Consider which composition type
best fits the workout experience
that you want to display to the user.
We saw that custom workouts
are a very useful composition type,
especially when a workout requires
different levels of effort and attention
with custom goals and alerts.
However, swimming isn't supported
with custom workouts.
You would need
to use a goal composition instead.
Also, alerts are only available
with custom workouts.
If you don't need to specify
your own alerts for something simple
like a 30-minute run,
consider using a goal
or pacer composition instead.
Be sure to handle validation
of your workout compositions.
We provide very granular validation errors
to help you pinpoint the source
of any incompatibility or error.
As a reminder,
not all activity types support distance.
Consider using a time
or an open goal instead.
And not all activity types will support
certain alerts in a custom workout.
Consider an alternative,
such as a heartrate zone alert.
Keep your scheduled workouts up to date.
Take advantage of any foreground
or background runtime
your app may have to do so.
And finally, please send us your feedback.
Try out the API.
All of the sample code you saw today
is available on developer.apple.com.
Also, don't forget
to check out the HealthKit session
on synchronizing workout sessions.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪