[light music]
Hello, and welcome.
My name is Chong.
I'm an engineering manager
on the App Store Connect team.
Later, I will be joined
by my colleague, Claire,
and in this session,
we are going to explore
what's new in App Store pricing.
In March of this year,
we released the largest set of upgrades
to App Store pricing capabilities
since the App Store first launched.
Today, we'll walk you through
the new global pricing features
and demonstrate
how to use them to set prices
for your apps
and in-app purchases in App Store Connect.
Additionally, we'll explore
advanced pricing tools
tailored for managing pricing by region,
which can support
more intricate use cases.
Let's dive into our first topic:
enhanced global pricing.
At the App Store, we understand
the challenges of managing pricing
across 44 currencies
and 175 regions,
with many of these regions
also incorporating local taxes.
To streamline this process,
we've developed global pricing tools
that simplify pricing of your apps,
in-app purchases, globally.
To provide you
with more pricing flexibility,
we have significantly increased
the number of available price points,
which now totals up to 900 price point
for apps, in-app purchases,
and subscriptions.
By default, you have access
to 800 price points,
and upon request,
an additional 100 higher price points
will be available.
These expanded price points
are also available
for 44 different currencies.
In addition to the expanded price points,
we have also introduced a pricing tool
that allows you to configure a base region
for your base price
from any of 175 regions,
facilitating streamlined global pricing.
Let me give you an example
to illustrate this process more clearly.
You can start by choosing a base region
for your base price.
The base region can be decided
by taking into account various factors,
such as your target market,
the location of your user base,
or any business-related reasons.
In this example, I will select
the United States
for my base region.
Next, you can choose a price
from any of 900 price points
to serve as the basis.
In this example, I will set $7.99
as my base price.
The App Store will then use
this base price
to generate equivalent prices
for the remaining regions,
factoring in foreign exchange rate
and certain taxes.
Global equalization also follows
the most common pricing convention
in each region,
ensuring that customers see prices
that are most relevant
to their local currency.
Moreover, the generated prices
will be automatically adjusted
to keep global prices in line
with your base price
as foreign exchange rate
and tax fluctuate.
For instance, if the UK pound
and Japanese yen
weaken against the US dollar
and other currencies,
prices in the UK and Japan
would increase to maintain
price equalization
with the base US price.
It is important to note that
the base price will not be
automatically adjusted
since it's set as the base
for other prices.
You can also schedule
a global price change in the future.
In this example, I will schedule
a price increase
for my base price to $9.99
on January 1, 2024,
and just like the initial price setup,
the App Store will generate
equivalent prices
with a new upcoming base price
in the remaining regions
with the same future start date.
Next up, Claire will provide
a comprehensive walkthrough
of how to make the most
of the new global pricing features
in App Store Connect,
as well as the associated
App Store Connect APIs.
Over to you, Claire.
Thanks, Chong!
My name is Claire Liu.
I'm a software engineer
for App Store Connect.
Over the next few minutes,
I'll walk you through how to set up
your global pricing
in App Store Connect
and with the App Store Connect APIs.
I'll use the app Backyard Birds
as an example,
set its price to $7.99,
and schedule a global price change
next year.
To set up initial pricing for your apps,
in the sidebar,
click Pricing and Availability.
Then, under the Price Schedule,
click Add Pricing.
From here,
select a base country or region.
The App Store will use this base
to provide comparable prices
on the other 174 regions.
You can change this base configuration
later at any time.
I'm going to choose the United States
for this app.
After selecting a base country or region,
select a price from the drop-down menu.
Initially, the list displays
25 price points
that follow
the most common pricing convention
for each country or region.
To view more available price points,
scroll to the end of the menu
and click See Additional Prices.
I'm going to choose 7.99
for Backyard Birds.
Next, you will see a screen
with comparable prices
for all the other countries or regions.
By default, the App Store
will automatically adjust prices for you.
You don't have to make
any changes if this is what you want.
Alternatively, you can choose
different prices
for individual countries or regions.
However, if you select your own prices,
you will not benefit
from the automatic repricing
for foreign exchange and tax rate,
and you will be responsible for reflecting
those changes in your prices.
I'm happy with the comparable prices
provided by the App Store,
so I will keep the original values
and go to the next step.
Finally, I will review
and confirm the prices.
After confirming my initial pricing,
I can see my base country or region
and prices
in the Price Schedule section.
The label "May Adjust Automatically"
indicates that the prices
for listed countries or regions
other than the base may be adjusted
to account for changes
in foreign exchange or tax rate.
So you might be wondering: what happens
when the prices are adjusted?
Whenever an automatic adjustment happens,
the upcoming changes will be displayed
in App Store Connect
at least 14 days in advance.
For example, I can see that there's
an upcoming price change
on September 1
in two countries or regions.
I'll click on the effective date to check
what the new prices will be.
In the pop-up modal, I can see the prices
in Japan and UK
will increase on September 1, 2023.
Let's come back
to my initial price schedule,
which has no adjustments.
Now, I'd like to schedule a price increase
for my app,
so I will click the plus button.
There are three types of price changes
you can schedule:
global, temporary, and custom.
I will talk about the last two options
later, but in this example,
I'm going to schedule
the global price change for my app.
Next, I will choose January 1, 2024,
as the effective date.
Then, I'm going to increase
the base price of my app to $9.99.
Next, the App Store will provide
the comparable prices
on the other 174 countries or regions
based on the new price.
I will review the prices in each region
carefully and confirm.
After confirming, I can see that there is
a price change on January 1, 2024,
in the Upcoming Changes section.
That's how enhanced global pricing
works in App Store Connect.
Now I'm going to show you how it works
with App Store Connect APIs.
You can get your app's price schedule,
including current prices
and upcoming changes,
from the AppPriceSchedules resource.
AppPriceSchedule has three relationships:
base territory, manual prices,
and automatic prices.
Manual Prices and automatic prices
contain multiple app prices.
Each AppPrice resource is linked
to an AppPricePoint,
which is linked to a territory.
App price point and Territory are
read-only reference data.
So, I need to make three API calls
to get the entire price schedule.
I'll go over the three APIs one by one,
using the initial price schedule
I just set for Backyard Birds app
as an example.
First, use Get/appPriceSchedules
/appId/baseTerritory
to get the base country or region
of the app's price schedule.
I can see that it is currently
the United States.
Then use Get/manualPrices.
I will include the price point
and territory relations
to get the price point information.
In this example, it contains
only one app price
that I set for the United States.
Finally, I can list
the automatically generated prices
by calling the Get/automaticPrices API.
The response will contain
the automatic prices
for regions you haven't manually set
prices for.
In my app Backyard Birds,
it will return 174 prices,
much more than what I can fit
on the screen.
Now you know how to read
the full price schedule.
If you'd like to make changes
to your app's price schedule,
you can update the baseTerritory
and manualPrices relationships
in the AppPriceSchedules resource.
The App Store will provide
comparable automatic prices
based on the base territory
and manual prices.
Let's take a look at the APIs you need
when updating
the price schedule one by one.
First, get all the price points
of your selected base country or region.
Choose a base price.
Next, preview the comparable price points
in other countries or regions.
Finally, update the price schedule
with all the necessary data.
I'm going to schedule a price increase
for Backyard Birds.
Let's take a closer look at how to use
these APIs to achieve it.
First, I get
all the available price points
in my app
of my selected base territory, US.
The price point resource includes
detailed pricing information.
I'll choose this $9.99 price point
and keep a record of its ID.
Before setting the chosen price point
in my price schedule,
I'd like to know
what the comparable prices will be.
I will get the comparable price points
of the price point I chose earlier,
in the previous step,
using the Get/equalizations API.
I will include territory relation
in the request
to identify the location
of the comparable price point.
For example, I can see
the comparable price in Canada is $12.99.
Next, I will need to update
the appPriceSchedule
with the Post/appPriceSchedules API.
AppPriceSchedule doesn't have
any attributes, just three relationships.
First, add the app ID in app relationship.
Next, specify the base country or region's
ID in base territory relationship.
I will use USA.
Finally, I need to define
the manual prices
for the base country or region.
Since this is a Post API,
my new schedule will overwrite
my existing schedule,
so I will need to include current prices
and add new prices.
I'm going to define a new current price
and assign it a temporary ID.
newprice-0.
If you're familiar
with the App Store Connect APIs,
you know that you can use any values
you want for these temporary IDs,
as long as they follow this syntax
with a dollar sign and braces
around the ID.
To schedule a global price change,
I'll add a new app price
and assign it
another temporary ID, newprice-1.
Now I need to define
the two new app prices.
This is my app's current price that I got
earlier from the Get/manualPrices API.
First, set the ID to be same as we defined
in the payload in the previous step.
Next, define the price point ID.
I will keep the current price point.
To schedule a global price change,
I need to end the current price
on the new price's start date:
January 1, 2024.
Next, define the new price's resource
with another temporary ID.
I need to set the new price's start date
to 2024, January 1,
and assign the new price point ID
to the price.
Coming back to the request entity,
I'll add an "included" section.
Then I take the new price resources
that I just defined
and insert them into this included array.
The final payload looks like this…
Before sending this payload
to Post/appPriceSchedules API,
keep in mind that if a price's start date
is null in the payload,
the price will go live immediately
in the associated region.
So I recommend testing this API
with an app that is not live
in the App Store yet.
That's how you would use
the new pricing tools
to effortlessly set global prices
and let the App Store do
all the heavy lifting.
If you want full control over your prices,
we have more options for you.
I will hand over to Chong to introduce
the new features
for managing pricing by region.
Chong?
Thanks, Claire!
As you can see from Claire's walkthrough,
the global pricing features provide you
with an easy way to price your apps
and in-app purchases globally.
Up next, let's explore
the new advanced pricing tools
designed for managing pricing by region.
In addition
to the automated global pricing,
we also provide you with more control
over your pricing at the regional level.
The advanced pricing tool
facilitate manually setting custom prices
and temporary prices
with any price point
on a per-region basis.
Let's start with temporary prices.
This is a way to manually set prices
for a short period of time.
Let me demonstrate this
with an example.
Here, I have set $7.99 in the US
as the base price
and autogenerated prices
for the rest of the regions.
And I plan to run a special promotion
in Canada and France for a few days.
For this promotion, I will lower the price
to $4.99 in Canada
and €4.99 in France
from February 1 to February 3, 2024.
After February 3,
the price will go back
to the initial price,
equalized to my base price.
During the temporary price change period,
the prices for Canada and France
will not be automatically adjusted.
And there's no limit to the number
of regions
you can manually manage.
And you have the option
to manually manage prices
in certain regions
while having the App Store
automatically adjust prices in others,
as demonstrated in this example.
You can also set up custom regional prices
on a permanent basis.
Let me show you how it works.
Here, I want to set up custom prices
for all the regions,
using USD as a currency,
to make their prices consistent.
In this example,
I will set custom prices to $9.99
for the United States and Argentina.
You may notice that in this example,
I have set a custom price
to my base region.
Setting a custom price for the base region
disables the automatic adjustment
of the prices for all the other regions.
Therefore, it is critical
to ensure you understand
and review your price changes
before they become effective
for your customers.
The custom price feature provide
the ability
to manually manage prices
for any region on a permanent basis,
but it comes with the need
for extra caution.
Once a custom price is set,
the App Store no longer makes
automatic adjustment,
meaning you will need to keep track of
and modify your pricing strategies
to accommodate fluctuations
in exchange rates and taxes.
And now, I will hand it over to Claire
once again.
She will provide you
with step-by-step guidance
and insightful tips
on how to effectively utilize
the advanced pricing tools
in App Store Connect,
as well as the related
App Store Connect APIs.
Over to you, Claire.
Thanks, Chong!
In the next few minutes,
I'm going to show you how to set up
temporary prices,
custom prices,
and show you some API examples.
Let's take a look at how to set up
temporary prices first.
For example, I'd like to schedule
a regional spring promotion
for Backyard Birds.
In the Pricing and Availability section,
next to Price Schedule,
I'll click the plus button.
From there, I will select
the Temporary Price Change option.
I'm going to schedule
a temporary promotion in early spring,
so I will choose February 1 to February 3
next year
as my start and end date.
Then, in the next step,
I'm going to choose Canada and France
for this promotion
and then click Next.
Select a country or region and a price.
The App Store will use this to provide
comparable prices
across the selected countries or regions.
I'm going to choose a lower price
of €4.99 in France,
since this is a promotion
outside of my base region.
You can review the comparable prices
for each selected country or region
and make any necessary changes.
I'm happy with the comparable prices,
so I will click Next
to review and then confirm my changes.
After I confirmed
my temporary price change,
the manually adjusted temporary prices
appeared in the Upcoming Changes section,
and the prices will go back
to be automatically adjusted
after the promotion.
Next, let's take a look
at how to set up custom prices.
I already have
the initial pricing schedule set up.
In this example, I'd like to have
full control
over my app's pricing starting October,
so I will click the plus button
and select Custom Price Change
option in the modal.
Next, I'm going to choose October 1, 2023,
as the effective date.
If you'd like to setup custom prices
in only a few regions,
select the first option,
"Manually manage prices
in specific countries or regions."
Then, use the same steps
as in the temporary price change flow.
Make your price selections.
However, I would like
to manually manage price
in all 175 countries or regions,
so I will choose the second option.
In the next step,
I will select a price for my base country
or region.
This price must be selected
for you to manually manage prices
in all 175 countries or regions.
You can keep the current base price
as is or update it.
To have more consistent prices in USD,
I'm going to increase the prices to $9.99
in countries or regions that use USD.
I'm not going to change the other prices.
I'll click Next and review the prices
for the countries or regions
that I didn't select a price for.
If you select a base country or region
in temporary price change flow,
you will see this step too.
Next, I will review and confirm
my custom prices
in all countries or regions.
After confirming the changes,
now I can see
the Manually Adjusted custom prices
in the Upcoming Changes section.
App Store Connect provides
a guided experience
for you to manually manage prices
by region,
and you can set up manual prices
in each region with APIs too.
It is important to remember
that temporary prices and custom prices
are manual prices.
I will show you an example of scheduling
a spring promotion in Canada with the API.
To schedule a temporary manual price,
I will use the Post/appPriceSchedules API
to overwrite my current price schedule.
Replace the manual prices
with the base price
and the new temporary price in Canada.
Before I define a temporary price
in Canada,
I need to define the current base price
in USA.
I will not change this price.
To define a temporary price in Canada,
I will link it to a Canadian price point
and set the start and end date.
Coming back to the request entity,
I will include the two manual prices
I defined
and send the payload
to the Post/appPriceSchedules endpoint.
Once I configured my manual prices,
the App Store will provide
comparable automatic prices
during the times I haven't manually set
a price
for each country or region
other than the base.
In this example, there will be
two automatic prices in Canada,
before and after the promotion,
and one automatic price per region
in the rest of 173 countries or regions.
That's how to manage manual prices
by region in App Store Connect!
With the new pricing capabilities,
managing pricing for your products
in the App Store
will be much easier.
Over to you, Chong!
Thanks, Claire!
And that's it
for the advanced pricing tools
for managing pricing by region.
The App Store's new pricing capabilities
provides you with remarkable flexibility
and control.
This enables you to create
tailored pricing strategies
that meet the needs of your users
and offer an even better experience
to the users around the globe.
As our wrap-up, I'd like to share
some useful pricing tips.
First, we've expanded
the number of price points available,
offering you more regional pricing options
and flexibility.
I encourage you to explore
these new price point
to find the best pricing option
for your business.
However, I also highly advise
carefully reviewing all the price changes,
including autogenerated prices,
before they become effective
for your customers.
Additionally, for all the apps
and in-app purchases
created before March 9 of this year,
the United States is set
as default base region.
I recommend reviewing
your base region settings
for your apps and in-app purchases
in App Store Connect
and configuring them as needed.
However, keep in mind that changing
the base region
will reset the existing price schedules.
Therefore, it is crucial
to carefully review the changes
to ensure all the pricing configurations
are set as expected.
Finally, with the recent 2.3 release
of the App Store Connect APIs,
we have introduced a new set
of pricing APIs.
To accommodate
the new pricing capabilities
in the App Store Connect APIs,
we needed to phase out
some older APIs
related to app pricing.
Although you can continue using
the deprecated APIs,
we intend to retire them later this year.
As a result, I strongly recommend
transitioning to the new APIs
to take full advantage
of the advanced pricing capabilities
and expanded price points.
We are thrilled
about these new pricing capabilities,
and we look forward to seeing
how you take advantage of them.
Thanks for watching.
[light music]