♪ ♪
Calvin: Hi. I'm Calvin Gaisford,
an engineer on the watchOS team.
In this code-along session, we'll build
a widget for the new Smart Stack
on Apple Watch.
We'll walk you through the whole process
of building a Widget
using an AppIntent configuration.
In the process, we'll be using
the latest WidgetKit and SwiftUI updates.
We'll use the Backyard Birds app
for our code-along.
Backyard Birds is an app
that lets you create
and manage backyards
that attract visiting birds.
Our widget will show a backyard's status.
If a bird is visiting,
it will show the bird
and also include the backyard's status.
The widget will provide relevant dates
to the Smart Stack
so it can prioritize our widget
when it's most relevant.
If you want to follow along,
you can download the sample code
associated with this session
and open the Backyard Birds Xcode project.
We've already added a Widget Extension
to the project
which generated some files,
including the BackyardVisitorsWidget file.
We'll spend most of our time
updating this file.
Here's what we'll cover.
First, we'll take a look at the widget
structure which defines our widget.
We'll also do a quick overview
of the widget configuration intent.
Then, we'll customize
our TimelineEntry structure
to hold data for our widget views,
and we'll build out our timeline.
Once our timeline has the data
we need to enable previews,
we'll build out our widget's views.
After our views are built,
we'll return to finish up the timeline.
Finally, we'll look
at the Relevant Intent Manager
and set intents for dates
when our widget should be prioritized
on the watchOS Smart Stack.
Let's get started
with the widget configuration
by looking at the widget structure
in our code.
The widget structure is where
a widget's configuration is defined.
New in watchOS
are AppIntentConfigurations.
We'll be using an AppIntentConfiguration
in our widget.
The configuration intent, provider,
and view were all stubbed out
when we created the WidgetExtension.
We'll be looking at each one
and implementing them
for our Backyard Birds widget.
This widget definition looks good,
so let's move on and look
at the WidgetConfigurationIntent.
Our widget is using
an App Intent Configuration
to allow it to do two things.
First, our widget can provide
a set of pre-configured widgets
in the watchOS widget gallery.
In the case of Backyard Birds,
we'll provide a configuration
for each yard in our app.
Second, the WidgetConfigurationIntent
will be used to specify dates
when our widget is most relevant.
The Smart Stack will use this information
to prioritize our widget
in the Smart Stack.
Let's look at our widget's
Configuration App Intent.
Each yard in Backyard Birds
has a unique ID.
I've already added a parameter
named backyardID,
so this can be used
to create a set of widget intents,
one for each yard
identified by their backyard ID.
For the widgets we're building,
that's the only parameter we need.
To learn more about App Intents
and how to further use
WidgetConfigurationIntent,
check out these sessions
about App Intents.
We have our widget structure defined
and a WidgetConfigurationIntent
that can hold a backyard ID.
Let's move on to our widget timeline
and take a look
at our TimelineEntry structure.
The TimelineEntry structure will hold
all of the data our widget views will need
to render themselves
for a particular date.
Back in the BackyardVisitorsWidget file,
locate the generated
SimpleEntry structure.
The date and configuration properties
were added when this file was generated.
We need to define
any additional properties
our widget views will need.
Our widget is going to show
a backyard's status
with its name, food, and water status.
If a bird is visiting, it's going to show
the visiting bird and the bird's name.
If there isn't a bird, it will show
how many birds have visited the yard.
To display information about the yard,
we'll use a structure
from the Backyard Birds app
that holds all of the information
about a backyard
for a given point in time.
This is important since
the TimelineEntry may have a future date.
Let's add the backyard property
to our TimelineEntry.
Now, let's add a few computed properties
based on the backyard property
we just added.
First, let's add a bird property
so the widget views can check
if a bird is visiting and display it.
Now let's add two more properties
that our views will use
to show more information about the yard.
waterDuration and foodDuration
will be used in the view
to show how long
the water and food will last.
These are calculated
from the date property
in the TimelineEntry.
A TimelineEntry also has
a property named relevance
that, if implemented, can tell
the watchOS Smart Stack
which timeline entries are most important.
Let's add the relevance property
to our TimelineEntry.
Inside, let's check to see
if the backyard has a visitor
for the TimelineEntry's date.
If there is a visiting bird, we'll return
a TimelineEntryRelevance structure.
The TimelineEntryRelevance structure
takes two parameters,
a score and a duration.
The score is used to prioritize an entry
against other entries
in the same timeline.
We'll set the score to 10
to rank an entry with a visitor
higher than an entry without a visitor.
This value is arbitrary and can
have any range of values
needed to rank entries in your timeline.
The duration is used
to tell the Smart Stack
how long this relevance entry is valid.
We've set the duration to last
until the visitor's endDate.
If there isn't a visitor,
let's return a Relevance structure
with a score of zero
This will tell the Smart Stack
which timeline entries are most important.
Depending on what else
is happening at the time,
our Widget may be raised in priority
on the watchOS Smart Stack.
Our TimelineEntry looks great and has
everything our widget views need
to render properly.
Let's move on
and build out our TimelineProvider.
There are four functions we need
to complete for our TimelineProvider:
placeholder, snapshot,
timeline, and recommendations.
The placeholder function is used
when the widget displays
for the first time
and should return quickly.
Since we updated our TimelineEntry
to take a backyard,
we need to supply one.
Let's fix that by adding a random backyard
from the app's data model.
That's good. Let's move on.
The snapshot function is used
when a widget is in transient situations.
This function should return quickly,
so using sample data is fine
as long as it doesn't take
more than a few seconds to fetch.
We can do that same thing we did
in the placeholder function
and pass a random yard.
That looks good, but we could do better.
The snapshot function is passed
a configuration intent
which has the backyardID property
that we added earlier.
Our data is all local,
so we can quickly look up
and return the proper backyard
rather than using a random backyard.
Let's get the configured backyard
from the backyardID in the configuration.
Now let's check the backyard and see
if we can get a visitorEvent from it.
Let's return an entry
configured with a visitor's date,
and if we don't have a visitor,
we'll return the configured yard
with the current date.
This will provide a better preview
for the user
since it will show
the configured backyard.
Before we dive into the timeline function,
I want to turn on
the Xcode canvas preview.
Let's fix the last SimpleEntry and give it
a backyard so we can see the preview.
Now let's turn on the canvas.
New in Xcode is the ability
to preview a widget timeline.
The canvas is showing a preview
of the rectangular widget,
and at the bottom is a series
of TimelineEntries
that make up the widget's timeline.
The canvas preview is using
the default view
that was generated
when we added the widget.
Before we finish the timeline provider,
let's go build out our view
so we can better visualize our timelines
as we build it.
Locate the BackyardBirdsWidgetEntryView.
Let's add an environment property
for the widgetFamily
so we can build views
specifically for each family.
Let's replace the body
with a switch statement
so we can implement a view
for each accessoryWidget family.
Now, let's create a case
for accessoryRectangular
with a view that takes an entry
as a parameter.
We'll implement this view below.
The rectangular view is unique,
in that it will be the view
of our widget
shown in the watchOS Smart Stack.
For our rectangular view,
we'll follow a common pattern
where we'll have an image on the left
and three lines of text on the right.
Let's go to the bottom of the file
and we'll create
the RectangularBackyardView.
The view uses the TimelineEntry
we modified earlier
to contain the backyard data.
Before we continue,
let's switch our canvas view
to the Smart Stack Rectangular view.
This will let us visualize the widget
as we build it.
Now let's put an image
and three lines of text
in our view's HStack.
Look at the preview.
That's not exactly it.
Let's put the lines of text
in their own VStack.
Okay, that's close.
Let's put actual data
into the view from the entry.
First, we'll use a ComposedBird view
from the Backyard Birds app
that can display a bird.
The bird is optional,
so we need to unwrap it.
Let's put the ComposedBird view
and VStack inside an if-let check
to see if there is a bird in the entry.
If there isn't a bird,
let's put an image of a fountain
for the yard and text that shows no bird.
We can now go through the timeline
and see entries that show a bird
with three lines of text
and entries that show no bird.
Let's fill out the details
for the case where there is a bird first.
For the first line,
we'll show the bird's name,
the second line, the backyard's name,
and the third line, we'll add information
about the yard's food and water.
For the case where there is no bird,
let's show the yard name,
the food and water information,
and then the number of visitors
to this yard.
Let's see what our entries look like.
That's great,
but let's fix up the layout a bit.
First, let's update the ComposedBird.
Let's make the view scaledToFit
and make it widgetAccentable
so it will tint when used
on a watch face that is tinted.
On the bird's name, let's add
the headline font, make it scale,
and also make it widgetAccentable
so it tints with the watch face.
We'll also make the text take on
the color of the bird's wing
using a foregroundStyle.
Let's add the scale factor
to both of our other views
in case the names go long.
Let's set the foregroundStyle
of the last line to secondary.
Finally, let's make our stack
leading aligned
so our three text views are aligned.
Our view looks pretty good.
Let's apply all of these same updates
to the views in the else statement
when there isn't a bird.
Now our widget is looking better.
Notice our widget has different spacing
when showing a bird or a yard.
Let's make those match by adding a frame
to the bird view and the image view.
We'll also add frames to the VStacks
so they align properly.
There's one more option we need to add
to finish our widget
for the watchOS Smart Stack.
New in SwiftUI is the containerBackground.
Let's replace the containerBackground
with a gradient from the backyard.
We'll set the containersBackground
placement to be a widget.
The containerBackground is
selectively used by the system
and here will only appear
in the watchOS Smart Stack
and not on the watch face.
Now our view is ready
for the watchOS Smart Stack.
The view looks great,
so let's go back to our TimelineProvider
and finish building out the timeline.
The timeline function is where
a widget generates
a collection of timeline entries
that contain data
to render the widget's view.
This is the workhorse-function
of a widget.
Right now it's generating five entries
with random backyard data.
Let's replace that
with a timeline full of bird visits.
At the top of the function
is an array of TimelineEntries.
We'll use this to build our timeline.
First, let's remove
the generated timeline code.
Now, let's get the configured yard
using the backyardID
from the ConfigurationAppIntent.
The backyard structure has
a property on it
that contains all of the visitorEvents
for that yard.
Let's iterate on the visitorEvents
for the retrieved yard.
For each event,
let's create a TimelineEntry that contains
the startDate of the visitorEvent
and pass in the configured backyard.
Our timeline preview updated.
Let's see how it changed.
Now as we select our timeline entries,
we see birds appearing.
That's what we expected.
However, every entry has a visitor.
We need to add entries
for when the birds leave too.
Let's create a second entry
and use the visitorEvent's endDate.
We'll use the same backyard
and append the entry to the entries array.
Let's look at the timeline now.
Okay, we have entries
for when the birds visit
and when they leave.
Our widget timeline looks great,
and this new timeline preview is amazing.
It's going to make building widgets
and timelines a lot easier.
Finally, let's implement
the timeline provider's
recommendations function.
Here, we need to return an array
of AppIntentRecommendations
which will contain
our WidgetConfigurationIntent,
which holds a backyardID.
Let's remove the default implementation.
Let's create an array
of recommendations to return.
Next, we want to create
a recommendation for each backyard
in our app, so let's iterate
through all of the backyards.
For each backyard,
we'll create a ConfigurationAppIntent
and set the backyardID.
And finally,
let's create an AppIntentRecommendation
using the ConfigurationIntent
and add it to our array.
We'll us the backyard's name
as a description.
The recommendations function
will now provide a list
of widget configurations,
one for each backyard,
in the widget gallery
when a person is selecting
a Backyard Birds widget.
Congratulations.
You've now built a widget on watchOS
that will surface
as a watch face complication
and the watchOS Smart Stack.
Earlier, we talked a little bit
about relevance
when we implemented the relevance property
on our TimelineEntry,
but there is more we can do.
Each yard in Backyard Birds app
keeps track of the water
and food available for birds.
Our new widget
is also gonna show that information.
We can provide the system
a list of relevant intents
during the time periods when we know
the water or food is running low.
Our widget will be prioritized
during those times,
letting people know
their yards need attention.
Back in our code,
let's create a new function
that will build relevant intents
for any of our possible widgets
and then update the RelevantIntentManager
with those intents.
We'll create a new function
named updateBackyardRelevantIntents.
In the function,
we need an array of relevantIntents.
And we'll update
the RelevantIntentManager with that array.
To fill out the relevantIntents array,
we'll loop through
all of the backyards in the app.
Next, we'll create
a configurationIntent for the backyard
and set the backyardID
to the current backyard.
We'll create a RelevantContext
based on dates.
In this case, we'll use
the backyard's future low food date
and the future empty food date.
Finally, we'll create a relevantIntent.
We'll use the configurationIntent
for our widget, our widget's kind,
and the relevantDateContext
we just created
and append this to our array.
Now, let's do the same thing
for the backyard's lowWater
and emptyWater dates.
That looks good.
Now the RelevantIntentManager
has the date ranges
when each possible configuration
of our widget has a higher relevance.
Let's go add this function
into key components
so the relevantIntents are updated
when appropriate.
First, let's go back to the timeline
function in the timeline provider.
Let's call our function
just before we return the timeline.
This will keep the relevantIntents
up-to-date
every time we update our widget timeline.
Let's also go over
to the Backyard Birds app.
The Backyard Birds app has
a detail view for each yard
and provides a page where a person can
refill the food and water.
This is also an ideal place
to update the relevantIntents
since the food
and water supply can change.
In the BackyardContentTab,
we'll add a Task
with our updateBackyardRelevantIntents
function
when the Refill button is tapped.
Since we know the food and water
has just been updated,
we should also make a call into WidgetKit
and reload our widget's timeline.
Now our relevant intents will be updated
and our widget's timeline will reload
when a person refills the water and food
in a yard.
We've now built a widget
for the watchOS Smart Stack
and we've updated
the RelevantIntentManager
with date intents to prioritize
our widget when it's most relevant.
Thanks for following along.
We look forward to seeing widgets
you build for the watchOS Smart Stack.
For more information about widgets,
the Smart Stack, and App Intents,
check out these sessions.
Be adventurous and never stop coding.