♪ ♪
Scott: Hi, I'm Scott Mionis
from the Virtualization Team,
and today we'll cover how features
in macOS Sonoma
enable you to create seamless
experiences with Virtualization.
Virtualization framework
lets you configure,
manage, and run virtual machines.
In macOS Sonoma,
virtual Macs and Linux virtual machines
are more powerful than ever.
They're easier to use,
and with new configuration options,
they are highly customizable.
There are a bunch of features
that make this possible.
In this session,
let's explore a few key items
and how to leverage them
in your applications.
First, new workflows in virtual machines
and improvements to the user experience.
Next, new storage
and keyboard configuration options.
And last, how Rosetta 2 is making x86_64
applications run even faster
in Linux virtual machines.
Let's dive into some of the new ways
to work with virtual machines.
We will go over two powerful new features.
First is the resizable display.
A new display option for virtual machines
that resizes at runtime
to fill the window.
And next,
saving and restoring a virtual machine.
A mechanism for serializing
a running virtual machine to disk
so it can be resumed later.
Let's start with the resizable display.
Screen size is a big part
of working on a virtual Mac.
With a resizable display,
the virtual machine dynamically adjusts
the screen resolution to fill the window,
making the most efficient
use of your space.
Let's put this into code.
To use the resizable display
in your own application,
First, initialize a VZVirtualMachineView.
To make the display resizable,
set the new
"automaticallyReconfiguresDisplay"
property to true.
And that's it!
Resizing the VZVirtualMachineView
will now automatically
tell the virtual machine
to adjust its display size.
And if you prefer
to keep the display fixed,
this property
can remain its default value.
Next, let's discuss saving,
and restoring a virtual machine.
Stopping a virtual machine
means powering off the VM.
Starting a virtual machine
means doing a cold boot.
But when working on a Mac,
most applications save your progress
as you work.
The same should hold for virtual machines.
Let's say I'm running a virtual machine,
And I want to close it
without losing my progress.
I can save my virtual machine to a file
and resume running it later.
Or, let's say I want to back up my work.
I can save my virtual machine
at any point,
making sure to clone external resources
like disk and auxiliary storage.
And if I want to jump back in time,
I can rewind the virtual machine,
right back to my previous state.
So much is possible with this feature.
So now let's put it into action.
I'm running macOS Sonoma,
and on my desktop is a virtual Mac,
also running macOS Sonoma,
in the Virtualization sample application.
And I'm doing some research for
my next exciting trip to the Apple Store.
Of course, I have Maps open,
and I'm browsing the Apple website
for more information on AirPods.
Now, I want to take a break
without turning off the virtual machine.
So I save my virtual machine
as I quit the application.
Later on,
I relaunch the application,
and my virtual machine resumes running
right where I left off,
with all my tabs open.
Let's explore how to build this
into your own application.
Before saving the virtual machine,
pause the virtual machine.
This puts the virtual machine into
a stable state, with execution suspended.
Then, invoke the new saveMachineState API,
which writes a file
to the URL you specify,
containing all of the runtime state
of the virtual machine.
Everything you need
to keep running it later.
External resources, like disk images,
should be copied separately.
Now that we've saved
the virtual machine, let's restore it.
To restore the state
of the virtual machine,
start by creating a new VZVirtualMachine
from the same configuration.
Instead of starting
the virtual machine directly,
which cold-boots the virtual machine,
invoke the new restoreMachineState API,
passing in the URL of the file
that was saved earlier.
And now, the virtual machine is
in exactly the same state as before.
You can resume running it
right where it left off.
When restoring a virtual machine
from a previous save,
there are a few things to keep in mind.
First, a save file contains
a virtual machine's data.
It needs to be protected.
These files are hardware encrypted
to provide
the strongest possible guarantees.
No other Mac or user account
can read another's save file,
or restore the virtual machine.
Also, files saved today are versioned,
so new capabilities can be added
in the future.
If the file format changes,
and a save file cannot be restored,
the framework will return specific error
codes so your application can handle it.
When this happens, discard the file,
reboot the virtual machine,
and you're back on track.
Next, let's explore some of the new ways
to build a virtual machine.
First is Network block device.
This allows a storage device
to be attached to a virtual machine
from over the network.
Next is support
for NVMe controller devices,
an alternative to the virtio block device.
And finally, the Mac keyboard,
which makes working
in a virtual Mac more intuitive
by mapping Apple-specific keys,
like the Globe key,
directly through to the virtual machine.
Let's start,
with Network block device.
In Virtualization framework,
storage is typically served locally,
reading and writing
a disk image on the same Mac.
But in macOS Sonoma,
Virtualization framework can serve storage
remotely from a server.
The protocol that allows this
is Network block device,
or NBD.
Let's dive into how it works.
Virtualization framework implements
the client side of the NBD protocol.
When a virtual machine accesses the disk,
the request is forwarded to an NBD Server
that adheres to the same specification.
After doing whatever I/O it needs,
the NBD server responds with data.
This is extremely flexible
for two reasons.
First, the storage can now reside
anywhere;
on the same Mac,
or on a remote server over the network.
And second, since the storage is managed
by your own server,
you can implement
whatever custom I/O you need,
whether that be custom image formats,
or even physical drives.
All of this completely transparently
to the virtual machine.
Let's look at how to set this up.
In Virtualization framework API,
there are two parts
to initializing a storage device.
First you choose a device type.
This defines the interface
that is presented to the virtual machine.
And then you choose an attachment,
This selects how the data is
actually represented on your Mac.
In virtual machines,
you can mix and match.
Virtualization framework
supports virtual devices
such as the virtio block device
and the USB mass storage device.
And with any of these devices,
you can use attachments
such as the disk image attachment,
which reads and writes data
on a disk image,
or the new,
Network Block Device attachment,
which reads and writes data
on an NBD server.
Let's set up this NBD attachment in code.
To use this in your application,
first specify a URL
that points to the NBD server.
This is a special URL that identifies
a specific disk on a specific server.
Then initialize the new NBD storage
attachment with this URL.
Finally, initialize a storage device
with this attachment.
This example uses the virtio block device.
For most use cases, this is likely
to be the most performant option.
Since storage is being served
over the network,
the connection can be lost at any time.
You may want to take action
when this happens,
to pause the virtual machine,
or re-establish the connection.
If this is the case,
you can attach a custom delegate class,
which will be notified when the state
of the connection changes,
so you can run whatever code you need.
Adding to Virtualization framework's
storage options
is Non-Volatile Memory express,
or NVMe.
NVMe is a standardized technology
enabled in many Linux kernels,
and its applications are more specific,
so let's start with why
you might want to use it.
For a vast majority of use-cases,
the paravirtualized interface
provided by virtio block storage
is the easiest and fastest to use.
This is certainly the case
for virtual Macs.
But some Linux virtual machines
don't have virtio drivers.
These may be kernels that are not built
to run in virtual environments.
What these kernels often do have
are drivers for NVMe controller devices.
In macOS Sonoma,
NVMe controller devices are emulated
by Virtualization framework,
allowing more operating systems
to be run in virtual machines.
To configure NVMe,
use the new device type
when building your virtual machine.
NVMe is for Linux virtual machines only,
and, of course, also supports NBD.
And now, with the Mac keyboard,
Apple-specific keypresses are captured
by a virtual Mac.
Meaning you can use the Globe key
for features like language switching,
or even emoting in a virtual Mac.
Now let's talk about Rosetta 2.
Rosetta 2, in a Linux virtual machine,
is the same technology used on macOS,
And in macOS Sonoma,
performance improvements mean
Rosetta 2 runs even faster
in a virtual Linux environment.
Let's dive into how this is possible.
Rosetta 2 translates
executable pages on-demand,
which allows it to launch the executable
much faster
than if it had to wait to translate
the entire x86_64 application.
But this also means that while
the application is running,
Rosetta 2 must stop execution periodically
to translate new regions of code.
This overhead is likely to be
the most noticeable
when the application
has just started running,
as code needs to be translated
for the very first time.
But if I launched another application
that linked against the same libraries
or ran the same executables,
Rosetta 2 has to do
all that work over again,
even though that code
has already been translated.
This problem can be solved with caching.
Whenever a library
or executable binary is translated,
Rosetta 2 saves the result
in a cache on disk
and shares that
with any other application that needs it,
avoiding unnecessary
retranslation overhead.
In macOS Sonoma,
Virtualization framework brings this
optimization to Linux virtual machines
with a new runtime daemon.
There are two steps you will need to take,
to set this up.
First, there is a new API
to configure the communication channel
between the Rosetta 2 runtime
and the new caching daemon.
And then, you'll need to launch the daemon
in the virtual machine.
The Rosetta 2 runtime and the new daemon
will now run alongside each other
in the virtual machine.
The two programs communicate
with Virtualization framework
to establish a connection.
Dynamic linker requests, among others,
will be forwarded to the daemon,
which manages the cache,
and the Rosetta 2 runtime
will fetch pre-translated binaries
directly from the daemon,
eliminating the retranslation overhead.
You'll see the biggest impact
on exec-heavy tasks
like compilation or package installation.
Virtualization framework allows you
to bring so many great options
to your applications.
Let's talk about ways to get started.
Consider using the resizable display
for both virtual Macs
and Linux virtual machines.
It significantly improves the user
experience with a single line of code.
The Mac keyboard is specifically designed
to work seamlessly
with the newest virtual Macs,
Configuring virtual Macs with this device
is an easy way
to boost the user experience.
A few of these features
are building blocks
that you can use
to build powerful experiences.
The ability to save a virtual machine
is one example.
Start investigating how rewinding
or saving progress
fits into your application.
And the flexibility offered by NBD
is incredible.
NBD can unlock a lot of possibilities
for applications needing custom IO.
This is just the beginning of what
virtual machines can do in macOS Sonoma.
Thank you.
The Virtualization team
can't wait to see what you build.
♪ ♪