♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hi, my name is Mark,
and I'm a SwiftUI engineer.
I'm pleased to invite you
on a journey out of the plane
and into space using SwiftUI.
To demonstrate how SwiftUI
works in a new dimension,
and to show how SwiftUI
and RealityKit work together
in the system to enable
incredible experiences,
we'll talk about
a handful of the APIs
powering a sample app
we've built called World.
World demonstrates several
different forms
applications can take
on the system,
from the familiar window
to the new volume,
allowing for bounded
3D experiences to full space,
which allows for the display
of unbounded virtual content.
While most of the APIs
we'll discuss in this talk
work whether you're adding
just a dash of 3D
in your primarily 2D window app,
or creating
an immersive 3D experience
leveraging full space,
we'll focus on using Volumes
as a container
since they provide a great way
to explore the realm of 3D
using SwiftUI in your app.
To learn more about the other
containers for SwiftUI content,
please refer to the
"Elevate your windowed app
for spatial computing" talk
and the "Go beyond the window
with SwiftUI" talk.
Once we cover
the basics of volumes,
we'll discuss how you can
create and position 3D content
with volumetric views
and layout,
how to integrate SwiftUI views
into the new RealityView,
and finally how to bring
everything together
with 3D gestures.
But before we get
too ahead of ourselves,
let's talk about what volumes
are and how they can help us
take our first step
into the realm of 3D.
World uses volumes
to emphasize its 3D content.
This scene has
no main glass window.
Instead it places its 3D content
directly into the scene
with a panel
of controls in front.
But the 3D content
is the star of the show here.
Volumes provide you
with a fixed scale container.
Unlike windows that dynamically
scale based on the distance
they're placed from you,
volumes maintain the same size
at any distance.
Volumes are horizontally aligned
and support viewing
from any angle.
Volumes are a great way to
display 3D content in your app
without taking over
the entire space,
and creating one
is incredibly simple.
All you have to do is use
the new volumetric window style
when creating a new scene,
such as a window group,
and you'll get all
these features automatically.
Now that we have
our volume set up,
let's get some content
inside it.
To help us do that,
RealityKit offers a new API
called Model3D, a SwiftUI view
that makes it simple
to load rich 3D assets,
such as USDZs,
while providing phases
to handle different parts
of the asset loading lifecycle.
Think of Model3D as
a counterpart to AsyncImage.
It handles all the work
of loading complex geometry
while keeping your app
running smoothly.
Let's use Model3D to show
one of the other models
from the World app, the moon.
Now, I've already added
a moon USDZ file to my project,
and I can just pass that name
to the Model3D initializer.
Now we can handle
the phase of the model.
Now, this isn't a phase
of the moon.
It actually indicates
the loading status of the asset,
and it has a couple different
states we can switch over.
Before the model has loaded,
I can show some text
or another piece of UI
indicating to the user
the content isn't ready yet.
I'll use a progress view here.
If the model failed to load,
I can show an error message
using the localized description
from the error.
And if the model succeeds,
I can use it in my UI.
Similar to images, I need to use
the resizable modifier
to tell the layout system
that the model can be resized
according to
its available space.
And I want the model to fit
within its available space,
so I'll use
the scaledToFit modifier.
Now I have a moon that loads
asynchronously in my app.
Let's keep building
on this example
to explore more
3D functionality in SwiftUI.
Let's inspect some
of the other models
that make an appearance
in the World app.
I want to show all of them
at once in a sort of display.
We can repurpose
the MoonView we just wrote
to handle displaying
any USDZ file.
Let's just rename it.
And pass in the name
of a USDZ file to load.
Now I can replace the hardcoded
Moon string.
Now let's make a data structure
to represent a celestial object.
I'll give each one
a name and a size.
I'll list out a few different
objects that I have
in my project:
the Earth, Moon, and sun.
Now I can display each object
in an HStack with a ForEach.
For each object, I can use
the new CelestialObjectView
we just created
using the object's name.
Let's vary the sizing
of each model
using a frame modifier
using the object size.
Our models look great
from the front,
but remember we're in 3D.
A change of perspective
reveals that our objects
are back face aligned,
as if their bounding boxes
were flush against a plane
behind all three of them.
This is the default alignment
for 3D content in SwiftUI.
If we want to change that,
we can specify
the depth alignment to use in
a frame depth modifier like so.
I can pass the object's size
to use for the depth
and specify that I want
the models front faces aligned
instead of the back.
Now the views all have their
front faces aligned instead.
Now I want to give
each object a label.
I can do that by giving
each Model3D an overlay.
Inside I'll make a text label
with a glass background effect
to make sure
it's always readable.
I'll also make these labels
are aligned to the bottom
of the model,
so I don't block the content.
The display looks great so far,
but it feels a bit static.
Finally, let's explore some
of SwiftUI's new additions
to geometry effects.
I can use a TimelineView
to animate a change in time.
Now I'll give our views
some spin
using the new Rotation3DEffect.
I'll make one
and give it an angle
based on the current date
with a scale factor.
And I'll have the objects
spin around the y-axis.
And just like that,
we've got our objects spinning.
Model3D is great for loading
and displaying simple assets
in your view hierarchy.
But for more involved 3D models,
scenes, or experiences,
RealityView is SwiftUI's
entry point
to unleash the power
of RealityKit in your app.
And indeed, the World app
uses RealityView
to break down its more
complex visualizations
using the RealityKit
Entity-Component system.
This allows for rendering
the individual models,
as well as advanced
rendering effects
like lighting and orbit paths.
Thanks to the new RealityView,
SwiftUI and RealityKit
go hand in hand on the platform.
For more information
about RealityView
and more new
RealityKit features,
please see "Build spatial
experiences with RealityKit"
and "Enhance your spatial
computing app with RealityKit."
For now, let's talk about
how you can make the most
of SwiftUI within
your RealityView
using the new
attachments API.
Attachments allow you
to pair a tagged SwiftUI view
with an entity that you can use
inside your RealityView.
Attachments are great
for adding annotations
or editing affordances
relative to specific entities.
If you've used
the Canvas API in SwiftUI,
attachments will
probably feel familiar.
The key difference
with attachments
is that they are live views,
not just snapshots.
This means they can respond
to state changes,
run animations,
and handle gestures.
Let's explore attachments
inside the World app
by adding on some
extra functionality
that will let me place
some markers
tracking my favorite places
around the world.
In the Earth view,
I've created some state
tracking an array of some
of my favorite places,
each with a name and location.
For each place, I can create
some text with its name.
And I can give it
a glass background effect
so that it's always legible.
And now I'll give it a tag
so that I can reference it later
in my RealityView.
This tag can be
any hashable value,
but I'll use a unique identifier
I've added for each place.
Now I can look up an entity
hosting each attachment view
using the tag I specified.
[KEYSTROKES]
I can add this entity
to my RealityView content.
And then I can use the lookAt
function to position and orient
the label along the surface
of the globe.
[KEYSTROKES]
We have a couple interesting
places pinpointed now.
But let's not get too attached
to this app quite yet.
I have some more ideas
for how we can take it
to the next level.
So, now we know how
to position 3D content
and make the most of SwiftUI
inside of RealityView
using attachments.
Now let's talk about how to
interact with all this content.
The platform brings the gestures
you're already familiar with
into the third dimension
with support for hands and eyes,
as well as new
trackpad mechanics.
Let's use these new capabilities
to extend our progress
on the World app.
We have
a pretty good thing going
with our "Favorite Places"
extension.
However I don't think
I'm satisfied
with the number of places
we have mapped out.
Let's make a way
to add some more
using a tap gesture
on the globe.
Before we jump into that though,
let's talk about
how to configure
an entity for input.
Let's say we're configuring our
RealityView with our content.
Here I've already added
a model of the Earth.
An entity hierarchy needs
an InputTargetComponent
to receive input
inside RealityView.
If the component
is added to an entity,
all that entity's descendants
can also receive input
unless otherwise specified.
In RealityKit,
CollisionComponent is used
for defining the shape of
an entity's interactive region.
Let's use a sphere for the Earth
model so that we can get
an accurate interaction point
on its surface.
This is all we need
to allow for our entity
to handle SwiftUI gestures
inside RealityView.
At this point, I can add
a SpatialTapGesture
to my RealityView.
But to make it even easier
to use SwiftUI gestures
with your RealityKit content,
we've added a new gesture
modifier called targetedToEntity
that I can use to target
my earthEntity specifically.
[KEYSTROKES]
If the tap doesn't occur
on this entity
or one of its descendants,
the gesture will fail.
Now let's handle
the gesture value.
[KEYSTROKES]
SpatialTapGesture has
a new location3D property,
allowing us to get
an accurate tap point
on the surface of the globe.
[KEYSTROKES]
The 3D location
is in the RealityView's
local SwiftUI coordinate space
in points, not meters.
To figure out where we want
to place our new label,
we'll need to convert
the location
into the RealityView's scene.
The targetedToEntity modifier
makes this super easy
by adding on some coordinate
space conversion helpers
to the gesture's value itself.
We can use that to convert
from SwiftUI local space
to the scene's coordinate space.
Finally, I can add the data
for the new place
using the location
we just calculated.
[KEYSTROKES]
I'll also scale up the location
just a tad so that the labels
float slightly above
the Earth's surface.
We now have a way to add more
favorite places to the globe
with just a tap.
But now we have a problem:
we need to discover more places!
To do that, let's launch
a satellite that can help us
pick out more exciting spots
around the world.
One way to add a satellite model
to our globe would be
to load a model
using RealityKit,
but let's use some of the other
techniques we've learned about.
I can add a Model3D
as an attachment.
Specifying a frame makes
resizing the satellite model
to a reasonable size super easy.
I'll also give my model a tag
so I can reference it
in my RealityView.
Just like with the labels,
I need to add my model
to my RealityView.
Now, let's define a gesture
that returns a 3D transform
that will let us define scale,
rotation,
and positioning
of our satellite.
[KEYSTROKES]
I'll start with dragging
using a DragGesture.
To convert from a drag gesture
to a transform, I'll use a map.
DragGesture has
several new properties
to handle manipulation in 3D.
We can use the DragGesture's
new translation3D property
to get how much the drag
has moved since it started.
[KEYSTROKES]
Now I'll create the transform.
I can pass in the translation
to the initializer
and return it from the map.
Now I can use
our manipulation gesture
that we just wrote
to transform my satellite.
I'm going to use
the updating modifier
to track when
the gesture is active.
[KEYSTROKES]
I can use this state
to shrink down all our labels
during the interaction
so that they don't
block our view of the Earth.
It's important to use
updating to track
any transient gesture state
I have
because it guarantees
that my gesture state
will automatically be reset
if the gesture fails.
When my gesture value changes,
I can set the state's
new transform
and then use offset modifiers
to position the satellite model.
I'll also animate changes
to the transform
using a spring animation,
so that when we let go
of the satellite,
it animates
back to its original place.
[KEYSTROKES]
Now we can drag
the satellite around.
This is a great start,
but we need to see this thing
in more detail.
Now that we have
everything hooked up,
let's add on
some scaling action.
For this I add a MagnifyGesture
that recognizes
simultaneously with the drag.
[KEYSTROKES]
I'll also add the new
RotateGesture3D,
which can measure unconstrained
3D rotation of the user's hands.
I'll plug in these new values
to our transform,
and finally I need to update
the rotation and scale
of the entity.
[KEYSTROKES]
I'll use the rotation3DEffect
and scaleEffect for this.
[KEYSTROKES]
And there we have it!
We can now freely drag, scale,
and rotate our satellite entity.
Our satellite looks like
it's ready for voyage.
The gestures we've added work
with all the input devices
and modes you'd expect,
including direct interaction
with hands,
indirect pinch, trackpad,
and accessibility features.
Using familiar SwiftUI gestures,
along with the new
targetedToEntity modifier,
you can quickly
build interactions
within intricate
entity hierarchies.
We're now ready to explore
the planet with our satellite,
but now it's time
for you to explore
SwiftUI's new 3D capabilities
in your apps.
New scene types like volumes
and full spaces allow you
to consider what an application
can be in all new ways.
The powerful layout and
rendering systems in SwiftUI
have been extended to make
SwiftUI not only a powerful way
to build apps on iOS, macOS,
tvOS, and watchOS,
but on this all-new platform
as well.
The new attachments API opens up
incredible new opportunities
to integrate SwiftUI views
into 3D scenes.
And finally we've explored
how to put the stories
you tell people right
into the palms of their hands,
using familiar and powerful
gestures in SwiftUI.
Thanks to SwiftUI
and RealityKit,
you have an exciting
journey ahead
beyond the bounds
of the 2D plane.
And we're only getting started.
Welcome to the platform!
♪