♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hello!
I'm Ivan, and I'm an engineer
on the RealityKit team.
Welcome to my session,
"Explore rendering
for spatial computing."
RealityKit is a framework
for rendering, animating,
and simulating 3D models.
One of the strongest suits
of RealityKit
is applying realistic rendering
for your content.
In order to help you make the
most of the rendering abilities
of RealityKit and enhance
the look of your content,
I wanted to share some rendering
considerations to keep in mind
while developing your app
for spatial computing.
We'll start with lighting and
shadows for your 3D content.
Then we'll learn what's new
with RealityKit materials.
Next, I will introduce
rasterization rate maps
which greatly improves
system performance.
I will share recommendations
on how to adjust your content
to make it work well
with this optimization.
Finally, I will introduce
a technique
called dynamic content scaling,
which ensures that the UI
is always sharp.
Let's start with lighting
and shadows.
If you are familiar with
RealityKit on iOS and macOS,
you will find that most
of that knowledge
also applies to building
spatial experiences.
We introduced image-based
lighting in RealityKit
to make your content
look realistic.
Image-based lighting, or IBL,
uses textures,
like the one on the right to
produce realistic reflections.
Shadows help us understand
how objects are positioned
with respect to each other.
Before we look at
the new features,
let's quickly go over
the components
of image-based lighting.
There are two main
components to an IBL:
an Environment probe texture
that is provided by ARKit
and is specific to the
physical space in the room
and the system IBL texture
which is packaged with the OS.
The system IBL texture
adds extra highlights
to ensure that your content
looks great in any environment.
The two components
are added together
to produce
the combined IBL texture.
If you have
an active environment,
it would also have an effect
on the combined IBL texture.
This year RealityKit adds
ability to override
the system IBL texture
in order to customize lighting.
Let's take a look at an example.
This is the "Hello World"
experience
that offers a view
of the solar system.
By default RealityKit would
light it using the system IBL.
However, if you assign
a new IBL
to the new image-based
light component,
it would replace the system IBL
and light those objects
using the surrounding
immersive environment.
Let me show you how that's done.
Here we first load
our 3D content.
In this case,
it's the satellite model.
Then we load an environment
resource called Sunlight.
It contains an image of the Sun
and stars surrounding the Earth.
We need both the model
and the environment resource
to set up IBL,
so let's make sure
both loading operations
have finished.
Next, we add the
ImageBasedLightComponent.
It references the Environment
resource that we've just loaded.
Finally we add
ImageBasedLightReceiverComponent
to the satellite entity.
You can add
these receiver components
even to other entities
in order to light them
using the same IBL.
And that's how easy it is
to customize lighting
in RealityKit.
Next, let's take a look
at how to add shadows
to your application.
Let's consider a simple example
where you place a 3D object
like this vase on top
of a floating plane.
Without any shadows turned on,
it might be hard to understand
the relative position
of the vase and the plane.
But by simply adding
RealityKit's grounding shadow,
it becomes a lot clearer
that the vase
is above the center
of the plane.
Let's see how
to do this in code.
We start by loading
the vase model.
Here, flower_tulip
is the name of our 3D model
in our project.
Next, we add the grounding
shadow component.
Make sure to set
castsShadow flag set to true.
And that's it!
The vase entity will now
cast grounding shadows.
Simple, isn't it?
Grounding shadows appear
on top of 3D models
as well as objects
in the physical environment.
Using a custom IBL
for lighting your scene
and including grounding shadows
can make your content
look a lot better,
but you could also directly work
on the look of your objects
by tweaking materials.
Most of the RealityKit materials
that are available
on macOS and iOS
can also be used on xrOS.
Let's quickly review them.
The most commonly used material
is PhysicallyBasedMaterial.
PhysicallyBasedMaterial
in RealityKit
reacts to lighting and can be
used to represent a variety
of real-world materials,
such as plastics or metals.
SimpleMaterial
also reacts to lighting,
but uses a smaller subset
of parameters.
It is especially good
for quick experiments.
UnlitMaterial doesn't
react to lighting.
In other words,
it maintains a constant look
under changing
lighting conditions.
VideoMaterial is a variation
of unlit material
that can map a movie file
onto the surface of an entity.
In addition to these materials,
RealityKit introduces
a new type of material
called ShaderGraphMaterial.
You can author the new
ShaderGraphMaterial
in Reality Composer Pro or
load it from a MaterialX file.
You can learn more about
ShaderGraphMaterial
in the session
"Explore Materials
in Reality Composer Pro."
The color output
of all of these materials
goes through a special step
called tone mapping.
Tone mapping is a transformation
that RealityKit applies
by default to the color output
of a material.
It enables more natural
perceived colors
using a variety of techniques.
One such technique is remapping
values above one
into the visible range.
Let me demonstrate this
with an example.
Here's a 3D render of a TV
with tone mapping disabled.
I assigned a texture with very
bright values to the display.
Now, if I enable tone mapping,
you can see more details
in the bright regions,
like these flower petals.
Tone mapping works great
in general
and renders beautiful visuals;
but for some use cases,
you may want to display
the exact colors of the object,
for which you will have
to opt out of tone mapping.
Let's look at an example.
Here's a simple application
that shows a traffic light
and three buttons with labels
"Stop," "Wait," and "Go."
The traffic light itself
is a 3D model,
and the three buttons
were added using SwiftUI.
In order to precisely match
the color of the lamp
to the color of the button,
we could use an unlit material
for the lamps,
since unlit materials
maintain the same
constant look of the object,
independent
of the lighting conditions.
However, the output of
unlit material is still affected
by tone mapping
which is on by default
for all of RealityKit materials.
So, even if the same color is
assigned to the SwiftUI button
and the material of the lamp,
they may appear
slightly different
from each other.
The screenshot you see was
taken with tone mapping enabled;
let me show you
what it looks like
when tone mapping is disabled
for the lamp material.
You will notice that the colors
of lamps and buttons
accurately match.
Let's toggle tone mapping for
lamp material one more time.
This is with
tone mapping enabled
and this is with
tone mapping disabled.
Let's take a look
at the code sample
that shows how tone mapping
can be toggled in code.
We start by loading
the traffic light model.
Here, traffic_light
is the name of our 3D model
in our project.
Next, we find the entity
named red_light.
This entity corresponds to the
top lamp of the traffic light.
Once we have the entity,
we access its model component.
Next, we create
a new unlit material.
We pass both our desired color
and a new Boolean parameter
called applyPostProcessToneMap.
This Boolean parameter is set
to false in order to disable
tone mapping transformation
for this material.
Finally, we replace material
on the model component
and assign the model component
back to the entity.
This is done for each
of the three lamps.
Now the color of button
and color of lamps
should match closely.
applyPostProcessToneMap flag
is useful in cases
when you want to show
an exact representation
of the colors in your scene.
This can come in handy
when using RealityKit
to build something like a menu
or a heads-up display.
This new property is also
exposed in the material editor
of Reality Composer Pro.
Now, let's take a look at
some quality considerations.
We'll start with
the rasterization rate maps
for spatial computing.
The displays used in the headset
have a high resolution,
and the OS needs
to update these displays
many times a second.
Let me explain this
with a visual.
As you may know already,
the headset has the ability
to detect exactly where
a person's eyes are looking.
Here's a simulated scenario
where a person
moves their eyes to the right
and then back to the center.
The yellow circle
represents the center point
of the person's focus.
The area that is
surrounding that point
is highlighted with a glow,
and the periphery is darkened.
Rasterization rate map makes it
so that fewer calculations
are performed in the areas
that are darkened.
You can see that
at any given moment
the highlighted region is small
in comparison to the periphery.
This allows the system
to achieve significant memory
and performance savings.
In RealityKit,
this optimization is
automatically enabled for you.
While it greatly improves
the system performance,
in some situations you may have
to adjust your content
to make it work well
with this optimization at play.
For example,
here's a palm leaf asset,
When placed in the center
of the screen,
it looks sharp and detailed.
But when I move
the object to the left
and apply the eye movement
simulation again,
you can observe flickering
on the palm leaf.
The flickering
is especially strong
when the yellow circle
representing the eye direction
is close to the right edge
of the screen.
The flickering happens because
the rasterization rate map
enables higher detail
around the point
where the person is looking,
and the pixels
around the palm leaf
are rendered at a lower detail
as the eyes move away from it.
Now, you can reduce
the flickering
by simply adjusting a few
parameters of your content.
Let's take a look at this.
Here's a representation
of the same palm leaf asset
with a red wireframe
overlay on top.
You can see that there are
a lot of small triangles here.
These small triangles were
the reason of flickering
in the periphery.
We can reduce the flickering
by simply making
the triangles larger
and storing the fine details
in an opacity texture.
Here's how the simulation looks
after adjusting the asset.
This 3D model looks
better after adjustment,
because RealityKit
automatically generates
lower-resolution versions
of the opacity map
when the asset is loaded.
Those lower-resolution versions
of the texture
are called mipmaps and
automatically used by the GPU
to improve the look
in the lower-detail region.
For more details
on rasterization rate maps,
please refer to the article
"Rendering at Different
Rasterization Rates."
Similar to rasterization
rate maps,
there is another technique
called "dynamic content scaling"
that automatically improves
the look of content
that was authored using SwiftUI.
Let's take a look.
Here's an application
that displays a list of months
arranged in a grid.
Each month is represented
with a text label.
When the eyes look
at the month of June,
the system rasterizes
the text in that area
at the highest level of detail.
The area marked in blue
surrounding "June"
will be rasterized at a slightly
reduced level of detail,
but still maintains
a high quality overall.
The area marked in purple,
however,
is rasterized at a much
lower level of detail
since human vision system
perceives fewer details
in the periphery and it wouldn't
be as noticeable.
This kind of rasterization
at variable levels of detail
based on what the eyes
are looking at
is called
"dynamic content scaling."
The system relies
on dynamic content scaling
to draw UI content
at the right scale
and ensures that
it's always sharp.
Dynamic content scaling
affects the relative size
in memory
for the rasterized content.
In other words,
our text labels are scaled
to different sizes depending
on how close they are
to the point where
the eyes are looking at.
For example, you can see that
the label that says "June"
is the largest --
it has the most resolution
and detail.
Then there is a group
of eight months --
January, February,
March, and so on
that have slightly less detail.
Finally, there is a group
of three months --
April, August, December --
that are farthest away
from eye look-at direction.
That last group would be
represented with smaller images
in memory.
Now, let's understand how to
enable dynamic content scaling.
If you are using
UIKit and SwiftUI,
your application
will automatically benefit
from this technique.
If you are relying on
the Core Animation framework
to build your UI,
there is a new API
to enable dynamic
content scaling.
Let's take a look at this API.
Dynamic content scaling
can be enabled by setting
the property of CALayer
wantsDynamicContentScaling
to true.
Note that this technique
relies on rasterizing
at higher resolutions,
so it is not recommended
to use with primarily
bitmap-based content.
You can find the full list
of recommendations
regarding dynamic content
scaling on developer.apple.com.
Let me summarize
everything we've learned.
We started by looking at how
to add image-based lights
and grounding shadows
to RealityKit applications.
Then we reviewed materials
that are available
for spatial experiences,
including the new
ShaderGraphMaterial.
And we've also learned how
to control tone mapping
for unlit material.
Next we learned how
rasterization rate maps
are used for spatial computing,
including an example
how to adjust 3D model to reduce
flickering in the periphery.
Finally, we learned how
dynamic content scaling works
on the system
and how you can make use of it.
We're very excited
about this year's release
and can't wait to see the
beautiful spatial experiences
you build on xrOS.
Thank you.
♪