♪ ♪
Ian: Hi, everyone.
I'm Ian, and I'm an engineer
on the App Store server team.
Today I'll share some exciting updates
about our server APIs for in-app purchase,
including new features
and important updates.
If you're not familiar,
we offer two primary APIs
that help you get the most
out of in-app purchases on your server.
The first is the App Store Server API.
You call the App Store Server API
on-demand from your server,
and it returns all the data you need
to effectively manage in-app purchases
made in your apps.
The API offers a variety
of powerful endpoints for retrieving
and even modifying in-app purchase data.
The other major API we offer
is App Store Server Notifications V2.
With App Store Server Notifications V2,
the App Store server
proactively sends updates
to your server
about in-app purchases made in your app.
That means
you can get minute-by-minute updates
without needing
to poll the App Store Server API.
Notifications cover
a comprehensive set of events,
including subscription renewals,
expirations, refunds, and much more.
These events allow you to track
the full lifecycle of in-app purchases,
so you can better understand
and respond to user behavior.
The App Store Server API
and App Store Server Notifications V2
share a lot of great features.
They both provide transaction data
in a familiar JSON format,
and the data is signed, so you can be
confident it came from Apple.
You can also use both APIs
to support your apps that use StoreKit 2
or the original StoreKit API.
And we actively support these APIs
with new features based on your feedback.
Today I’m happy to announce
the latest collection of updates coming
to the App Store Server API
and App Store Server Notifications V2.
We have so many new features,
I only have time to cover a few
in today's session.
Please check out our developer
documentation for the full details
of all these new features.
Now let's dive into this great selection
of App Store server updates.
I'll share today's updates in three parts.
First, I'll detail some new features
that make working with transactions
on your server easier.
Next, I'll cover enhancements
to App Store Server Notifications
that will help you reliably determine
the status of your users' subscriptions.
And finally,
I'll provide important updates
about migrating away from our older APIs.
Let's get started with transactions.
Transactions are a core data object
for in-app purchase.
They represent
an in-app purchase on a device
and contain important information
about that purchase,
such as the product identifier, the type,
the purchase date, and much more.
The App Store Server
represents a transaction
through a JSON object signed with JWS.
This is a secure,
standardized format that you'll see
across the App Store Server API
and App Store Server Notifications V2.
The primary way
to retrieve these signed transactions
is using the Get Transaction History
endpoint of the App Store Server API.
This endpoint returns
the full transaction history
for a given user of your app,
so you can use it to keep up-to-date
with all of a user's purchases,
from past to present.
But sometimes, your server
is already aware of a transaction,
for example, due to a call made
from your app to your server.
Server-side, you may want
to further validate that transaction
and ensure you have the most
up-to-date information for it.
Previously, this use case required calling
Get Transaction History
and sifting through the response
for the matching transaction.
Once found, you could refresh your record
of the transaction with the data
in the response.
This process might feel tedious,
particularly if your user's transaction
history spans multiple pages,
requiring multiple calls to the endpoint.
And it also doesn't work if you're looking
for a finished consumable transaction,
as those don't appear
in the Get Transaction History response.
This use case simply demands
a more specific solution.
That's why today,
we're introducing a new endpoint
that will directly address this use case.
With the new
Get Transaction Info endpoint,
you can request the signed transaction
information for a single purchase,
and all you need
to provide is a transactionId.
All transactionIds are supported,
no matter the product type
or the finished status of the transaction
on the user's device.
That's right, you can even fetch
finished consumables from this endpoint.
Let's take a quick look
at how the new endpoint works.
You'll send a GET request to
this new endpoint on the App Store server,
including the transactionId
as a path parameter.
You'll receive a response containing
a signedTransactionInfo string.
By decoding the signedTransactionInfo,
you can view the transaction information
for the ID you provided in the request.
And that's it.
The new Get Transaction Info
endpoint is quite simple,
but makes for greater flexibility when
working with transactions on your server.
I think you'll find it useful
for a variety of use cases.
Now, let's take that theme of flexibility
and extend it even further.
You might be familiar with these popular
endpoints of the App Store Server API.
Each of these endpoints require
an originalTransactionId
as a path parameter.
This id indicates to the server which user
you're requesting or sending data for.
But you might not always have
an originalTransactionId handy.
What if all you have is a transactionId?
You could send it to the new
Get Transaction Info endpoint
in order to retrieve
the originalTransactionId,
but why call one endpoint
just to call another?
Instead, starting today, you can call
these endpoints with any transactionId.
Just provide the ID in the path
of your request, just as you did before.
We hope this greater flexibility
will make it easier than ever
to call these core endpoints
of the App Store Server API.
And if you're
already calling these endpoints
with originalTransactionIds,
don't worry,
they will continue to work as well.
Now let's switch over to updates
coming to App Store Server Notifications.
If your app offers
auto-renewable subscriptions,
it's important for you to keep track
of the status of those subscriptions
and how it changes over time.
Here you can see the five
possible statuses of a subscription.
With App Store Server Notifications V2,
you receive prompt notifications
for events that lead
to changes in this status,
so you can quickly enable
and disable content
at the appropriate time
and maintain a smooth user experience.
Let's take a look at how notifications
can inform your knowledge
of a subscription's status.
Many notification events directly indicate
the status of the subscription
through their type and subtype.
Take for example this SUBSCRIBED
notification with subtype INITIAL_BUY.
This notification indicates
a new subscription to your product,
so you know the subscription's status
is Active.
Here's an even simpler example,
where the notification type is EXPIRED.
This clearly indicates that the status
of the associated subscription
is now Expired.
But for some notifications,
the subscription status
may not be so clear.
Take for example this REFUND notification.
This notification type is sent
when a refund is granted
for an in-app purchase made in your app.
Checking the signedTransactionInfo
of this notification will tell us
what purchase was refunded.
In this case, we see the refund
was for an auto-renewable subscription,
so we'd like to update our record
of the subscription's status.
It might be tempting to assume
the status is now "Revoked,"
but that's not necessarily the case.
If there's a more recent
subscription renewal purchase
with the same originalTransactionId,
the status
of the subscription could still be Active.
If that's the case,
you should not disable access
to the subscription content.
In this situation, the status
of the subscription is simply unclear,
and the data in the notification alone
is not enough to update it.
This is not ideal.
When you receive an App Store
server notification for a subscription,
we want it to clearly indicate
the latest status of the subscription,
so you can keep this important
information up-to-date on your server.
That's why today,
we're introducing a new status field
to the data object
of App Store Server Notifications V2.
This field is a simple integer
that indicates one
of the five core states
of a subscription I detailed earlier.
This new field will be included
in every notification we send
for auto-renewable subscriptions.
Now you can get the status
of a subscription without having to call
the Get All Subscription Statuses endpoint
of the App Store Server API.
Let's see how this new field improves
the scenario I described earlier.
Now when you receive a REFUND notification
for a subscription,
you can simply check the status field
to understand the status
of the subscription.
In this case it's 1, so you know
the associated subscription is Active.
The new status field makes
App Store Server Notifications
more useful than ever,
so useful, that you'll want
to ensure you don't miss a single one.
But if your server experiences an outage,
the App Store server may not be able
to reach it to send a notification.
That's why we offer
the Get Notification History endpoint
of the App Store Server API.
This endpoint allows you to request
up to the last six months
of version 2 notifications the App Store
server generated for your app.
That way when your server
has a known outage,
you can call this endpoint
for the outage period
and retrieve any notifications
your server missed.
For some use cases though,
this process
might not feel very efficient.
Occasionally, your server may miss
a notification even outside of an outage,
for example,
due to transient network issues.
In this situation,
you might not have a clear time period
to query the endpoint with,
leaving you to sift through pages
of notifications that your server
has largely already received.
To address this use case,
we're introducing a new request field
to Get Notification History
called "onlyFailures".
This optional field will limit
the notifications returned to only those
that have failed to reach your server.
The response
will even contain notifications
that are currently in the retry process.
Now you can recover from outages
and occasional network issues much faster,
as you only need to parse notifications
that your server hasn't already seen.
Let's take a look
at how this new field works.
You send a request
to the Get Notification History endpoint,
and you include the new field,
onlyFailures, in the request body.
Here's the response.
Each entry in the notificationHistory
array represents a notification,
and since you included the new
onlyFailures field in your request,
every notification listed here
has failed to reach your server.
Let's zoom in
to a single notification entry.
Here we have the signedPayload.
We can decode this string
to view the contents of the notification,
just as it was
originally sent to your server.
Taking a look at the sendAttempts array
for this notification,
we can now see the result
of each send attempt.
This array may contain up to six entries,
with one for the initial send attempt,
and up to five for retries.
Here we see only two entries,
and both have failed,
so the notification must
still be in the retry process.
If a later retry is successful,
this notification will no longer appear
for subsequent requests
that include the onlyFailures field.
So that's how
the new onlyFailures field works.
I think you'll find that it makes
Get Notification History even more useful.
Finally, an important update
about migrating away from our older APIs.
If your app has offered
in-app purchases for some time,
you're likely familiar
with the verifyReceipt API.
In 2021, we released
the App Store Server API as the new way
to get in-app purchase data
from the App Store Server.
Let's compare these two APIs.
With verifyReceipt,
you can verify and decode the receipts
you receive from clients running
the original version of StoreKit.
With the App Store Server API,
you can fetch all the same data
you find in receipts and more
using these three endpoints.
And the App Store Server API
also provides a variety
of additional endpoints
that offer useful data
and powerful functionality
you won't find anywhere else.
Shifting to our notification APIs,
we still support the older
App Store Server Notifications V1.
But in 2021, we introduced
App Store Server Notifications V2.
Now let's compare these APIs.
App Store Server Notifications
V1 and V2 both offer
real-time in-app purchase events
sent directly to your server.
But V2 offers greater clarity
by defining events
using both a type and subtype.
And the differences don't stop there.
V2 also offers notifications
for additional events,
the ability
to request a test notification,
access to notification history,
and the brand-new status field
for tracking the state
of your users' subscriptions.
By adopting the App Store Server API
and App Store Server Notifications V2,
you'll unlock a wide array
of new features for securely
and efficiently managing
in-app purchase data on your server.
Ultimately, that means a better in-app
purchase experience for your customers.
That's why today,
we're announcing the deprecation
of verifyReceipt
and App Store Server Notifications V1.
Starting today,
these APIs are considered deprecated
and will no longer
receive feature updates.
Start planning your migration now
to enjoy all the benefits
of the newer APIs.
Migration requires just a few short steps.
To migrate from verifyReceipt
to the App Store Server API,
you'll first need to sign a JWT
to represent your app,
which is a simple process
outlined in our documentation.
Whenever you call
the App Store Server API,
you'll provide this JWT as a header.
It will prove that you own
the requested app data.
Next, you'll need to save a transactionId
for each of your users.
You'll provide this transactionId
as a path parameter
whenever you call core endpoints,
like Get Transaction History
and Get All Subscription Statuses.
Any transactionId will work.
If you maintain a database
you likely already have one saved.
Otherwise, you can extract one
from a receipt for each of your users.
And that's it.
You'll then have access to all the same
data you used to get from verifyReceipt
and so much more.
Migration
from App Store Server Notifications V1
to V2 is even simpler.
First, prepare your server to parse
the new V2 format.
If you're already using
the App Store Server API,
this step should be straightforward,
as App Store Server Notifications V2 uses
the same JWS transaction format.
Once your server is ready,
visit App Store Connect to change
your preference
from V1 to V2 notifications.
To test your implementation,
you can start by receiving version 2
notifications in sandbox only.
After switching your preference,
the App Store server will start sending
new notifications in the V2 format.
If you have any V1 notifications
in the retry process,
you may continue to receive them
for up to three days.
For more assistance with migration,
we have additional resources available.
The App Store Server API
and App Store Server Notifications V2
are available in the sandbox environment,
so you can test your implementation
before rolling it out to production.
And this week, we are releasing
the App Store Server Library,
a new open-source library
for calling the App Store Server API
and parsing
App Store Server Notifications V2.
It can help you easily call our endpoints,
verify the signed data you receive,
and even extract transactionIds
from receipts to make migration easier.
I hope you'll check out its dedicated
session at WWDC this year titled
"Meet the App Store Server Library."
And for more tips on how to migrate,
see the WWDC22 session titled,
"Explore in-app purchase integration
and migration".
That concludes our App Store Server
updates for this session.
I hope you'll utilize the great new
capabilities we announced today,
and check out our documentation
for even more features
we didn't have time to review.
Every feature is available now
in both sandbox and production,
so you can first test in sandbox,
then roll out to your production server
whenever you're ready.
And we'd love to hear from you.
If you have feature requests
for the App Store server,
please let us know
through Apple’s Feedback Assistant.
Thanks for joining me at WWDC23!
♪ ♪