♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
Howdy!
Welcome to
"Enhance your iPad and iPhone
apps for the Shared Space."
My name is John Marc.
I'm a platform compatibility
engineer.
Most iPad and iPhone apps
run great without any changes,
taking advantage of the hard
work you've already done
and making it work
on Apple's latest platform.
If you're just getting started,
watch "Run your iPad and iPhone
apps in the Shared Space"
first to learn about
the system's built-in behaviors,
functional differences,
and testing setup.
In this video, I'll go over
how to enhance
your iPad or iPhone app
from a great app
to one that feels at home
on this new platform.
I'll review the new interaction,
visual-appearance changes,
and media recording
and playback functionality
your app should expect.
Interaction on this platform
is fun and feels familiar.
One of the key components is
the new natural input technique.
Tap allows people
to look at a button,
then tap their fingers together
to interact.
People can tap to toggle, tap,
hold and swipe to interact
with a slider, or tap a button.
Direct touch requires
reaching out to the app
and touching the button
in the space with one finger.
Regardless
of interaction method,
the button provides
continuous visual feedback
to help with
interaction accuracy.
In this video,
the cursor represents
where a person is looking.
When looking at a button,
a highlight hover effect tints
the control's color to help
understand where focus is.
Notice that
each item highlights
while looking through this list.
That highlight follows focus
to the left, or right
so it's clear what's happening.
Hover effects exist on controls
to inform
where people are looking.
Controls that are inactive
do not get hover effects.
System controls take care of
all these hover effects for you.
If you're only using
the standard controls,
you're ready to rock and roll
without any changes here.
If you're building
custom controls,
your hover effects
may need some tuning.
Here's an example of an app
with a card-based interface
on iPad.
Each card contains a photo,
title, date, and menu button.
Here is that same app
running in Simulator.
Because the menu button
is a system control,
it's already working
as expected.
However, each card is a simple
VStack with a .onTap modifier,
so it does not receive
hover effects.
That entire card
is a tap target,
so it needs hover effects
to inform people
it has an available interaction.
Let's focus on
one of those cards to fix it.
System controls, like Button,
receive hover effects
automatically,
so the button used as a menu
here already has a hover effect.
However, in this example,
people click the entire card
to view more detail.
By adding .hoverEffect
onto the VStack,
the entire card
becomes available
for interaction update and
informs people it's tappable.
Many custom video players
have optimized hit targets
so people don't have to be
quite so precise
to interact with them.
In this example of a custom
video player on iPad,
the tap targets
are significantly larger
than the symbols
on the skip forward
and skip backward buttons.
The bordered boxes here
show the size of the tap targets
where people can interact.
On Simulator now,
hover effects
highlight those tap targets,
which shows a tappable region
over the entire area.
That same example
in the Shared Space
now shows the hidden attributes
with hover effects.
This change of appearance
is exposing the truth
but does not feel correct.
If we zoom into our example,
to keep the existing
tapping behavior
with reduced appearance,
add a custom shape
to the .contentShape modifiers.
By using a custom shape, apps
can provide an origin and size
to the .contentShape modifiers,
which will be smaller
than the tappable region.
In this video, people
looking directly at the button
will see a hover effect.
And with this change, tapping
outside the hover effect bounds
will match expectations from
iPad and iPhone experiences.
Back on the simulator
with the full example.
Now with this custom shape,
the hover effect
appears on just the buttons
but allows tapping
outside of them.
Excellent!
In most cases, hover effects
on system controls work great;
however, the ability
to customize hover effects
is powerful.
With the new hover effect API,
apps can create hover effects
for custom buttons,
custom shapes,
or even opt out
of a control if necessary.
Let's inspect how to do that.
.buttonStyle is a great way
to consistently apply
a custom style
to all buttons in apps.
When applying custom styling,
it turns off hover effects.
To reenable hover effects on
a custom .buttonStyle button,
add the .hoverEffect() modifier
to app elements.
Here is my simple button
with a custom button style.
Looking at the custom
button style,
here, we need to add
the .hoverEffect modifier
to add hover effects to
the button with custom styling.
Many apps have fun
and custom interfaces.
In this example
of a beekeeping app,
buttons are honeycombs,
where each honeycomb cell
is its own tap target.
Apps implementing custom shape
buttons will need to inform
the system how to render
their hover effects.
Frame width here is larger than
the area the shape occupies,
so the default
system-provided hover effect
covers the entire button frame,
unbounded to shape.
By passing a custom shape
to the .contentShape modifier,
hover effects will trim
to the button's bounds.
Let's add that here.
Now it is perfect,
because when people look
at individual buttons,
the hover effect is trimmed
to the geometry
of the button's shape.
System controls that
are disabled due to app state
automatically do not get
hover effects.
If apps want to de-emphasize
specific interface elements,
they can opt out
individual items.
People expect hover effects
to be apparent
and consistent
across the system,
so they should be
turned off sparingly.
The system accepts a maximum
of two simultaneous inputs
since each hand
is a distinct touch.
Custom gesture recognizers
are also supported,
but you may need to update them
to run smoothly
with the natural input
expectations.
Games, or other apps that need
rapid or simultaneous input,
need to support
game controllers.
iPad and iPhone apps have long
been able to indicate support
for game controllers.
On this platform,
it's even more critical
for additional input methods.
By including GCSupports
ControllerUserInteraction
in the Info.plist and adding
Game controller capability,
it adds a badge
to the app's product page.
This improves communication
with people using App Store
to find games,
and makes the availability
of game controllers even more
evident across all platforms.
For information
about game controllers
and games on App Store,
watch the videos
"Advancements in
Game Controllers"
and "Build great games
for spatial computing."
iPad and iPhone apps
running on this platform
match their iPad
light-mode appearance.
In most cases, that looks great.
If you're using
system standard controls,
layouts, and colors,
there's no new work
for you here.
The system optimizes rendering,
using dynamic content scaling
so all images and text
are always sharp
at any angle,
from any distance.
To provide the best experience,
use vector-based content.
Prompts on iPad and iPhone
are presented modally,
so the prompt must be interacted
with before continuing.
On this new platform,
prompts do not present modally.
Prompts such as asking
for location permission,
Sign in with Apple, or OAuth,
do not require handling
before continuing.
These interfaces
create their own chrome
and windowed experience.
Apps should be aware and handle
cases where they get the prompt,
but may not get immediate
cancelled or success call backs.
People capturing, sharing,
and posting content
is a great way
to express themselves.
On this platform,
there are some differences
apps should be aware of.
There are multiple external
and internal facing cameras.
However, many of these cameras
are not available for app use.
It is critical to use
discovery sessions to detect
which cameras and microphones
are available for use.
To ensure apps have
an excellent capture experience,
use AVCaptureDevice
discovery session
to confirm
hardware availability.
Additionally,
similar to other platforms,
requesting permission
before use is required.
Lastly, generalize your
authorization prompt string
to inform people of use,
without mentioning specific
hardware or software versions.
When apps request camera
and microphone availability,
expect different values to be
returned than iPad and iPhone.
When querying microphone,
apps will receive
a single .front
location microphone.
When querying camera,
apps will find two cameras.
The .back camera returns
a black camera frame
with a no camera glyph.
This is a nonfunctional camera
to support apps
that assume back camera
availability.
When querying for front camera,
apps find
a single composite camera.
If no spatial persona
is found on a device,
then no camera frames
will return to apps.
AVRoutePickerView
and Picture in Picture
are unavailable
on this platform,
which has been reflected
in system-provided players.
Apps that implement
custom players need to check
both availabilities before
showing these controls.
Lastly, this platform locks
once removed.
Apps that utilize
background audio
should consider
this difference,
as they will no longer
get this background mode
when the device is locked,
and will be fully suspended.
Apps that import media should
consider alternative sources
when capture hardware
isn't available.
Options such as iCloud
or content pickers,
like document or photo picker,
are excellent alternatives.
Additionally,
apps that use VisionKit's
VNDocumentCameraViewController
will automatically capture
with Continuity Camera
on a nearby device.
These alternatives bring
even more media-import options
to existing iPad
and iPhone apps.
iPad and iPhone apps
run great on this new platform.
Make sure hover effects
are added
to all your interactive
controls.
For games, add controller
support to ensure players
continue to have
a great experience.
Finally, review your assumptions
about camera
and microphone presence
by checking for availability
before use.
Now you know how to optimize
iPad and iPhone apps
for this new platform.
I'm looking forward to using
your apps in the shared space.
♪