♪ ♪
Keith Holleman:
Hi, my name is Keith Holleman,
and I’m part of the Internet Technologies
team here at Apple.
Today I’ll be talking about
how you can use network relays
to enhance the privacy
and security of your apps.
We will start this session by exploring
the technology used for network relays.
Relays are used across
many privacy features at Apple.
We love how this technology is both
effective and easy to use,
and now you will have two ways to
use relays in your apps as well.
First, you can configure relays within an
app
to protect the network traffic
for your app.
Second, you can extend relays to
the device
for accessing private resources
in an enterprise,
as an alternative to a VPN.
Let’s dive in and get started.
Relays form the basis of great features,
such as iCloud Private Relay,
Mail privacy protection,
and hiding IP addresses from trackers
in Safari.
Your app may also handle
sensitive information about users
that they want to keep private,
and you may want to ensure that
your own servers can’t associate
that information with client IP addresses.
Now, your app can use relays
that you select
to provide strong privacy protections
for all of your users.
A relay is a special type of proxy that is
optimized for performance,
uses the latest transport and
security protocols,
and is natively built into
the modern network stack
available on Apple platforms.
There are two standard protocols
defined by the IETF
that these relays use:
MASQUE and Oblivious HTTP.
MASQUE relays are a great way
to enhance the privacy of your app
or access private resources.
You can send any TCP or UDP connection
through a relay
without needing to modify
the back-end server.
You can chain relay servers together
so that no single entity can combine
an IP address and browsing activity
into a detailed profile of a user.
This is the cornerstone technology
behind iCloud Private Relay.
Relays are also a great way to access
enterprise resources.
A relay provides a better user experience,
is more performant,
and is easier to manage than a VPN.
MASQUE relays use TLS 1.3
to secure all traffic to the proxy,
unlike legacy proxy protocols.
MASQUE uses QUIC,
the latest transport protocol,
and HTTP/3 to efficiently proxy
and multiplex
many connections over a single tunnel.
And for cases where QUIC is blocked
by a network,
they can fall back to using HTTP/2.
If your app sends HTTP requests that
you want to make sure are private
and not linked to any other requests,
such as anonymous metrics reports,
database lookups, or DNS queries,
you can also use Oblivious HTTP.
With Oblivious HTTP, you can get
great performance and privacy
with only a single relay hop.
Unlike MASQUE relays,
Oblivious HTTP doesn't work with
arbitrary servers;
your server needs to
explicitly support it.
To learn more about Oblivious HTTP,
watch the session "What’s new in Privacy."
You can use both of these relay types to
proxy connections made by your app.
This allows you to use specific
relay servers that you choose
in order to increase your app’s privacy.
The new ProxyConfiguration class
allows you to define your relays
in Network framework,
URLSession, and WebKit.
All three APIs use this common class
in a similar manner
and let you define relays for your entire
app or just specific connections.
Within the ProxyConfiguration object,
you can define proxies based on
five different protocols.
This is where you can specify
the new relay types
for both MASQUE and Oblivious HTTP.
The same object can also be used to
configure legacy proxy types.
If you were configuring proxies on
URLSession
or WebKit with dictionaries before,
now is a great time to switch to using
this new object.
For legacy proxy types,
you can configure HTTP CONNECT,
with newly added support for
TLS to the proxy, as well as SOCKSv5.
Here is how you define
a ProxyConfiguration
that will be used to connect to
a MASQUE relay over HTTP/3.
First, use an NWEndpoint to specify
the server name or URL,
and use it to define a relay hop.
For these relay hops,
you can specify support for
HTTP/3, HTTP/2, or both.
The HTTP/2 server will be used as a backup
in case access to HTTP/3
using the QUIC protocol
is blocked by a network.
Then, create a proxy configuration
by passing your relay
to a "relayHops" array parameter.
If you want to define
a multi-hop relay configuration,
you can pass two relays here.
To use your ProxyConfiguration
with an NWConnection from
Network framework,
create a PrivacyContext or use
the default context
and add the proxy configuration to
that context.
Set the context on your NWParameters,
and then pass these parameters
when you create and start the connection.
Now this connection is sending
all of its traffic through the proxy.
You can also use this same proxy
configuration we already defined
directly in URLSession.
To do this, add your configuration
to the proxyConfigurations array
on your URLSessionConfiguration.
Then, run tasks in your URLSession
as you would normally,
and they will now also use the proxy.
The same proxy configuration object can
also be used
to proxy connections
made in a WebKit view!
First, initialize a web view configuration,
add a data store,
and add your proxy configuration
to the data store.
Then initialize a web view
with your configuration.
Once that’s done, you can load
the requested URL
and use the WebKit view
as you normally would.
Now, this Webkit view is also sending
its traffic through the relay.
Besides adding relays to your own apps,
in iOS 17, you can configure them
for the whole device.
In addition to letting you build
privacy features,
this is a great way to use relays to
provide access
to private enterprise network resources.
You may be using a VPN to provide access
to your enterprise resources.
Relays are an alternative to VPNs that can
provide a better user experience
and are easier to manage.
A network relay does not require
complex session negotiation
and often requires fewer round trips
before actual user data is transferred.
This ensures that a user’s first load of
a private resource is
the most responsive interaction possible.
A relay also avoids the usage of tunnels,
virtual interfaces,
and additional IP addresses
that are associated with VPNs.
Since you can configure multiple relays
simultaneously,
it is easier to access different private
domains located in different networks.
Enterprise companies that
want to use relay servers
as an alternative to VPNs
now have options to use them
with their own infrastructure.
Cisco is providing
an enterprise relay service
as part of the Cisco Secure Edge offering.
We are excited to see enterprises
adopt this option
for providing remote access
for their users.
There are two ways to install
a MASQUE relay configuration on a device.
Enterprise organizations can push
a configuration
via Mobile Device Management, or MDM,
to define relays using
a new relay payload type.
These payloads can apply to managed apps,
domains, or the entire device.
Second, you can write an app that uses the
NERelayManager API to define your relay.
These configurations can apply to
specific domains or the entire device.
Both of these are available in macOS, iOS,
iPadOS, and tvOS.
And now that Network Extension support is
added to tvOS,
VPNs are also newly supported in tvOS 17.
Here's how you configure a relay
using a configuration profile.
Just like in the ProxyConfiguration API
for your apps,
you define the relay URL.
Just like in VPN profiles,
you can use a client certificate for
authentication to your enterprise servers
by referring to a certificate payload
in the same profile.
You can have the relay apply to
specific domains
by adding them in the MatchDomains
portion of the payload.
Next, we will see how an app can use
the NERelayManager API
to add relays to a device
programmatically.
To define a relay, you will need to
initialize a NERelay object
and then configure
the URLs of your relays.
Here, I am using the same relay
for both HTTP/2 and HTTP/3.
If your relay requires
additional HTTP headers,
add them to the NERelay object.
You will also need to access to
the shared NERelayManager object,
as this is where you will store
the NERelay object you just created.
If you want your relay to apply to
only specific domains
instead of the whole device,
add those domains to
the matchDomains array.
The final step is to make sure
your relay is enabled,
and install your NERelayManager object
into the system preferences.
Let’s look at relays in action.
I really love mountain biking
and I even opened my very own bike shop.
My shop has an online store
and an internal website
where I can track all of my orders.
That website is on my internal network
and only available to employees.
If I open Safari and attempt to look at
my open orders,
I can’t see them because
I’m not on my internal network.
Once I install a relay configuration,
I’ll be able to access my internal network
from anywhere.
If I open my sample relay app with
the code we just walked through,
I can configure the entire device
to use my shop’s relay
while accessing my internal domain.
This configuration will now
also be visible in Settings,
and we can see that it will be using the
relay when I access internal.example.com.
Now, when I return back to Safari and
again attempt to look at my open orders,
now I can see them and just how many
orders I need to get shipped out.
It’s that simple, fast, and responsive
on the first load.
Relays are modern, standards-based proxies
that can improve the security and privacy
of your app
without compromising performance.
Directly adopt MASQUE relays
and Oblivious HTTP relays in your app
to enhance privacy for your users.
And for enterprises,
start replacing the use of VPNs
with relays that are easier to manage and
provide a more seamless user experience.
Thank you taking the time to watch today.
I can’t wait to see how you use relays.