♪ ♪
Evan: Hi, my name is Evan.
Today, we are going beyond
the basics of structured concurrency,
exploring how structured tasks
can simplify realizing useful behaviors.
Before we get started, if you're new
or want to review structured concurrency,
priority propagation,
and useful task-local value behaviors.
Then we will cover some patterns
with task groups
to help manage resource usage.
Finally, we'll look at how all
of these come together
to facilitate profiling and tracing tasks
in a server environment.
Structured concurrency enables
you to reason about concurrent code
using well-defined points where execution
branches off and runs concurrently,
and where results
from that execution rejoin,
similar to how "if"-blocks and "for"-loops
define how control-flow behaves
in synchronous code.
Concurrent execution is triggered
when you use an "async let",
a task group,
or create a task or detached task.
Results rejoin the current execution
at a suspension point,
indicated by an "await".
Not all tasks are structured.
Structured tasks are created
using "async let" and task groups,
while unstructured tasks are created
using Task and Task.detached.
Structured tasks live to the end
of the scope where they are declared,
like local variables,
and are automatically cancelled
when they go out of scope,
making it clear
how long the task will live.
Whenever possible,
prefer structured Tasks.
The benefits of structured concurrency
discussed later
do not always apply to unstructured tasks.
Before we dive into the code,
let's come up with a concrete example.
Suppose we have a kitchen
with multiple chefs preparing soup.
Soup preparation consists
of multiple steps.
The chefs have to cut ingredients,
marinate chicken,
bring the broth to a boil, and finally,
cook the soup before it is ready to serve.
Some tasks can be performed in parallel,
While this expresses which tasks
can run concurrently and which cannot,
this is not the recommended way
to use concurrency in Swift.
Here is the same function expressed
using structured concurrency.
Since we have a known number
of child tasks to create,
we can use
the convenient "async let" syntax.
These tasks form a structured relationship
with their parent task.
We will talk about
why this is important shortly.
makeSoup calls a number
of asynchronous functions.
One of them is "chopIngredients",
which takes a list of ingredients
and uses a task group
to chop all of them concurrently.
Now that we are familiar with makeSoup,
let's take a look at the task hierarchy.
Child tasks are indicated
by the colored boxes,
while the arrows point
from parent task to child task.
makeSoup has three child tasks
for chopping ingredients,
marinating chicken, and boiling broth.
chopIngredients uses a task group to
create a child task for each ingredient.
If we have three ingredients,
it too will create three children.
This parent-child hierarchy forms a tree,
the task tree.
Now that we've introduced the task tree,
let's start identifying
how that benefits our code.
Task cancellation is used to signal
that the app no longer needs the result
of a task and the task should stop
and either return a partial result
or throw an error.
In our soup example, we may want to stop
making a soup order if that customer left,
decided they wanted to order
something else, or it's closing time.
Unstructured tasks are cancelled
explicitly with the "cancel" function.
Cancelling the parent task results
in the cancellation of all child tasks.
Cancellation is cooperative,
so child tasks aren't immediately stopped.
It simply sets
the "isCancelled" flag on that task.
Actually acting on the cancellation
is done in your code.
Cancellation is a race.
If the task is cancelled before our check,
"makeSoup" throws
a "SoupCancellationError".
If the task is cancelled
after the guard executes,
the program will carry on
preparing the soup.
If we are going to throw
a cancellation error
instead of returning a partial result,
we can call "Task.checkCancellation",
which throws a "CancellationError"
if the task was cancelled.
It's important to check
the task cancellation status
before starting any expensive work
to verify that the result
is still necessary.
Cancellation checking is synchronous,
so any function,
asynchronous or synchronous,
that should react to cancellation
should check the task cancellation status
before continuing.
Polling for cancellation
with "isCancelled"
or "checkCancellation" is useful
when the task is running,
but there are times when
you may need to respond to cancellation
while the task is suspended
and no code is running,
like when implementing an AsyncSequence.
This is where
"withTaskCancellationHandler" is useful.
Let's introduce a shift function.
The cook should make soups
as orders come in
until the end of their shift,
signaled by a task cancellation.
In one cancellation scenario,
the asynchronous for-loop
gets a new order before it is cancelled.
The "makeSoup" function
handles the cancellation
Instead, we have to use
the cancellation handler
to detect the cancellation event and
break out of the asynchronous for-loop.
The orders are produced
from an AsyncSequence.
AsyncSequences
are driven by an AsyncIterator,
which defines
an asynchronous "next" function.
Like with synchronous iterators,
the "next" function
returns the next element in the sequence,
or nil to indicate
that we are at the end of the sequence.
Many AsyncSequences are
implemented with a state machine,
which we use to stop the running sequence.
In our example here,
when "isRunning" is true,
the sequence
should continue emitting orders.
Once the task is cancelled,
we need to indicate that the sequence
is done and should shut down.
We do this by synchronously
calling the "cancel" function
on our sequence state machine.
Note that because the cancellation handler
runs immediately,
the state machine is shared mutable state
between the cancellation handler
and main body,
which can run concurrently.
We'll need to protect our state machine.
While actors are great
for protecting encapsulated state,
we want to modify and read individual
properties on our state machine,
so actors aren't
quite the right tool for this.
Furthermore, we can't guarantee the order
that operations run on an actor,
so we can't ensure that our cancellation
will run first.
We'll need something else.
I've decided to use atomics
from the Swift Atomics package,
but we could use a dispatch queue
or locks.
These mechanisms allow us
to synchronize the shared state,
Instead of having to worry about
a cancellation token and synchronization,
we let the Swift runtime
handle it for us safely.
Remember, cancellation does not
stop a task from running,
it only signals to the task
that it has been cancelled
and should stop running
as soon a possible.
It is up to your code
to check for cancellation.
Next, let's consider
how the structured task tree
helps propagate priority
and avoid priority inversions.
First, what is priority,
and why do we care?
Priority is your way to communicate
to the system how urgent a given task is.
Certain tasks,
like responding to a button press,
need to run immediately
or the app will appear frozen.
Meanwhile, other tasks,
like prefetching content from a server,
can run in the background
without anyone noticing.
Second, what is a priority inversion?
A priority inversion happens
when a high-priority task is waiting
on the result of a lower-priority task.
By default, child tasks inherit
their priority from their parent,
so assuming that makeSoup is running
in a task at medium priority,
all child tasks
will also run at medium priority.
Let's say a VIP guest who comes
to our restaurant looking for soup.
We give their soup a higher priority
to ensure we get a good review.
When they await their soup, the priority
of all child tasks is escalated,
ensuring that no high-priority task
is waiting on a lower-priority task,
avoiding the priority inversion.
Awaiting a result from a task
with a higher priority
escalates the priority
of all child tasks in the task tree.
The span name is presented
in the tracing UI.
You'll want to keep them
short and descriptive
so that you can easily find information
about a specific span without clutter.