♪ ♪
Harry: Hi, I'm Harry,
an engineer on the SwiftUI team.
Welcome to Beyond Scroll Views
where I'll talk about
some new improvements to scroll views
in SwiftUI.
The things our devices want to do
can rarely be contained
within their fixed screen sizes.
One way they handle this complexity
is by introducing scrolling.
This allows them to show us everything
that won't fit on screen.
SwiftUI offers a few different components
that let you integrate scrolling
into your own apps.
Today, I'll be talking about
one of those components.
ScrollView.
A ScrollView is a building block
that lets your content scroll.
Scroll views have axes
that defines the directions
in which they're scrollable.
Scroll views have content.
When that content exceeds
the size of the ScrollView,
some of that content will be clipped,
and people will need to scroll
to reveal it.
Scroll views ensure that the content
is placed within the safe area
by resolving the safe area
into margins outsetting its content.
A ScrollView evaluates its content
eagerly by default.
You can change this behavior
by using a lazy stack.
The exact position of where
the ScrollView is scrolled
within the content
is called the content offset.
SwiftUI has offered
the ScrollViewReader API
as a way to control the content offset.
This year,
SwiftUI is introducing more ways
to both influence and react to the content
offset managed by a ScrollView.
In this talk, I'll start by discussing
ways to influence a ScrollView's margins
and how they relate to safe areas.
I'll then talk about managing
a ScrollView's content offset
through scroll targets
and scroll positions.
Finally, I'll show off how you can add
some real flair to your apps
with scroll transitions.
Ever since I started making my Colors app,
my users have really liked showing me
some of their favorite color combinations.
I'd like to feature
some of these combinations
so that other people can enjoy them.
To do this, I've been working on adding
a gallery feature to my Colors app.
I've already made some progress
implementing my gallery.
Throughout this talk
I'll be polishing both the header
and content
of the featured section of my gallery.
In my gallery, I have a horizontal
ScrollView wrapping a lazy stack.
I'll first make this view look a bit nicer
with some margins.
Your first instinct might be
to add some padding to a ScrollView,
and this will inset a ScrollView,
but notice that now its content is clipped
when scrolling.
Instead of insetting
the ScrollView itself,
I'd like to extend the content margins
of the ScrollView.
I can do that
with the new safe area padding modifier.
This behaves like
the normal padding modifier,
but instead of padding the content,
it adds the padding to the safe area.
Now my ScrollView expands the whole width,
which lets the next item peek out.
Before I go further,
I'd talk a little about safe areas
in relation to ScrollView’s.
Safe areas most commonly come
from the device your app is running on.
The can also come from APIs
like the safe area padding
or safe area inset modifier.
A ScrollView resolves the safe area into
the margins it applies to its content.
This includes content
you are responsible for,
but also additional content that the
ScrollView is responsible for
like scroll indicators.
This means it's not possible
to configure different insets
for different kinds of content
by modifying the safe area.
If you want to apply different insets,
you can use the new contentMargins API.
This API allows you to inset the content
of the ScrollView separately
from the scroll indicators.
Or inset the indicators
separately from the content.
Going back to my gallery,
I'll update my safe area padding modifier
to use the content margin API.
Now that my views
have a bit of margins applied,
one of the things I'd like to do
is control what content offset
the ScrollView will scroll to
once someone lifts their finger.
By default, a ScrollView uses a standard
deceleration rate
along with the velocity of the scroll
to calculate the target content offset
the scroll should end at.
It does not take into account
things like the size of the ScrollView
or its content.
But sometimes those things matter.
New in SwiftUI, you can change
how a ScrollView calculates
this target content offset
with the scrollTargetBehavior modifier.
This modifier takes a type conforming
to the scrollTargetBehavior protocol.
Here I've specified the paging behavior.
Now my ScrollView swipes
one page at a time.
The paging behavior is special.
It has a custom deceleration rate
and chooses where to scroll
based on the containing size
of the ScrollView itself.
This works well for iOS,
but becomes a little bit much
on the larger screens of iPadOS.
Instead of aligning to the containing size
of the ScrollView,
I'd like to align to individual views.
The view aligned behavior aligns
the ScrollView to views,
so the ScrollView needs to know which
views it should consider for alignment.
These views are called scroll targets,
and there's a new family of modifiers
that let me specify
which views are scroll targets.
Here I'll use the scroll target
layout modifier
to have each hero view in the lazy stack
be considered a scroll target.
You can also mark individual views
as targets
using the scroll target modifier.
But when using lazy stacks,
it's important to use
the scroll target layout modifier.
Views outside the visible region
have not yet been created.
The layout knows about which views
it will create, though,
so it can make sure
the ScrollView scrolls to the right place.
Now my ScrollView is looking
a lot better on iPad.
The paging and view aligned behaviors
are built off of the new
ScrollTargetBehavior protocol.
While SwiftUI provides these
common behaviors for you,
it also allows you to conform
your own types to this protocol
and implement your own custom behavior,
much like you would adopt the previously
introduced layout protocol.
Conform your own types
to the ScrollTargetBehavior
by implementing the one
required method: updateTarget.
SwiftUI calls this method when
calculating where a scroll should end,
but also in other contexts
like when the ScrollView changes size.
Customizing the behavior is easy.
Here if the target is close to the top
of the ScrollView,
and the scroll was flicked up,
I'll prefer to scroll to the exact top
of the ScrollView
by modifying the provided target.
This will result in the ScrollView
choosing a different content offset
to be the end point of the scroll.
And that's all it takes to insert
my own custom code
for influencing
where a ScrollView chooses to scroll.
Let's go back to my gallery view.
I'd like to talk about layout.
Notice that my hero view is sized
in relation to the overall width
of the device.
And if we look at iPad,
two views fit
evenly within the device's width.
Previously you would've had to use
a GeometryReader to accomplish this,
but this year SwiftUI makes this
much easier
with a new API called
the containerRelativeFrame modifier.
I'll show you
how my hero view uses this API.
I'll start with a stack of color views,
along with a frame modifier
specifying a fixed height.
I'll add the containerRelativeFrame
modifier to my view.
Here I specify the horizontal axis,
which lets the view just take on
the width of its container.
In my case the container will be
the surrounding ScrollView,
but it might also be the nearest column
of a navigation split view,
or the window of your app.
When the width of my container changes,
the size of my views automatically update.
I can create a grid-like layout
of these views by providing a count
and spacing.
I can conditionalize the count
based on the horizontal sizeClass
to have two columns on iPad
and one column on phone.
What's even better is that I can
remove the OS conditionals
as the horizontal sizeClass
environment property
is now available on all platforms.
Finally,
I'll use the aspectRatio modifier
to have a height relative to the width,
instead of hardcoding a fixed height.
So I've gotten the layout
and scroll behavior of my gallery done.
There's some more changes
I'd like to make.
One thing you'll notice
are the scroll indicators.
I'd like to remove those.
I can use the existing
scrollIndicators API to accomplish this.
This looks great
when swiping my finger on an iPad,
but I often use my gallery on a Mac.
And on a Mac, I might not be able to
easily perform a horizontal swipe gesture
like when using a mouse
or other input devices.
And when I connect a mouse,
the indicators are visible,
even though I've requested they be hidden.
Using a mouse can make scrolling difficult
or impossible without scroll indicators.
For this reason, the default behavior
of the scrollIndicators modifier
is to hide the indicators
when using more flexible input devices,
like trackpads,
but to allow the indicators to show
when a mouse is connected.
You can provide a value of never
to the scrollIndicators modifier
to always hide the indicators
regardless of input device.
But my app still needs to support people
who use a mouse.
So I'll need to provide an alternative
means to scroll my gallery for them.
Instead of scroll indicators,
I'll render some views
that allow users to scroll
to the previous or next views
with a click.
To start building that,
let's clean my ScrollView up a bit.
I'll move my ScrollView into a VStack
with my header view.
Now I'll focus on the header view.
I'll add some custom paddle views
into the header view.
In past versions of SwiftUI,
I would have reached
for a ScrollViewReader
to pass to my paddles
and scroll to the appropriate view.
New in SwiftUI, though,
is the scrollPosition modifier.
This modifier associates a binding
to a state wrapping an identifier.
I'll pass that
to my scrollPosition modifier
which the ScrollView will read from
and to my header view.
In the paddles of my header view,
I can write to the binding
like any other piece of state.
When the binding is written to,
the ScrollView will scroll
to the view with that ID.
Just like the view aligned
ScrollTargetBehavior,
the scroll position modifier
uses the scroll target layout modifier
to know which views to consider
for querying their identity values.
The scroll position modifier
also allows me to know the identity
of the view currently scrolled.
So I can add to my header view
some text that shows the value
of the hero image currently scrolled.
When the most leading view
in my ScrollView changes,
the binding automatically updates.
Now my mouse users
can scroll through my gallery.
There's one last bit of polish
I'd like to add to this view.
Just like its useful to know
which view is currently scrolled,
sometimes I want to visually alter a view
based on where it is
within the ScrollView.
There's new API called ScrollTransitions
in SwiftUI that make this really easy.
A ScrollTransition is a lot like
a normal transition.
A transition describes the changes
a view should undergo
when its appearing or disappearing.
When a view has appeared,
it's in its identity phase
where no customizations should be applied.
A ScrollTransition describes
a similar set of changes as a transition
but instead applies those as a view enters
the visible region of a ScrollView
and then leaves the visible region.
By default, when the view is
in the center of the visible region,
it's in the identity phase
of the ScrollTransition.
Let's look at this
in the context of my hero view.
I'll clean this up a bit
to focus on ScrollTransitions.
As a view gets near the edges
of the ScrollView,
I'd like it to scale down a bit in size.
I'll start by adding
the scrollTransition modifier.
This API takes content and a phase
and allows you to specify visual changes
to the content based on the phase.
Here I'll specify a decrease in scale
when the view
is not in its identity phase.
That looks great!
ScrollTransitions work with
a new protocol called VisualEffect.
This protocol provides a set of
customizations for view content
that are safe to use as functions
of layout
like the content offset of a ScrollView.
Many of them might look familiar to you.
You already know about the scaleEffect.
You can also customize the rotation,
or the offset
much like you would with view modifiers.
However, not all view modifiers can be
safely used inside of a scrollTransition.
For example, customizing the font
is not supported and will not build.
Anything that will change the overall
content size of the ScrollView
cannot be used
within a scrollTransition modifier.
Wow, we've covered a lot
so let's do a quick review.
We talked about the differences
between safe areas and contentMargins
and their relationship to ScrollViews.
I showed you how you can use the paging
and view aligned scrollTargetBehaviors
to influence how a ScrollView behaves
and how you can write
your own conformances
to the scrollTargetBehavior protocol.
You learned about how much easier it is
to create layouts
relative to their container using
the containerRelativeFrame modifier.
I hooked into the state of a ScrollView
using the scrollPosition modifier,
allowing me to both
programmatically scroll
and be informed
of which view is currently scrolled.
And finally, I created visual effects
based on the content offset
of my ScrollView
with the scrollTransition API.
I hope you've enjoyed learning
about these improvements to ScrollViews.
Thanks, and have a great WWDC.
♪ ♪