♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Christopher Figueroa:
Hello, I'm Christopher Figueroa
from the ARKit team at Apple.
Peter Kuhn:
And I'm Peter Kuhn from Unity.
Christopher: Unity has brought
their engine and XR ecosystem
to this new platform,
making it simple for a Unity
developer like yourself
to easily bring
your project over.
Peter and I will show you
how to build
a fully immersive experience,
like Rec Room here,
using Unity workflows
you're already familiar with.
You'll start by creating
an Immersive Space
with a Full Immersive style.
This allows your app
to hide passthrough
and transport someone
to another world.
In a fully immersive experience,
Unity utilizes
Compositor Services,
and gives your app the power
of Metal rendering capabilities.
Unity also takes
advantage of ARKit
to recognize your body position
and the surroundings,
including skeletal
hand tracking.
Unity builds upon
these technologies
to provide the same services
in the Unity Engine.
There are two main approaches
for creating immersive
experiences
on this platform with Unity.
You can bring a fully
immersive Unity experience
to this platform,
replacing the player's
surroundings with
your own environments.
Or you can mix your content
with passthrough
to create immersive experiences
that blend in
with their surroundings.
If you're interested
in the second approach,
I recommend you check out
"Create immersive Unity apps."
Now, Peter will go over how
these new Apple technologies
help Unity developers bring
fully immersive VR games
to this platform.
Peter: Thanks, Christopher.
First, I wanted to start off
by showing you Rec Room
from Against Gravity.
It's a popular VR social
platform that allows users
to create and play games
and experiences with others
from around the world.
It's built on the Unity
game engine,
which provides a powerful
and flexible platform
for game development.
I'll introduce you to some
of those tools and technologies
that will to make it easier
for you to bring your VR content
to this new platform,
just like Rec Room.
I'll tell you about some things
to keep in mind when planning
to bring your Unity content
to this new platform.
First I'll cover the workflow
you'll use to deploy content
from Unity to the device.
There are a few things
you'll need to keep in mind
related to graphics
on this platform.
And finally, I'll talk about how
to adapt controller inputs
to hand input,
and some of the tools
that Unity provides to help
with this transition.
To start, there's a build
and run workflow
that you should already
be familiar with.
We've built full support
for this platform into Unity,
so you can see your projects
running on this device
in just a few steps.
The first is to select the build
target for this platform.
Then, like you would
for any other VR platform,
enable the XR Plug-in.
If your app relies
on native plug-ins,
they'll need to be recompiled
for this platform.
On the other hand,
if you are using
raw source code or .mm files,
you're already good to go.
Building from Unity will now
generate an Xcode project,
just like it does for an iOS,
Mac, or Apple TV target.
Then, from within Xcode,
you can build and run
to either the device
or the device simulator
for faster iteration.
The graphics pipeline
you'll use to transform
someone's surroundings into
a fully immersive experience
is likely to be familiar
to you as well.
But there are a few new concepts
that are important
to understand.
One choice every project
makes right in the beginning
is which rendering pipeline
to use.
The Universal Render Pipeline
is an ideal choice.
It enables a special feature
unique to this platform
called Foveated Rendering.
Foveated Rendering
is a technique
that concentrates more pixel
density in the center
of each lens where the eyes
are likely to be focused,
and less detail on
the peripherals of the screen
where the eyes are
less sensitive to detail.
This results in a much
higher-quality experience
for the person
using the device.
When you use
the Universal Render Pipeline,
Static Foveated Rendering
is applied
throughout the entire pipeline.
And it works with
all URP features,
including post-processing,
camera stacking, HDR, and more.
If you have custom render passes
that would benefit
from Foveated Rendering,
there are new APIs in Unity 2022
that can take advantage
of this technology.
Since rendering now happens
in a nonlinear space,
there are also shader macros
to handle that remapping.
Taking advantage
of Static Foveated Rendering
means you'll spend resources
on the pixels that matter
and produce a higher-quality
visual experience.
Another way to optimize
your graphics on this platform
is by using Single-Pass
Instanced Rendering.
In Unity, Single-Pass
Instanced Rendering
now supports
the Metal graphics API,
and it will be enabled
by default.
With Single-Pass
Instanced Rendering,
the engine submits only
one draw call for both eyes,
and reduces the overhead
of certain parts
of the rendering pipeline
like culling and shadows.
This reduces the CPU overhead of
rendering your scenes in stereo.
The good news is, if your app
already renders correctly
on other VR platforms using
Single-Pass Instanced Rendering,
shader macros ensure
it should work here as well.
There's one last thing
to consider.
Make sure your app
is writing to the depth buffer
for every pixel correctly.
The system compositor uses the
depth buffer for reprojection.
Wherever the depth information
is missing,
the system will render
an error color as an indication.
One example is the skybox which
normally is infinitely far away
from the user, so it writes
a depth of zero with reverse Z.
This requires modification
to appear on the device.
We've fixed all
of Unity's shaders
to write correct values
to the depth buffer,
but if you have any custom
effects such as a custom skybox,
or perhaps a water effect
or transparency effects,
ensure that some value is
written to depth for each pixel.
Now that you've rendered
your graphics to the device,
it's time to make them
interactive.
Interaction on this device
is unique.
People will use their hands
and their eyes
to interact with content.
There are a few ways
you will be able
to add interaction to your Unity
apps on this platform.
The XR Interaction Toolkit
adds hand tracking
to make it easier for you
to adapt existing projects.
You can also react
to the built-in system gestures
with the Unity Input System.
And you can access
the raw hand joint data
for custom interactions
with the Unity Hands Package.
The XR Interaction Toolkit,
also known as XRI,
provides a high-level
interaction system.
The toolkit is designed
to make it easy
to translate input
into interactions.
It works with both 3D
and UI objects.
XRI abstracts away
the type of input,
like hand tracking,
and translates that input
into actions that your app
can respond to.
This means your input code
can work across platforms
that accept different types
of input.
XRI makes it easy to respond
to common interactions
like hover, grab, and select,
both in 3D space
and in the UI
for 3D spatial worlds.
The toolkit also includes
a locomotion system
so people can travel
through a fully immersive space
more comfortably.
As people interact
with your world,
visual feedback is important
for immersion.
XRI enables you to define
the visual reactions
for each input constraint.
The core of XRI is a set
of base Interactable
and Interactor components.
Interactables are objects
in your scene
that can receive input.
You define Interactors,
which specify how people
can interact with
your Interactables.
The Interaction Manager ties
these components together.
The first step is to decide
which objects in the scene
can be interacted with,
and how to react
when those interactions occur.
We do this by adding
an Interactable component
to the object.
There are three built-in types.
Simple marks the object
as receiving interactions.
You can subscribe to events
like SelectEntered
or SelectExited
with this component.
With Grab, when the object
is selected or grabbed,
it will follow
the Interactor around
and inherit its velocity
when released.
Teleport interactables like
TeleportArea and TeleportAnchor
enable you to define areas
or points for the player
to teleport to.
And you can create
your own custom Interactables.
Interactors are responsible
for selecting
or interacting with the objects
you've tagged as Interactable.
They define a list
of Interactables
that they could potentially
hover over or select each frame.
There are several types
of Interactors.
Direct Interactors
select Interactables
that are touching it.
You would use one
of these when you want to know
when a person's hands touch
an interactable object,
or when they are close
to interactable objects.
Ray Interactors are used
for interacting from far away.
This Interactor
is highly configurable
with curved and straight lines,
and customizable visualizations
to help you adapt it to the
visual style of your project.
Once the user starts
the interaction,
you have options on how
that interaction works.
For example,
if it's a grab interaction,
you may want to move
the object to the user's hand.
And the Ray Interactor
makes it possible
to limit the degrees of freedom
for the grab
in order to match
your gameplay needs.
A common interaction
in a fully immersive experience
is grabbing an object
and placing it
somewhere contextual
to that object.
For example, placing
a battery in a socket.
The Socket Interactor
shows the player
that a certain area
can accept an object.
These Interactors are not
attached to the hands.
Instead they live
somewhere in the world.
With hand tracking
or even controllers,
a common type of interaction
that users naturally want
to perform is
the poke interaction.
This is similar
to a direct Interactor,
except that it includes
direction filtering
so that correct motion
must be performed
in order to trigger
an interaction.
If you want people
to interact by looking,
the Gaze Interactor
provides some extensions
to the Ray Interactor to make
gaze a bit easier to deal with.
For example, Gaze Interactors
can automatically
make the colliders larger
for Interactables
so that they're easier
to select.
To bring it all together,
the Interaction Manager serves
as a middleman between the
Interactors and Interactables,
facilitating the exchange
of interactions.
Its primary role
is to initiate changes
in the interaction state
within a designated group
of registered Interactors
and Interactables.
Usually, a single Interaction
Manager is established
to enable the possibility
of all Interactors
affecting all Interactables.
Alternatively,
multiple complementary
Interaction Managers
can be utilized,
each with their own
unique assortment
of Interactors
and Interactables.
These managers can be
activated or deactivated
to enable or disable
specific sets of interactions.
For example,
you may have a different set
of Interactables per scene,
or in your menus.
Finally, the XR Controller
component helps you make sense
of the input data
you'll receive.
It takes input actions from
the hands or a tracked device
and passes it to the Interactors
so that they can decide
to select or activate something
based on that input.
You will need to bind
Input Action References
for each of the XR Interaction
States, such as Select.
You're not limited to just one
XR Controller component
per hand or controller,
which gives us the flexibility
to support both hands
and controllers independently.
Sample code
that is bundled with XRI
shows you how you can do this.
In addition to
the advanced features of XRI,
you've also got the option
of simply using
the system gesture inputs
directly from
the Unity Input System.
You can then map the platform's
built-in interactions,
like tap gestures,
to your own interaction system.
You can use the binding paths
from the Unity Input System
to access and respond
to these system gestures.
The pinch gesture, for example,
comes through as a value
when active,
with position and rotation.
These can be bound
to input actions.
Where the person is directing
their focus comes through
in the same frame
as a pinch gesture,
with position and rotation.
For even more flexibility,
you can use
the Unity Hands Subsystem
to access
all of the raw hand joint data
from the system
through the Unity
Hands Package.
The Unity Hands Package
provides access
to low-level hand joint data
that are consistent
across platforms.
For example, you can write
code to look at each joint
and determine how close the pose
is to a certain gesture,
like a thumbs up
or a pointing index finger,
and translate those
into gameplay actions.
This is powerful but can
be challenging to get right
since everyone's hands
are different sizes
and people have a variety
of range of motions.
This code defines a method
which tells you
if the index finger is extended.
You can call this method from
the OnHandUpdate event
and pass in one of the hands.
First, get a few specific joints
to check
if the index finger is extended.
If any of them are invalid,
it will return false.
If all joints are valid,
do a simple check
to make sure that
the index finger isn't curled.
You can extend this logic
to other fingers
to start to implement some
basic gesture detections.
Another use for
the raw hand joint data
is mapping it to a custom
hand mesh visual.
This can help make
the hands fit more
into the art style of your game.
For example, Rec Room used
the raw hand joint data
to show a stylized hand model
that fits their visual style.
They also show other player
hand models for more immersion.
The Unity Hand package has some
sample code to get you started
if you want to explore more
about raw hand joint access.
I'm excited to see
your VR experiences
come to this new platform.
To get more information
about Unity's support
for this platform and to sign up
for early beta access,
please visit unity.com/spatial.
Christopher: Those are the tools
you can use
to bring a fully immersive VR
experience to this new platform
using Unity workflows
you're already familiar with.
Peter: To recap,
this session introduced you
to some of the tools
and technologies
that will make it easier for you
to bring your VR content
to this new platform,
just like Rec Room.
If you're starting
a new project,
use Unity 2022 or later.
If you have
an existing project,
start upgrading to 2022.
Consider adopting
the Universal Render Pipeline.
While the built-in graphics
pipeline is supported,
all future improvements will be
on the Universal Pipeline.
Start adapting any
controller-based interactions
to hands.
You can start today
with the XR Interaction Toolkit
and the Unity Hands package.
Christopher: And finally,
to learn more about
how you can use Unity
to create immersive experiences
with passthrough,
I recommend
"Create immersive Unity apps."
And check out "Build great games
for spatial computing"
to get an overview
of what's possible
for game developers
on this platform.
Peter: We're excited to see
what you bring to the platform.
Christopher:
Thanks for watching.
♪