♪ ♪
Bhavya: Hi, my name is Bhavya,
and I'm an engineer
on the Accessibility team.
In today's session, we're going to focus
on how to perform accessibility audits
in your app.
First, we'll cover how easy it is
to perform automated accessibility audits
in your UI tests.
And then we'll discuss
how to expose elements
in a way that gives us
a great testing experience
and a great accessibility experience
at the same time.
Let's start with accessibility audits.
Testing is a fundamental component
in the app development process.
By writing tests, we're able to catch
and fix bugs before we ship code.
It's how we ensure
the quality of the product.
And an accessible product
is a high-quality product.
Approximately one in seven people
worldwide have a disability
that affects the way they interact
with the world and their devices.
People use tools like VoiceOver
to interact with your apps
in the way that's best for them.
Delivering a high-quality product means
delivering an application
that's accessible for everyone
so they can have the highest-quality
experience with your app.
I know from personal experience
how accessibility can be
a deep and complex subject.
Let's explore how accessibility audits
can make this a simple task.
Xcode ships with a tool
called the Accessibility Inspector.
This tool provides
an easy way to find, diagnose,
and fix accessibility issues
within your app.
One of the powerful ways
in which I can leverage this tool
is by performing audits on my app.
The Inspector can audit
individual views in your app
for common accessibility issues.
This is my sample app. It has two tabs.
The first tab provides me
with motivational quotes,
and the second lets me write down
my thoughts for self-reflection.
In the quote tab, I have a text view
which displays the quote.
And this text view is placed
on top of a background image.
There's also a New Quote button
which refreshes the quote.
I can launch the Accessibility Inspector
and perform an audit of my app.
The Inspector checks
for all kinds of issues,
like providing
sufficient element descriptions
and ensuring proper contrast.
And the issues it finds are
displayed in a table
with detailed descriptions
about each issue.
Accessibility audits are powerful,
and now they are automatable.
You are now able to perform audits
in your UI tests.
Calling performAccessibilityAudit
on your XCUIApplication
will audit the current view
for accessibility issues
just as the Inspector does.
There's no need for assertions:
if any issues are found,
your test automatically fails.
Let's dive into a quick demo
to see this in action.
I've opened my demo app in Xcode.
It's written in Swift
and utilizes standard UIKit views.
I've already written a few passing tests
which verify that the elements
on the screen exist.
For example, testQuoteTabView verifies
that the image view and the text view
exist in the quote tab.
One thing to note is that these tests
also help us test accessibility.
In order for XCTest to find these views,
they must be accessibility elements.
That means if your UI tests
can find the elements,
so can our assistive technologies.
It's great that I get a little bit
of accessibility testing this way,
but I want to add some audits to my tests
to make sure I'm catching
all kinds of issues.
I'll create another test called
testAccessibilityQuoteTabView.
I'll do some setup to launch my app
and navigate to the Quote tab.
And finally, I'll call
performAccessibilityAudit
on the application.
The audit can report multiple issues,
so to allow my test
to continue reporting issues
after the first failure,
I'll set continueAfterFailure to true.
That's it.
Let's run the test
by clicking on the test diamond.
Seems like my test failed.
The issues are reported in-line
within the Xcode source editor.
My audit caught two issues:
Element has no description,
and the label is not human-readable.
Let's figure out
what the problematic elements are.
I can dig deeper into these two issues
by going to the Report navigator,
clicking on Tests,
and then clicking on the disclosure
triangle next to my test.
This view shows a detailed breakdown
of the test run and the issues.
For the first issue,
"element has no description,"
I can double-click the element screenshot
which shows me that the image view
has no description.
I can do so similarly
for the second issue,
which shows me that the label
on the text view is not human-readable.
Let's take a moment to discuss how
to handle the issues my audit just found.
It's important to explore
each issue individually and fix it,
as they will lead to real interaction
or navigation issues
for users of your app
who rely on assistive technologies.
It's also important to acknowledge
that you may run into issues
which should be filtered out and ignored.
Perhaps the issue is a false positive
or expected behavior.
Accessibility audits makes it easy
to ignore these kinds of issues.
We'll touch on an example
for ignoring issues later in the talk.
To learn more about best practices
in accessibility,
please check out our 2018 talk titled
"Deliver an Exceptional
Accessibility Experience."
Let's investigate the first issue
my audit found:
the accessibility label on the text view
is not human-readable.
If I inspect the text view
in the Storyboard,
I can see that the accessibility label
has been set
to QUOTE_TEXTVIEW.
Users who rely on assistive technologies
like VoiceOver
will first hear the accessibility label,
and then the accessibility value,
like this.
VoiceOver: QUOTE_TEXTVIEW,
"Live one day at a time
and make it a masterpiece."
Bhavya: The label doesn't sound great,
and ideally,
VoiceOver should skip it
and speak just the quote itself.
I can delete the accessibility label,
but then my UI tests will break,
because they depend on this label
to identify the text view.
Ideally, this string should be set
as the accessibility identifier.
The accessibility identifier allows you
to uniquely identify an element
when writing UI tests without affecting
the accessibility or UI experience.
I'll head over to my Storyboard.
I'll select my text view,
cut this string from the label,
and paste it into the identifier.
The other issue my audit found was
that the image view has no description.
Typically, it's important
that images are accessible
with descriptive but succinct labels.
However, in my app, this is
a background image which is decorative.
It isn't a part of the main content
and doesn't add additional meaning
to the quote itself.
Ideally, technologies like VoiceOver
should skip this image view.
I can achieve this behavior
by overriding accessibility elements
on the view controller's view.
By setting it to just the quote text view
and the New Quote button,
VoiceOver will no longer land
on the image view.
Let's head over to Xcode and do that now.
I'll go to my view controller file
and set accessibilityElements.
Awesome.
Let's go back to my audit
and run my test case
to see if I fixed all the issues.
Sweet. My audit is now passing.
You'll notice
one of my UI tests is now failing,
but we'll come back to that later.
When adding accessibility audits,
you may run into issues
which need to be filtered.
As an example,
let's say my audit found an issue
with the contrast being too low
on a specific label.
After investigating,
the contrast turns out to be just fine,
and the issue seems to be
a false positive.
Let's explore how I can ignore this issue.
The performAccessibilityAudit function
takes in additional parameters.
The first parameter allows me
to specify an option set
of the categories of audits
that I want to run.
These are categories
like dynamic type and contrast,
the same categories
that you're already familiar with
in the Accessibility Inspector.
In this example, I'm choosing to audit
for only dynamic type and contrast issues.
The second parameter allows me
to specify a closure.
This closure is called
on all the issues found by the audit
and lets me choose which issues to ignore
and which issues to report.
I'll start by defining a variable
called shouldIgnore to false.
By default, issues should not be ignored.
Let's say I'd like to ignore
a contrast issue
on an element with the label "My Label."
I can get the XCUIElement
associated with the issue
using issue.element.
If this element has the label "My Label"
and the type of issue is a contrast issue,
then I know I've got the right issue,
so I'll set shouldIgnore to true.
Setting it to true indicates
that I'd like the issue to be ignored.
At the end, I'll return shouldIgnore.
If the conditions above aren't met,
then shouldIgnore will be false,
indicating the issue should be reported
as a failure.
And that's it.
You can extend this example
and customize the criteria for ignoring
by using other properties,
like the element type
or the identifier, and so on.
As you begin to write accessibility audits
for your own apps,
it's helpful to keep in mind
the following considerations.
An audit is limited
to the elements on the screen.
That means in order to provide
complete coverage,
you should add accessibility audit tests
for all the different views
your app may show.
In the case of my sample app,
I should add another test
which navigates to the second tab
and runs an audit.
A quick way to immediately add audits
for multiple tests
is to override
and perform the audit in teardown.
You could define variables
in the scope of the class.
This way, tests can override
these variables
to opt in or out of the audit
and to allow the tests to customize
the closure for ignoring issues.
Test plans are an excellent way to group
audit-specific tests in your project.
They allow you to selectively enable
test targets, cases,
or individual methods in the test plan.
And finally, audits shouldn't substitute
real testing with assistive technologies.
Ultimately, testing your app by turning on
technologies like VoiceOver
or Dynamic Type is the best way
to ensure a high-quality experience.
You can achieve
great accessibility and great testing
without having to compromise on either.
Automation elements allow you
to expose elements
specifically for the purpose of automation
without affecting the accessibility
of those elements.
Now, in UIKit,
you'll be able to leverage this API
to expose exactly the elements you need
for automation,
while still being able to customize
the accessibility
for these elements at the same time.
You may remember from earlier
that as I fixed the issues from my audit,
I also broke one of my UI tests.
The image view doesn't seem
to be available anymore.
It's missing in my UI test
because it's also missing
in accessibility.
Because this image view was decorative,
I overrode accessibility elements
to exclude it from accessibility.
However, by doing so, I also caused it
to become excluded from my UI test.
Let's explore how automation elements
can help me expose my image view
to my UI test.
I'll go to the view controller file
in Xcode.
And I'll set automationElements
on the view controller's view
to the image view.
Keep in mind that when overriding
automationElements,
you need to specify all the elements
which need to be exposed to automation.
That means I also need to add
the text view and the button to my list.
When overriding automation elements,
you are overriding the existing elements
that are already exposed to automation.
Let's try running our test case
to see if it's passing again.
[no audio]
Awesome.
We were able to write
some great UI and accessibility tests
and fix some accessibility issues too.
Accessibility audits are a fantastic way
to add easy, automated
accessibility testing for your app.
Fixing the issues identified by the audits
helps ensure everyone can enjoy your app.
Create great accessibility
and automation experiences
without having to pick one over the other.
Automation elements allows you
to expose elements
specifically for your UI tests
without impacting
the accessibility experience.
I encourage you to go to your UI tests
and add a quick call
to performAccessibilityAudit.
Thank you.