♪ ♪
Nikolas: Hello and welcome to "Support
external cameras in your iPadOS app."
I'm Nikolas Gelo
from the Camera Software team,
and this session about how your iPad app
can start using external cameras.
Stage Manager's powerful set
of features include the ability
to extend your iPad's display
across multiple screens.
And with iPadOS 17,
your app can start using external cameras
such as the one
in the Apple Studio Display.
On this iPad Pro, FaceTime is open,
and it's using the camera
in the display that it's connected to.
This is great because now the people
on the other side of the call
have a better viewing angle of me
when I run the app
on this big Apple Studio Display.
I can also use Center Stage with it,
which helps keep me
in the frame as I move around.
FaceTime, Code Scanner,
and WebKit use external cameras,
and they are great examples
of what your app can do.
When using monitors
that don't have built-in cameras,
like the Apple Pro Display XDR,
people often place a USB camera
on top of it.
If the USB camera is connected
to the monitor,
then when the monitor
is plugged into the iPad,
the camera will also be available
to your app.
Your iPad app
can use external cameras and webcams
to take photos and record movies.
They also support
other system camera features,
like the Portrait Blur
and Studio Light video effects
available from Control Center.
iPads with USB-C connectors
support external cameras.
Your app can use devices
that conform to the USB Video Class,
or UVC, specification.
It defines a standard for USB devices
to support video streaming.
And there are many popular cameras
your app can use.
Some external cameras
have built-in microphones,
which are also available to your app.
Some manufacturers make non-camera devices
that conform to the UVC spec,
like HDMI switchers
that change between multiple inputs
to output a single video stream.
iPadOS allows your app
to use devices like these.
External camera support
is a great enhancement
to iPad's rich media ecosystem.
I'll show how your app can use them
by starting with discovery and usage.
Next, I'll circle back
and demystify video rotation.
Then I'll cover how
your app can use microphones
that are included with external cameras.
And lastly,
I'll discuss best practices for your app.
First up, I'll discuss how your iPad app
can start using external cameras.
iPad apps use the camera
for many features,
like taking photos, recording movies,
or sending camera frames
over the network for video calls.
The AVFoundation framework allows your app
to use built-in and external cameras,
specifically,
with its AVCapture-prefixed classes.
Let's review how
an app can use the camera.
First, an app uses AVCaptureDevices,
which represent cameras and microphones.
Then they are wrapped
in AVCaptureDeviceInputs,
which allow them to be plugged
into an AVCaptureSession.
The AVCaptureSession is the central
control object of the AVCapture graph.
AVCaptureOutputs render data
from inputs in various ways.
The MovieFileOutput
records QuickTime movies.
The PhotoOutput captures
high-quality stills and Live Photos.
Data outputs, such as the VideoDataOutput
or AudioDataOutput,
deliver video or audio buffers
from the camera or mic to your app.
And there are other kinds of data outputs,
such as Metadata and Depth.
For live camera preview,
there's a special type of output,
the AVCaptureVideoPreviewLayer,
which is a subclass of CALayer.
Data flows from the capture inputs
to compatible outputs
through AVCaptureConnections.
These classes are available on iOS,
macOS, and tvOS.
If you're new to AVCapture,
I invite you to learn more
at the Capture Setup start page
on developer.apple.com.
New in iPadOS 17, your app can
access external cameras with AVCapture.
If your app already uses built-in cameras,
you can make simple updates
to start using external ones.
Discovering them is easy.
Each external camera is represented
by an AVCaptureDevice instance.
And you can find them with existing API
from AVCaptureDevice
and AVCaptureDeviceDiscoverySession.
There are three main attributes
of an AVCaptureDevice:
Its media type, device type, and position.
External cameras provide video media data
just like built-in cameras do.
And their device type is external.
For macOS app developers who are familiar
with using external cameras,
this deprecates
the external unknown device type.
Because external cameras
can move independently from the iPad,
their device position is unspecified.
These three attributes can be used
to find external cameras
with the AVCapture API.
It's easy to start using
external cameras in your app.
In this session,
I'll modify the popular sample camera app,
AVCam, to stream from the external camera
in an Apple Studio Display.
You can download the completed version
of AVCam with all of the changes
I make in this session
from developer.apple.com.
Currently, the app uses built-in cameras,
and it lets the user switch
between a front and rear-facing camera
when a button is pressed.
When AVCam launches,
it starts with a rear-facing camera.
I'll change the code
to have the app prefer looking
for an external camera
before a built-in one.
With the iPad connected
to the Apple Studio Display,
I'll run the app, and when it launches,
it will use the external camera.
This is great.
AVCam is now using an external camera,
and all it needed was a few lines of code.
The AVCaptureVideoPreviewLayer
mirrors external cameras by default,
which is suitable for using the camera
in the Apple Studio Display.
You can disable this behavior
if you prefer.
I'll describe how to do this
in the best practices section
at the end of this session.
Now I'll move the app
to the iPad's display.
And just for fun,
I'll unplug the external camera.
Uh-oh, the app's camera preview is frozen,
and it's not using any camera now.
AVCam will need more changes to handle
connection and disconnection events
of external cameras.
External cameras require special care
because, unlike built-in ones,
the user can connect and disconnect them
from the iPad at any time.
Your app can monitor these events
to know when a camera has become available
or can no longer be used.
If the same physical device
is reconnected,
it will be represented using
a new instance of AVCaptureDevice.
There is existing API your app can use
to listen for connection
and disconnection events.
You can key-value observe the isConnected
property on AVCaptureDevice
or the devices property
on an AVCaptureDeviceDiscoverySession
that updates as cameras come and go.
AVCaptureDevices also post notifications
when their connection status changes,
and your app can observe them
to monitor a camera's availability.
The system calls
key value observation code
and posts notifications
on background queues.
So be sure to synchronize your handling
with your AVCaptureSession queue
and the main thread.
Going back to AVCam,
I'll add some code to listen
for connection and disconnection events
of an external camera.
After the app looks
for the default device,
it observes
when the camera is disconnected.
And when that happens,
AVCam switches to a built-in camera.
Now when the app launches,
it still uses an external camera.
And when it disconnects,
the app switches to a built-in camera.
But when the external camera
is reconnected,
AVCam doesn't switch to it.
How should AVCam handle external cameras
being connected while it's running?
Should it switch to it
after I've plugged it in?
A tricky aspect of adopting
external cameras in your iPad app
is handling connection
and disconnection events.
To make this easier,
iPadOS is introducing API
for automatic camera selection.
The API allows your app
to integrate with the operating system
to use the best available camera.
It is another way
for your app to change cameras.
macOS Ventura introduced API
for automatic camera selection
to support Continuity Camera.
The behaviors I describe
in this session are specific to iOS.
For more information on how
to use this API for Mac,
see our previous session "Bringing
Continuity Camera to your macOS app"
from 2022 and its section
"Building a magical experience."
Automatic camera selection works
by using two new class properties
introduced to AVCaptureDevice on iOS:
userPreferredCamera
and systemPreferredCamera.
Both of these properties
are key-value observable.
userPreferredCamera
is a read/write property
that indicates the user's choice
of what camera should be used.
It should be set whenever a user
picks a camera in your app.
Doing so allows the system
to learn the user's preference.
systemPreferredCamera
is a read-only property
which specifies the best camera
to use as determined by the system.
By default, the system recommends
using the front camera,
but if you would like
to use a back camera instead,
your app can inform the system
of its desired behavior.
As different cameras
are chosen by the user,
the recommendation changes.
But you might be wondering how
the system know which camera is best.
I'll dive into that in a bit.
I'll first describe AVCaptureDevice's
userPreferredCamera property.
For this property,
the system stores a short history
of chosen cameras for each app
across launches and system reboots.
It allows your app
to combine the user's history
with the system's knowledge
of which cameras are currently connected.
So if a camera is disconnected,
the system returns
the next available camera
based on the user's history.
If there is no user selection history,
or none of the preferred cameras
are connected,
the system will always try
to return a camera that's ready to use
and prioritize cameras
that have been previously streamed.
Your app can use this property
to let the system store
your user's camera preference.
AVCaptureDevice's
systemPreferredCamera property
intelligently returns
the best camera to use.
It first checks the user's preference.
And when the user connects
an external camera to the iPad,
the system returns the new device.
This is because,
when a user connects a new camera,
they're implicitly indicating
their intent to use it.
These two inputs determine
the system preferred camera.
The automatic camera selection API
is flexible for an app
to choose how it integrates
with the system.
While only iPad supports external cameras,
iPhone apps can also use the API
for its user preferred camera storage.
Some apps allow users to change cameras,
while others stick to one
without giving a way to switch.
The API allows apps to choose between
automatic and manual camera selection.
FaceTime, Code Scanner,
and WebKit are great examples
that have different camera selection
behaviors to suit their needs.
When FaceTime launches,
it always uses the front
or external camera.
And during calls, it allows users
to switch between built-in cameras.
But when an external camera is used,
it hides the camera switch button.
FaceTime enables this behavior
by setting userPreferredCamera
when it switches devices and observing
the systemPreferredCamera property
for when an external device is plugged in.
It also makes its own decisions
for when it is appropriate
to use the automatic camera selection API.
For example,
while you can use the back camera
in a FaceTime Video call,
it always uses
the front or external camera
on the main screen
that shows the list of calls.
Code Scanner,
available from Control Center,
has different behavior.
It uses the back-facing camera
when it launches,
and it doesn't allow the user
to change cameras,
but it does listen
to the systemPreferredCamera property
and switches when notified.
The WebKit framework allows webpages
to access the iPad's cameras.
While it allows switching to any camera,
it returns the system preferred camera
as the first one in its list.
Now that I've shown you
how automatic camera selection works,
I'll add support for it in AVCam.
AVCam is a traditional photography app,
since you can take photos
and record movies with it.
It's different
from FaceTime and Code Scanner,
which are communication and utility apps,
respectively,
and WebKit, which is a system framework.
Now instead of needing a series
of "if, else if" statements
to find the external camera
with fallbacks,
AVCam just needs one line
to get the system preferred camera.
Since this is the first time the app is
using the automatic camera selection API,
the system returns
the built-in front camera.
But AVCam prefers
to continue starting with the back camera.
Before it gets
the system preferred camera,
the app checks if this is the first time
it has queried for it
by looking for a value stored
in the app's user defaults.
If no value is saved,
then the app hasn't set its initial state
for automatic camera selection.
So if this is the first time launching,
the app sets the user preferred camera
to be the back device.
The app finds the back camera
using an AVCaptureDeviceDiscoverySession,
which sorts the list of the devices
using the provided device types.
Then it sets the user preferred camera
and saves a value
in the app's user preferences,
so it only does this setup once.
To handle connections and disconnections
of external cameras,
it doesn't have to observe the connection
status of a specific camera anymore.
Instead, AVCam key value observes
the system preferred camera property.
This allows it to automatically switch
to the best available camera.
In its KVO handling,
the app gets the new system
preferred camera and switches to it.
but what if AVCam
is in the middle of a recording?
The app shouldn't interrupt the recording
by switching cameras.
So the app only switches if it is not
in the middle of a recording.
Then when the movie recording finishes,
the app queries
for the system preferred camera
to see if it is different
from what it is currently using.
If the system preferred camera did change,
the app switches to it.
This way it doesn't interrupt
the recording.
Decisions like these
are steps you'll have to make
when adopting external cameras
and the automatic camera selection API.
Do what makes the most sense for your app.
AVCam has a button to switch cameras
and behaves by changing
between front and back devices.
On this iPad Pro,
there are multiple cameras
that can be used at both positions.
So AVCam has some logic for choosing
which camera to use at a given position.
How should the button work now
that the app supports external cameras?
I'll choose to treat an external camera
like it is front-facing.
The camera
in this Apple Studio Display is facing me
like the iPad's built-in front camera.
If the changeCamera function
has no specific device to switch to,
the app checks the position
of the current device.
In the switch statement that checks
the current device's position,
the app looks for a rear-facing camera
if it is currently using one
with an unspecified or front position.
External cameras report
that their position is unspecified.
And if the app
is using a rear-facing camera,
it switches to an external device
if one is available.
Otherwise, it switches
to a built-in front facing camera.
To find external cameras, the app creates
a AVCaptureDeviceDiscoverySession
using the external device type,
the video media type,
and unspecified device position.
Then in the switch statement when
the current device's position is back,
it first looks for an external camera.
And if one is not found, it switches
to a built-in front facing camera.
Then when the app finds the camera
it would like to use,
it tells the system of the selection
by setting the userPreferredCamera class
property on AVCaptureDevice.
Setting this property allows the system
to learn the user's preferences.
You can choose how your app
will support external cameras
and how to allow a user
to switch between them.
For AVCam,
I chose to allow a user to switch
between front, back, and external cameras
by treating external cameras
like they are front-facing.
This way, the camera switch button
only changes between two devices.
AVCam is almost ready
to support external cameras.
There is just one more aspect to handle.
This whole time I've been using AVCam,
the iPad has been mounted in landscape
with the USB-C port on the right.
If I rotate the iPad, the external
camera's preview is now upside down.
But the external camera
in the display hasn't moved.
Just the iPad has.
AVCam doesn't have this rotation problem
with built-in cameras though.
This is because the app doesn't know
how to orient external cameras
whose position
is independent from the iPad.
AVCam will need further modifications
to properly display
an external camera's video preview.
Next up, I'll discuss
why video rotation is important
so that live preview and captured photos
and movies appear correctly.
Video rotation is not a new concept
for camera apps.
But when using external cameras,
it is important to know
that they move independently
from the iPad.
Apps are used to built-in cameras.
And because of this,
they rely on the iPad's orientation
to rotate the camera's video and use
the AVCaptureVideoOrientation enum.
This is what AVCam
was doing in the previous demo.
It tried rotating the external camera
to match the iPad's orientation.
In iPadOS 17,
AVCaptureVideoOrientation is deprecated,
as well as the API that use this enum.
It describes how the iPad is oriented
and assumes
the camera rotates with the device.
It's not expressive enough
for orienting external cameras,
which move independently.
To use this enum, an app typically
converts from UIDeviceOrientation,
which also describes the iPad and is
an indirect signal for orienting a camera.
So we're introducing new API
to handle video rotation.
New to all platforms, including iPadOS,
the AVCaptureDeviceRotationCoordinator
class can help properly orient any camera.
The class's initializer
takes an AVCaptureDevice
and optionally a CALayer
that displays the camera's video preview.
Apps often use
AVCaptureVideoPreviewLayer
or AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer
to show camera preview.
Both of these are subclasses of CALayer
and can be passed to the initializer.
Apps that use Metal
or other rendering methods
can simply pass the layer of the UIView
displaying the camera's preview.
The coordinator has two properties:
A video rotation angle
for horizon-level preview
and a separate angle
for horizon-level capture.
Both of these read-only properties
return an angle in degrees
and are key-value observable.
Previewing and capturing
content horizon-level means
that the video frames
from the camera are always upright
relative to gravity,
no matter if the device is in portrait,
landscape, or upside down.
Use the
videoRotationAngleForHorizonLevelPreview
to display video frames in the CALayer
passed to the coordinator's initializer.
It describes how much rotation
to apply for preview.
The angle is relative to the UIKit
and SwiftUI coordinate systems.
The
videoRotationAngleForHorizonLevelCapture
allows your app to take photos and movies,
so they are always upright
when someone views them later.
This property describes
the physical orientation of the camera.
And its value may be different
than the angle the app needs for preview.
These two properties
have different purposes.
To explain video rotation,
I'll start with scenarios
you are familiar with
when using built-in cameras.
Later, when I modify AVCam,
I'll explain how these concepts apply
to external cameras.
The camera app on iPhone
is a good example of the differences
between the video rotation angles
for horizon-level preview and capture.
In this example of the app
displaying the back camera's preview,
the iPhone is in portrait.
The UIKit coordinate system's origin
is at the top left of the drawing area,
where its positive x-axis
extends to the right
and positive y-axis extends down.
The back camera sensor's coordinate system
has a different origin.
The camera sensor first scans
along the height of the phone,
then along the width.
To account for the physical orientation
of the camera,
the app rotates the camera's video frames
90 degrees for preview in the UI.
It also rotates photos and movies
it captures,
so they are upright when viewed later.
It has different behavior
when the iPhone is in landscape.
The app only displays the UI in portrait,
no matter the device's orientation.
You can tell based on where
the home affordance indicator is.
For Camera app on iPhone,
it always stays on the side with the port.
The UIKit coordinate system's origin is
still at the top left of the drawing area,
and in this case, it stays fixed
to a single location on the device,
since the app's UI only supports
one orientation.
And the back camera sensor's coordinate
system still differs from the UI's.
Since the app
only displays the UI in portrait,
it applies a constant
90 degrees of rotation for preview,
no matter the iPhone's orientation.
But unlike for preview,
the app applies a different amount
of rotation when taking photos and movies
when the iPhone is in landscape.
When the iPhone is in the camera
sensor's native orientation,
the app does not need to rotate photos
or movies for them to appear upright.
All of this talk of rotation
really makes your head spin.
But the AVCaptureDeviceRotationCoordinator
takes care of this complexity
and provides correct angles to preview
and capture from all cameras.
Rely on it to provide angles rather
than trying to calculate them yourself.
As your app switches cameras,
be sure
to create a new rotation coordinator.
To apply video rotation,
use the angles the coordinator provides
with new API on AVCaptureConnection.
Only connections that deliver video
or depth media data support rotation.
To check whether
a connection supports an angle,
you can call
its isVideoRotationAngleSupported method.
To have the connection perform rotation,
set its videoRotationAngle property
to a supported value.
Use
videoRotationAngleForHorizonLevelPreview
to display the camera preview.
Apps using AVCaptureVideoPreviewLayer
can apply the property's value
to an AVCaptureConnection instance's
videoRotationAngle property.
Apps can also use it
when displaying buffers
from a video data output in a CALayer.
To synchronize with system animations,
change the preview rotation immediately
in your app's key value observation code.
Your app can expect to receive updates
to this property on the main queue
to update its UI.
Not all apps use
AVCaptureVideoPreviewLayer
for displaying camera preview.
Some apps display buffers
from a video data output
when applying custom effects or filters.
One option for displaying custom preview
is to use the AVSampleBufferDisplayLayer.
Avoid requesting rotation
by setting the angle
on the video data output's
AVCaptureConnection.
Changing the connection's angle
causes a frame delivery interruption
as the capture render pipeline
reconfigures itself
to apply the new amount of rotation.
Instead, rotate the CALayer
displaying the camera preview.
Doing so allows your app's camera preview
to rotate smoothly.
Use
videoRotationAngleForHorizonLevelCapture
when photos and movies,
so they're level relative to gravity.
Your app can apply the property's value
on capture connections
to a photo output or movie file output.
Alternatively,
if your app uses a video data output
with an AVAssetWriter
for recording custom movies,
avoid rotating the video
with AVCaptureConnection.
Instead, set the rotation
with an AVAssetWriterInput instance's
transform property,
which alters the output file's metadata.
With this approach, video apps
apply the rotation during playback,
which uses less energy than rotating
each frame with the capture connection.
Your app needs to convert
the rotation angle from degrees
because an asset writer input
uses a CGAffineTransform
that applies rotations in radians.
Some outputs efficiently apply rotation
without added overhead.
For instance, a movie file output applies
rotation using a QuickTime track matrix.
The photo output
handles orientation with Exif tags.
And the preview layer transforms
its contents to perform rotations.
However, your app may increase
a device's power consumption
if has the video
or depth data outputs perform rotation
because they use more memory
and energy to rotate their buffers.
Instead, your app
can take a more efficient approach
by rotating the CALayer that previews
buffers from video or depth outputs.
Use AVCaptureDeviceRotationCoordinator
on all available platforms,
including iOS, tvOS, and macOS.
Mac Catalyst and iOS apps on Mac
can also use it.
Your app can use the rotation coordinator
to correctly orient photos or movies
and display video preview for any camera.
And it helps your app
handle complex layouts
with Stage Manager
or when it is on an external display.
Now it's time for the final changes
to support external cameras in AVCam.
When configuring the capture session,
the app sets up its camera preview.
So it creates
a device rotation coordinator,
which gives the app the rotation angles
it needs for preview and capture.
When creating a coordinator,
the app updates the preview layer
with the current rotation angle
for preview.
It also observes changes to the angle
and updates the preview.
When AVCam switches devices,
it also creates
a new rotation coordinator,
so the preview looks right
for the new camera.
When taking photos,
the app uses the rotation angle
for capture to make sure they're upright
when someone views them later.
And it does the same
when recording movies.
With these changes, AVCam is ready
to support external cameras.
Now when I rotate the iPad,
the external camera appears correctly.
We've covered a lot so far
in this session,
and I thank you
for following along with me.
Now that I've shown how your iPad app
can use external cameras,
I'll discuss how you can also use
microphones included with these devices.
Some webcams and displays include mics.
When they are plugged into an iPad,
they can be used by your app.
iPadOS 17 has improved support
for external microphones
on iPads with USB-C.
Telephony apps that use
Core Audio's AUVoiceIO audio unit
can now use external microphones like
those included with webcams or displays.
Previously,
the only external wired devices
these apps could use were headset mics.
AUVoiceIO is a popular interface,
since it performs echo cancellation,
and new tunings have been introduced
for external mics.
Voice Isolation mode
available from Control Center
removes unwanted background noise,
such as typing on keyboards,
mouse clicks, or leaf blowers
running somewhere in the neighborhood.
Your app can use this system feature
with external microphones.
The iOS audio routing system allows
only one microphone to be used at a time.
It also automatically changes
to the last connected microphone.
This is because,
just like when connecting a camera,
the user is indicating the newly
connected microphone should be used.
On iOS, the system returns only one
AVCaptureDevice for the microphone.
You can find it by searching
for the device with the audio media type
or with the new microphone device type,
which deprecates builtInMicrophone
because not all mics
are built-in to the iPad.
The audio routing system decides
which available microphone to use,
be it built-in or external.
When the system changes the input route,
the microphone AVCaptureDevice's
localizedName property changes
to reflect the device in use.
Your app can use AVAudioSession
for more control over the microphone.
You can use it
to configure your app's audio behaviors
by setting a category or mode.
And you can choose to use a specific mic,
like one included with an external camera,
by setting the preferred input.
For the final topic of this session,
I'll discuss some best practices
for your app when using external cameras.
As you begin adoption, consider
what makes most sense for your app.
Earlier, I showed how FaceTime,
Code Scanner,
and WebKit chose to support
external cameras differently.
Use them as examples
of different ways your app can adopt.
Configure your iPad
for wireless debugging with Xcode
while the USB-C port is in use
by an external camera.
Some capabilities that your app
can expect from built-in cameras
may not be supported by external devices.
For example, if your app relies
on depth data capture for some feature,
you might have to disable it
when an external camera is in use.
Apps that use multiple cameras
at the same time
with an AVCaptureMultiCamSession
can add external cameras
for creative capture setups.
iPadOS gives external cameras
some treatment
that it also applies
to front-facing cameras.
The AVCaptureVideoPreviewLayer
mirrors external cameras by default.
This works well
when the camera is facing the iPad user.
But this isn't suitable for all use cases.
If your app's users stream
from HDMI switchers
or point the external camera
away from them,
consider allowing users
to disable preview mirroring.
In a previous section,
I described camera rotation.
While your app likely won't need
to apply video rotation
for an external camera,
be aware that if you do,
the system rotates external cameras
clockwise towards the scene it is facing.
This is the same way
it applies rotation for built-in cameras.
Prepare your app to handle cameras
with different capabilities.
For example, some external cameras
may only report two formats,
like a VGA format of 640x480
and an HD format of 1280x720.
And some external cameras
support pixel formats
that are not typically used on iOS.
We've chosen to convert these
to more common formats
that iOS camera apps are used to handling.
Uncompressed formats like yuvs
and 2vuy are converted to 420v.
And compressed formats like streaming
JPEG and H264 are converted to 420f.
Because an external camera
can have formats of any size,
it may not support
all AVCaptureSessionPresets.
For example, the HD 4K preset requires
the device to have a compatible format.
Your app can check
whether it can use a preset
by calling the supportsSessionPreset
method on AVCaptureDevice.
Your app can configure
an external camera,
including changing its resolution,
frame rate, and zoom factor.
iPadOS supports a limited set
of the camera controls
available
in the USB Video Class specification.
So query the AVCaptureDevice
for its capabilities.
Let's wrap up everything
I just talked about.
I showed how you can discover
and use external cameras,
how to properly rotate
a camera's video frames,
using external microphones,
and lastly, best practices for your app.
We're excited to see how you start
using external cameras in your iPad app.
Thank you, and I hope your app rocks.
♪ ♪