♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hello there!
I'm Ilya Veygman,
an engineer with Core Location.
I'm here today to talk to you
about Core Location
for spatial computing.
Whether you're brand-new
to Apple's ecosystem
or a longtime
App Store developer,
you probably have
lots of questions
about the kinds of things
this system can do.
xrOS is great at showing you
the fruits of your imagination,
while Core Location is there
to help you have an anchor
in the real world.
Today, I'm here to tell you
all about how to do just that
with Core Location.
For those of you
who are brand-new
to the Apple developer
ecosystem, welcome!
I'd like to start off
with a simple example
to show you just how
straightforward it really is
to add location to your app.
For experienced developers,
it never hurts
to review one's basics.
So let's start by looking
at some sample code
for this demo application
associated with
my colleague's session,
"Discover streamlined
location updates."
In this actor,
we request live updates
from CLLocationUpdate,
and we'll get them
asynchronously down here
as they become available.
For more details
on the location updates API,
please refer to the session
associated with this demo.
Apps must request
the user's permission
before accessing sensitive
information such as location,
so here, we invoke
this API to do so.
In this simple example,
we do it when the view inits.
We also have to ensure
that we set this string
in the app's info
under Build Settings.
Again, apps must ask
the user's permission
before they can get sensitive
information such as location,
and this string is there
to explain to the user why.
It will later be displayed
in a prompt
shown to the user
requesting this access.
So let's see how this looks
when we run it in the simulator.
Again, in this application,
we ask for location access
straightaway because
it's a simple example.
This will not always
be the case with your apps.
You can see that we get
a prompt asking the user
if they will grant access
to their private information.
Now before moving on,
let's chat a little bit more
about how Core Location treats
user privacy on this system.
Even if you are new
to our developer ecosystem,
you might already be aware
that Apple is heavily focused
on privacy
in its user experience.
Location access is not
an exception to this maxim.
Before you can get updates
about geolocation,
you must first ask
the user for permission
to access
their location information.
You will not get location
updates without user consent.
You can ask for consent
on this system by creating
a location manager and invoking
requestWhenInUseAuthorization,
along with setting
the usage description string
in your app's Info.plist.
This, again, tells the user
why your app
needs to know their location.
Finally, you should only ask
for this access in a context
when your application
actually needs it.
Not only is this better
from a privacy perspective,
it also ensures the user is more
likely to allow access at all.
Recall that we did this
in our sample code
since it was
a very simple example
and starts asking for location
updates immediately.
So what does this prompt
look like and what does it show?
Users will see a prompt
from your application
similar to the one here.
This may look familiar
to those of you watching
who already have experience
with iOS development.
A user can grant location access
for just this session,
while using the app,
or deny it entirely.
Users may also choose
to grant your application
knowledge of either their
precise or approximate location
using the highlighted button,
just like on iOS.
For more information
on how exactly
this precise versus
approximate location works,
please refer to
"What's new in location"
from WWDC20,
hosted by a younger version
of myself.
So back to the demo.
After we grant this application
access to precise location
and authorize it while in use,
we can now start
getting location updates
and see our app
getting position updates.
So what exactly did I mean by
"precise location"?
That is, how accurately can the
headset know a user's location?
For a unit by itself,
you should expect accuracy
similar to that of a Mac,
so that's about 100 meters.
This will be sufficient
for applications like those used
for finding nearby restaurants,
parks, and other attractions.
However,
if your iPhone is nearby,
this device can leverage
existing connections
between these two devices
to improve the location accuracy
you would get from the headset
to be on the same level
as that of an iPhone.
Your device works even better
when together
with our other Apple hardware.
This opens up a whole new range
of applications
which can run on a spatial
computing system like this one,
such as precise weather updates,
geotagging, and more.
Now for both newcomers
and experienced developers,
you've also heard me say
that an app is eligible
to get location updates
while a user is using it.
What this means
is fairly straightforward
on iPhone or watch,
but what does it mean for us?
The user experience is,
after all,
very different
from an iPhone or a watch.
So, let's talk about that.
Let us call back to
"What's New In Core Location"
from 2019 where we discussed
how and when foreground apps
are considered to be
in use on iOS.
For a platform like iPhone,
this is fairly obvious.
There can only really be one app
foregrounded at any given time.
There is also
a short grace period
after the app is backgrounded
while it can still get
location updates.
So what about here?
Your application
on this platform
can be fully immersive,
or you could have apps
running in something
like a window.
"How does Core Location
treat this?"
you're probably wondering.
For a fully
immersive experience,
this is straightforward.
As long as the user
is running your application,
we consider it to be
in use and eligible
to get location updates,
assuming that the user
has granted consent for your app
to get their location.
On this system,
Core Location provides location
information to your app,
so long as the user
has recently looked at the app.
To wit, on this platform,
we consider apps
running in a window to be
eligible to get location updates
if the user has consented to
giving their location to them,
and if the user has
recently looked at the app.
Let's examine this
more concretely.
Imagine that both of these apps
have been authorized
to access the user's location
while in use.
So long as the user
is not interacting with
or looking at either app,
neither one will be able
to get location updates.
If the user starts looking at --
that is, interacting with --
the app on the left, that app
can now get location updates,
while the right one
still cannot,
even if it happens to be
in the user's peripheral vision.
And this will remain true until
the user looks somewhere else,
such as at the app
on the right,
or moves the two apps together
such that they can look at both
of the apps at the same time.
Just like in iOS,
there is also a grace period
before Core Location considers
the app to no longer be in use.
This means that if the user were
to look at an app on the left,
then at the app on the right
before looking somewhere else,
there will be
a short period of time --
a few seconds --
when both apps are still
eligible to get location
before Core Location considers
these apps to be out of use.
We feel that such a model
of location access
provides a good experience
on this platform
while being respectful
of user privacy,
since a user would not
have their location tracked
without their permission
or knowledge,
particularly since
this device is intended
to be used interactively,
rather than as something
which runs stashed somewhere
like in your backpack.
As such, apps will not
be able to get location updates
while they're not running.
Similarly, updates
from our monitoring APIs
would not be delivered.
So this brings me to something
else which many developers
who already have location-using
apps for Apple platforms
are probably wondering about:
How will my app behave when
running in compatibility mode?
So what happens if I just run
my iPhone or iPad app
with no code changes
for a device running xrOS?
Let's talk about that a bit.
As already discussed, the
"in-useness" of "while in use"
derives from where the user
has looked recently.
And apps are eligible
to get location
only when the user
is looking at them.
So what about apps which request
Always authorization?
Apps which prompt for Always
will have their request
redirected to request
authorization while in use.
You will similarly see
that Always is not an option
for your application
under Settings.
Location on this system
works best for single-shot
or continuous updates
while your app is being used.
If your compatible
iPhone or iPad app
uses region monitoring
or our new CLMonitor,
it will not be delivered events.
Consider if your iOS app
is designed in such a way
that assumes a particular API
is always supported,
and might behave in
unexpected ways if, for example,
monitoring APIs
never deliver events.
Similarly, consider whether
your app relies
on getting location updates
in the background
while it's not running.
To learn more about
our API in general,
especially what's new
this year,
I would recommend that you watch
these other two sessions
from my colleagues,
as well as any of our other
sessions from previous years,
especially if you're a newcomer
to our ecosystem.
"Discover streamlined
location updates"
discusses some new developments
in our API,
particularly around
how we recommend
getting location updates
and ways in which we have
made our API more compatible
with Swift concurrency.
"Meet Core Location Monitor"
further discusses
new developments
in monitoring APIs,
and how we've reimagined
the ways an app can get notified
about events such as
geographic entries and exits.
If location is something
you care about for your app,
I am certain that you'll find
these to be time well spent.
xrOS provides
a really cool experience
that I'm sure many of you
have been anticipating
for quite some time.
We have been too,
and we worked hard to ensure
that you can provide the best
possible user experience
both for apps
which were designed
specifically for this device,
and for those compatible
iPhone or iPad apps.
We also want to make sure
that user privacy is respected
in the best ways possible,
and that a transition
to this platform
is as seamless as possible
for those of you who have
existing apps in our store.
Now that said, do consider
how your compatible apps
might behave in a scenario when
they don't receive notifications
about events
like region changes or visits.
I definitely encourage you
to watch
any of the other sessions,
both specific to Core Location
and to spatial computing
in general,
which might pique
your interests.
Thank you
and enjoy the rest of WWDC.
♪