♪ ♪
Kyle: Hi, I'm Kyle
a member of the SwiftUI team.
Animation is a key component
of modern app design.
When tastefully applied, it can bring
both clarity and life to your UI.
Making it simple
to add animation to your app
was one of our core motivations
when we began developing SwiftUI.
It's a big reason why SwiftUI
is shaped the way that it is.
This session is an overview of SwiftUI's
powerful animation capabilities
and how they work together
to produce impressive visual effects.
I'll cover how SwiftUI
refreshes the rendering of a view,
determines what
to animate using Animatable,
interpolates values over time
using Animation,
and propagates context
for the current update using Transaction.
In recent years,
there's been debate among my colleagues
about who makes the best furry--
or not so furry--companion.
We were curious
if we could come to a consensus,
so we made an app to take a poll.
There's a button to cast a vote
for each pet.
When you tap, the vote count changes,
and the avatars slide around
to reflect the current standings.
In the last poll, as is proper,
cats came in first place,
but only narrowly.
The stakes are too high
to leave this next poll purely to chance,
so I'm adding a new feature.
On tap,
the avatar of my choice will scale up
in order to nudge people
towards voting for the proper pet.
And I can tap again to scale it back down.
This is already working pretty well,
but it would be way better
with an animation.
Before adding that,
I'm gonna trace through how SwiftUI
refreshes the rendering of a view
to give you a better understanding
of the anatomy of a view update.
For this exercise, I'm gonna focus
on the pet avatar view in isolation.
SwiftUI tracks a view's dependencies,
like this selected state variable.
When an event, like a tap, comes in,
an update transaction is opened.
If any of its dependencies change,
the view is invalidated,
and at the close of the transaction,
the framework calls body
to produce a new value
in order to refresh the rendering.
This view's body
is composed of a tap gesture,
a scale effect, and an image.
Behind the scenes, SwiftUI maintains
a long-lived dependency graph
that manages the lifetime
of views and their data.
Each node in this graph,
called an attribute,
maps to a fine-grained piece of the UI.
When the selected state changed to true,
the value of each of these downstream
attributes became stale.
They're refreshed by unwrapping
the new view value one layer at a time.
Once the corresponding graph attributes
have been updated,
the view's body value is discarded.
Finally, the graph emits drawing commands
on your behalf to update the rendering.
I'll zoom in on just the graph in order
to visualize the lifetime of an attribute.
An attribute is born
with an initial value.
An event comes in,
and an update transaction opens.
An upstream dependency changes.
The framework calls body.
The attribute's value is updated.
The transaction closes.
And in this way, the current value of each
attribute in the graph evolves over time.
So that's the anatomy of a view update.
Now I'll add an animation.
If I wrap withAnimation
around my state change,
when the tap gesture closure fires,
the animation is set for the transaction.
Then selected is toggled,
and the downstream attributes
are invalidated.
As before, body is called
to provide new attribute values.
And here's where it gets interesting.
scaleEffect is a special attribute,
an "animatable attribute."
When the value
of an animatable attribute changes,
it checks if an animation
is set for the transaction.
If so, it makes a copy
and uses the animation to interpolate
from the old value to the new value
as time passes.
I'll zoom in
on the scaleEffect animatable attribute
to examine how this plays out.
The first thing to notice
is that animatable attributes
conceptually have both model
and presentation values.
Right now they're the same.
Then an event comes in,
and a transaction is opened,
this time with an animation.
State is changed,
and body is called
to refresh the stale attribute values.
Because the value has changed,
the attribute makes a local copy
of the animation to calculate
the current presentation value.
SwiftUI knows when the attribute graph
contains running animations
and will call
into the appropriate animatable attributes
to produce the next frame.
For built-in animatable attributes
like scaleEffect,
SwiftUI is very efficient.
It's able to do this work
off the main thread
and without calling into any
of your view code.
Here's the animation in action.
Nice.
When someone uses the word "animation,"
they're probably referring
to the overall visual experience
of the way a view changes over time.
What I've covered so far is that,
in SwiftUI,
there are two orthogonal aspects
contributing
to the overall visual experience.
Animatable attributes, like scaleEffect,
determine the data being animated,
while the Animation determines
how that data changes over time.
I'll dive deeper
into each of these in turn,
starting with Animatable,
which determines what to animate.
SwiftUI builds an animatable attribute
for any view conforming
to the Animatable protocol.
The only requirement
is that the view define a readwrite vector
of the data it wants to animate.
The data must conform to VectorArithmetic.
VectorArithmetic matches
the textbook definition
of a vector from your math class.
It supports vector addition
and scalar multiplication.
If you're rusty
or not familiar with vectors,
don't be discouraged.
A vector is basically just
a fixed-length list of numbers,
and for SwiftUI animation,
the purpose of dealing in vectors
is mostly just to abstract
over the length of that list.
For example, CGFloat and Double
are one-dimensional vectors,
while CGPoint and CGSize
define two-dimensional vectors,
and CGRect defines
a four-dimensional vector.
By dealing in vectors,
SwiftUI is able to animate all
of these types and more
with a single generic implementation.
So far, for the sake of simplicity,
I've represented scaleEffect
as if it were
a one-dimensional scale factor.
The Animatable conformance
for a one-dimensional scaleEffect
would be straightforward.
Its animatableData
would just be a CGFloat.
In reality, scaleEffect allows you
to independently configure
the width, height,
and relative anchor point
of the transformation--all animatable.
So scaleEffect actually defines
a four-dimensional vector
for its animatable data,
a CGSize for the width and height scale,
paired with a UnitPoint
for the relative anchor.
AnimatablePair fuses the two vectors
together into a single, larger vector.
It's a public type,
and you can use it too.
It might come in handy
if you're conforming one
of your own views to Animatable.
scaleEffect is just one
of the many animatable visual effects
that come built into SwiftUI,
so the vast majority of the time,
Animatable is not an API
you'll need to use directly.
In rare circumstances, though,
an advanced use case may call
for conforming one
of your own views to Animatable.
Consider the pet Podium view,
which distributes its subviews
along the arc of a circle
using a custom RadialLayout.
By default, changing the offset angle
within an animation
animates the pet avatars to their new
positions along a straight line.
Notice how the pets are taking a shortcut
and trespassing
on the interior of the circle?
That's not what I want.
Instead, I want my avatars to animate
along the perimeter of the circle.
I can get this effect by conforming Podium
to animatable
and using the offset angle
as its animatable data.
Why does this result
in such a different effect?
To explain,
I'll step through an animated update
for each version of the Podium view,
starting with the default behavior,
which animates the avatars
along a straight line.
Podium's body is composed
of a RadialLayout and three avatars.
When a transaction opens,
if the offset angle has changed,
body is called to refresh
the stale downstream attribute values.
Then layout is run,
updating the position of each subview.
So this is what an animated update is like
in the default version.
The active animatable data
is the view position CGPoint,
which interpolates
in a cartesian coordinate space,
meaning each avatar moves
along a straight line.
In the custom version,
when I conform Podium to Animatable,
what changes is that body
becomes the active animatable attribute,
with the offset angle
as its animatable data.
How does this result in each avatar
moving along an arc?
In this custom version,
for every frame of the animation,
body is going to be called
by SwiftUI with a new offset angle,
and the layout will be rerun.
This is super powerful, and sometimes,
like when you're animating
custom layout or drawing code,
it might be the only way
to achieve the effect you're going for.
Just keep in mind
that a custom Animatable conformance
can be much more expensive to animate
than a built-in effect because it'll
run body for every frame of the animation.
So only use this tool if you can't
achieve the effect you're going for
using the built-in effects.
Next, I'll cover Animation,
the generic algorithms that interpolate
animatable data over time.
Earlier, I added an animation
to the pet avatar view
by wrapping the state change
in withAnimation.
You can customize this
by passing an explicit animation,
like a bouncy spring.
SwiftUI comes with a ton
of powerful animations built in.
They can roughly be categorized
into three buckets:
Timing curve animations,
Spring animations,
and Higher order animations,
which modify a base animation.
Timing curve animations
are likely the category
of animation you're most familiar with.
For example,
easeInOut is a timing curve animation.
All timing curve animations take a curve,
which defines the speed of the animation,
and a duration.
A timing curve can be created
using bezier control points.
By adjusting the start
and end control points,
you change the initial
and final velocity of the animation.
The UnitCurve type can be used standalone
to calculate the value and the velocity
at a relative point between 0 and 1.
SwiftUI comes with a number
of built-in timing curve presets:
Linear,
easeIn,
easeOut,
and easeInOut.
All timing curve animations
can also specify a custom duration.
The next category of animation,
Springs, determine the value
at a given point in time
by running a spring simulation.
You may be familiar with traditional ways
of specifying a spring,
for example, mass, stiffness, and damping.
But we've never found these ways
to be particularly intuitive,
so we invented a new way.
You just specify
the perceived duration of the animation
and how bouncy you want the spring to be.
It's much more approachable.
Similar to UnitCurve,
the Spring type can be used standalone
to calculate the value and the velocity
of a spring at a given time.
SwiftUI comes
with three built-in spring presets:
Smooth, which has no bounce,
snappy,
which has a small amount of bounce,
and bouncy,
which has a larger amount of bounce.
If you're uncomfortable
parameterizing a spring animation,
these presets are a reliable way
to get something that feels good.
Each preset can be also tuned to adjust
the duration or tweak the bounciness.
We highly recommend
using spring animations
because they give your UI an organic feel
by preserving velocity
and naturally coming to rest.
In fact, we feel so strongly
about the benefits of spring animations
that we made a smooth spring
the new default when you use
a bare withAnimation
in iOS 17 and aligned releases.
The last category of animations,
Higher order, modify a base animation.
They can slow it down or speed it up.
They can add a delay
before the base animation starts.
And they can repeat a base animation
any number of times,
optionally toggling between playing
forwards and playing in reverse.
And now we're introducing
an entirely new category of animation:
Custom animations.
The CustomAnimation protocol
gives you access
to the same low-level generic entry points
we use to implement all the animations
that come built into SwiftUI.
The CustomAnimation protocol
has three requirements:
animate, shouldMerge, and velocity.
I'll start by focusing on animate.
shouldMerge and velocity
are optional requirements.
I'll get back to them later.
Animate is passed the vector
to animate towards,
the amount of time that has elapsed
since the animation began,
and the context,
which includes additional animation state.
Animate returns
the current value of the animation,
or nil if the animation has finished.
Where does this value vector come from?
It comes from a view's animatable data.
In the pet avatar view,
that's the scale effect.
Recall that scaleEffect's animatable data
is a four-dimensional vector,
including a two-dimensional width
and height scale.
When the avatar is selected,
it's animated to a scale factor
of 1.5 by 1.5
from a scale factor of 1 by 1.
Vector addition and scalar multiplication
operations allow SwiftUI to subtract
these two vectors from one another
to calculate the delta between them.
This delta
is actually what's being animated.
This means, in practice,
the animation running
in the scaleEffect animatable attribute
isn't interpolating from 1 to 1.5,
but from 0 to 0.5.
Among other things,
this makes it more convenient
to implement the animate method.
Let me show you.
I'm going to implement
a linear timing curve animation
configured by a duration
to interpolate over.
Recall that animate is passed
the delta vector to animate towards.
I can use scalar multiplication
to scale the vector by the proportion
of the duration that has elapsed.
And once the full duration has elapsed,
I'll return nil to indicate
that the animation has finished
and can be removed.
That's it.
And because
this implementation is generic,
it works with animatable data
of any number of dimensions.
So that's how Animatable
and Animation work together
to produce the impressive visual effects
that appear in your UI.
Next, I'll return to CustomAnimation's
two optional requirements:
shouldMerge and velocity.
What are they for?
Imagine for a moment that you're
the scaleEffect animatable attribute.
The user taps down, a transaction opens,
your value changes,
you make a local copy of the animation,
and you start happily animating
your delta vector.
Everything is going great.
That is, until the pesky user taps again
before the animation has finished.
What do you do?
You set up a new animation,
and you call shouldMerge on it.
The default implementation returns false--
this is what timing curve animations do--
in which case both animations will be
run together,
and their results will be combined
by the system.
This is another reason why
SwiftUI animations
deal in terms of delta vectors.
It makes it easy to calculate
the correct combined presentation value
when multiple animations are running.
But what if I'd chosen a spring animation,
not a timing curve animation?
Spring animations
override shouldMerge to return true
and incorporate the state
of the previous animation.
This allows them to preserve velocity
and retarget to the new value,
which can feel more natural
than combining additively,
like timing curve animations.
And that's what
this final velocity requirement is for.
Implementing it allows velocity
to be preserved when a running animation
is merged with a new one.
So I'll finish off
my linear timing curve animation
by adding an implementation for velocity.
I've used the term "transaction"
throughout this talk to refer to the set
of work that's performed
for a given update to the UI.
In SwiftUI code,
Transaction also refers to a related,
powerful data-flow construct
and family of APIs.
You may already be familiar
with Environment and Preferences,
dictionaries SwiftUI implicitly passes
down and up the view hierarchy,
respectively.
Transaction is similar.
It's a dictionary SwiftUI uses
to implicitly propagate all the context
for the current update,
most notably the animation.
My explanation earlier
of how an animatable attribute
reads the current animation
was a little vague.
So I'm gonna trace through another
animated update of the avatar view.
This time, I'll be more specific.
When the tap gesture closure fires,
withAnimation sets an animation
in the root transaction dictionary.
Body is called
to update the attribute values.
The transaction dictionary is propagated
across the attribute graph.
When it reaches an animatable attribute,
the attribute checks
if an animation is set.
And if so, it makes a copy
to drive its presentation value.
The Transaction is only relevant
for a specific update,
so once the stale attributes
have been refreshed, it's discarded.
Flowing the animation
down the view hierarchy
within the transaction dictionary
makes possible a number of powerful APIs
for controlling when and how
animations apply to your views.
Right now, the pet avatar view
can only be selected via tap.
I'll change
the selected State variable to a Binding.
That way, it can be also be
selected programmatically.
But how do I animate a programmatic
change to a view property?
I can use the transaction modifier
to access the animation
as it flows down the view hierarchy
inside the transaction dictionary.
If I set an animation
from within this modifier,
then whenever body is called,
even if there is no animation
or a different animation
in the transaction,
the attribute will override the animation.
And when it reaches the scale effect,
this animation will be used
to interpolate the scale factor.
Pretty cool.
But there's a problem with this pattern.
Indiscriminately overriding the animation
for all descendants
whenever SwiftUI refreshes a view
can lead to accidental animations.
Instead, for uses cases like this,
SwiftUI provides
an animation view modifier.
It takes an additional value argument,
which allows you to scope the effect
much more precisely.
It will only write the animation
into the transaction
if the value has changed.
Now that that's hooked up,
this withAnimation
isn't accomplishing anything,
so we can remove it.
The animation view modifier
is also a powerful tool for situations
where you want to apply different
animations to different parts of a view.
For example, the pet avatar has a shadow,
which I've omitted thus far
from the example
for the sake of simplicity.
The shadow radius increases
when the avatar is selected
to accentuate the illusion
that it's elevated above the background.
After playing with it,
I've decided I want the shadow's animation
to be more subdued
than the scale effect's.
To accomplish this, I can insert
another animation view modifier
between the scaleEffect and the shadow.
Now the transaction
picks up the bouncy spring
for animating the scale effect.
And it picks up
the more subtle smooth spring
for animating the shadow radius.
Because animation modifiers
are only active
when their value has changed,
the odds of an accidental animation
are greatly reduced.
But if the avatar's image
had just happened to change
in the same transaction as selected,
it would have inherited
the shadow's smooth spring animation
for its content transition.
This is a point worth lingering on.
This animation view modifier
works well for leaf components
where the entire sub-hierarchy
is under your control.
But for non-leaf components,
which contain arbitrary child content,
it's much more likely
for an accidental animation to occur.
For example,
if I want to reuse my avatar
in another app
that has nothing to do with pets,
I could make it more generic
by accepting arbitrary child content.
In this scenario,
I have less of a guarantee
that when selected changes,
the child content won't also have changed.
This could result
in an accidental animation.
Whoops.
Good news.
We have a new version
of the animation view modifier
specifically designed
for use cases like this.
It narrowly scopes the animation
to the animatable attributes
specified in its body closure.
Here's how it works.
Imagine there's
no animation in the transaction.
When the transaction reaches
the animation view modifier's attribute,
a copy is made that's populated
with the specified animation.
The copy is propagated downstream,
but only
to the scoped animatable attributes.
Once it's done its job,
the copy is discarded,
and the original transaction
picks up where it left off.
So when the transaction
reaches the child content,
because the original transaction
is unaffected by any
of the intermediate
animation view modifiers,
there's no risk of accidental animations.
A limited set of transaction APIs
have been available
since the first version of SwiftUI.
Now we're introducing the capability
to define custom transaction keys,
so you can leverage
the transaction dictionary
to implicitly propagate
your own update-specific data.
If you've ever declared
a custom environment key,
declaring a custom transaction key
will be familiar.
The pattern is to create
a unique type that conforms
to the TransactionKey protocol.
The only requirement
is to provide a defaultValue.
Then declare a computed property
as an extension on Transaction
that reads and writes from
the transaction dictionary using your key.
Here, I've defined
a boolean key to track whether,
for the given update,
the avatar was tapped or not.
I'll decide which animation
to use based on its value.
If the avatar was selected interactively,
I'll scale it up or down
using a more lively spring.
But if the avatar
was selected programmatically,
I'll scale it using a more subdued spring.
I can set a value
in the transaction dictionary
for the given update by wrapping
withTransaction around my state change.
This should seem familiar.
withAnimation is just a thin wrapper
around withTransaction.
The arguments passed
to withTransaction are a keypath
to a computed property
on the Transaction and the value to set.
Transaction is unique among SwiftUI's
implicit data-flow constructs
because it's discarded
at the end of every update.
This means, unless explicitly set
for the current update,
every value in the transaction dictionary
reverts to just being
the default value for its key.
In the avatar view,
when the tap gesture closure fires,
avatarTapped is set
to true for the current update.
The transaction
also contains the default value
for the animation key, which is nil.
The transaction propagates
across the view hierarchy
until it reaches the transaction modifier.
Here, the avatar view reads avatarTapped,
and based on its value,
sets the appropriate animation...
Which propagates down the view hierarchy.
This works pretty well,
but just like earlier,
it can result in accidental animations.
To give you finer-grained control
over modifying the transaction,
we're introducing two new variants
of the transaction modifier.
One lets you scope
using a value argument.
And the other lets you scope
to a sub-hierarchy
defined in a body closure.
These variants mirror
the scoped animation view modifiers
covered earlier.
In this session, I explained
SwiftUI's powerful animation primitives,
Animatable, Animation, and Transaction.
As a next step, I recommend
checking out two related sessions.
"Animate with springs" provides
more guidance on why and how
to effectively use spring animations
in your app.
And "Wind your way through
advanced animations in SwiftUI"
introduces powerful new tools
for constructing multi-step animations.
I hope this content
gives you a better understanding
of how SwiftUI animation works
and empowers you
to more skillfully leverage
animation in your app.
Thanks.
♪ ♪