♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hello, and welcome to
"Meet SwiftUI
for spatial computing."
I'm Andrew, an engineer
on the SwiftUI team.
We're so excited
about spatial computing.
It opens up a world
of new possibilities
for building groundbreaking
applications.
In this talk, I'll walk you
through what you need to know
to build your own great apps
for the platform
and the powerful new features
in SwiftUI
that make it all possible.
When you build an app
for spatial computing,
the best way to build it
is using SwiftUI.
We're bringing SwiftUI
into a bold new future,
with all-new 3D capabilities
like volumes,
immersive experiences
with Full Space,
new 3D gestures,
effects, and layout,
deep integration
with RealityKit,
and so much more.
These new capabilities
only exist in SwiftUI.
If you have existing code
for your apps,
much of it will still work
on the platform.
For all new code,
the best way to write it
is with SwiftUI.
We believe so deeply in SwiftUI
that we built the system
from the ground up
using SwiftUI.
From core building blocks
of an app like Buttons, Toggles,
and TabViews,
to core elements
like the Home View
and Control Center,
to familiar apps
like TV and Safari,
to all-new experiences
like 3D boards in Freeform
and immersive rehearsals
in Keynote,
SwiftUI powers all of these
things and so much more.
With SwiftUI, you describe
your app's user interface,
leaving the system to choose
intelligent defaults for you
so you can learn
these concepts once
and apply them anywhere.
This is even more useful
with an entirely new platform.
Your existing SwiftUI knowledge
transfers over seamlessly
to an entirely new
look and feel.
Consider a button.
Buttons on the system
have a lot in common with
the buttons you already know
and love from other platforms.
For example, like on macOS,
buttons on this platform
use a bordered style by default.
But buttons also have
some key differences
to adapt to the idioms
of the platform.
Let's zoom in to our simulator
and take a closer look.
Bordered buttons like these use
a vibrant material background.
And all buttons gain rich hover
effects that react to your eyes,
hands, and to pointer input.
They can also scale down
and provide audio feedback
when pressed.
And with buttons in places
like navigation bars,
they can automatically
display a tooltip
with your button's label
when people look at them.
Or consider TabView,
which hangs off the side
of your app,
providing quick
and easy navigation
without interfering
with your app's content.
And TabView expands
to display more detail,
like each tab's labels,
just by looking at it.
TabView is a prime example
of how SwiftUI
can take advantage of what makes
the platform unique,
like having your app's interface
react to where you're looking.
We've applied this same
thoughtful design
to all of the core
building blocks of an app,
from navigation
and presentations
to controls and interactions.
We provide these
intelligent platform defaults
so your app can fit right in
from the start,
allowing you to focus
on what makes your app great.
But we didn't stop there.
SwiftUI also includes
a whole suite of brand-new APIs
purpose-built
for a 3D environment.
And those APIs
start with scenes.
Recall that an app in SwiftUI
is made up of scenes,
and scenes
are made up of views.
Scenes form the top-level entry
points to your app,
like WindowGroup for displaying
one or more windows.
With spatial computing,
there are three kinds of scenes
that make up an app: windows,
volumes, and Full Spaces.
Windows are great
for building traditional
and familiar interfaces,
ranging from rich and complete
apps like Safari or Freeform,
to menus that serve
as an entry point
to more immersive
experiences like Mindfulness.
Volumes are a new
3D window style
purpose-built for displaying
objects or experiences
in a bounded space.
Volumes can also be displayed
alongside other apps,
making them a great tool
for building lightweight
3D experiences,
from previewing 3D models
with Quick Look
to playing board games
over FaceTime with your friends.
Finally, we have Full Spaces,
a brand-new way
to build rich, immersive apps.
Full spaces give your app
complete control,
hiding windows from
other apps and allowing you
to place your content anywhere.
Full spaces can augment
the real world
while keeping people grounded
in their surroundings,
or they can fully immerse people
in incredible new experiences.
From realistic rehearsals
in Keynote to thrilling
new kinds of games,
Full spaces unlock
a world of new possibilities.
And these scene types are
designed to be used together.
Each one is purpose-built
for different use cases,
and you can mix and match them
in whatever way makes sense
for your app.
You can present a volume
from a window,
like to show a lightweight
3D preview
of an architectural model.
Or you could present
a Full Space from a volume
to completely immerse people
in that model.
You can also use multiple scenes
of the same type,
which is a great way to organize
your app into separate pieces
that people can open
and close independently.
Let's dig a little deeper
into each of these scene types,
starting with windows.
I'm a big fan of astronomy,
and I've been working on an app
with some of
my fellow stargazers
to help others learn more about
the Earth and solar system.
Now, they've already gotten
a great start on this app,
building out this gorgeous
introductory page
in a window.
But I have big plans
to go further.
To show our window,
I'm using the same
WindowGroup API
that works on
all other platforms
By using WindowGroup,
I also automatically support
creating multiple windows,
just like on macOS or iPadOS.
Now, I've been really keen
to add a new feature to the app:
a library to collect
all kinds of fun facts
about our solar system
and universe
so my fellow space students
can keep on learning.
But I've been stuck
trying to figure out
where in the app
to put this feature.
To help answer that question,
let's break down
the structure of a window
into its building blocks.
Windows on the system start with
a beautiful glass background,
keeping people grounded
by letting your surroundings
show through while keeping
your app's contents easy to see.
Within my window, I can use
the same navigation containers
that I'm already familiar with
on other platforms.
For example, I can use a TabView
to organize my app
into several
top-level components
displayed on the leading edge
of my window.
I can also use navigation stacks
and split views
to help organize
my app's hierarchy
and display rich information,
following a similar structure
as iPadOS.
Lists are another powerful tool
for organizing information
with a beautiful new style
that fits right in.
And of course, I can add
interactivity to my app
using built-in controls like
buttons, toggles, and pickers.
Now, I think this Library view
would be a great use
of a TabView,
which is perfect for making
the top-level entry points
to my app
accessible at all times
so deeper knowledge
is always just a tap away.
To do that, I'll wrap my content
in a TabView,
and provide a tabItem
with a label for each tab.
Looks great!
TabView has a unique appearance,
hanging off the edge
of my window.
TabView is a great example
of a new concept
we've added to SwiftUI:
ornaments.
Ornaments allow you
to place accessory views
relative to your app's window,
and they can even extend
outside the window's bounds.
These are great for displaying
additional controls
that don't belong
in the window itself
and can avoid interfering
with your app's content.
And we can even create
our own ornaments
using the new ornament modifier.
Let's take a look at
the Library detail view
I've been working on.
I've already gotten started
on this page,
broken up into a few sections:
some summary text,
a grid of interesting stats,
and a horizontally scrolling
list of fun facts.
But these sections
are missing something.
To figure out what,
let's take a closer look
at our app's materials.
Windows by default are grounded
in a beautiful,
new glass background.
Glass is designed to compose
with new, vibrant materials
that help provide
a visual hierarchy for your app.
Glass adapts automatically
to the environment
to keep content legible
no matter where it's used,
allowing your app
to look great in any setting.
This means that
on this platform,
there is no dark or light
appearance for your app.
Materials do
the hard work for you.
Let's see how
we can use materials
to make my Library tab
fit in and improve legibility,
starting with the stats grid.
My stats grid section
is currently just made up
of a VStack with a title
and the grid itself.
Let's try giving it
a material background
and make this card really pop.
To do that, I've used
the regular material,
which adds a vibrant,
darker background
on top of our window's glass
that grounds the shape
of my card and improves
legibility for the detail text.
I've used a rounded rect shape
and added some padding
to make the card
feel just right.
I'll apply the same treatment
to our fun fact cards as well.
That's looking much better!
Next, let's turn
to our fun fact cards
and zoom in for a closer look.
This card is built as a button
that can show more details
about the fact when I press it.
I've also used
a custom button style
that provides that nice
material background.
The button's contents
are composed of a title,
detail body, and a footnote
inviting people
to tap to learn more.
The "Learn more" text is looking
a little too heavy, though.
To fix that, I'll use
the secondary foreground style
for my text.
Notice that this secondary style
automatically adapts within
our background material
to use a beautiful
new vibrant treatment,
giving greater visual weight
to my content
while still keeping
that secondary text legible.
These hierarchical shape styles
are great for expressing
relative visual weight,
letting SwiftUI take care
of automatically adapting
the specific materials
to use based on context.
Use them and the other rich
shape style and material APIs
in your apps to create
gorgeous interfaces
that look great in any context
and on any platform.
Next, let's turn to interaction.
With spatial computing,
there are brand-new ways
to interact with apps.
The most common form
of interaction
is to simply look at an element
and use an indirect
pinch gesture to perform a tap.
You can also directly interact
with apps using your hands
just by reaching out
and touching them.
And with a connected trackpad
or a hand gesture,
you can use a pointer
for the most precise input.
The system also works with
a connected hardware keyboard,
with support for
keyboard shortcuts, Focus,
and key modifiers to supercharge
productivity in your apps.
Finally, the system supports
the same great
accessibility technologies that
you're already familiar with
from other platforms, like
VoiceOver and Switch Control.
The best part
is that SwiftUI controls
are built to be accessible
out of the box,
doing much of the heavy lifting
for you,
which allows everyone to get
the same great experience
when using your apps.
The gestures you're
already familiar with
in SwiftUI work great,
adapting automatically
to each form of interaction,
like TapGesture and DragGesture.
And we've added some brand-new
gestures to enable
all-new kinds of rich
3D interactions
like RotateGesture3D to rotate
a view in all three dimensions,
using two hands
or a connected trackpad.
And of course, all of the same
accessibility APIs
and technologies from other
platforms work great too,
from VoiceOver and rotors to
Dynamic Type and Invert Colors.
And many of these features
have been reimagined
for the platform.
Like Dwell Control,
which allows people to use
and navigate your apps
using only their eyes.
To learn more about these
great features
and how to make your app
accessible to everyone,
check out "Create accessible
spatial experiences."
A critical tool to making
interaction feel easy
and intuitive with spatial
computing are hover effects.
For example, simply by looking
at an interactive view,
the system shows a subtle
highlight effect over the view
to provide feedback
that you can interact with it.
These effects
adapt automatically
to each form of input,
giving people confidence
in what they're
interacting with.
Hover effects are useful
not only to provide
responsive feedback, but also
to assist with targeting.
And hover effects are
the only way to make your app
react to exactly where
people are looking.
These effects are applied
outside of your app's process
to respect people's privacy.
Hover effects are added
automatically to most controls,
like buttons, toggles,
text fields, and more.
If you use the built-in styles
provided by SwiftUI,
you'll get these effects
in your app automatically.
If you're using
a custom control or style,
make sure to add hover effects
to make them feel responsive
and easy to use.
Let's return to those fun fact
cards I've added to my app
and check out how they work
with hover effects.
Those cards are looking great,
but there's one big problem.
Because I'm using
a custom ButtonStyle,
I'm now in charge of providing
my own hover effect.
Without one, there's no feedback
that these cards
are actually interactive.
The good news is
that's super easy to fix.
My ButtonStyle currently
just adds some padding
and a custom material background
to the button's label.
To fix that missing
hover feedback,
I'll add the hoverEffect
modifier to my ButtonStyle.
This selects
an automatic effect for me
that is appropriate
for the context.
In this case,
that'll be the highlight effect.
Let's take a closer look.
When I look at
these card buttons,
I now get a nice,
subtle highlight effect
that makes it clear
that they're interactive.
The effect even automatically
matches the shape
of my button's background,
ensuring that nobody misses
a chance to learn a fun fact.
There's a lot more to cover
about building
great windowed apps.
To go further, check out
"Elevate your windowed app
for spatial computing,"
where you'll walk through
updating a multiplatform app,
learn how to add ornaments,
dive deeper on hover effects,
materials, and more.
Next let's take our app to
the next dimension with volumes.
I want to help my fellow
outer space observers
gain a new perspective
on the planet that we call home.
And a volume is perfect
for doing just that.
To add a volume to my app,
I'll use the same
WindowGroup scene
that I used for my main window,
and simply specify
a volumetric window style.
I can also provide a default
3D size for the window
so it can fit our content.
Let's check out
our volume in the simulator.
Within my volume's content,
I'm using the new Model3D API
from RealityKit
to display the 3D Earth model
our designer has put together.
And with Model3D,
it's really just that easy
to add 3D content to my app.
A Model3D is similar
to an Image,
making it easy to load and
display beautiful 3D content.
Unlike an Image, a Model3D
always loads asynchronously,
as 3D content can take time
to load and be ready to display.
Similar to the AsyncImage view,
Model3D can automatically
display a placeholder view
while we wait
for the content to load.
Or I can take full control
and display my own
placeholder instead.
It's worth taking a moment
to notice here
that Model3D is just another
SwiftUI View.
Bringing 3D into your SwiftUI
app builds on the same concepts
you're already familiar with
with natural extensions
to the layout system,
visual effects,
gestures, and more.
Let's build on this example
so we can understand how.
I want to add some controls
to help bring the Earth to life.
I've already built out
my control panel UI,
and I'd like to place it
in front of my Earth model.
To do that, I can simply use
a ZStack layout.
Layouts like ZStack
are automatically aware
of the depth
of your content,
just as they are
with width and height.
And Model3D by default is sized
to fit its content
in all three dimensions,
just like an image is in 2D.
In fact, the entire layout
system is aware
of your content's depth
and its available space
and adjusts
your layouts accordingly.
And there are even new modifiers
to control how depth behaves
with layout in your apps,
like the new padding3D
modifier to add spacing
between your SwiftUI views
along their front or back faces,
which we can use here
to give our controls
some room to breathe.
Remember that volumes
are designed to be viewed
from any angle,
so it's important to think
about how your app's content
is arranged
in all three dimensions.
Finally, to make my controls
look great and feel grounded,
I'll make sure to use the new
glassBackgroundEffect modifier,
giving it the same beautiful
glass treatment we had
in our standard window before.
Now these controls
are looking ready to rock.
Another thing I'd love to add
to our 3D globe is an easy way
to spin the globe
to a random place,
which is my favorite way to plan
my next vacation destination.
To do that, I'll add a 3D
rotation effect to my Model3D,
in this case about the y-axis.
And I'll use a state variable
to track the rotation to use.
Then I'll add a tap gesture
and when it fires,
I'll change the rotation
by some random amount
with a new
bouncy spring animation.
Let's give this a spin.
Ah yes,
the western hemisphere.
That really narrows down
my summer plans!
Notice that the rotation effect
we just applied
to our globe is truly 3D.
We've upgraded these
geometry effects
you already know how to use
with new 3D capabilities,
including scales, offsets,
and custom 3D transforms.
Now this is already a great way
to check out the globe,
but I think we can make it
even better.
To do that,
I'll use RealityView,
a new SwiftUI View
that provides easy access
to the full power of RealityKit.
With RealityView,
I provide a closure
to load and make
my RealityKit content.
To display my Earth model,
I'll create a ModelEntity
and await until it loads.
And once it finishes loading,
I'll add it to my RealityView's
content to display it.
Notice that I can use
async-await
directly in my
RealityView's closure.
Just like with Model3D,
it will automatically display
a placeholder until
my content has loaded.
Now that I've loaded
my Earth entity,
I have access to the rich
library of RealityKit APIs
to make my content really shine.
In this case, I want to add
some lighting to the Earth
to give it
a sunnier disposition.
I've already written some
RealityKit code
to add my special
image-based lighting,
so I'll call that here.
Now that is looking delightful!
There's so much more
to cover with RealityView.
With RealityView,
it's never been easier
to blend the worlds
of user interfaces
and rich 3D experiences.
RealityKit allows you to add
all kinds of rich behaviors
like custom materials
and shaders,
physics and complex animations,
and so much more.
To learn more about RealityView
and RealityKit,
we've prepared several talks
that go much deeper.
Check out "Build spatial
experiences with RealityKit"
when you're ready dive in.
For now, let's focus on two
cool features of RealityView:
gestures and attachments.
With RealityView, SwiftUI
gestures work automatically,
making it easier than ever to
bring your 3D content to life.
I want to build on
the tap gesture we added before
to also place a marker
on the globe
based on where I tapped
so I know exactly
where to travel to next.
To do that,
I'll use a SpatialTapGesture,
which now gives me
the full 3D location of the tap.
To help me identify where
in the Earth's entity I tapped,
I'll use the new
targetedToAnyEntity
gesture modifier.
This provides me
with the context I need,
like the entity I tapped on
and the location relative
to that entity,
which I'll use to look up
the location for my pin.
To display the pin on my globe,
I can use RealityView
attachments.
Attachments are great for mixing
custom SwiftUI views together
inline with RealityKit entities.
I can add other SwiftUI views
directly within my RealityView's
attachments closure,
making them available to place
as RealityKit entities
anywhere in my RealityView.
I'll add a pin attachment here
and give it a tag
that I can use to identify it.
Then in my update closure,
I'll look up the entity
for my attachment
and add it to my RealityView's
content to display it.
And then I'll place that entity
to match the tap location.
Let's give this another spin!
Looks like I'd better
get packing!
We're so excited
about the possibilities
for building amazing
volumetric apps
that we've prepared
an entire talk
to help you take your SwiftUI
apps to the next dimension,
where you'll learn more
on using SwiftUI
together with RealityKit,
building rich 3D interactions,
adding depth to your layouts,
and more.
Finally, let's take this app
beyond the window
with Full Spaces,
a brand-new way to build rich,
immersive 3D experiences
using SwiftUI.
With a Full Space,
you take full control.
You can place content
anywhere in the environment
to augment people's surroundings
in creative new ways.
Or you can fully immerse people
by hiding their surroundings
to create stunning
new experiences.
Let's dive into space and bring
our solar system to life.
I've already gotten a head start
on this page in our main window,
inviting our armchair astronauts
to view outer space
for themselves.
Now I just need
to create my space
and wire up this
button for liftoff.
To add a Full Space
to my app,
I'll simply add a new
ImmersiveSpace scene
as I did with my WindowGroups.
Within its body,
I'll provide a root view
for my space's content.
I'll also provide an ID
for my space
so I can programmatically
open it from our main window.
To open this space,
I'll use the new
openImmersiveSpace
environment action.
Within my button,
I'll call that action
and pass in the ID
for our space.
And just like that...
...we have liftoff!
This is a great start.
I can get up close to the Earth
in a way that I never could
before,
letting me really appreciate
all the rich detail,
like those realistic clouds.
But there's something
missing here.
I want to feel truly immersed
in this space.
To do that, I'll use
a powerful tool of spaces:
immersion styles.
A Full Space can come in one
of several immersion styles,
and you can transition between
these styles on the fly.
With mixed immersion,
your space's content
coexists with the real world,
which makes it great
for lightweight experiences
and augmenting
people's surroundings.
With full immersion,
your app can become
fully immersive
and hide people's surroundings,
transporting them
into stunning new worlds.
And progressive immersion
is a great middle ground
for experiences that
keep people grounded
in the real world
in their periphery.
With progressive immersion,
people can also use
the Digital Crown on the device
to dial in exactly how much
immersion feels right to them.
Now I think a fully immersive
space would be the perfect fit
for my app to make
it truly feel out of this world.
To do that, I'll return
to my ImmersiveSpace scene
and add in the new
immersionStyle modifier
with the full immersion style.
Here I provide both a list
of supported styles
and a current selection,
allowing me
to change the style on the fly.
When I use full immersion,
the system completely hides
people's real-world
surroundings.
So I need to provide
a virtual environment
in which to immerse
the people using my app.
And of course,
what better environment to use
than outer space itself?
We'll reach for the stars
with our environment
by creating a new RealityView
to display our star field.
Within our RealityView's
make closure,
I'll load our star field entity,
and when it's ready,
I'll add it to
the RealityView's content.
Then I'll add
the Starfield view
to our solar system's body
alongside our Earth and Sun.
Let's zoom in for a closer look.
Now this is making me feel
truly starstruck.
To take my space
to the next level,
I can use ARKit.
ARKit is a powerful
framework deeply integrated
with the system,
providing access
to rich real-time understanding
of people's real-world
surroundings,
with APIs like world tracking
and scene understanding
that allow you to place content
on real-world surfaces.
And hand tracking,
an incredible new tool
that you can use to build
custom hand gestures,
interact with your
content using realistic physics,
and so much more.
To learn more about how you can
use ARKit in your spaces,
check out "Meet ARKit
for spatial computing."
Now I'm so excited
about the possibilities
that ARKit unlocks with my app
that I wanted to give you
a sneak peek of one more feature
that I've been working on.
By integrating ARKit
into my space,
I was able to implement
a new hand gesture
to summon the Earth.
So you can hold the world
in the palm of your hand.
We're just scratching
the surface of what you can do
with Full Spaces.
And we've prepared another talk
for you to launch into space.
Check out "Go beyond
the window with SwiftUI"
to dive deeper on
the fundamentals of spaces
and learn about advanced
tools like adding effects
to your surroundings,
displaying virtual hands,
integrating with SharePlay,
and more.
And if you need full control
over rendering the content
in your space,
you can do that too using Metal
and the new CompositorServices
framework.
Check out "Discover Metal for
immersive apps" to learn more.
We can't wait to check out
all the amazing new apps
you're going to build
using SwiftUI.
From beautiful windows
to an entirely new dimension
with volumes,
to incredible immersive
experiences with Full Space,
a world of new possibilities
await you.
If you're ready to dive deeper,
we've got even more great talks
for you to check out,
like
"Principles of Spatial Design,"
where you can learn more
about how to design your app
to really shine.
And if you have existing
UIKit code
you want to bring
to the platform,
check out "Meet UIKit
for spatial computing."
Thanks for watching, and have
a blast with spatial computing!
♪