♪ ♪
Patrick: Hi, I'm Patrick,
an engineer on the Device Management team.
Together with my colleague Jonathan,
I'm delighted to share with you
the new features we have
for managing Apple devices.
We love seeing Apple devices being used
every day at work and school.
Whether this is to teach a subject
to a class
or enabling and simplifying
business workflows.
We want to help IT administrators
to make it easy for their users
to do something great with their devices.
In this session we'll be covering
many of the new features
that will help you
to manage and deploy at scale.
Many will be covered in this section,
but before we dive in,
I want to highlight a few other sessions
that cover areas
where we've additionally
made significant improvements.
Managed Apple IDs became more powerful
and versatile this year
with updates to Continuity, Apple Wallet,
and iCloud Keychain.
And IT administrators get
additional controls to make it easier
for their users to sign in to the apps
and services they need at work.
A Managed Apple ID can also be used
in more places to enroll a device
while keeping personal
and work data separated.
And to allow even more organizations
to leverage those benefits,
we are also adding OpenID Connect support
in Apple School Manager
and Apple Business Manager.
This allows federation with any identity
provider supporting this protocol.
Be sure to check out session "Do more with
Managed Apple IDs" to learn more.
With the addition of iCloud Keychain
to Managed Apple IDs
and new Declarative Device Management
configuration options,
businesses can now go passwordless
with passkeys.
Our dedicated session
"Deploy passkeys at work"
provides more information on that topic.
Declarative device management
has been significantly enhanced
and supports new ways to deploy
applications, certificates,
and on macOS, even manage
common service configuration files.
Software Update takes advantage
of declarative device management
and now allows IT administrators
to enforce software updates
to specific deadlines
with improved user transparency.
Watch session "Advances in declarative
device management" for in-depth details.
And this year, we are expanding
device management to Apple Watch.
Apple Watch can now be enrolled into MDM,
supporting even more
institutional use-cases.
The session "Discover watchOS management"
has more details on how it works
and what you can do.
For this session we'll focus on
how macOS can support organizations
to more easily meet
their security requirements
and how you can use your identity provider
in even more places,
how iOS and iPadOS are better supporting
common use-cases
and what's new with cellular networks.
Throughout the session we will also
discover how Apple Configurator can help
to reduce manual steps
and increase automation.
Let's get started with macOS.
To tell you all about it,
I'm going to hand over
to my colleague Jonathan.
Jonathan:
Thank you, Patrick.
Hi, I'm Jonathan Broskey, an Engineer
on the Device Management team.
I'm really excited to be here today
to tell you about
some awesome new device
management features in macOS 14.
Starting with Automated Device Enrollment.
This is a great way to provide
a seamless enrollment
and setup experience for your users.
However, we understand
that organizations want to ensure
certain security configurations
are in place
even before the Mac is enrolled
and the user logs in for the first time.
For example, organizations want
to make sure FileVault is turned on,
the device is on a specific version
of the operating system,
and enrolled in MDM.
We have some great improvements
to the Automated Device Enrollment process
this year.
Starting with FileVault.
macOS 14 allows MDM to require FileVault
enablement right during Setup Assistant.
IT administrators can chose whether
to show the FileVault recovery key
during Setup Assistant
or optionally escrow it to MDM.
Additionally, MDM can require the device
to be on a specific operating system
version in order to enroll.
This ensures that devices are on
the necessary OS version
before being put into production.
The MDM will send a JSON 403 response
when the device requests
the enrollment profile.
If the minimum operating system version
is needed,
the user will be guided through a process
of updating their Mac.
Restarts will be performed automatically.
Once completed,
the Mac returns to Setup Assistant
and the user can finish the enrollment
and setup process.
Lastly, we have added safeguards
to ensure the user completes
Automated Device Enrollment
once a network connection is established.
Currently, in the case where
the Mac is not connected to a network
during the initial setup,
the MDM enrollment is skipped.
A notification will appear
requesting to be enrolled.
This year, we have changed
the entire user experience
by launching into
a full screen Setup Assistant.
After a network is connected,
the user will be presented with
"Setup Assistant" giving them two options:
continuing the enrollment, or "Not Now"
which will allow the user eight hours
before they will be required
to enroll in MDM.
Something to note,
that user can still enroll at any time
by going to System Settings.
Now with the changes to macOS 14,
the user and the IT administrator can
ensure that the data is secure,
the device is on
the proper operating system,
and the device is managed in MDM.
We think you're really going to like
these new additions
to Automated Device Enrollment.
Now that the device is configured,
and enrolled in MDM,
you will need access
to your Applications and Websites.
User authentication is an important aspect
to ensure only authorized individuals
get access to their corporate data.
However, oftentimes this requires
different digital identities.
Platform Single Sign-On helps with this.
In macOS Ventura,
Platform Single Sign-On made it possible
to authenticate once with an account
from the organization's Identity Provider
and get access to all services
a user should have access to.
This year,
we are taking Platform SSO even further
with exciting new capabilities
that allow users to use their corporate
identity in even more places in macOS.
System Settings can now show
the status of Platform SSO.
You can repair your registration
or reauthenticate
with your Identity Provider.
Many organizations that use shared devices
also want to create new users at login.
Platform SSO now also supports
on-demand creation of a local account,
when a new user authenticates
at the login window
using a credential from
their organization's Identity Provider.
It's enabled by using a shared device key
that allows the device
to maintain a trusted connection
to the Identity Provider
independent of a specific user.
Certain requirements need to be in place
for the local account creation to happen.
The Mac needs to be able to connect
to the Identity Provider.
The device also needs to be at
login window with FileVault unlocked.
The organization's MDM must support
Bootstrap Tokens.
If all of those conditions are met,
users can use their Identity Provider
username and password
or SmartCard to create an account.
With this new support,
SmartCards can now be used
to authenticate at the login window
and screen saver.
After authentication,
Identity Provider groups can be used
to assign user permissions.
The MDM profile can define
which access level will be used:
standard user permissions,
administrator privileges,
or permissions defined
by the group membership.
The same profile can also define
how identity provider groups
map to local groups on the Mac.
With network authorization, we expand
the concept of group management
to users which do not have a local account
and allow them to be used
at authorization prompts.
Bear in mind that non-local users
cannot be used for authorization prompts
specifically asking
for the current logged in user,
or require a user with SecureToken
or ownership rights.
Let's look at an example of
how this could be configured.
In this Extensible SSO profile,
Platform SSO group membership
is configured
in the new Platform SSO dictionary.
Group membership is applied to local users
when the UserAuthorization mode is Groups.
The same groups are also used for network
accounts when EnableAuthorization is true.
For AdministratorGroups, if the local
or non-local user is part of a group
listed in this array, they can be used
at admin authorization prompts.
AuthorizationGroups are specific groups
used to grant access
to otherwise restricted rights
as defined by the authorization database.
In this example, the user gets the ability
to modify printer configurations
in System Settings,
without requiring
administrative privileges.
An entry in the AdditionalGroups array
creates a local group
if it doesn't exist and makes it available
in the local directory service.
In this example,
sudo is configured to use this group.
Another part of user authentication
is password management.
I'm excited to touch on a few additions
we have made in this area.
Securing passwords is essential
in a corporate or educational environment.
Some environments have
more complex password requirements
than what can be configured
with the existing options.
This year we are adding even more
flexibility by allowing password policies
to be defined as regular expressions.
Since regular expressions
can be difficult to work with,
you should still use existing
password policy options whenever possible.
We have also added stronger
Password Compliance management.
For macOS 14, we've changed the way
Password compliance is communicated.
When a stricter password policy
is installed,
a notification will be displayed
advising that the user's password
may not be compliant.
The notification will only appear
if the password may not meet
the installed payload policy.
Compliance will be checked
during the next time the user logs in,
and if the password is not compliant,
a notification will be displayed.
The user will be given an option
to change now or change later.
If the user decides
to change the password at a later time,
the same notification will be shown
every time the user logs in
until the password is compliant.
Now let's take a look
at some new restrictions
that help secure your Mac even further.
Sometimes organizations want to restrict
what settings
users or administrators can configure
on their Mac.
In the past,
entire System Preference panes were hidden
to fulfill this requirement.
With the introduction of System Settings,
we were able to implement
a granular management approach.
Instead of hiding entire panes,
the administrator can restrict
modifications of a specific setting
which now shows a label
about its management state.
Now in macOS 14,
new restrictions prevent users
from modifying Apple ID Logins
and Internet Accounts,
adding local user accounts,
and many more,
like preventing Time Machine Backups.
Last year we introduced
Managed Device Attestation,
a security feature
that uses the attestation capabilities
of the Secure Enclave.
A device provides strong evidence
about itself when making a request.
Managed Device Attestation means
legitimate devices
reliably access resources,
and attackers are foiled.
It does this by providing these assurances
about the device.
This is a building block
that only provides security benefits
if the deployment model built around
managed devices use attestations properly.
Here are some deployment models
to consider for your organization.
This first model proves
the device's identity to the MDM server
and does not involve other servers.
There is an ACME server integrated
into the MDM server,
which issues certificates
only for MDM purposes.
The MDM server also uses
DeviceInformation attestation
to keep tabs on the device's properties.
In this model it is important to use
both the ACME attestation
and the DeviceInformation attestation
to know all about the device
it is managing
to make sure
the security requirements are addressed.
The second model puts the most authority
on the ACME server.
The ACME server performs trust evaluation
starting with properties' attestation,
and decides whether to issue
a certificate or not.
The issued certificate can contain
whatever your organization needs.
Subsequent servers
that the device connects to,
also known as relying parties,
don't need to perform
any additional tasks.
With the third model, the ACME server
doesn't perform trust evaluation.
Instead, it simply copies
the device properties
from the attestation
into the issued certificate.
It's up to the relying parties to perform
their own trust evaluation.
Something to note,
you can combine concepts from each model
to suit your environment.
And this year, I am so happy to announce
that we've brought
Managed Device Attestation to macOS!
Just like iOS, it supports all the
features of Managed Device attestation.
Also on macOS, ACME attestation
provisions hardware-bound keys
based upon
those same reliable device properties.
As a reminder, hardware-bound keys are
stored in the data protection keychain.
These keys can be used
with services such as VPN,
802.1x, Kerberos, Exchange, and MDM.
For more information
on how Managed Device attestation works,
please visit last year's WWDC session,
"Discover Managed Device Attention."
We are also adding new properties
to the attestation certificate,
which include
SIP Status, secure boot status,
and whether third-party kernel extensions
are allowed.
We are also adding new properties
for all platforms
that support Managed Device Attestation.
The new attributes will attest:
the low-level boot loader version,
operating system version,
and Software Update Device ID.
A new Secure Enclave Enrollment ID
property
associates the attestation
with an enrollment.
If two different attestations
have the same ID,
you have strong evidence that those
attestations came from the same device.
If the device unenrolls and reenrolls,
the IDs change.
Different servers can prove they
are communicating with the same device
by comparing
Secure Enclave Enrollment IDs.
None of these new properties
are device-identifying,
so they are available
for all enrollment types.
We have covered a lot,
from Configuration Profile Updates
to New Restrictions,
but there's even more
management updates to discover.
Now, let's take a look at the enhancements
we have made to Application management.
Applications installed via MDM
have been supported for years.
macOS Big Sur introduced
managed applications
which support configuration and feedback,
automatic removal on unenrollement,
and the ability to remove
the application via MDM.
Previously,
for an application to be manageable,
the package must contain
a single application
that is installed into /Applications.
With macOS 14,
we are expanding that functionality
of the InstallApplication command
to allow the package to install
multiple Applications.
Any application the package installs
into /Applications
will be considered managed,
and can be removed individually via MDM.
Something to note,
content installed outside of /Applications
will not be tracked,
so we strongly recommend
using self-contained applications.
Wow, we have covered a lot
of awesome macOS updates,
I am now going to hand it over to Patrick
to talk to you
about some enhancements
coming to iOS and iPadOS.
Take it away, Patrick.
Patrick: Thank you, Jonathan.
I'm delighted to cover
some exciting enhancements
we have made
to managing iOS and iPadOS devices.
In many deployments, devices are handed
from one user to the next
on a fairly frequent basis.
Although devices can be erased remotely,
getting them back into service
is a manual process,
as it requires someone
to physically touch them
and take them through Setup Assistant.
This year we are removing
the additional manual step
with the introduction of Return to Service
for iOS and iPadOS.
This is how it works:
The MDM server sends
an Erase command to the device.
The command includes
additional information
which allows the device to reset,
securely erase all data,
connect to Wi-Fi, enroll into MDM,
and get back to the Home Screen,
ready to be used.
To implement this behavior,
an additional dictionary can be added
to the EraseDevice command.
This dictionary needs to include
the profile of a Wi-Fi configuration
to allow the device to connect to,
once erased.
As an alternative, the device can also
connect to the Internet
by different means,
like a tethered connection.
Secondly,
the dictionary should include a profile
with the necessary enrollment information.
In case the device is registered
in Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager,
this profile can be omitted,
which triggers the device to check for
an enrollment profile during activation.
As part of the process, the previously
selected language and region get applied.
I now want to touch on
a couple of enhancements
which we think will be specifically
relevant for educational organizations.
Getting a class started can be
a stressful process for the teacher.
They have to ensure
everyone's signed in and ready to go.
This is even more challenging
for larger classes.
To make the process of signing in
easier and quicker,
we are introducing easy student sign-in.
To initiate the sign-in flow,
the teacher needs to be signed into
their managed Apple ID.
Additionally,
the student needs to have their iPad open
to the iCloud sign-in view
within Settings.
iPads are brought close to each other
and the teacher's iPad opens up
a sign-in proximity card.
The teacher taps on
"Continue to Sign In Student."
The proximity card transitions
to a camera scan on the teacher's iPad
and the view on the student's iPad
changes to a particle cloud.
The teacher then scans the particle cloud.
The teacher continues on
to the student selection process.
The teacher can either select a class
to see the current student roster,
or, they can instead use the search bar
to look up a student they had in mind.
In this illustration, the teacher taps
on the "Mathematics" class.
A list of students in the selected class
is appropriately shown.
The teacher then subsequently selects
Allison to sign in to the student iPad.
After the iPad is set up,
the teacher gets a successful confirmation
and the student iPad
is signed in successfully.
To use the streamlined login process,
multiple prerequisites
need to be in place.
First, the teacher and student
need to be part
of the same Apple School Manager location.
Second, both devices need to be
in physical proximity of each other.
And lastly, if the students are using
personal devices,
they first need to authorize the teacher
in a new prompt
to enable this functionality.
We have also made it easier
to log into a Shared iPad.
With the new AwaitUserConfiguration,
an MDM solution can keep the device
in the login process
after user authentication
until all necessary configurations
have been applied.
This is similar to a process
already available on devices
using Automated Device Enrollment
and does require for the MDM server
to release the device from this state
via a specific MDM command.
To streamline the login flow even further,
MDM solutions can make use of the new
'SkipLanguageAndLocaleSetupForNewUsers'
key which prevents the device from showing
the respective selection screens
during the first log on,
and instead applies the system defaults.
In case a Shared iPad is used
by temporary users only,
the device now honors the quota
configuration for this temporary user.
This allows IT administrators to reserve
sufficient space to assign new apps
and content while a user is logged in.
Now we shift gears and are going to look
at another key element
of many iPhone and iPad deployments:
cellular connectivity.
We know that many organizations
are looking forward to leverage
the great new capabilities that private
5G and LTE networks have to offer.
Common use cases include providing
network connectivity in large areas
where Wi-Fi may not be available
or feasible.
Since last year,
iPad devices have supported private LTE
and non-standalone 5G networks
with the ability to install eSIMs
through device management.
We are adding the same features
to 5G-capable iPhone models
and on both platforms, the ability to
connect to private standalone 5G networks.
Searching and associating
with a private network
requires an active SIM
and can be an energy consuming task.
Specifically,
when the network is not available.
Thanks to our tight integration
of hardware and software,
we were able to create
a power efficient method
to enable the SIM only when needed.
This allows organizations to define a set
of geolocations that the device monitors,
and if it enters one of them,
only then will the SIM
of the private network get activated.
Based on network quality measurements,
iPhone and iPad devices
intelligently select
the best cellular SIM
for data connectivity.
As an optional value,
an organization can also define
that a device prefers the private network
even over a potentially available
Wi-Fi network.
We are also adding
5G network slicing support.
This allows individual managed apps
to be assigned to a network slice
which may provide specific
network capabilities
and characteristics
to optimize the app experience.
The assignment is done using the new
CellularSliceUUID app attribute
in either the MDM app installation command
or declarative app configuration.
The string value of the network slice
to put into the key
needs to be provided
by the supporting carrier.
Something to note is that 5G network
slicing will not be used
if either the specific app or the entire
device is configured to use a VPN.
To conclude our updates on connectivity,
I'm excited to make you aware
of a new way to provide secure access
to enterprise network resources:
relays.
Relays are secure proxies
that are natively supported on iOS,
iPadOS, macOS, and tvOS.
If you're using a VPN
to access your enterprise resources,
relays are an alternative that can provide
a better user experience
and are easier to manage.
Relays can be configured by an MDM
with a new profile payload type,
without needing to install an app,
or can be configured
using the NERelayManager API
in the NetworkExtension framework.
These configurations can apply
to managed apps, domains,
or the entire device,
and can be used in conjunction
with iCloud Private Relay
to enhance user privacy
while accessing enterprise resources.
To learn more about this great new
built-in way to secure your traffic,
please watch session "Ready, set, relay:
Protect app traffic with network relays."
There are many more
new configuration possibilities
like requiring a minimum version
during automated device enrollment.
In addition to the ones common with macOS,
there are also
some platform-specific enhancements
like configuring 802.1X authentication
for ethernet networks on iOS,
iPadOS, and even tvOS
and allowing tap-to-pay applications
to be used more easily and securely.
Just as a reminder, in a future release,
we will execute on
previously announced deprecations.
We will remove the APN payload,
as well as top-level cellular keys
from the DeviceInformation query.
Please use the com.apple.cellular payload
and ServiceSubscriptions response instead.
Again, in a future release
we will also change
the listed restrictions
to require supervision.
In addition, some will only apply
to a personal Apple ID
logged in on the device.
There is even more
I haven't had a chance to talk about,
like added VPN support on Apple TV.
Please be sure to check out
the documentation for all the details.
We additionally have exciting news
about Apple Configurator for iPhone.
Since its introduction,
Apple Configurator for iPhone
has been used by many IT administrators
to add devices
to their Apple School Manager
or Apple Business Manager organizations.
Adding a device is a two-step process.
First, the device needs to be added
to the organization.
Secondly, a user with the role
of Device Enrollment Manager
needs to sign in to the web portal
and assign the device
to the correct MDM server.
This year, we are allowing users
to automatically assign each device
to an MDM server
right in Apple Configurator.
The user has three options to choose from
for assigning devices;
don't assign to an MDM server,
assign to the default MDM server
configured for its type,
for example Mac or iPad,
or assign to one
of the organization's MDM servers.
The list of available MDM servers
is provided automatically
after the user signs in
with their Managed Apple ID.
Let's take a look at Apple Configurator
for Mac as well.
It's a great tool for configuring
iOS and iPadOS devices
and helps perform actions
on multiple tethered devices at once.
This year we are making those workflows
even more automated
with the addition of Shortcut actions.
Using Shortcuts, IT administrators
can build powerful custom shortcuts
with Apple Configurator's actions.
We are adding Shortcut actions
to update, restore,
erase, and prepare
iPhone and iPad devices.
Shortcuts can be triggered to run
when a device attaches or detaches.
If you combine those additions
with actions an MDM provides,
you will have a very powerful
automation toolbox.
Let's look at an example
of a simple shortcut
that leverages Apple Configurator actions.
Here, we see a basic shortcut
for provisioning an iPad.
First, we reset the device
and install the latest version of iPadOS.
The device then uses
Automated Device Enrollment
to enroll in MDM and can take the device
completely through Setup Assistant,
eventually landing it on the Home Screen.
Because the Mac is sharing
its internet connection
and has content caching enabled,
commands are received from the MDM server
and apps begin to install quickly.
Once done,
the shortcut updates the MDM server
with the asset tag number
from a separate csv file.
Once you perfect your shortcut,
you can use new Shortcuts settings
in Apple Configurator
to run it every time
you attach or detach a device.
If you're an MDM developer,
we think it's important to provide
easy integration with Shortcuts.
Your customers will want to easily
interact with your MDM server
to send commands
from your product to the device.
They will also want to send information,
like an asset tag number,
back to your product
to update a device's information.
We can't wait to see what you will do
with the new possibilities!
This concludes our updates
on iOS and iPadOS.
We've covered many enhancements
during this session,
so let's take a moment to recap.
As Jonathan has mentioned,
macOS provides new options to
organizations
to ensure devices are in
the desired state.
We also covered great new ways
to create and manage local user accounts
based on your identity system.
Managed Device Attestation
comes to the Mac
and gets additional attributes
on all supported platforms.
And for iOS we have looked at an easy way
to put a device back into service
and great enhancements
to classroom setups and Shared iPad.
We also spoke about increased support
of private cellular networks
on both iPhone and iPad.
We additionally looked at how
Apple Configurator streamlines the process
of registering devices,
and its new options
to create powerful automations.
We can't wait for you to use
the great new management capabilities,
and we look forward to your feedback.
Thank you very much for joining us.
♪ ♪