♪ ♪
Dima: Hello, and welcome
to "What's new in UIKit in iOS 17”.
I'm Dima, an engineering manager
on the UIKit team.
UIKit, the powerful framework
behind your applications,
has been upgraded
to support new features for iOS 17.
In this video,
I will guide you through:
New key features
and core architectural improvements,
advances in building interfaces
for all users
irrespective of the language setting,
improvements for iPadOS apps,
as well as numerous general enhancements
included in the release.
We've introduced
major architectural enhancements to UIKit,
making it easier
to create powerful applications,
as well as dramatically improving
integration with SwiftUI.
I am going to guide you
through 5 key new features.
I'll go over the Xcode previews support,
view controller life cycle updates,
advances in the trait system,
animated symbol images,
and a new API
to represent empty state in your apps.
First, a big change.
You can use Xcode previews
directly with UIKit.
To take advantage of this feature,
use the Preview macro
to specify the name of the preview
and return a view controller.
I can set any properties
on the view controller
just to configure
and populate the preview with data.
You can also preview UIViews directly,
no view controller necessary.
Previews help you visualize UI components
and give immediate feedback
as you iterate on your code.
And once your app has been created,
Xcode Previews enable testing
across an array
of configurations and settings.
Next, I'd like to cover
an important improvement
to the view controller lifecycle
during appearance transitions,
such as when you present
a view controller,
or push or pop in a navigation controller.
There's a new view controller callback
named viewIsAppearing,
which is called after viewWillAppear
but before viewDidAppear.
viewIsAppearing is the best place
to do things each time the view appears.
When it is called,
both the view controller and the view
have an up-to-date trait collection.
Additionally,
the view has been added to the hierarchy
and has been laid out by its superview.
This makes viewIsAppearing
an ideal callback to run code
that depends on the view's
initial geometry,
including its size.
Lastly, this new viewIsAppearing method
back-deploys all the way to iOS 13,
so you can take advantage of it even if
your app runs on older versions of iOS.
Here is an illustration of how the new
viewIsAppearing callback
fits in with some other key events
during a typical view controller
appearance transition.
I'd like to point out a few things.
First, note how viewWillAppear gets called
before the view is added to the hierarchy,
and before layout begins.
This is why it's too early
to use the trait collection,
or to do anything that depends on
the view's size or other geometry.
Next, notice how viewDidAppear is called
in a separate CATransaction at the end,
after any animations take place.
This means any changes you make
in viewDidAppear don't become visible
until the transition completes,
so it is too late to make changes
you want visible during the transition.
On the other hand, viewIsAppearing
is called within the same transaction
as viewWillAppear.
This means any changes you make
in either of those callbacks
become visible to the user
at the same time,
right from the very first frame
of the transition.
Finally,
though their timing may be similar,
there's a key difference
between viewIsAppearing
and layout callbacks
like viewWillLayoutSubviews.
Layout callbacks are made
whenever the view runs layoutSubviews,
which can happen multiple times
during the transition,
or any time later on
while the view is visible.
But viewIsAppearing is only called once
during the appearance transition,
and it still gets called
even if the view doesn't need layout.
This is why I like to think
of viewIsAppearing
as the Goldilocks callback:
it's not called too early,
or too late, or too often.
It is just right.
The trait system in UIKit
has been upgraded in iOS 17.
Traits automatically propagate data
through your app's hierarchy.
UITraitCollection contains
many system traits,
such as user interface style,
horizontal and vertical size classes,
and preferred content size category.
Now you can define custom traits
to add your own data to UITraitCollection.
This is an entirely new way
for you to propagate data
to the views and view controllers
in your app.
We've also added new trait override APIs
to easily modify trait values
on any view or view controller.
You can also adopt more flexible APIs
to receive callbacks
when traits change value,
instead of needing to override
traitCollectionDidChange in a subclass.
Finally, you can bridge
custom UIKit traits
with custom SwiftUI environment keys
to seamlessly pass data between UIKit
and SwiftUI components in your app.
To learn all about these
exciting new enhancements,
check out the video
"Unleash the UIKit trait system".
Across all our platforms,
SF symbols enable a consistent look
for toolbar icons,
navigation bars, and other UI elements.
They are designed to automatically align
with text labels
and can be easily customized for weight,
scale, and appearance
to match your app's design.
In iOS 17, UIKit supports animated symbols
with the new symbol effects API.
These effects can be applied to
any symbol image, even custom ones.
To apply symbol effects, use the new
addSymbolEffect() method on UIImageView.
Here, I add a bounce effect,
which causes the symbol
to bounce a single time.
Now I'll add a variable color effect.
Unlike bounce, the variable color effect
animates indefinitely when added.
Use the removeSymbolEffect() method
to end the effect.
Finally, I can use the new
setSymbolImage() method
to perform a transition effect
across symbols.
There's a lot more to symbol effects
than the three features I went over.
Check out the video "Animate symbols
in your app" to learn more.
Next, we've added a new API
to make it easy to represent empty states.
Empty states are moments in your app
where there is no content to display.
They typically occur
upon the first launch of your app,
as no content has been created.
They also arise when your app
can't display content
due to a limitation,
such as a lack of Internet connection.
UIContentUnavailableConfiguration is a
composable description of an empty state,
and can be provided with
placeholder content,
such an image or text.
In this example, I inform that there
are no favorite translations to display.
To represent this empty state,
I set the configuration
as the view controller's
contentUnavailableConfiguration.
In addition to the .empty() configuration,
UIKit offers the .loading() configuration
to represent content
that is being prepared.
What's more, you can leverage
the UIHostingConfiguration API
to represent your app's empty state
with a SwiftUI view.
This works just like using
UIHostingConfiguration with cells.
The best place to update
your view controller's
content unavailable configuration
is inside the new method,
updateContentUnavailableConfiguration
(using: state).
This example
uses the .search configuration
which has been designed for queries
that return no results.
The configuration provides
localized primary and secondary text,
with the query interpolated
from the nearby search controller.
Whenever the availability of content
in your view controller changes,
call setNeedsUpdateContentUnavailable
Configuration to request an update.
Across all Apple platforms,
it is essential to deliver a consistent,
high-quality experience,
irrespective of the language setting.
To facilitate that,
we've made significant advancements
in the area of fonts and text rendering.
In this section I will tell you about
the dynamic line-height adjustments
that help prevent clipping and collision
of text in certain fonts and languages.
You'll also learn about the improved
line-breaking and hyphenation rules,
as well as the new API
to request images based on the locale.
First, a closer look
at fonts and their metrics.
Font metrics are defined
using several terms.
The baseline represents an imaginary line
upon which letters or words rest.
The line-height refers to
the space between these baselines.
And, the x-height is a line
that sits atop lowercase letters.
Some fonts have ascenders and descenders
that extend beyond these lines.
Ascenders are the parts of a font
that extend above the x-height.
Descenders, on the other hand,
hang below the baseline.
For some languages
like Arabic, Hindi, and Thai,
these elements require significantly more
vertical space than Latin letters,
leading to possible collisions
or clipping issues.
To prevent the overlapping of ascenders
and descenders in all languages,
we introduced a dynamic line-height
adjustment feature.
This ensures that text elements,
such as UILabels,
automatically adjust their line-heights
and vertical dimensions
for optimal readability.
We also made substantial enhancements
to line-breaking behavior
for languages such as Chinese,
German, Japanese, and Korean.
These improvements apply different rules
based on what kind of text style
you're using.
This will work automatically
in most cases,
as long as you adopt text styles,
but for more information
about best practices
and how to make sure your app works
with all languages,
check out "What's new with Text
and Text Interactions."
In certain situations,
a significant portion of the UI
may be displayed in a language that
differs from the user's selected language.
For example,
when the content comes from the web.
In these cases, you can use
the new typesetting language trait
to indicate the interface's language,
which will help adjust line-height
and hyphenation rules accordingly.
UIKit now supports accessing
specific localized variants of images.
For example,
the character.textbox SF Symbol
has eight different locale-based variants.
By default, UIKit pulls the variant
matching the current language setting
on the device.
So if the current language
is U.S. English,
then the Latin variant is displayed.
On iOS 17,
apps can request specific variants
by providing a Locale
in the image's configuration.
Here, I look up the Japanese version
of the symbol
by providing a configuration
with a Japanese locale.
With all of these changes
to text rendering and locale support,
your apps can feel closer to home
for everyone.
Now, I'll take you through improvements
for building apps for iPad.
I'll cover improvements in 5 areas:
a new window dragging interaction,
enhanced sidebar behavior
in Stage Manager,
keyboard scrolling support,
advancements in building
document-centric apps,
and the new Apple Pencil features
and APIs.
In iOS 17, we've updated
the window dragging functionality
in Stage Manager by expanding the area
in which the drag gesture can begin.
Now, dragging anywhere
inside of a UINavigationBar
will start moving a window.
This gesture plays well with
other gesture recognizers
that might be present in your app,
such as pan or swipe gestures.
If you're not using a UINavigationBar
as part of the UI in your app,
you can adopt UIWindowSceneDragInteraction
and add it to any view.
You can also set up gesture relationships
with other pan gestures in your app
to make sure there aren't any conflicts.
This also works with Mac Catalyst
right out of the box.
Column-style UISplitViewControllers
have gained graceful new resizing behavior
in Stage Manager.
Sidebars are automatically hidden
when necessary,
and they'll remain hidden
until specifically requested to be shown.
When sidebars are requested
at narrower widths,
UISplitViewController uses overlay
or displace behavior as necessary.
An overlaid sidebar persists
as the window resizes larger.
When dismissed and recalled
at the larger width,
it will come back tiled.
Triple-column split view controllers,
such as in Mail, behave similarly.
This new behavior happens
with UISplitViewControllers
created with the double-column
or triple-column style.
To summarize: the automatic behavior
tiles the columns whenever possible,
hides sidebars as necessary
when width is decreased,
overlays or displaces
the secondary column with the sidebar
if there's not enough room to tile
when the sidebar button is tapped,
and you can override the behavior
in your application
using preferredDisplayMode
and preferredSplitBehavior.
In iPadOS 17 we've improved the support
for document-centric apps.
UIKit offers
a new UIDocumentViewController
that serves as the base class
of your content view controller.
It ensures a system default experience
and offers many features
without additional adoption,
such as automatically configuring
the title menu,
sharing, drag and drop,
key commands, and more.
Additionally, UIDocument now conforms
to UINavigationItemRenameDelegate
and offers a full renaming experience
when set as the rename delegate
of the view controller's navigation item.
To learn more about these
and other new features
for apps focused on document management,
check out
'Build better document-based apps'.
Apple Pencil adds an extra facet
to iPadOS apps
and there are a lot of new APIs as well.
With the new iPad Pro and iOS 16.4,
we introduced hover with Apple Pencil.
To capture hover from the pencil
you can use UIHoverGestureRecognizer.
The z offset reflects the normalized
hover distance from the screen,
ranging from 0 to 1.
You can also capture the altitude
and azimuth of the pencil
while in hover range
to accurately render the preview
of what your brush stroke
might look like on screen.
With pencil hover,
you can also hover across the home screen,
and toolbar icons in apps.
If you're using UIPointerInteraction,
no additional adoption is required.
However, it's worth noting,
the visual interactions
when using mouse or trackpad input
versus Apple Pencil input
are slightly different.
For example,
pointer styles such as the system pointer
aren't visible while using Apple Pencil.
Make sure to try out
pencil hover with your app.
In iOS
17, PencilKit becomes even more expressive
and introduces new inks.
The monoline pen is great for detail,
giving you a consistent sized width.
The fountain pen mimics calligraphy,
with thick downstrokes and thin upstrokes.
Watercolor allows for beautiful strokes
and expressivity.
And crayon is a fun addition.
With the new inks,
keep backward compatibility in mind.
Previous versions of iOS cannot load
the PKDrawings that contain the new inks.
A new content version property
on data model types like PKDrawing,
PKStroke, and others indicates
which PencilKit version
is required to load the object.
A content version of 1 denotes inks
that shipped in iOS 14
and 2 is for the new inks in iOS 17.
To provide a good user experience,
use this API to detect incompatibility
and provide a message
or render a fallback image.
When maintaining backwards compatibility
isn't possible,
use the new
maximumSupportedContentVersion API
to limit which features are available
via the canvas and toolpicker.
To make iPads even more powerful
when paired with a hardware keyboard
like Magic Keyboard, we have added support
for keyboard scrolling.
New in iOS 17,
UIScrollViews can be scrolled
using Page Up,
Page Down,
Home, and End keys, if available.
You can override this behavior
using a new API on UIScrollView,
allowsKeyboardScrolling.
Lastly, I'm going to guide you
through general enhancements
we've made in multiple areas of UIKit.
I'll tell you all about
8 general enhancements:
collection view improvements,
new spring animation parameters,
text interactions, and more.
I'll start with collection views
which have been greatly optimized,
with many performance improvements
in iOS 17.
These graphs show how much faster
collection view is in iOS 17
when performing operations
with a large number of items.
iOS 17 is nearly twice as fast as iOS 16
to invert the sort order
of a collection view
containing ten thousand items,
and it's almost three times as fast
to perform an update
that deletes half those items.
What's more, when you perform updates
without animations,
collection view performance
is improved even further.
Whether you're applying snapshots
to diffable data source,
or manually performing batch updates,
collection view is faster across the board
in iOS 17.
These improvements make your app
feel more responsive
and result in fewer hitches in your apps.
Now, I'll talk about a powerful
new feature in Compositional Layout,
by first starting with an example
of a fairly typical layout.
Here is the brand new Health app on iPad,
where the favorites section is using a
compositional layout with rows of 2 items,
all self sizing using
NSCollectionLayoutDimension.estimated.
Notice how the medications cell
has a height
that doesn't match that
of the cell next to it.
This would look much better if the items
in this row had the same height.
In iOS 17, Compositional Layout
gets a brand new layout dimension:
uniformAcrossSiblings.
This new feature allows self-sizing items
in your layout
to receive a consistent size
based on the size of the largest item.
When you need this kind of layout,
simply replace your estimated dimensions
with uniformAcrossSiblings.
Keep in mind, when you use this feature,
it requires all sibling items
to be created and sized
to determine the size of the largest item;
so avoid using it when you have
large numbers of items in a group.
Back to this example of the Health app.
There are two items in this group
with different item heights.
We updated all the items in this layout
to use uniformAcrossSiblings,
so the Medications cell grows to match
the height of the Sound Levels cell,
getting the layout we want.
Next, for spring animations,
we've been refining a new way
to specify parameters
that is easier to understand and
to work with.
It uses just 2 parameters:
duration and bounce.
The duration defines how long until you
perceive the spring animation to settle,
not how long the animation takes
to fully complete,
and it is independent of bounce.
And increasing the bounce from zero
adds bounce to the animation,
without changing
how long the animation feels.
We've added a new method on UIView
that takes these spring parameters.
And all of them are optional,
so now you can even write just "animate"
and get a spring animation
that matches the system default.
Watch the “Animate with Springs” talk
for more insight
into this new way of describing springs.
Next, I'll cover new features and APIs
for interacting with text.
We've made some significant improvements
to the text cursor
and text selection UI in iOS 17,
including a new redesigned
selection loupe.
Developers who have custom text views,
for example word processors,
can now use the system-provided views
for selection UI
without adopting all of UITextInteraction.
Text item interactions in text views
are now more customizable
through new APIs on UITextViewDelegate,
making it possible to modify
the primary action or menu
for text items like
links or text attachments.
Moreover, you can also tag
custom ranges of the content
to enable interactions on them,
making it easier to add actions or menus
to text that are not links.
To learn more about
the text cursor improvements
and the text item actions and menus,
watch "What's new with text
and text interactions."
Now I am going to provide an update
on a well-established element of iOS:
the status bar.
The status bar styling on iOS
is controlled by the application under it,
with a default style that switches
based on the app or view controller
being in dark or light mode.
There are cases with user content that can
be tricky to get right to ensure contrast.
The default style here is dark because
the app is using a light user interface.
But some of the user content is dark.
Now, in iOS 17,
the default style continuously adjusts
to the content of the app
and automatically changes
between dark and light styles
in order to maintain contrast.
It even allows the status bar
to spilt styles when needed.
Since apps no longer need to specify
dark and light explicitly
for all of these cases,
there are opportunities
to remove customization code
and make use of the default style.
Drag and drop
is getting more powerful in iOS 17.
Supported files and content can now
be dropped onto icons on the Home screen
and opened directly
in the respective apps.
This will work automatically today
for many document-based apps
without any changes.
The system uses CFBundleDocumentTypes
as defined in your app's Info.plist file
to determine if the dropped file
is supported.
On drop, the files are opened
using the existing scene delegate methods,
just like any other URL.
Simply make sure your app defines
its supported document types
to opt into this feature.
UIKit adds support for ISO HDR Images,
allowing you to easily display
these images with UIImageView,
and to manipulate them
with UIGraphicsImageRenderer.
Additionally, the new UIImageReader
gives you more control
when loading images,
including converting
some HDR image formats,
such as those
from the Camera Roll to ISO HDR.
For more information check out the session
"Support HDR images in your app."
UIPageControl has gained new features
to represent fractional page progress.
Today, page controls are commonly used
in apps to display slideshow content
that automatically page on a set duration,
or along video content.
With the new progress
and timer progress API,
you can now represent the fractional
page progress in the active indicator
to provide better context
on when the page will change.
To set up
a fractional progress page control,
simply set the new progress property
on UIPageControl with a progress object.
UIPageControlTimerProgress
has a built-in timer
to make it easy
to configure each page's duration.
UIPageControl will automatically change
its page when the timer duration is met.
For pages that need to follow
video players or external timers,
which have their own source of truth,
use the base UIPageControlProgress type
to manually update the currentProgress
value as the content progresses.
iOS 17 and macOS
Sonoma introduce Palette Menus.
Palettes are a row of menu elements
generally used
for choosing from a collection of items.
This style of control can be found
in the Books app on iOS,
or in Mail and Finder on the Mac.
Now it's available as
a first class control in UIKit.
To turn any menu into a palette,
just add .displayAsPalette
to its options like this.
Since elements in a palette
are relatively small,
selection isn't indicated
with a checkmark,
as it is in regular menu elements.
Instead, UIKit will choose
the appropriate selection indicator
based on the provided image.
If all elements in a palette
use monochromatic SF Symbols
or template images,
the selected element is tinted
with the app's tint color.
If the elements
have multi-colored SF symbols,
a tint-colored stroke is drawn
around the selected one.
If you're using entirely custom images
for your menu elements,
or if you'd like to override
the built in behavior
by providing your own selection indicator,
you may use the new selectedImage property
on the UIMenuLeaf protocol.
In this example, the selectedImage is
being set in the UIAction's initializer.
UIKit's menu APIs are available on iOS,
iPadOS, and Mac Catalyst,
allowing you to build complex menus
with the same familiar API.
And starting with tvOS 17,
all of the same APIs are available
on Apple TV
with a brand new appearance
and native tvOS behaviors.
Wow! We've covered a lot of ground.
UIKit has certainly acquired
an array of features,
enhancing its capabilities even further.
What's Next?
Compile your app using the iOS 17 SDK.
Incorporate the new UIKit features
and take advantage of Xcode previews
in your projects.
And ensure that your UIs are flexible
to accommodate varying text metrics
in non-Latin languages.
I hope you enjoyed
the brief overview of these topics.
For a more in depth look,
check out the related videos.
Thank you.
♪ ♪