♪ ♪
Aasim: Hello, I'm Aasim Kandrikar,
and later,
I'll be joined by Raleigh Ledet.
We are both Engineers on the AppKit team.
In this video, we are going to talk about
"What's New in AppKit" in macOS Sonoma.
We'll be covering a broad range of topics,
starting with new features
and API enhancements to AppKit Controls,
improvements to menus powered
by a brand-new implementation,
changes to how app activation
works on macOS,
graphics refinements
and new features for images and symbols,
a new text input experience
and improvements to text layout
in non-English languages,
and improvements
to working in Swift and SwiftUI.
macOS Sonoma includes
some exciting new features
and API refinements to AppKit controls.
NSTableView and NSOutlineView provide
a lot of functionality out of the box,
making it a critical element
in designing great Mac apps using AppKit.
In macOS Sonoma, there is new API
to present column customization menus.
The menu allows users to toggle
visibility of columns in your table.
Previously, this would have required
a custom implementation
to create and present this menu,
but now you can add this
in as little as three lines of code.
Adopt the new delegate method
tableView userCanChangeVisibilityOf.
Specify which columns the user can hide,
and AppKit will handle the rest,
including localizing the menu and
restoring hidden column state on relaunch.
The Progress type from Foundation
represents work your application performs.
You may be using this in your apps
to represent a download in progress
or images that are being processed.
In macOS Sonoma,
you can now use the Progress type
from Foundation
with NSProgressIndicator.
Assign the progress
to the new observedProgress property
and progress indicator
will automatically update its value
as the progress changes,
even on background threads.
The Button bezel style API
has been updated,
starting with a brand-new bezel style,
automatic.
This bezel style will adapt
to the most appropriate style
depending on the contents of the button
and where it is in the view hierarchy.
For example,
when the button is in a window,
it will pick the push button style.
When the button is placed in a toolbar,
it will pick the toolbar style.
For tall content, the button will pick
the flexible push button style.
The automatic bezel style is now
the default bezel style
for all button initializers.
The existing bezel style names
have been updated
from descriptions on their appearance
to modern names
based on their semantic usage.
For example, the formerly named
"Recessed" button
is now "Accessory Bar" button,
indicating that this bezel style
is most commonly used
in Accessory Bars.
Discouraged bezel styles
are now deprecated.
The deprecations now refer
to alternative bezel styles
with clear semantic usage.
We've introduced a brand-new
split view type, inspectors.
Inspectors are a trailing split view item
that displays contextual information
about content that is currently selected
in a document.
Similar to sidebars,
inspectors use the full height
of the window when
the full size content view mask is set.
The new inspectors
back deploy to macOS Big Sur.
Adding an inspector
to your app is straightforward.
First, create a new split view item
using the new
inspectorWithViewController initializer.
Then, add the new splitViewItem
to your existing split view controller.
Next, update your toolbar delegate
to include the new toggle inspector
toolbar item.
You generally want
the toggle inspector item
to be placed over the inspector
on the trailing edge of the window.
To do so,
add the new inspector tracking separator
and a flexible space
before your toggle inspector item.
We've brought
some improvements to NSPopover.
First, we've added support
for anchoring popovers from toolbar items.
We've also added a way
to support full size popover content,
so your views
fill the entire popover bounds.
I'll start with toolbar anchoring.
There is a new method to present
your popover relative to a toolbar item.
When the toolbar item
is in the overflow menu,
the popover gracefully appears
anchored to the overflow chevron.
Next, popover content can now extend
into the popover chevron.
If you had a popover
with a colored background header view,
it might have looked something like this.
Notice that the color
in the header background doesn't extend
into the popover chevron.
To extend popover content
into the chevron area,
set the new hasFullSizeContent property
to true.
Use the safe area rect
to layout content that shouldn't be
obscured inside the popover.
And now I'll pass it over to Raleigh
to talk about exciting changes to Menus.
Raleigh: Thanks Aasim.
Menus have been re-written
to fully use Cocoa.
This reduces AppKit's carbon footprint
by significantly reducing memory
and CPU usage.
It also enables new features.
Specifically,
I'm going to cover section headers,
palette menus,
new selection behaviors, and badges.
These features open up new opportunities
and will reduce the amount
of code you need to write.
Section headers are a new addition
that aid in conveying groups
in your menu and can be created
with a single line of code.
Use the new class function,
sectionHeader(title:) to create one,
and add it to a menu,
like any other menu item.
In this example,
three menu sections are created,
each with a section header and two items.
Palette menus are an exciting new feature
allowing you to build menus
where the items are laid out
in a horizontal series.
For example, this simple color picker.
You can turn any menu into a palette menu
by setting the menu's presentationStyle
to .palette.
For each menu item, set its image.
For template images,
AppKit will automatically add
the appropriate selection tint.
Alternatively, you can set
the offStateImage and the onStateImage.
The onStateImage is used
to indicate selection.
There are a couple of selection modes
you can choose from.
.selectAny toggles the state
of individual menu items,
but will not change the state
of the other items in the group.
.selectOne will set
the selected menu item's state to on
while setting the other members
of the group's state to off.
You can also get or set
which items are in the on state
via the selectedItems property.
Note: selectionMode and selectedItems
work by organizing menu items
that have the same target/action pair
into a logical group.
When manually creating palette menu items,
give each item the same target/action pair
to take advantage of the new selectionMode
and selectedItems behavior.
And here's a tip: This technique
is not limited to palette menus.
It also works for menu items that have
the same target/action pair
in regular menus.
NSMenu also provides
a convenience function
to create common palette menus.
The colors array determines the number
of palette items and their tint.
Titles are used for accessibility,
so make sure you add them.
The optional template parameter specifies
which template image to use for tinting.
For example,
the flag symbol image used here.
If you don't specify a template,
then AppKit will default
to filled circles.
There is also
an optional closure parameter.
This closure is called any time the user
toggles a menu item in the palette.
Menu is passed to the closure.
From it, you can get an array
of the menu items in the on state
with the selectedItems property.
Menu items can now be badged
in a variety of ways.
You can use a simple string
or just a count.
There are also
three specialized count badges:
Newitems, alerts, and updates.
When you use one of these badges,
AppKit will automatically
add the appropriate text.
Further, AppKit will properly
localize the text as well.
In this example, Japanese.
Notice, though,
that you are still responsible
for localizing the menu item itself
and the generic string badge variant.
That's the completely new
menu implementation:
improved performance,
badges, palettes, and section headers.
In macOS Sonoma, we have introduced
Cooperative App Activation.
Cooperative app activation
reduces unexpected application switches,
for example, an app switch
while you are in the middle of typing.
There are two parts
to cooperative app activation.
Activate is now a request,
as opposed to a command.
The system considers the broader context
of what the user is doing
to decide
if the activate request is appropriate.
The new yield API allows
an application to influence the context
of a future activation request.
Now that activate is a request,
the ignoringOtherApps parameter
and option are ignored.
As such, in macOS Sonoma,
the activate(ignoringOtherApps:) function
and the activateIgnoringOtherApps option
are both deprecated.
Replace them with the new activate APIs
for NSApplication
and NSRunningApplication.
Only the active application
can influence the activate context.
It does so by yielding
to an explicit target application
before the target application
is activated.
Then, when the target application
requests activation,
the system will use the yield as part
of the context when making its decision.
If the request is honored,
the active app will deactivate,
and the target app will activate.
Otherwise, the active app remains active.
NSWorkspace automatically handles this
for you when opening URLs or applications.
In other cases, to manually hand
activation to another application,
yieldActivation to the target
NSRunningApplication or bundle identifier.
The system will use the yield context
when the target app
requests activation itself
or is otherwise activated on its behalf.
That's the new cooperative
app activation behavior.
We've also made some significant changes
and added new API
to graphics and drawing in macOS Sonoma.
You can now create CGPaths
from NSBezierPaths and vice versa.
NSBezierPath gains a new init(cgPath:)
initializer and a cgPath property.
Initing with, setting,
or getting the cgPath
always results in a copy of the path.
Further mutations of the NSBezierPath
are not reflected in the original
or copy CGPath instances.
That is, they are not toll-free bridged.
This addition makes using
NSBezierPath with CGPath API,
such as the path property on a CAShapeLayer,
a single line of code.
You can now create
a CADisplayLink object on macOS.
This is the same CADisplayLink
that you may be familiar with from iOS.
For those not familiar with CADisplayLink,
it is a timer object that allows your app
to synchronize its drawing
to the refresh rate of the display.
A directly initialized display link object
is synchronized with the main display,
but macOS is not limited
to a single display.
Therefore, on macOS you can get a display
link object directly from an NSView,
NSWindow or NSScreen
with their new
displayLink(target:selector:) functions.
The best approach
is to get a CADisplayLink object
directly from the most specific
applicable element, usually a view.
This is because,
when created from a view or window,
the CADisplayLink will automatically track
whatever the display or view
the window is on
as it moves around the desktop,
including suspending itself
when not on a display.
In this view subclass,
when startAnimating is called,
with two lines of code,
it creates a DisplayLink object
to call its stepAnimation function,
synchronized to whatever display
the view is on,
and adds the displayLink
to the main runloop for the common modes.
When the animation is complete,
it calls invalidate
to stop the display link and remove it
from all registered runloop modes.
NSColor now offers five new system colors
for filling background shapes.
The fill colors provide varying level
of emphasis for shapes of various sizes.
Smaller shapes on the scale
of a slider track or a progress bar
background use a higher level of emphasis
to stand out, such as system fill
or secondary system fill.
Larger shapes, like group boxes
and font backgrounds prefer
a more subtle level of emphasis,
such as quaternary or quinary system fill.
These fill colors are dynamic,
so they automatically adapt
to different appearances,
including Increased Contrast
and Dark Mode.
If you're building custom UI elements,
these new fill colors are a convenient way
to fit in with the system design
and support accessibility.
NSViews clip their drawing contents
to their bounds.
That sometimes leads to drawing
not displaying the way you want,
like the bottom of this Hindi glyph
in a FreeForm alert window.
Common places this can occur
is with font rendering,
shadows, or other sub-view accents,
like a badge
or a flame on that "hot" item for sale.
There are ways to solve this.
For example, embed the combined views
as siblings in a larger view.
However,
each technique has its own drawbacks.
In this case, combining the enclosing view
with a button in a simple horizontal stack
doesn't line up the base lines
of the text by default.
And now you have another problem to solve.
There is a better way.
When linked on macOS Sonoma,
most NSViews no longer clip
to their bounds by default.
Hit testing remains unchanged
and is determined
by the geometry of the view.
Of course, you can
override hitTest to change this.
Now that a view may draw
outside of its bounds,
its calculated visibleRect
may also extend past its bounds.
Review any code that uses visibleRect
and adjust accordingly.
This also impacts the dirtyRect
parameter of the draw function.
Specifically, the dirtyRect
is not constrained by a view's bounds.
AppKit reserves the right
to pass a dirtyRect that is larger
than the view's bounds.
AppKit also reserves the right
to subdivide drawing
into as many rectangles as it needs.
What this means for you
is that you should use
the dirtyRect to decide what to draw,
not where to draw.
This is an example of unexpected
drawing results that may occur.
This draw override fills the passed in
dirtyRect with a background color,
causing the fill to spill
outside the view's bounds,
covering other UI in the window.
The view isn't using
the dirtyRect to draw the frame.
Likewise,
its background fill should precisely fill
what your design requires,
no more, no less.
Drawing outside the dirtyRect
is always safe.
The performance benefits
of the dirtyRect occur when used
to decide which parts of your data
you can avoid drawing in this pass.
Perhaps calculating the stroke paths of
my name in this fancy style is expensive.
If the dirtyRect is just
this little corner,
it won't intersect with the text frame,
so the view can avoid
those expensive calculations.
Drawing the background
and the frame are still required,
but, filling the entire bounds
and drawing the entire frame
in this pass won't affect
the other already drawn portions
of the view because AppKit clips
the drawing to the dirtyRect.
The new NSView .clipsToBounds property
is available
all the way back to OS X Mavericks 10.9.
But note, on older OSes turning off
.clipsToBounds may have some rough edges.
Test accordingly.
Most views will behave just fine
with both clipping on and off.
Some container views
make their own explicit decisions.
NSClipView,
true to its name, behaves this way.
There may be specific instances
where you disagree
with a view's default clipping behavior
and need to selectively change it.
Consider on a case-by-case basis
which of your own views
require an explicit clipsToBounds value.
The right choice is the one
that realizes your vision for your app.
Now back to Aasim to talk about images.
Aasim: Thanks Raleigh.
Symbols are an essential part
of designing your apps.
In macOS Sonoma,
symbols gain brand-new functionality,
symbol effects.
With symbol effects,
your symbols
can now have effects like bounce,
replacement transitions,
and pulse animations.
Symbol effects are great way
to emphasize an action
that has occurred
or state change in your apps.
Adding a symbol effect is simple.
First, set the imageView's image property
to a symbol image.
Then, when you want the effect,
simply call addSymbolEffect
to the image view.
Note that this will only work if
your NSImageView uses a symbol image.
For more info on using symbol effects,
check out
the "Animate symbols in your app" video.
In macOS Ventura,
we introduced support for SF Symbols
to automatically adapt
to the user's current locale.
Now in macOS Sonoma,
your asset catalog images and symbols
get that same ability.
Like SF Symbols in macOS Ventura,
they follow the system locale by default.
Use the image locale method
to obtain an image with a fixed locale.
Next, I'll talk about High Dynamic Range
content, or HDR for short.
HDR content can express light levels
far beyond standard content.
macOS has supported extended
dynamic range for several releases,
allowing you to take full advantage
of displays such as the Liquid Retina XDR
in Macbook Pros and the Pro Display XDR.
macOS Sonoma makes it easier than ever
to display HDR content in your apps
with NSImageView
gaining support for HDR content.
Images containing HDR content
will now be displayed in HDR
on Extended Dynamic Range
capable hardware.
To display HDR content
in standard dynamic range,
use the preferredImageDynamicRange
property to override.
For more info on adopting this API,
check out the "Support HDR images
in your apps" video.
Starting in Xcode 15,
images and colors in your Asset Catalog
are automatically reflected into your code
as static properties
on NSImage and NSColor.
This allows you to use clean dot notation
to access the image
instead of initializing it with a string.
The images are non-optional,
so you can also remove
any force unwrapping or guard checks.
If you modify the Asset Catalog to remove
or rename an image,
the compiler will catch any mismatch
with your code and produce an error
when building your apps,
which allows you to fix it immediately,
instead of catching it later at runtime.
macOS Sonoma introduces significant
changes to the typing experience
and improvements to text layout
in non-English languages.
It starts
with a brand-new insertion indicator
that adapts to the current accent color,
and leaves a trailing glow
as you dictate text.
Next, there is now a cursor accessory
below the insertion indicator
that displays key information,
like input mode,
dictation state, and caps lock state.
The accessory tracks the current insertion
position and will be pinned to the bottom
of the document if the insertion
position is outside the visible view.
Apps using standard AppKit text views
will get this automatically.
If you have a custom text view,
we have new API that you can adopt.
You can replace your custom
text insertion indicator drawing
with the NSTextInsertionIndicator view.
Add this view as a subview
on your custom text view,
and you will get
the new insertion indicator
that is consistent across the OS.
Note that you will be
in charge of updating the frame
of the insertion indicator
and whether it is visible.
Update the displayMode property
to hidden when your text view
resigns first responder
to hide the indicator.
MacOS Sonoma features
several improvements to text layout
for non-English languages.
An important highlight
is the changes we've made
for wrapping and hyphenation,
as some languages require different rules
for line breaking,
depending on the text context.
For example,
in traditional typesetting for Korean,
body text may have a line break
in the middle of a word,
but title text will only wrap
at word boundaries.
Breaking within words in titles
can feel jarring in Korean.
In this sheet from Maps,
the Korean word for “time”
is split between two lines.
macOS Sonoma
will now perform different line breaking
depending on the text style font used.
In Korean, title and Headline text styles
like in this sheet will not wrap
at word boundaries.
While the body text style may have
a line break within words if appropriate.
Here is another example.
In narrow layouts, some German words
can be longer than an entire line width,
which can cause individual characters
to spill over into the next line.
This wrapping isn't ideal.
It looks unbalanced,
and there's a component of the word--
which is called a morpheme--
that's being split across lines.
In macOS Sonoma,
if you have a title text field
with hyphenation disabled,
macOS will automatically hyphenate
the text at a morpheme boundary
instead of character wrapping.
The resulting layout is more
balanced and easier to read.
This is a great time
to adopt text styles in your app.
In macOS Sonoma,
AppKit has been updated to make it easier
to adopt Swift-first features
like Swift concurrency and transferable.
SwiftUI has also been updated
to allow you to use SwiftUI views
and modifiers in more places
in your AppKit app.
The majority of AppKit classes
are restricted to the main thread.
Under Swift concurrency,
these classes are marked as main actor
to generate appropriate compiler errors.
However, there are certain classes
in AppKit such as NSColor and NSShadow
that can be safely accessed
outside the main thread.
In macOS Sonoma, these classes
conform to the Sendable protocol,
which indicates that they can be freely
transferred across actor boundaries.
Transferable is a Swift protocol
to describe how objects can be
serialized and deserialized.
This powers features like
Drag and Drop and Sharing in SwiftUI.
In macOS Sonoma NSImage,
NSColor, and NSSound conform
to the Transferable protocol.
This makes it easier for AppKit apps
to adopt features like Drag and Drop
or Sharing in SwiftUI Views.
In macOS Ventura 13.3,
we introduced a new property wrapper
for NSViewController, ViewLoading.
Use ViewLoading on properties
that are initialized in loadView.
If these properties
were previously optional,
you can remove the optionality
and any related checks.
The view controller will make sure
that the property is initialized
by calling loadViewIfNeeded.
A similar property wrapper, WindowLoading,
is also available for properties
on NSWindowController.
With Xcode 15,
you can now use Previews
to display your AppKit views
and view controllers.
Use the new Preview macro, provide a name,
and return your view or view controller.
The preview will stay up to date
as you make changes to your code.
Check out the “Build programmatic UI
with Xcode Previews” video for more info.
NSHostingView and NSHostingController
are a great way
to incrementally adopt SwiftUI
into your AppKit app.
In macOS Sonoma,
there are some new features that allow you
to adopt SwiftUI in more places.
SwiftUI modifiers
like toolbar and navigation title
now work on NSWindows.
If the hostingView
is the contentView of the window,
SwiftUI will automatically bridge
all available scene modifiers
to your NSWindow.
For more control,
there is a new property on NSHostingView
and NSHostingController,
sceneBridgingOptions.
Using this, you can explicitly state
which properties should be bridged
from your SwiftUI view to the NSWindow.
That's just some of the new features
for AppKit in macOS Sonoma.
What's next?
First, compile your apps using
the macOS Sonoma SDK and audit it
to ensure that the changes
to clipping and activation don't cause
any unwanted side effects.
Next, adopt the new controls API,
like the new full-height inspector
and the new table column
customization API.
Update your app's design
to take advantage
of symbol effects in macOS Sonoma.
And finally, use the new
Swift focused AppKit additions,
like Transferable
and improvements to NSHostingView,
to adopt SwiftUI
in more places in your app.
Thanks so much for watching.
We hope you enjoy all
the new features of macOS Sonoma!
♪ ♪