♪ Mellow instrumental hip-hop ♪
♪
Hi, welcome to "Discover Quick
Look for spatial computing."
My name is Youssef,
and I'm an engineer
on the AR Quick Look team.
Today, I'll be talking to you
about all of the capabilities
of Quick Look on xrOS
and how you can use it
to unlock new experiences
for your apps and websites
on the platform.
Before we get into all of that,
let's first go over
what Quick Look is.
Quick Look is a system
framework that allows you
to easily preview and edit files
on iOS, macOS, and now xrOS.
Quick Look comes
with powerful editing features
like trimming for videos
and Markup
for PDFs and images
right out of the box.
It also handles the secure
and safe access of files,
so you don't have to worry
about opening up
untrusted files in your app.
Quick Look shows up in many
places across Apple's platforms.
On iOS, you see it whenever
you open an attachment
from a message thread.
On macOS, you enter Quick Look
whenever you hit the Space bar
on a selected file
from Finder or desktop.
Quick Look is the system viewer
for file-backed content on xrOS.
And just like on iOS and macOS,
xrOS apps can leverage
Quick Look to easily gain
feature-rich file viewing
and editing.
Let's see what that looks like.
Recently, I've been working
on remodeling an apartment,
and I've been using an app
to track the progress
of that project
and collaborate with my team.
One of the interior designers
I'm working with
just sent me a folder with
some ideas he has for the house.
I have that folder
opened up here
so let's see
what he came up with.
It looks like
there's a USDZ model
of the proposed living room.
Let's open it up.
To do this, I'll pinch
and drag the file out
and drop it outside
of any application.
Dropping the USDZ file presents
a 3D Quick Look preview
right where I dropped it.
And I can immediately start
to interact with it.
Using a pinch and drag gesture,
I can rotate the model
to get a better look at the
beautiful exposed brick facade.
To take a closer look
at the living room,
I'll just zoom into the model
to scale it up.
It looks like my designer
also sent a picture
of the neighborhood
surrounding the home.
Finally, it looks like
there's a document here
with a list of the features
planned for the home.
A lot of these look great
but I'm not sure
about this last one,
so let me leave a note
to get back to it later.
I'll open up the menu
at the top of the window
and select Markup,
which brings up
the Markup palette.
Let me quickly circle the item
I want to get back to.
We were able to drag a file
from an application
and preview it
outside of that app.
We did this with multiple files
and viewed them all
alongside
the source application.
This new way to present files
in Quick Look
is called Windowed Quick Look.
In this session,
we'll learn more
about this presentation style
and how apps and websites
can adopt it.
Then we'll go over how
to present Quick Look previews
directly within an application.
But first, let's take a deeper
dive into Windowed Quick Look.
Windowed Quick Look allows you
to present Quick Look previews
outside of your application.
This is perfect
for nonblocking experiences
where you want to be able
to view your file content
alongside your app.
Since windowed
Quick Look previews
are hosted in a separate app,
you can close your application
while still having
those previews persist.
Windowed Quick Look also offers
a much richer viewing experience
for 3D models backed
by USDZ and Reality files.
You can scale and place
3D content independent
of your application.
You can also scale the 3D model
which will dim the environment
and hide all other scenes,
allowing you to focus
on just the 3D content.
Certain file types presented
in Quick Look windows
offer SharePlay experiences
so you can share a file
and view it over FaceTime.
When sharing 3D content
over SharePlay,
Quick Look will sync
the 3D model's orientation,
scale, and animations.
When sharing images
over SharePlay,
you'll be able to mark up
that image together with others.
SharePlaying files
with Quick Look offers you
an easy and simple way
to collaborate on files
with a group.
Both applications and websites
can present content
in Quick Look windows and take
advantage of the many benefits
it has to offer.
First, let's take
a look at how apps
can present Windowed Quick Look.
Apps can present files
in Quick Look windows
by providing a drag source
containing some URL.
During a drag-and-drop
interaction,
when a drop target
is outside of any app,
the system will copy and present
your provided URL
in a Quick Look window.
If your provided URL
is pointing to a file
hosted in a remote destination,
like iCloud,
the system will
download it first.
Keep in mind,
that because a copy
of your provided
file is presented,
any edits such as markups on an
image made to the presented file
will not be written back
to the URL you provide.
To see this in action,
let's go to Xcode.
Before we add drag
support to our app,
let me quickly give you
an overview of the app.
The app lets you see
the progress of the project
and view a list of the files
shared by other team members.
Here we have a list view
which displays FileViews.
Since we want to be able
to drag out each file,
we'll need to turn each FileView
into a drag source.
To do this, I'll add the onDrag
modifier onto the FileView.
The onDrag modifier
expects an NSItemProvider,
so I'll return an item provider
containing the URL
for the file being displayed
in that FileView.
Building and running
the app in the simulator,
I can now drag out
from the file view
and present that file
in a new Quick Look window.
I can also close out my app
and still have that
file's preview displayed.
By adding just
a few lines of code,
I've enabled drag and drop
within my app
and allowed content to be
viewed in a separate window
letting me still use
my app freely.
Now let's see how we can
do this for websites.
Since iOS 12, websites have
been able to link to and view
3D content in AR Quick Look
on iPhone and iPad
by marking up links
with the AR attribute.
When you open a link to
marked-up 3D content on xrOS,
Safari will present
the 3D content
in a new Quick Look window.
Websites already supporting
AR content linking on iOS
and iPadOS will have
this behavior carry over
to xrOS with no additional
work needed.
xrOS will also respect
customization options
such as disabling
content scaling.
For more information on
those customization options,
see the "Advances
in AR Quick Look" session
from WWDC19.
If you haven't setup
your website
to present 3D content
from Safari,
all you have to do is mark up
your links like this.
By adding rel="ar" to your link
or anchor element,
Safari won't navigate on tap.
Instead, it will present
that 3D file
in a Quick Look window
alongside the website.
Let's go over to Safari
and check this out.
We have the AR Quick Look
gallery page
open in Safari here.
There are a bunch of 3D models
linked to from this page
so let's open some of them up.
Tapping on a link
to this teapot,
downloads and presents that 3D
model in a Quick Look window.
Once it downloads,
the model will appear.
Tapping on the link to this mug
presents it near the teapot
and Safari.
This is really great
for e-commerce sites
where you might want
to view and place products
in shared space to get
a sense if it's right for you.
We just went over
presenting files
in a Quick Look window
to preview it outside your app.
There are some use cases where
you may want to preview files
directly inside of your app.
Displaying in-app
Quick Look content is as simple
as passing in some URLs
to the quickLookPreview function
in SwiftUI.
When presented using
quickLookPreview,
the preview will display
as a sheet
on top of your view's content.
If you want more
customization options
over your presented previews,
you can use
a QLPreviewController
here instead.
If you're bringing
your iOS app to xrOS,
existing uses
of quickLookPreview
or QLPreviewController API
will carry over for free.
Let's hop over
to the simulator and see
where we could take advantage of
this in our Project Tracker app.
I have a view where I can review
some new designs my team has
before sending them off
to the homeowner for approval.
I can currently see
a list of files,
but I can't actually preview
any of the files.
Let's go to Xcode
and see if we can fix this.
This is my view right now.
To preview the files directly
in my application,
first I'll import QuickLook.
Then I'll add the SwiftUI
quickLookPreview function
passing all of the files
I want to preview
and the specific file
I want initially selected.
Let's run this
and see what we get.
Going back to our app,
now when I select this view,
I can see a sheet
with our previews
appear directly within our app.
I can cycle through the files
using the navigation controls
in the toolbar and make sure
everything is fine
before sending them over
to the homeowner.
Presenting file previews
directly within our app
was as easy as passing
in some URLs
to the quickLookPreview
function.
Now that we've covered
both flavors of Quick Look
on the platform,
let's touch on the file types
with supported previews.
Quick Look supports
the most common file types
including images, videos,
PDFs, and USDZ files.
Spatial images and videos
shown in Quick Look
will look just as stunning
as they do in Photos.
And that's a quick look
at Quick Look on xrOS.
Now let's recap all
we went over today.
We talked about the rich preview
and editing features
that Quick Look
can provide apps.
We then discussed
Windowed Quick Look,
a new way for apps to preview
content using Quick Look,
and the capabilities
that Windowed Quick Look
has to offer,
such as multipreview support
so you can view content
alongside your application,
volumetric immersive
3D content viewing,
and SharePlay support.
We then went over how
applications can streamline
their workflows and take
advantage of Quick Look windows
by adding support
for drag and drop,
and how websites can leverage
Quick Look windows
to present 3D content
alongside Safari as well.
We also saw how simple
it was for apps to present
Quick Look content within
their own scenes in SwiftUI.
If you're bringing an app
that already uses Quick Look,
you'll have to do
little to no work
to get a great Quick Look
experience on this platform.
Similarly, websites already
linking to AR content
will have that behavior
carry over for free as well.
Quick Look can provide apps
with simple, powerful,
and secure file-viewing
experiences,
and we can't wait to see what
you build using Quick Look
on xrOS.
♪