♪ ♪
Allen: Hello, everyone!
I'm Allen,
an engineer on the accessibility team,
and welcome
to "Meet Assistive Access" at WWDC.
At Apple, we strive to ensure
our products are accessible
and inclusive to everyone.
We understand that cognitive disabilities
can present their own unique set
of challenges in how people interact
with our technology.
Assistive Access is a mode that distills
apps and experiences to their core
to lighten cognitive load
for people with disabilities.
With the help of a trusted supporter,
for example,
a parent, guardian, or conservator,
customizations
in Assistive Access' settings
will make it easy to navigate
and use apps with greater independence
than before on iPhone and iPad.
Today, we'll discover how to set up
and turn on Assistive Access,
as well as explore how it works.
Next, we'll explore some of the goals
and core values of Assistive Access.
We'll discuss how your application will
behave when Assistive Access is turned on.
And finally, we'll discuss
additional things to consider
about your app's presentation
in Assistive Access.
With that, let's get started.
Setting up Assistive Access is simple.
As mentioned, trusted supporters
can use the Settings app
to customize Assistive Access to the needs
of the person using the device.
When first accessing this mode
through settings,
trusted supporters will be guided
through the initial setup process.
They'll be able to customize many aspects
of Assistive Access,
from choosing the preferred apps
that will be allowed to run
to choosing
whether the battery indicator is present.
Assistive Access can be
turned on from its settings
or by using the accessibility shortcut.
Once entering into Assistive Access,
the system displays a new lock screen
with the capability
to change its wallpaper in settings
and an interface
to inform people of notifications.
Navigating past the Lock screen,
a new Home screen is displayed
with larger app icons and larger text.
I've set up Assistive Access
to include five Apple apps
designed specifically for this mode:
“Calls” to make or receive calls
from friends and family,
“Messages” to send and receive messages,
“Music” to have access
to favorite playlists,
“Camera” to take pictures,
videos, and selfies,
and “Photos”
to view saved photos and videos.
Assistive Access is crafted with a set
of design and development objectives
aimed at creating an effective experience
to reduce cognitive strain.
Many apps on iOS and iPadOS
have plenty of user interface items,
including buttons,
icons, menus, images, and more.
For some people,
this level of functionality
and completeness
can become a challenge to operate.
People should be able
to complete a task without distractions.
Assistive Access
reduces the available options,
so people can find and navigate
to their items of interest.
Fewer steps and fewer options
can help provide a clear path
to success in completing a task.
Recognizing and recovering
from errors can be difficult.
When people encounter significant actions,
such as deleting a file,
they should be given clear instructions
and given the opportunity
to understand what
is happening before continuing.
This also includes reducing actions
that are time-dependent
and make it easy to go back at any time.
Creating
familiar interactions and patterns
is crucial to Assistive Access.
It establishes a sense
of predictability and comfort,
while also engaging
in a multi-modal experience,
like seeing both text and images.
This helps reduce cognitive strain,
makes the interface familiar,
and increases the chance
the interface will be understood.
By reducing complexity,
helping people prevent errors,
and creating familiar interactions,
people can use iPhone and iPad
with less difficulty.
Now, let's take a look
at how your app will behave
when Assistive Access is turned on.
In Assistive Access,
third party apps will just work.
In this setup, I've added my app.
Let's see how it looks.
When I open my app, Assistive Access
adds the large back button
displayed prominently
at the bottom of the screen.
To make room for the back button,
apps are displayed
in a reduced frame by default.
This is to ensure
your app still looks great,
in case you've designed your app based
on individual device screen size.
In addition,
navigating back to the home screen
can be done by tapping on the back button.
Some apps
are designed specifically to be adaptive
to varying devices and screen sizes.
We've created a new info.plist key
that will allow your apps to run
in full screen, excluding the back button.
Add UISupportsFullScreenInAssistiveAccess
to your info.plist file
and set its value to yes.
Use this key to let Assistive Access know
you've designed your app
to be adaptive to arbitrary screen sizes.
My app has be designed for my audience
and to have an adaptive layout,
so this key is relevant to my app.
Let's take a look at how my app
behaves after adding this key.
Great, my app uses all
of the available space
in Assistive Access.
Let's look at ways to ensure
your app can do the same.
Great apps on iPhone and iPad
are designed to have a consistent layout
that adapts
regardless of your user's device.
This means that your app
does not hard code layout
based on the device or screen size.
In SwiftUI, developers can
take advantage of layout containers,
such as Stacks and Grids,
to arrange views,
as well as layout modifiers
to adjust or constrain the size,
position, and alignment of a view.
If you need
a more customized layout for your app,
check out the session
"Compose custom layouts with SwiftUI."
In UIKit, we can use AutoLayout and take
advantage of two important features.
The first is the Safe Area,
which is the portion of the screen
that is not obstructed by system
hardware or software elements,
such as the Dynamic Island
or the Home indicator.
Use the safeAreaInsets property
to position your views
within the visible portion
of the interface.
Layout Guide is the second feature,
which defines a rectangular region
that helps you position
and align your content on screen.
Use the safeAreaLayoutGuide property
to adjust elements
and apply standard margins around content.
To learn more
about making your apps adaptive,
check out the session
"UIKit: Apps for Every Size and Shape."
Whether using SwiftUI or UIKit,
this new Info.plist key,
along with an adaptive layout,
can ensure all users
in Assistive Access have
a great experience in your app.
Let's make sure
everyone can enjoy and use your app,
even in Assistive Access.
Thanks for watching.
♪ ♪